<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3844803</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/503696</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR860305</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Chapter in Public Theology from the Perspective of Human Rights: Interreligious Interaction and Dialogue in an Intercivilizational Context</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Johannes A.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>van der Ven</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Radboud University of Nijmegen, the Netherlands</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>July 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>86</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2006.86.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>412</fpage>
         <lpage>441</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/503696"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>In Honor of Don Browning</title>
         <p>I want to start this article, which I dedicate to my colleague and friend Don Browning, by briefly sketching his contribution to the development of practical theology internationally, more particularly to research on marriage and the family. In so doing I shall use seven key words—partly because “seven” is regarded as a rhetorical and ritual number, but mainly because I cannot sketch the value and significance of his work in less than seven words! I commence with his specific research contribution, not only because everybody who knows Browning will have it vividly in mind, but because its quality and magnitude evoke admiration and set an example. Anyone who thought that Browning ultimately would legitimize traditional church marriage was profoundly mistaken. However, in terms of what he calls his critical constructive approach, he is an ardent proponent of the continuation of the family as institution, albeit in a critical, open, modern, and future‐oriented fashion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>In view of the many family problems people encounter, the messes they themselves create, the conflicts they endure, a steadily increasing divorce rate, and the children who in many instances are the victims of all this, there is no room for judgment, let alone condemnation.</p>
         <p>Why is Browning’s work so open‐minded? Could it be that his pastoral wisdom prevents him from judging? No doubt. But above all it is his analysis of the situation in which present‐day marriages and families find themselves that causes him—and along with him, his readers—to understand the complexity of the causes of the many crises. In many ways these causes are beyond the responsibility, often even the capacity, of the family members. By analyzing these factors, Browning identifies perspectives from which one can critically search for solutions; an uncritical adaptation of modern or—worse—fashionable trends is out of the question. The project looks into many issues, such as covenant marriage, contraception, adoption, abortion, same‐sex marriage, and the single mother. This inquiry is solidly based on scholarly, historically supported argumentative communication.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>In short, Browning’s “family project” highlights both the potential and the significance of present‐day practical theology.</p>
         <p>The first important point to be made about the project, which characterizes Browning’s whole oeuvre, is his commitment to the development of practical theology as public theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>He has always opposed social developments that force religion into a peripheral position in society, as well as churches submitting helplessly and blindly to such developments. Browning is not a street corner protester, but a theologian who seriously and systematically joins in public debate, especially on issues concerning marriage and the family.</p>
         <p>The second major point is that he—because of a strategic decision, I think—consistently chooses themes that relate to social institutions such as marriage and the family. The convictions, norms, and values supporting a society are embodied and anchored in these institutions. When the institutions are in crisis and crumble there is a need for religion, and indeed for theology, as critical‐constructive reflection on religion.</p>
         <p>To Browning the issues—and that is the third point—are not parochial or provincial. His concern is with their international, even global dimensions: marriage and the family are declining worldwide, implying fresh challenges for children, mothers, and fathers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>The different religions are not only witnesses to this crisis, but with their rich resources they can contribute to the renewal of marriage and the family. Accordingly Browning has embedded his whole project in a multireligious framework, including not only the religions of the book—Judaism, Christianity, and Islam—but also Hinduism and Buddhism.</p>
         <p>The fourth characteristic is his empirical orientation. Even though his own contribution to empirical research, in the technical sense, is not the principal part of his practical theology, his scholarship is clearly based on an empirical orientation. For him practical theology is unimaginable without the processing of empirical data, collected both by fellow practical theologians and scientists, as in other disciplines. This explains his frequent collaboration with social scientists. It ensures that he has both feet planted firmly on the ground and does not indulge in far‐fetched speculations unrelated to the real lives of real people.</p>
         <p>However, being a practical theologian, he considers empirical description—“descriptive theology,” as he calls it—without normative reflection worthless: this is the fifth characteristic.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>In short: practical theology arises from interaction between empiricism and normativeness.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>For this interaction, Browning coined the term “practical‐theological ethics.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>For Browning the normative choices made in practical theology are crucial. He and I share an admiration for the synthesis made by Paul Ricoeur, who ingeniously combined three moral traditions: teleology, deontology, and situational ethics. In this synthesis, deontology (especially Immanuel Kant) functions as a filter for teleology (especially Aristotle), whereupon this teleology is applied with wisdom in people’s concrete, contingent, and unique situations to direct their actions.</p>
         <p>This moral normativeness is expressed judicially in an institutional sense in law and jurisprudence, both of which are ultimately founded in human rights—this is the sixth characteristic.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>As a matter of fact, anyone who thinks in institutional terms and keeps the moral dimension in view will inevitably end up in judicial explication and positivization. This explains why Browning attaches such importance to the interaction between marriage and the family, on the one hand, and law, on the other, the more so because this interaction is part of the substance of religion, especially religious family law.</p>
         <p>The final point is this: How did all this start for Browning, and what is his ultimate aim? This is a complex question with no easy answer. Who can really answer it for himself or herself, let alone for someone else? Nevertheless, I can say at least the following: the driving force behind Browning’s research is a fundamental hermeneutic concern. Ultimately he is concerned about the identity and relevance of the Christian tradition in present‐day society. Without relevance the Christian tradition will end up on the periphery of society; hence, it is of the utmost importance to join in the public debate. Without its identity the Christian tradition sells out to the interests of the economy and state bureaucracy and thus dissipates into nothing; hence, it is of the utmost importance to delve into its rich resources anew and learn how it can contribute to what Ricoeur so aptly called “naming God.” I expect that Browning’s contribution to the hermeneutic approach in practical theology will withstand the ravages of time and that<italic>A Fundamental Practical Theology</italic>will turn out to be his greatest scholarly work.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Don Browning, “Critical Familism, Civil Society, and the Law,”<italic>Hofstra Law Review</italic>32, no. 1 (2003): 313–29.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Don Browning,<italic>Marriage and Modernization</italic>(Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2003); Don S. Browning, Bonnie J. Miller‐McLemore, Pamela D. Couture, K. Brynolf Lyon, and Robert M. Franklin,<italic>From Culture Wars to Common Ground: Religion and the American Family Debate</italic>(Louisville, KY: Westminster/John Knox, 1997); and Don Browning and Gloria Rodriguez,<italic>Reweaving the Social Tapestry: Toward a Public Philosophy and Policy for Families</italic>(New York: Norton, 2002).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Don Browning, “The Idea of the International Academy of Practical Theology,”<italic>Pastoral‐Theologische Informationen</italic>14 (1994): 3–11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Browning,<italic>Marriage and Modernization</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Don Browning,<italic>A Fundamental Practical Theology</italic>(Philadelphia: Augsburg Fortress, 1991), 110–35.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Don Browning, “Hermeneutik als Grundlage und Aufgabe praktisch‐theologischer Ethik,” in<italic>Christentum und Spätmoderne: Eine internationale Diskurs über Preaktische Theologie und Ethik</italic>, ed. W. Gräb, Gerhard Rau, Heinz Schmidt, Johannes A. van der Ven, and Denise M. Ackermann (Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 2000).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Browning,<italic>Marriage and Modernization</italic>, 160–66.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Ibid., 166–81.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>I shall return to these seven characteristics—which I, too, consider characteristic of practical theology—at the end of this article, albeit from the angle of a specific question on which I propose to focus. The question is as follows: What is the relevance of practical theology as public theology from the perspective of human rights? I understand public theology to be a theological reflection on public religion. Public religion in its turn refers—to quote Martin Marty—to religion’s public implications.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>This contradicts the notion of, for example, Max Weber and Jürgen Habermas that religion belongs exclusively to the private domain. Persuasive reasons for rejecting this notion are advanced in the volume on public theology, which was edited by Browning and Francis Schüssler Fiorenza.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>In this article I would like to reflect theologically on religion’s public implications from the perspective of human rights. Although such reflection has been advocated before, it has never been undertaken systematically.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>I consider it a challenge, because the connection between religion and human rights is by no means self‐evident, even though the churches often profess to be the source of human rights. Thus Marty comments ironically that these churches “might at least send a card of thanks to modernity, to the Enlightenment, for having led them to the delayed—fifteen centuries late!—discovery of the latent pro‐human rights, pro‐religious rights, elements in their treasury.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>
         </p>
         <p>A practical theology that wants to operate as public theology should avail itself of what Browning, following David Tracy, calls the revised correlational approach in hermeneutics and, in the process, should interrelate two reflective processes. For a theological hermeneutics of human rights this implies critical reflection on the tradition of the Christian religion from the contemporary perspective of human rights, and conversely, critical reflection on the contemporary belief in human rights from the perspective of the rich resources within the Christian tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>In other words, practical theology as public theology would have to be a critical and constructive theological hermeneutics of human rights if it is to exist at all.</p>
         <p>Nonetheless this poses a problem, especially when it comes to the interpretation and implementation of human rights.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>Thus some countries insist on their own religious interpretation of human rights, as is evident in the Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam preparatory to the Second UN Human Rights Conference in Vienna in 1993, which states that “the islamic Shari’ah is the only source of reference for the explanation or clarification of any of the articles of this Declaration.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>As for the implementation of human rights, there are religious institutions like the Catholic Church, which, while recognizing human rights in societal domains outside their own, reject or limit some of these rights within their own domains, for instance, gender equality, freedom of religion, and freedom of speech—and do so on religious grounds.</p>
         <p>This brings us to the specific theme I want to discuss in this article: the interaction and dialogue between the different religions viewed from the perspective of human rights. I consider this a key theme of any public theology, and I hope that the reflection in this article will be seen as a contribution to public theology. I refer once again to a deep concern that I share with Browning: the fact that in his family project he has devoted increasing attention not only to the interaction between different religions but also to its judicial implications. It comes as no surprise that under his guidance many books on Jewish, Christian, and Islamic law have already been published, and many more are bound to be published in future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The question I want to consider is this: How should religions deal with one another? What forms of relationship suggest themselves and which are to be preferred? This question has become more urgent in recent times. The armed conflict between Israel and Palestine, which has been going on for decades; the Gulf War and the Balkan wars during the 1990s; the terrorist attacks on New York on September 11, 2001, and on Madrid on March 11, 2004; and last but not least, the war in Iraq, which still continues as I write this—all these tragedies have made my question a burning topic of discussion in the Western world.</p>
         <p>The answer I would like to propose in this article entails, first, a distinction—as indicated in the title—between interaction and dialogue; and second, that both are viewed in a human rights perspective. In other words, I want to contribute to the current theme of the interreligious dialogue within the theology of religions with regard to two dimensions: both its breadth and its depth. Breadth can be attained by not immediately opting for a participant perspective, which is characteristic of interreligious dialogue, but first approaching it from a more detached observer perspective and, on that basis, putting it in the framework of the interaction between religions and of human rights (see the first section). Depth can be attained by switching between an observer and a participant perspective and, in that framework, analyzing what the conditions for fruitful dialogue are. I hope to show that these conditions will also gain in profundity by viewing them in the context of human rights (see the second section).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Martin Marty and Jonathan Moore,<italic>Politics, Religion, and the Common Good: Advancing a Distinctly American Conversation about Religion’s Role in Our Shared Life</italic>(San Francisco: Jossey‐Bass, 2000), 15. This definition of public theology is both simpler and more modest than the claim that it refers to the theology of the public realm, because the term “public realm” is an abstraction, as there are only public realms (plural!) that exist in or are mediated by (more or less institutionalized) associations and organizations (plural!), including religious ones (M. Lamb, “Communicative Praxis and Theology: Beyond Modern Nihilism and Dogmatism,” in<italic>Habermas, Modernity and Public Theology</italic>, ed. Don Browning and F. Schüssler Fiorenze [New York: Crossroad, 1992], 111–13).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Browning and Fiorenze,<italic>Habermas, Modernity and Public Theology</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>M. Stackhouse and S. Healey, “Religion and Human Rights: A Theological Apologetic,” in<italic>Religious Human Rights in Global Perspective: Religious Perspectives</italic>, ed. J. Witte and J. van der Vyver (The Hague: Nijhoff, 1996), 490.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Martin Marty, “Religious Dimensions of Human Rights,” in Witte and van der Vyver,<italic>Religious Human Rights in a Global Perspective</italic>, 11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Browning,<italic>A Fundamental Practical Theology</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>P. van Dijk,<italic>Rechten van de mens: Universaliteit versus waardenrelativisme</italic>(Amersterdam: Koninklijke Academic van Wetenschappen, 1994); G. van Hoof, “Human Rights in a Multi‐Cultural World: The Need for Continued Dialogue,” in<italic>Essays in Honour of Wang Tieya</italic>, ed. R. Macdonald (Dordrecht: Nijhoff, 1994), 877–92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>W. van Genugten, “Ignatieffs observaties en dilemma’s onder een internationaal‐rechtelijk vergrootglas,” in<italic>Mensenrechten en terreur</italic>, ed. M. Ignatieff et al. (Budel: Damon, 2002), 90.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>See the project “Sex, Marriage, and Family and the Religions of the Book” in the brochure of the Center for the Interdisciplinary Study of Religion, Emory University, Atlanta, 2003.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>The insights in this article are worked out in greater detail in chap. 13 of Johannes A. van der Ven et al.,<italic>Is There a God of Human Rights? The Complex Relationship between Human Rights and Religion: A South African Case</italic>, ed. Johannes A. van der Ven, Jaco S. Dreyer, and Hendrik J. C. Pieterse (Leiden: Brill, 2004).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Interreligious Interaction from the Perspective of Human Rights</title>
         <p>To put interreligious interaction in a human rights framework, we have to follow a specific detour. This can be justified as follows: in the Western world human rights belong to the cultural judicial domain, a result of viewing Western society from an observer perspective. From this perspective human rights can and should contribute to a free and equal society and even guarantee it step by step. Therefore, I first focus on the observer perspective, the more so because in theology it is often neglected in comparison with the participant perspective. Those who adopt an observer perspective on interreligious problems cannot ignore the fact that religions are not separate entities, not even in the different cultures to which they belong, but are components of the bigger civilizations that have ruled the world. The second step, then, is to look into the problematic interactions between these civilizations—what may be called the struggle of civilizations. The third and final step is to present human rights as an appropriate framework in which to deal with the problematic interaction between religions.</p>
         <sec id="sc3.1">
            <title>Observer Perspective and Participant Perspective</title>
            <p>I shall start with the participant perspective, because we are most familiar with this perspective. It refers to people’s ties with their own civilization, culture, and religion, in terms of which they perceive, interpret, and evaluate their environment and the people, things, and situations in it. We cannot observe the diverse processes and structures in our environment from any angle but that of our own ties and loyalties (and we must encounter them in those terms). We certainly cannot understand these processes, however, if we take the context we live in for granted and regard it as a self‐evident background. A lot of what we do from day to day is done according to ingrained patterns, familiar procedures, and internalized control mechanisms without giving it much thought.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>
            </p>
            <p>The self‐evidence that marks the world as “our world” also forms the perspective in which we encounter “the other” in the person of representatives of another civilization, culture, and religion whose meaning, substance, and contours are foreign to us. Also the other, the “alien” other, and the “strange” other: we view them and face them in terms of the cognitive, affective, and attitudinal schemes that we, from our own experiential field, apply to other people and things. They differ from us in convictions, opinions, emotions, habits, rituals, practices, clothing, gestures, hairstyles, odor, and color.</p>
            <p>It could also be—if we become genuinely interested, which cannot be taken for granted; all we can take for granted is “our world”—that we adopt a more abstract perspective and, by comparing the other’s ideas and customs with our own and those of people we know a little better, try to understand the “other” confronting us. That is when one can speak of an observer perspective. Adopting an observer perspective is like entering a helicopter and ascending from ground level into the sky—not too high, otherwise one can no longer see the tiny men, women, buildings, streets, villages, and cities, but high enough to be able to survey the whole panorama so as to impose some sort of structure on the mishmash of data: a structure of similarities and dissimilarities.</p>
            <p>In the religious domain, too, both perspectives are needed. The participant perspective is necessary to get to know and understand our own religion better, even if we have grown up in it. A religion can only be understood by examining it from the inside, experiencing its myths and rituals from the inside, and joining personally in the community. Conversely, we only get to know the distinctive character of our own religion by comparing its structures and processes with those of other religions and determining the similarities and differences between people’s religious experiences in our own and in other religions. In short, we need to (learn to) switch between the participant and observer perspectives not only in respect of other religions but also in respect of our own.</p>
            <p>To avoid misunderstanding I should point out that the antithesis, “participant perspective versus observer perspective,” is not the same as the antithesis, “self‐perspective versus other perspective,” to be dealt with below. The two are often confused in the literature, so it is important to be alert to the difference from the outset. I can mention at this stage that both antitheses are epistemic; the first one falls in the sociospatial category of proximity and distance (belonging and distancing), whereas the second is an interpersonal category: the dialogue between “self” and “other.” Self‐perspective is in fact a participant perspective in that the self belongs to her religion as an insider, but so is the other perspective: the other belongs to his (a different) religion, and both are aimed at mutual participation. The observer perspective, by contrast, is totally different: the insider belongs, the outsider is detached.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>I shall return to this when I come to interreligious dialogue.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn18">
                  <label>18</label>
                  <p>A. Schütz,<italic>Der sinnhafte Aufbau der sozialen Welt</italic>(Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 1981).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn19">
                  <label>19</label>
                  <p>J. S. Dreyer, “The Researcher: Engaged Participant or Detached Observer? A Reflection on the Methodological Implications of the Dialectics of Belonging and Distanciation for Empirical Research in Practical Theology,”<italic>Journal of Empirical Theology</italic>11 (1998): 2, 5–22.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc3.2">
            <title>Civilization, Culture, and Religion</title>
            <p>I now proceed to look, detachedly as an outsider from an observer perspective, at the broader framework in which cultural and religious problems in present‐day society present themselves. One might be inclined to see this society as comprising so many islands of diverse cultural and religious communities, but they are embedded in larger cultural entities called civilizations. These may be regarded as a kind of broader cultural space or setting encompassing a number of nations, each national culture representing a particular form of the whole. In fact a civilization may be seen as the broadest cultural entity there is, comprising the largest possible cultural space and setting.</p>
            <p>Civilizations are characterized to a significant extent by the religion that forms their core, from which their constituent nations and communities derive their cultural identity and social attributes. This is not to equate civilization with race, for the great missionary religions, Buddhism, Christianity, and Islam, encompass societies comprising a variety of races. Even though civilizations die—they rise, expand, dominate, decline, and vanish, as in the case of the Egyptian and Babylonian civilizations—they are extremely long lasting (<italic>longue durée</italic>, as Fernand Braudel once put it), spanning many centuries if not millennia. They are said to outlive everything and everybody: governments, judicial structures, political systems, and even empires. Not that they are static and rigid: they are dynamic and adapt to new developments, which they in their turn influence.</p>
            <p>Against this background we can distinguish between several civilizations in our day and age, such as the Chinese, Japanese, Hindu, Islamic, and Christian (with a further distinction between Western and Orthodox). Whether there is a Latin American and an African civilization is a topic of debate. Because of the powerful Western influence Latin America may be regarded as a subcivilization of Western civilization with its own attributes. As for Africa, the northern parts and the East Coast are characterized by Islamic civilization, and the southern part by Christian civilization. By contrast, tribal identities are pervasive and intense, giving rise to a sense of African identity that may lead to sub‐Saharan Africa developing into a distinct civilization.</p>
            <p>Today, each and every society displays a multicivilization diversity because of the diversity of cultural and religious communities belonging to the various larger wholes or civilizations. Even before the major migration influxes got under way, at least in Europe, this might have applied on a smaller scale, but because of the massive escalation we are only properly realizing it now. In this new awareness the call for “re‐evangelization” and “re‐Islamization” from fundamentalist and conservative circles features prominently. Whereas formerly people often lived side by side as decent neighbors, accepting each other, we now hear a multicivilization and multireligious saber rattling right round the globe that makes us far more alert than we used to be. This poses enormous problems for the religious communities that constitute the larger civilizations. The crucial question is how they should deal with one another.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc3.3">
            <title>Religious Identity and Power</title>
            <p>Let me examine the realities of interreligious interaction with the aid of a matrix (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tb1">table 1</xref>). It pertains to the various interaction styles that religions employ.<table-wrap id="tb1" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                     <title>Religious Interaction Styles</title>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="tb1"
                           position="float"
                           mimetype="image"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
                  <oasis_0:table xmlns:oasis="//OASIS//DTD XML Exchange Table Model 19990315//EN"
                                 xmlns:oasis_0="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
                                 frame="topbot"
                                 colsep="0"
                                 rowsep="2"
                                 pgwide="1"
                                 orient="port">
                     <oasis_0:tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <oasis_0:colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="11.01pi"/>
                        <oasis_0:colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="11.01pi"/>
                        <oasis_0:colspec colnum="3" colname="3" colwidth="11.01pi"/>
                        <oasis_0:tbody valign="top">
                           <oasis_0:row>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="1" morerows="1"/>
                              <oasis_0:entry namest="2"
                                             nameend="3"
                                             colsep="0"
                                             rowsep="1"
                                             align="center"
                                             valign="bottom">
                                 <sc>Identity</sc>
                              </oasis_0:entry>
                           </oasis_0:row>
                           <oasis_0:row>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="2"
                                             colsep="0"
                                             rowsep="1"
                                             align="center"
                                             valign="bottom">Particularistic</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="3"
                                             colsep="0"
                                             rowsep="1"
                                             align="center"
                                             valign="bottom">Universalistic</oasis_0:entry>
                           </oasis_0:row>
                           <oasis_0:row>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0">Power:</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
                           </oasis_0:row>
                           <oasis_0:row>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"> Strong</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">(1) Miltant style: exclusivism and inclusivism</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">(2) Open style: dialogue</oasis_0:entry>
                           </oasis_0:row>
                           <oasis_0:row>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="1"> Weak</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="1">(3) Isolationist style: sectarianism</oasis_0:entry>
                              <oasis_0:entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="1">(4) Adaptive style: inculturation</oasis_0:entry>
                           </oasis_0:row>
                        </oasis_0:tbody>
                     </oasis_0:tgroup>
                  </oasis_0:table>
               </table-wrap>
            </p>
            <p>According to this scheme religious interaction is determined by two dimensions: differences in senses of identity and differences in power. The first difference relates to the fact that one religion has a particularistic sense of identity and another religion has a universalistic sense of identity. Particularistic means that one is not actively aware of other religions and, if one is, one regards their meaning as restricted and wants to limit their influence. Universalistic means that while one is actively aware of other religions and has a message for them—a message for the whole world—one approaches them with an open attitude. The second difference relates to the degree to which one religion occupies a position of strength and the other a position of weakness. If a religion has constructed a particularistic identity and occupies a position of considerable power, it will adopt a militant attitude toward the other religion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tb1">table 1</xref>, cell 1); if it perceives its identity from a universalistic perspective and occupies a position of power, it will adopt an open style (cell 2); if its identity is particularistic, but it occupies a weak position, it will tend toward isolation (cell 3); and if it experiences its identity as universalistic but occupies a position of weakness, it will look for adaptation (cell 4).</p>
            <p>This matrix helps us to understand some of the interaction styles between religions referred to in theology of religions, which will be dealt with in more detail below. In terms of this theology the first cell refers to a militant style expressed in exclusivism and inclusivism. The identity of these religions is particularistic vis‐à‐vis other religions, and they occupy a position of power. Exclusivism is found in fundamentalist, orthodox, and conservative communities, which insist that they are the sole purveyors of truth and salvation. Inclusivism differs from exclusivism in that it acknowledges at least elements of truth and salvation in other religions. It does not view other religions from its perspective but always from the perspective of their own religion, and it seeks to incorporate the elements of truth in other religions into its own.</p>
            <p>The second cell refers to an open style expressed in what theology of religions calls dialogue, which one encounters in liberal communities. This style stems from a universalistic rather than a particularistic orientation, with the result that liberal communities are tolerant and respectful toward other religions and, since they wield considerable power, are ready to engage in dialogue.</p>
            <p>Remarkably, theology of religions fails to describe the other two styles encountered in interreligious interaction, namely, isolationism and adaptation. An isolationist attitude is typical of all minorities with a particularistic identity but little power, as in the case of sects. An adaptive style is the product of a universalistic identity combined with lack of power, expressed in enculturation. Examples of enculturation abound: Catholicism in India with its Hindu culture; Protestantism in Africa with its indigenous cultures; and Christianity—transcending Catholicism and Protestantism—in Europe with its humanism and Enlightenment.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Modern societies constitute, as I said, multicultural rather than monocultural systems. But the problem is even more complex: they are not just multicultural but multicivilization systems. The evidence is there: countries with several cultural and religious communities that belong to the same civilization may have conflicts verging on provocation, as in Northern Ireland. But countries accommodating different civilizations become cleft countries, in which the various communities drift apart—witness the Balkan war and all sorts of recurrent uprisings in Asia (India, Sri Lanka, Malaysia, Indonesia) and Africa (Sudan, Nigeria, Tanzania, Kenya, Ethiopia/Eritrea). History shows that intercivilization contacts are not always close, are usually cool, and many times are hostile, and when peace prevails it is at most “cold peace.”</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn20">
                  <label>20</label>
                  <p>See Phillip Jenkins,<italic>The Next Christendom: The Coming of Global Christianity</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), 107–39.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc3.4">
            <title>Human Rights</title>
            <p>As noted already, I believe that the whole complex of problems associated with multicivilization society should be viewed from an observer perspective. This perspective ensures the tolerance necessary for interreligious interaction before any dialogue is feasible. This tolerance is claimed rather than practiced, as history teaches us that “the blood of thousands is at the doors of churches, synagogues, and mosques … that of dissidents, women, children, and sojourners, most prominently.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>
            </p>
            <p>The proper framework for promoting the kind of tolerance needed for a peaceful interreligious coexistence and interaction is a constitutional state founded on human rights. The constitutional state is an important form of political organization, because it is grounded in a constitution in the sense of the nation’s compact with itself, implying that the people—“we, the people,” as the opening words of many constitutions, including the U.S. constitution, state—have agreed to be bound by it. Constitutionalism means that citizens are able to assess the legitimacy and propriety of public policies. This in its turn means that government is publicly accountable and its politics have to be transparent. It also means that all laws that are promulgated must accord with the spirit and the letter of the constitution and must not exceed the constitutionally entrenched limits and procedures that are designed to prevent arbitrary exercise or arrogation of power. The normative premise on which the constitution is based is human dignity. Not only is it the basis of the constitution, in a sense it also forms a connecting link with human rights, of which it is the first and most important principle.</p>
            <p>Here I would like to add that the relevance of the constitutional state and human rights is evaluated positively not only in the West but also by scholars and their intellectual communities in Islamic countries, as can be seen from the declarations by Muslim conferences, statements by individual Muslim scholars, as well as scholars in other religions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>Moreover, almost every state in the world signed not only the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (1948) but also the United Nations Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action Adopted at the World Conference on Human Rights (1993), which constituted customary international law.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>
            </p>
            <p>When I propose that the complex of multicivilization problems should be tackled in the framework of human rights, this does not imply an approach based on specific human rights, for example, the first generation of human rights, which includes the rights to freedom of conscience, religion, association, assembly, and freedom of the press. I also do not have in mind the rights to elementary necessities of life, like food, housing, health care, work, and education, all of which belong to the second generation of human rights. Nor do I have in mind the third generation of human rights, for example, the right to a healthy environment or cultural and religious minority rights, however important they may be. I have in mind an approach premised on the fundamental principles of human rights—human dignity, freedom, and equality, including the principle of nondiscrimination. Hence, my approach focuses on the religious implications of these principles.</p>
            <p>
               <italic>Human dignity</italic>.—In nearly all constitutions human dignity is of overriding importance. It does not derive from the Christian tradition but from the Stoics, as do many other concepts, for instance, in the Pauline corpus. In Stoicism it acquired a meaning that is relevant to our context: instead of signifying only the dignity associated with the political position a person occupies in public life, it indicates the intrinsic dignity peculiar to every human being. Kant defined it clearly with his distinction between the concepts of price and value: human beings have intrinsic value and cannot be sold at any price. It is accompanied by this wise Kantian maxim: a human being may never be used as a means only but always at the same time as an end in itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>The reason is that human dignity is founded in the person’s moral autonomy. If Pico della Mirandole had ever read Kant, he would probably have said that this makes it possible for people to see their lives as their own project, and Boethius would have said that it made humans as project‐creating beings aesthetically beautiful.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>
            </p>
            <p>If human beings are autonomous in designing their own life projects—an autonomy they cannot be deprived of, since that is what makes them human and constitutes their human dignity—then the same applies to their religious life: that, too, may be seen as a project that they design autonomously. The person’s own identity, values, rituals, and practices form the very core of this project. Any contempt of whatever religious conviction or habit—be it fundamentalist Christian, liberal‐Christian, Islamic, Hindu, or indigenous—is harmful. Nor is shame about one’s own rituals and convictions compatible with such a project.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>The reason is that both contempt and shame undermine the person’s self‐esteem and self‐regard, thus violating human dignity.</p>
            <p>A serious objection against the concept of autonomy is that it does not allow for the polarity between activity and passivity that controls human life every moment of the day, and that this concept permits only an activist anthropology that conflicts with the contingency, vulnerability, fragility, and finitude of human life. Does this concept of autonomy really not allow for the three forms of passivity that Ricoeur identified—the passivity that my body imposes on me, the passivity inherent in our mutual recognition of each other, and the passivity that provides the soil in which the seed of the voice of conscience lodges?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>In my view autonomy and passivity are not necessarily mutually exclusive, for why can people not handle these forms of passivity autonomously? Why can they not accept the transience of physical life with dignity? Why can they not consort with a beloved with dignity, when the supreme form of loving lies in being loved? And why can they not be a sounding board for the voice of conscience with dignity? Finally, why should their autonomy conflict with their creaturely relation to God, since autonomy is in fact implicit in creation, as Georg Essen rightly puts it?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>Freedom</italic>.—Freedom of religion is a much vaunted principle, but the practice in which it should be realized often reflects the reverse. This principle has solid support in Christian tradition insofar as it concerns freedom of the act of faith. Many patristic theologians, especially Augustine, insisted that faith should not be forcibly imposed, a point that was constantly reiterated in the Christian tradition: during the Roman period it was not to be enforced by the sword, during the crusades by the lance, during the “discovery” of America by the musket, during the period of colonization by the cannon, or during the Inquisition by the rack. But apart from being free to accept the faith, were people also free to change their belief? Were they equally free, if they wanted to take their own position within their religious community, occasionally to turn their back to these communities, and perhaps, eventually, live their lives as skeptics, agnostics, or outright atheists? How did religions react to that, especially the Christian religion?</p>
            <p>A critical analysis of the Vatican II document on freedom of religion brought me to the conclusion that people are indeed free in their choice of a religion, but this freedom, at least for Catholics, ceases once they have accepted the faith. Then only obedience to the institution representing the church’s doctrinal authority counts. Whoever does not submit to this authority can expect some form of punishment, for example, a reprimand, a warning, denial of the sacraments (which seems to be the case in the United States in 2004 with John Kerry, the Catholic presidential candidate, who is in favor of prudential abortion laws and stem cell research), compulsory public recantation, suspension, expulsion from office, laicization, and excommunication. Thus it is often stated in defense of the church—at least the Catholic Church—that it is a case of the “right of truth” versus the “right of the person” and that the latter is obviously subordinate to the former.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>But if one is to avoid lapsing into personifying abstractions, the right of truth is tantamount to the right, hence the power, of a particular group to dictate to others what the truth is, so the right of the person is set up in opposition to the right of the group, here the church’s doctrinal authority.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>
            </p>
            <p>In human rights thought the freedom of religion is usually taken to mean that one is free to join a religion, practice it, and change one’s religion for another, as the Universal Declaration of Human Rights of 1948 puts it (art. 18). It also implies giving up religion altogether and living life as a practicing atheist.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>It also contains the right to make propaganda, either as a church member or as an atheist, and as a church member to express freely one’s faith within the church, which raises the issue of the intraecclesiastic aspect of religious freedom.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>Equality</italic>.—The principle that human relations should be determined by equality, implying equal treatment in equal cases, is as old as human rights and democratic thought, which is rooted in Greek antiquity, notably in Aristotle’s philosophy. According to his<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>such equality, in the sense of equal treatment in equal cases, is the cornerstone of justice. Of course, it is far from clear what the expression “equal cases” means: What is the criterion of equality? Which cases are to be compared with which? Which and how many cases in terms of time and place? At all events, equality is assigned a “position of preeminence” in human rights thought.</p>
            <p>The crux of the equality clause is a prohibition of direct and indirect discrimination on grounds of race, gender, sex, pregnancy, marital status, ethnic or social origin, color, sexual orientation, age, disability, religion, conscience, belief, culture, language, and birth. Indirect discrimination is discrimination that is neither conscious nor intended and may not even be discernible on the surface, for instance, when something is taken for granted but still has a discriminatory impact and leads to discriminatory effects. Significantly, those who discriminate have what is known as the “onus of proof”: they have to show that they are not discriminating, instead of those who feel discriminated against having to prove their case. This is what makes the equality clause so important: it articulates the principle that all people have equal worth on the basis of their human dignity.</p>
            <p>In religious communities, where one would expect equality to be paramount, there are numerous examples of indirect discrimination in the sense of being neither conscious nor intended. What should one make of the exclusion from church celebrations of members who cohabit outside wedlock, divorcees who have remarried legally but without religious confirmation of the new union, or practicing homosexuals? What should one make of the exclusion from a religious funeral service of religious community members who, after mature deliberation, conscientiously and honorably decided on euthanasia? What should one make of religious community members being excluded from leadership positions because they are female, married, or frankly homosexual? If onus of proof enters into these cases at all, some religions may have real problems.</p>
            <p>The equality clause has implications not only for interaction within religions but also for dealings between religions. Let us take the example of the Vatican document<italic>Dominus Jesus</italic>, a declaration of the Catholic Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith from 2000, which, we know, testifies to undiminished exclusivism and endeavors to prevent syncretic tendencies.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>Does this also imply a prohibition of interreligious dialogue? Not explicitly, but in spirit it does. This document says that dialogue with other religions should be conducted according to the principles of freedom and equality (no. 22). With regard to freedom, it refers to the aforementioned, halfhearted statement of Vatican II about freedom of religion, and when it comes to equality one also needs to be watchful. The document defines equality as follows: “Equality, which is a presupposition of inter‐religious dialogue, refers to the equal personal dignity of the parties in dialogue, not to doctrinal content, nor even less to the position of Jesus Christ—who is God himself made man—in relation to the founders of the other religions” (no. 22). Although this document mentions human dignity, it does so in a way that is entirely indifferent to the beliefs of adherents of other religions and the rites in which these beliefs are expressed. The same sentence reveals the crux of the problem: the position of Jesus Christ “who is God himself made man,” as the document puts it in terms of a “christology from above.” The next phrase is no less noteworthy. It does not state: “Jesus Christ … in relation to the other founders of religions,” but “in relation to the founders of the other religions.” Jesus is elevated above the founders of other religions in a unique and absolute manner as qualitatively superior.</p>
            <p>What does this imply for communication? Because whatever religious dialogue may or may not be, it is a form of communication. Whoever separates an attitude of respect for the other from the other’s beliefs breaks the first rule taught in first‐year communication sciences: “Pay attention to both attitude and content.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>But such a person also disregards an elementary philosophical insight, namely, that people’s identity cannot be separated either from their convictions or from the ritual practices in which they enact their identity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>Respect that ignores convictions and practices is hollow and rather smacks of disrespect.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn21">
                  <label>21</label>
                  <p>J. Witte, “Introduction,” in Witte and van der Vyver,<italic>Religious Human Rights in Global Perspective</italic>, xx–xxi.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn22">
                  <label>22</label>
                  <p>For declarations by Muslim conferences, see the Teheran International Conference on Human Rights (1968), the Universal Islamic Declaration of Human Rights (1981), the Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam (1990), the Arab Charter on Human Rights (1994), and the Organization of the Islamic Conference on Human Rights in Islam (2002). For statements by individual Muslim scholars, see Sultan Hussein Tabandeh,<italic>A Muslim Commentary on the Universal Declaration of Human Rights</italic>(London: F. T. Goulding, 1970); Abdullahi Ahmed An‐Na’im,<italic>Toward an Islamic Reformation: Civil Liberties, Human Rights, and International Law</italic>(Syracuse, NY: Syracuse University Press, 1990); Ann E. Mayer,<italic>Islam and Human Rights: Tradition and Politics</italic>(Boulder, CO: Westview, 1991); Mohammed Hashim Kamali,<italic>Freedom of Expression in Islam</italic>(Cambridge: Islamic Texts Society, 1997); Farid Esack,<italic>Qur’an, Liberation and Pluralism: An Islamic Perspective of Interreligious Solidarity against Oppression</italic>(Oxford: Oneworld Publications, 1997); Talal Asad,<italic>Formations of the Secular, Christianity, Islam, Modernity</italic>(Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2003); Fatima Mernissi, Sadik Al‐Azm, and Abdulkarim Soroush,<italic>Religie en moderniteit</italic>(Breda: De Geus, 2004). For statements by scholars in other religions, see Joseph Runzo et al.,<italic>Human Rights and Responsibilities in the World Religions</italic>(Oxford: One World, 2003).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn23">
                  <label>23</label>
                  <p>R. Drinan,<italic>The Mobilization of Shame: A World View of Human Rights</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2001).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn24">
                  <label>24</label>
                  <p>Immanuel Kant,<italic>Groundwork of the Metaphysics of Morals</italic>(New York, 1964).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn25">
                  <label>25</label>
                  <p>J.‐P. Wils, “Würde,” in<italic>Handbuch Ethik</italic>, ed. M. Düwel, C. Hübenthal, and M. Werner (Stuttgart: Metzler, 2002), 537–42.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn26">
                  <label>26</label>
                  <p>Martha Nussbaum,<italic>Hiding from Humanity: Disgust, Shame, and the Law</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2004).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn27">
                  <label>27</label>
                  <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn28">
                  <label>28</label>
                  <p>Georg Essen,<italic>Die Freiheit Jesu, Der neuchalkedonische Enhypostasiebegriff im Horizont neuzeitlicher Subjekt‐ und Personphilosophie</italic>(Regensburg: Pustet, 2001).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn29">
                  <label>29</label>
                  <p>W. Kasper, “Religionsfreiheit II. Katholische Kirche,” in<italic>Staatslexikon, Recht, Wirtschaft, Gesellschaft</italic>, vol. 4 (Freiburg: Herder, 1988).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn30">
                  <label>30</label>
                  <p>Ernst Wolfgang Böckenförde,<italic>Religionsfreiheit: Die Kirche in der modernen Welt</italic>(Freiburg: Herder, 1990), 23–24, 63–64, 110–11.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn31">
                  <label>31</label>
                  <p>M. Evans,<italic>Religious Diversity and Religious Liberty as Human Right</italic>(paper presented at the UNESCO Human Rights Conference, Malta, May 1999, 5).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn32">
                  <label>32</label>
                  <p>R. Sebott,<italic>Religionsfreiheit und Verhältnis von Kirche und Staat: Der Beitrag John Courtney Murrays zu einer moderner Frage</italic>(Rome: Universita Gregoriana Editrice, 1977), 216ff; and M. Broyde, “Forming Religious Communities and Respecting Dissenter’s Rights,” in Witte and van der Vyver,<italic>Religious Human Rights in Global Perspective</italic>, 203–34. As for the right to change one’s religion, it should be noted that—at the insistence of Islamic states, who were fearful of missionary activities by other religions—this right was watered down in subsequent international law declarations to the right to “adopt” a religion or worldview and to have a religion or worldview of one’s own choice (International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, 1966, art. 18), whereas the European Human Rights convention of 1950 (art. 9) explicitly recognizes the freedom to change one’s religion (P. Wuthe,<italic>Für Menschenrechte und Religionsfreiheit in Europa</italic>[Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 2002], 102–11).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn33">
                  <label>33</label>
                  <p>C. van Wijnbergen, “Reacties op de verklaring<italic>Dominus Jesus</italic>in het Duitse taalgebied,”<italic>Concilium</italic>37, no. 3 (2001): 162–67; Phillip Jenkins,<italic>The Next Christendom: The Coming of Global Christianity</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002), 197. Joseph Cardinal Ratzinger, “Declaration `Dominus Jesus,' On the Unicity and Salvific Universality of Jesus Christ and the Church” (Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, Vatican City, August 2000).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn34">
                  <label>34</label>
                  <p>P. Watzlawick et al.,<italic>Pragmatics of Human Communication: A Study of Interactional Patterns, Pathologies, and Paradoxes</italic>(New York: Norton, 1967).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn35">
                  <label>35</label>
                  <p>Paul Ricoeur, “De la métaphysique á la morale,” in<italic>Réflections faite: Autobiographie intellectuelle</italic>(Paris: Esprit, 1995).</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Interreligious Dialogue in the Perspective of Human Rights</title>
         <p>I have now described the complexity of multicivilization problems in the interaction between the diverse cultures and religions in modern society from an observer perspective and indicated that the constitutional state and human rights provide an appropriate framework for the human dignity, freedom, and equality that they should accord each other. The aim is to prevent religious apartheid and cold peace between religions from deteriorating into cold war, conflict, and strife. That does not rule out interreligious dialogue, as I pointed out, but it has to be situated in a framework of constitutionalism and human rights. One should not expect too much from this framework, for it cannot be assumed that age‐old civilizations, each encompassing many nations and peoples, will put their beliefs, values, and norms at stake in transforming dialogue just like that.</p>
         <p>No, not just like that. But to regard interreligious dialogue, including its transforming orientation, as totally impossible would be going to the other extreme. Because I definitely see a modest but essential place reserved for interreligious dialogue, I shall now examine it more closely. To draw its outlines as clearly as possible I locate it in the debate on Alan Race’s trichotomy of exclusivism, inclusivism, and pluralism, from which it emerged, at least in a reconstructive sense. One could say that it arose as a solution to the dilemma posed by exclusivism and inclusivism, on the one hand, and pluralism, on the other. I shall explain this more fully to demonstrate that the dilemma is incorrectly stated: it is a false dilemma.</p>
         <p>This insight dawned on me after puzzling for years about a contradiction between theology and empirical research. In theology pluralism is evaluated negatively, whereas in empirical research it is evaluated positively. I must concede that there is no worldwide empirical research project on which I can base my opinion in this instance, but at least one cross‐cultural research project has been conducted in the Netherlands, Germany, India, and South Africa, respectively, the last one in South Africa on four consecutive occasions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>I asked myself where this contradiction comes from. I think that I have located its source in the false dilemma theologians have created between exclusivism and inclusivism, on the one hand, and pluralism, on the other, as we will see.</p>
         <sec>
            <title/>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn36">
                  <label>36</label>
                  <p>J. A. van der Ven, “Religious Values in the Interreligious Dialogue,”<italic>Religion and Theology</italic>1, no. 3 (1994): 244–60; P. Vermeer and J. A. van der Ven, “Looking at the Relationship between Religions: An Empirical Study among Secondary School Students,”<italic>Journal of Empirical Theology</italic>17 (2004): 36–59; H.‐G. Ziebertz, “Religious Pluralism and Religious Education,”<italic>Journal of Empirical Theology</italic>6, no. 2 (1993): 82–99; F.‐V. Anthony, “Interreligious Conflict and Participation: An Empirical Study among the Youth in Tamil Nadu, India” (paper presented at the Second Conference of the International Society of Empirical Research in Theology, Bielefeld, Germany, April 22–24, 2004); van der Ven et al.,<italic>Is There a God of Human Rights?</italic>
                  </p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc4.1">
            <title>Exclusivism, Inclusivism, Pluralism, and Dialogue</title>
            <p>This discussion started with Race’s trichotomy of exclusivism, inclusivism, and pluralism, to which the model of interreligious dialogue was added as a solution to the dilemma—in my opinion a false dilemma—of exclusivism and inclusivism, on the one hand, and pluralism, on the other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>That, at least, is my reconstruction of the debate. Race’s trichotomy is not without problems, considering the flood of literature published afterward. It is said to be characterized by rigidity and oversimplification but, despite its limitations and hazards, still useful.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>
            </p>
            <p>The studies following the trichotomy of exclusivism, inclusivism, and pluralism all recapitulate the arguments for and against the first two models and weigh the pros and cons. However, the third model, pluralism, is not evaluated in terms of positive and negative aspects but mainly in comparison with the other two models, while attracting a flood of criticism. There is no point dealing with this in detail—one can read it anywhere. Let me merely sum up the gist of it. A cardinal objection is the cultural and religious relativism allegedly evinced by the model of pluralism: Christianity and the other religions are all just vehicles of knowledge about, and devotion to, God, contextually confined as they are both temporally and spatially. The cultural relativism evident in this view inevitably leads to religious relativism, which is incompatible with Christianity’s claims, not merely to universality but also to uniqueness and absoluteness. Christianity not only has a universal message for all peoples in all ages; that message also contains the unique truth, transmitted to us only through the unique, divine person of Jesus the Christ; and this truth is also absolute, not to be experienced by any other religion. That, in a nutshell, is the critique of pluralism in the Vatican document<italic>Dominus Jesus</italic>of 2000.</p>
            <p>Of course there are major problem areas in this regard, but the questions remain—what kind of universalism, what kind of uniqueness, and what kind of absoluteness are at issue. But that is not the point I want to pursue right now. In my opinion the real problem lies elsewhere. In the literature the three models are usually put on a par, and the pluralist model is then singled out, consciously or unconsciously, for criticism in terms of the exclusivist and inclusivist models. I believe that a very different approach is possible if one abandons the notion that the three models are on a par.</p>
            <p>To this end I reintroduce the distinction made earlier in this article between the participant and observer perspectives. I recall that the exclusivist and inclusivist models are approaches from a Christian participant perspective. This means that those who identify with Christianity view their tradition from their insider perspective and then examine and evaluate other religions from that same perspective. Pluralism proceeds differently. It examines all religions, including the one that the person identifies with (e.g., Christianity), from an observer perspective. One adopts the position of an outsider, also toward Christianity, and describes how individuals and groups in the various religions are inspired by divine manifestation with a veridical force that stimulates them to follow the way of (active and/or passive) salvation, individually and/or collectively, spiritually and/or materially.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref>That is what distinguishes pluralism from the other two models: one distances oneself and takes a sort of helicopter view of the diverse ways followed by people in different religions in their search for truth, oneness, and wholeness. In this they appear to be inspired by myths and rituals, which function as cognitive, affective, and enacted models of reality, and to be motivated by these myths and rituals as models for reality to attain reconciliation and peace in their own microcosm and macrocosm.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref>
            </p>
            <p>In other words, whereas pluralism is criticized from a participant perspective, particularly that of exclusivism and inclusivism, because of its emphasis on cultural and religious contextualism and relativism, from an observer perspective it can be viewed in a wholly positive way. It ensures tolerance, respect, and comprehension, especially if applied in a framework of constitutionalism and human rights. It does not achieve the same depth of comprehension that can be reached with a participant perspective, but it puts religious particularities in a broader classificatory framework, thus revealing aspects that remain hidden from a myopic insider view.</p>
            <p>My postulate is that the interreligious dialogue model emerged as a solution to a dilemma that strikes me as a false dilemma. The dilemma is that theologians feel bound to reject exclusivism and inclusivism for being overly particularistic and to reject pluralism for being overly relativistic. To get rid of the dilemma, according to my reconstruction, they then create a new model and append it to Race’s trichotomy: the dialogue model. But there is no dilemma: what is taken for one is a false dilemma. After all, there can be no dilemma if we relate statements made from a participant perspective, such as that of exclusivism and inclusivism, to statements made from an observer perspective, such as that of pluralism. I am not saying that the statements could not pose problems for each other—they certainly, almost invariably, do—but not a dilemma. That only arises when the two kinds of statements are put on a par. And in the case of statements made from two such different perspectives it does not arise.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn37">
                  <label>37</label>
                  <p>A. Race,<italic>Christians and Religious Pluralism: Patterns in the Christian Theology of Religions</italic>(London: SCM, 1983).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn38">
                  <label>38</label>
                  <p>P. Knitter,<italic>No Other Name? A Critical Survey of Christian Attitudes toward the World Religions</italic>(New York: Maryknoll, 1988), 25–26.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn39">
                  <label>39</label>
                  <p>T. Ryba, “Manifestation,” in<italic>Guide to the Study of Religion</italic>, ed. W. Braun and R. McCutcheon (New York: Cassell, 2000), 45–56.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn40">
                  <label>40</label>
                  <p>Clifford Geertz, “Religion as a Cultural System,” in<italic>The World Yearbook of Religion: The Religious Situation</italic>, ed. Douglas K. Cutler (London: Evans, 1969), 639–88.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc4.2">
            <title>The Interreligious Dialogue: Two Pairs of Perspectives</title>
            <p>Even if there is no dilemma between exclusivism and inclusivism, on the one hand, and pluralism, on the other, it remains questionable how one can relate the dialogic model to the participant perspective and the observer perspective. I now will reflect on this question, because I have argued that the dialogue model could play a modest but essential role in the broad framework of the complex of multicivilization problems in society.</p>
            <p>This is not easy, because the point at issue in the dialogue model has two pairs of perspectives: first, the participant and observer perspective, and second, the perspective of self and other. The importance of these two pairs of perspectives has already been alluded to. I have indicated that both pairs entail epistemic angles; they merely differ in regard to their regulatory principles. The observer versus participant perspective is regulated sociospatially in terms of distance and proximity (distancing and belonging), whereas the self‐perspective versus other perspective has an interpersonal regulatory principle. But both self‐perspective and other perspective are participant perspectives and are aimed at mutual participation. It is essential to distinguish between the two sets of contrasts lest one ends up in conceptual confusion. A further point is that, while the self‐perspective versus other perspective is more important for interreligious dialogue, a lesser but nonetheless essential role is reserved for the other pair, participant versus observer perspective. I shall not confine myself to these general comments but will explicate them with reference to three conditions for interreligious dialogue: information exchange, perspective exchange, and perspective coordination.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>Information exchange</italic>.—The first condition cannot easily be overestimated, since many prejudices result from a lack of information. These prejudices have three aspects that impede dialogue: stereotypes used (unknowingly) when viewing the other party, ethnocentrism that depicts the other party as an outsider and thus as inferior, and finally more or less subtle forms of discrimination that humiliate the other party. Merely supplying written information is not sufficient to neutralize lack of information; research has shown that the best method is contact with the other party with a view to “live information exchange.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref>It seems that ecclesiastical documents satisfy this condition, as they do not advocate mutual exposition (from an observer perspective) but mutual witnessing (from a mutual participant perspective), like the Vatican declaration “Dialogue and Proclamation” from 1991 (nos. 40 and 55). The problem with these documents is that interreligious dialogue mostly stops short at witnessing. Hence the interreligious dialogue is restricted to mutual witnessing and does not lead on to the two other conditions I mention, perspective exchange and perspective coordination. As a result the dialogue is truncated, deficient. Can this mean anything else than the traditional view of mission in which dialogue, despite claims to the contrary, is subordinated to the growth of the church?</p>
            <p>To this I would add that information exchange that consists mainly of mutual witnessing, plus supplementary information to put such testimony in a proper context, occurs from two participant perspectives: those of the self and of the other. After all, the two parties are informing each other, each from its own religious tradition, about the beliefs, values, norms, rituals, and customs they hold dear and what these mean to them. Put differently: it is not a case of communicating religio‐scientific, but theological, insights.</p>
            <p>
               <italic>Perspective exchange</italic>.—The idea that perspective exchange differs from information exchange, as well as the fact that it is essential for interreligious dialogue, crops up only sporadically in the theology of religions. There are three possible reasons: philosophical, civilizational, and religious reasons. Concerning the first reason: following a period of modern subject philosophy and ego psychology the insight in the “other as other,” “the other as<italic>totaliter aliter</italic>” in postmodern philosophy, has influenced people in such a manner that the simple fact of perspective exchange, as the basis of all relationships and communication of (higher animal species and) people, may have been lost. This is actually depressing, because the concept already has a long history. It emerged for the first time in American pragmatism, specifically in the symbolic interactionism of G. H. Mead.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>Since then there has been a lot of research in both developmental and social psychology, and it has become a standard textbook concept.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">44</xref>In the past twenty years we have witnessed intensified interest in this concept, specifically in cognitive science, including cognitive psychology and cognitive anthropology, whether these disciplines use different, traditional, or new terms like role taking, social attribution, empathy, and “theory of the mind.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref>According to research in these disciplines, perspective exchange seems to be a natural disposition of (higher animal species and) people; it starts developing at a very young age, and its roots lie in the functioning of the brain. Expressed negatively, the concept refers to the socioemotional disposition that enables people to step out of their own perspective in which they experience and interpret situations, other people, and themselves. It indicates, moreover, their ability to let go of their own desires, preferences, intentions, plans, and expectations. Expressed positively, it is the socioemotional disposition that enables people to switch to the perspective of the other and to experience and interpret situations, other people, and themselves the way in which the other would. It indicates, furthermore, the ability to understand, comprehend, and appreciate the other’s desires, intentions, hopes, and expectations from that person's perspective, as well as sensitivity to their goals, disappointments, and aims. It can also be expressed in terms of the concepts I have just mentioned: one is able to take on other people’s roles the way in which they perceive them (role taking); one has the capacity to ascribe to others the aims, desires, expectations, convictions, feelings, and plans they ascribe to themselves (social attribution); one enters into the life of the other in order to experience what they experience (empathy); and one is able to decipher other people’s minds and read their emotions, desires, preferences, intentions, plans, and convictions (“theory of mind”).</p>
            <p>The second reason why the concept of perspective exchange occurs so infrequently in the jargon of theology of interreligious dialogue is this: cognitive scientific research has indicated that dispositions, like the disposition for perspective exchange, which is a natural function of the brain, can be blocked out by the influence of the person’s culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">46</xref>This is more likely if that culture is characterized by a constant marking of boundaries between “us” and “them,” when it focuses on exclusion rather than inclusion and exhibits hegemonic tendencies, as pointed out by the cognitive scholar J.‐P. Changeux.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">47</xref>In my opinion it is important to inquire frankly and critically to what extent Christianity manifests these characteristics, not only in terms of what is currently regarded as exclusivism and inclusivism but since its early beginnings. At all events, this question has opened my eyes to both the religious and moral particularism in biblical books such as the law codes in the Pentateuch, Isaiah, and Psalms and revealed to what extent there is some kind of breakthrough in Paul’s letter to the Romans and the earliest texts in the synoptic Gospels on the acts of Jesus.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">48</xref>Meanwhile, Sunday after Sunday, all these books are read and contemplated, and for centuries they have directed religious socialization and profoundly influenced the experience, thoughts, and actions of innumerable Christian groups.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">49</xref>In other words, Christianity, or rather Christians, like all people, are naturally capable of perspective exchange but may be hindered from doing so by unconscious and conscious forms of religious and moral ethnocentrism that have crept into the origins, history, and culture of their tradition—at least, that is my hypothesis in this article.</p>
            <p>Note that the perspective exchange required again involves a self‐perspective and an other perspective, both of which are participant perspectives. After all, both partners proceed from their own participant perspective and try to adopt the other’s participant perspective; hence, their aim is mutual participation. One could put it more formally. Partner A proceeds from his perspective and from that perspective furnishes information—both cognitive and affective—about the beliefs and ideas current in his religion (A/A). Partner B does the same from her perspective (B/B). Partner A then switches perspectives and tries to fathom B’s beliefs from her participant perspective (AB). Partner B does the same, reversing the roles (BA).</p>
            <p>
               <italic>Perspective coordination</italic>.—However complicated perspective exchange may be in itself, there is a third condition for interreligious dialogue: perspective coordination. Let us first say what perspective coordination is not. It is not a fusion of horizons, as Hans‐Georg Gadamer would have it, because that entails the risk of confusing differences.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">50</xref>What is needed is differentiated perspective coordination. Like cultural differences, religious differences should be analyzed into different elements. These are then treated as selected differences in desires, intentions, beliefs, and practices, which need not be accepted and agreed on blindly but which should be discussed and evaluated from the perspective of truth and justice, thus relating them to specific religious desires, wants, convictions, norms, habits, and practices.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">51</xref>Who would be ready to accept the totality of beliefs and practices in one’s partner religion when one cannot even do so for one’s own religion, troubled as one may be by certain more or less crucial elements of it?</p>
            <p>How does one conduct such discussions and evaluations of selected differences in perspective coordination? I believe that the figure of an imaginary judge offers a solution, thus applying to interreligious dialogue an insight developed by Ricoeur in the field of historical research.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">52</xref>In a nutshell: to avoid partiality in such dialogue one requires an imaginary judge, who functions in the dialogue partners’ minds as a kind of regulatory principle of impartiality. He guides—in the partners’ imagination—the discussion and evaluation of the aforementioned selected differences.</p>
            <p>The point at issue has nothing to do with neutrality, because a judge is never totally neutral and can never be, but with impartiality: a judge strives to be as impartial as possible. In a nutshell: dialogue partners strive to judge both their own and the other religion, at least in some aspects, like an impartial judge.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">53</xref>
            </p>
            <p>What does a judge do? Let me subdivide the process of judgment, somewhat artificially, into three stages. First, the judge takes the parties seriously, treats them as equals, and assumes their authenticity and sincerity. He hears the parties out as fully as possible and takes note of the information provided by their witnesses and expert witnesses. In addition, the judge takes into account the specific situations of the two parties, especially factors that determine their singularity, uniqueness, and precariousness. Second, before passing judgment he weighs the arguments for and against the claims pressed by the parties and tries to determine the pros and cons, effects and side effects, of these. Finally he pronounces a judgment, advancing a concise argument for it. In so doing he is aware that this is merely what Ricoeur would call an “attestatory judgment,” that is to say, a judgment that is fragile, albeit carefully considered, based not on mathematical proof but on rational insight, and not on logical decision but on prudential decision; a judgment not intended to stand for all eternity but based on current data and insight that may come up for review if new information or insight is ever presented.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">54</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Again I need to comment on the kind of perspective exchange or, rather, perspective exchanges, that are at issue. Perspective coordination is more complicated than either information exchange or perspective exchange. What does a judge do when we view her actions from the angle of the two sets of paired contrasts I have identified: that of the participant self‐perspective and other perspective, and that of the participant and observer perspective? In the first stage the judge performs a participant perspective exchange, trying to transpose herself to the perspectives of both parties in turn. She establishes their situations and contexts, what their beliefs and practices are, what reasons they advance for these, what consequences they link with them, and so on. In this way she seeks to transpose herself to the “world” of each party, that is to say, she adopts their participant perspectives. But at some point she has to distance herself. That is the second stage, when she looks as an outsider at the beliefs and practices, the reasons for them, and their consequences. In other words, she adopts an observer perspective. Finally, in the third stage she has to deliberate in order to arrive at what Ricoeur calls an “attestatory judgment” or a “wise judgment in situation.” This deliberation entails a dual exchange of perspectives: first an exchange of the participant perspectives of both parties to which she keeps transposing herself, and second, an exchange of participant and observer perspectives.</p>
            <p>The latter is important, for however hard judges try to stand in the shoes of both parties—which they have to keep doing to the very last minute—ultimately they have to take a position above the parties, for they in fact occupy the position of a “third party.” This is analogous to what is known as the accusatorial principle that was probably already current in Roman law but has certainly functioned in canon law since Gregory I. It requires that the two parties, accuser and accused, be tried on an equal footing by a third party, carefully distanced from both and above them.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">55</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the process of judgment entails, in the first stage, a participant self‐perspective and other perspective, in the second an observer perspective, and in the third a dual perspective exchange—one between the participant self‐perspective and other perspective and one between the participant and observer perspectives. This vividly illustrates the importance of maintaining a distinction between the two sets of paired contrasts. As noted already, the observer and participant perspectives fall in the sociospatial category of distance and proximity, while the two participant perspectives, self‐perspective and other perspective, fall under interpersonal dialogue aimed at interpersonal participation.</p>
            <p>The question is, What criteria does the judge apply in reaching his verdict? I believe that there are two: a theoretical and a practical criterion. Both these criteria are fraught with problems, but I confine myself to just one of these. The theoretical criterion has to do with the striving for truth, where one must distinguish between truth claims and regimes of truth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">56</xref>Religions quite rightly present truth claims, but any claim to possessing the truth, which is typical of exclusivism and inclusivism, is an obstruction to interreligious dialogue, if not to truth itself. Hence I cannot see how one can (want to) achieve interreligious dialogue from an exclusivist or inclusivist position. Striving for truth in dialogue of any kind is difficult enough in itself.</p>
            <p>However difficult striving for truth can be, it cannot and may not be abandoned, especially when one realizes that in this area we are merely “on the way to the path of truth.” What kind of truth is at issue? Or rather, which aspects of truth—correspondence, coherence, and/or pragmatic truth? In the case of correspondence truth I follow Donald Davidson, who stresses that in the search for truth we have no direct access to the reality “behind” the various versions of reality that we human beings entertain, but that we can proceed on the principle of epistemological charity, assuming a fair amount of overlap between these versions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">57</xref>Coherence truth strikes me as equally important, since incoherence may be taken to signify epistemic confusion or even chaos, which conflicts with the order and unity that one ultimately expects the truth to possess. As for practical truth, it has time‐honored credentials dating back at least to high scholasticism and was advocated at the beginning of the twentieth century by the pragmatic philosopher William James and, in the latter part of that century, by the equally pragmatic philosopher Habermas. They concur on the notion that the truth of diverse claims is proven in everyday practical life.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">58</xref>Browning, as well, time and again underlines the importance of this pragmatic approach of truth in his writings.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">59</xref>Besides, coherence and practical truth may be regarded as two aspects of one and the same conception of truth, namely, semantic and pragmatic coherence truth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">60</xref>In the context of this article I cannot but interpret this pragmatic truth in terms of justice, as articulated in human rights, particularly in the principles of human dignity, freedom, and equality.</p>
            <p>By way of summary: in this article I have argued that interreligious interaction, first of all, should be approached from an observer perspective and, hence, should be placed in an intercivilization context in which human rights can function as a directive for the application of the principles of human dignity, freedom, and equality—all principles that relate to respect and tolerance. This links up with the notion of pluralism in theology of religions. In this context interreligious dialogue can fulfil an important function if it meets three conditions: information exchange in the form of mutual witnessing; perspective exchange, with all the attendant problems; and perspective coordination. Close analysis of this kind of interreligious dialogue reveals two kinds of perspective exchange: that of self‐perspective and other perspective, and that of observer and participant perspective. Here human rights once more act as a criterion: a criterion of truth and justice. This is my attempt at explaining why young people, in test samples of empirical theological research done on different continents, assign pluralism priority over all other approaches, including interreligious dialogue.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn41">
                  <label>41</label>
                  <p>J. A. van der Ven,<italic>Formation of the Moral Self</italic>(Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1998), 272.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn42">
                  <label>42</label>
                  <p>J. Berry et al.,<italic>Cross‐Cultural Psychology, Research and Applications</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002), 371–75.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn43">
                  <label>43</label>
                  <p>George H. Mead,<italic>Mind, Self, and Society</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1972).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn44">
                  <label>44</label>
                  <p>R. Selman,<italic>The Growth of Interpersonal Understanding</italic>(New York: Academic Press, 1980); R. Selman and D. Byrne, “A Structural‐Developmental Analysis of Levels of Role‐Taking in Middle Childhood,”<italic>Child Development</italic>45 (1974): 803–6; and M. Hoffman, “Empathy, Social Cognition, and Moral Education,” in<italic>Approaches to Moral Development: New Research and Emerging Themes</italic>, ed. A. Garrod (New York: Teachers College Press, 1993), 157–79.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn45">
                  <label>45</label>
                  <p>B. Omdahl,<italic>Cognitive Appraisal, Emotion and Empathy</italic>(Mahwah, NJ: Erlbaum, 1995); Steven Pinker,<italic>How the Mind Works</italic>(New York: Norton, 1997), and<italic>The Blank Slate: The Modern Denial of Human Nature</italic>(New York: Penguin, 2002); J.‐P. Changeux and P. Ricoeur,<italic>What Makes Us Think?</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2002), 134–78; Berry et al.,<italic>Cross‐Cultural Psychology, Research and Applications</italic>, 114–46; R. Winston,<italic>The Human Mind</italic>(London: Bantam, 2003), 86–90.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn46">
                  <label>46</label>
                  <p>A. Damasio,<italic>The Feeling of What Happens</italic>(New York: Harcourt, 2000), 57.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn47">
                  <label>47</label>
                  <p>Changeux and Ricoeur,<italic>What Makes Us Think?</italic>236–37.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn48">
                  <label>48</label>
                  <p>Van der Ven et al.,<italic>Is There a God of Human Rights?</italic>chap. 4.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn49">
                  <label>49</label>
                  <p>R. Eisinga and P. Scheepers, “Etnocentrisme in Nederland” (PhD diss., Katholieke Universiteit Nijmegen, 1989).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn50">
                  <label>50</label>
                  <p>Hans‐Georg Gadamer,<italic>Wahrheit und Methode: Grundzüge einer philosophischen Hermeneutik</italic>(Tübingen: Mohr, 1960).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn51">
                  <label>51</label>
                  <p>See S. Griffioen and J. Tennekes,<italic>Het debat over culturele universalia en de praktische implicaties daarvan: Paper voor Conceptuele Studies, Sociale Cohesie/De Nederlandse Multiculturele en Pluriforme Samenleving</italic>(Den Haag: NWO, 2001), 39–40; Lawrence Blum, “Recognition, Value, and Equality: A Critique of Charles Taylor’s and Nancy Fraser’s Accounts of Multiculturalism,” in<italic>Theorizing Multiculturalism: A Guide to the Current Debate</italic>, ed. Cynthia Willett (Malden, MA: Blackwell, 1998), 73–99.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn52">
                  <label>52</label>
                  <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>La mémoire, l’histoire, l’oubli</italic>(Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 2000), 413–36.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn53">
                  <label>53</label>
                  <p>Georg Lohmann, “Unparteilichkeit in der Moral,” in<italic>Die Öffentlichkeit der Vernunft and die Vernunft der Öffentlichkeit Festschrift für Jürgen Habermas</italic>, ed. Lutz Wingert and Klaus Günther (Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 2001), 434–58.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn54">
                  <label>54</label>
                  <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>,<italic>Le juste</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1995), 185–92,<italic>La mémoire, l’histoire, l’oubli</italic>, 413–36; cf. J. Searle,<italic>Rationality in Action</italic>(Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2001), 61–96.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn55">
                  <label>55</label>
                  <p>K.‐Th. Geringer, “Prozess, kanonischer,”<italic>Lexikon für Theologie und Kirche</italic>8 (1999): 673.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn56">
                  <label>56</label>
                  <p>Bruce Lincoln, “Theses on Method,”<italic>Method and Theory in the Study of Religion</italic>8, no. 3 (1996): 225–27.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn57">
                  <label>57</label>
                  <p>Donald Davidson,<italic>Inquiries into Truth and Interpretation</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1985).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn58">
                  <label>58</label>
                  <p>William James,<italic>Pragmatism</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1975); and Jürgen Habermas,<italic>Wahrheit und Rechtfertigung: Philosophische Aufsätze</italic>(Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 1999).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn59">
                  <label>59</label>
                  <p>Don Browning, “Internists of the Mind or Physicians of the Soul: Does Psychiatry Need a Public Philosophy?”<italic>Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry</italic>27 (2003): 131–37.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn60">
                  <label>60</label>
                  <p>Jürgen Habermas,<italic>Faktizität und Geltung: Beiträge zur Diskurstheorie des Techts und des demokratischen Rechtsstaats</italic>(Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 1993), 272–91.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>I trust that what I have written here clarifies, in the course of the discussion, the relevance and significance of the seven characteristics of Don Browning’s style of theologizing. Following in his footsteps I hope to have made a contribution to the public theology he espouses—the first characteristic I mentioned at the beginning of this article. I trust that I have likewise shown my interest—the second characteristic—in the institutions determining people’s concrete daily lives, as well as influencing and coloring their norms, values, and religiosity. I have referred specifically to the institution of law, especially human rights law. The third characteristic is also clear: as Browning’s study of marriage and the family is conducted in a global, more especially an interreligious perspective, I have paid due attention to interreligious interaction and dialogue, which dominate not only politics and the mass media but also the conversations in our living rooms. Both of us are convinced that any public theology must be characterized by an empirical approach—the fourth characteristic. In his family project, Browning not only collaborates with social scientists but also incorporates their empirical research into the goal and content of his project. In this article, I, too, have used insights from political and social sciences, as well as empirical‐theological research, in order to relate the assumptions and principles of interreligious interaction and dialogue directly to empirical reality.</p>
         <p>Nevertheless, empiricism does not have the last word—it perhaps never has the last word, not even in what might be called “positivist empiricism,” and certainly not in practical theology, as this discipline is characterized by the interaction between empiricism and normativeness. We both share this conviction—the fifth characteristic. Therefore human rights—no matter how contested they are, which is neither surprising nor extraordinary—offer an important perspective, as the normative criteria they embody always require critical and constructive reflection. In the last part of the article I have even presented them as regulative principles of truth and justice, as a result of which they offer a kind of worldview‐related and morality‐related infrastructure for the social institutions that determine human actions in societal and personal life—the sixth characteristic. After all, for both Browning and me the ultimate issue is—the seventh characteristic—the vitality of the Christian tradition in terms of relevance and identity in the context of a multicivilization society.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
