<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">lusobrazrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100267</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Luso-Brazilian Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00247413</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15489957</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">25654810</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>O Mal e a Metamorfose em Machado de Assis</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>José Luiz</given-names>
                  <surname>Passos</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2009</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i25654803</issue-id>
         <fpage>57</fpage>
         <lpage>74</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2009 Board of Regents of the University of Wisconsin System</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/25654810"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>It has become commonplace to describe Machado de Assis's characters and narrators as deeper than those of his contemporaries, and his novels as representations more creatively ambiguous than most literary depictions of nineteenth-century Brazil. In this essay I argue that throughout his novels psychological depth is a function of moral imagination; and a troubled moral imagination is a necessary condition for the literary representation of the modern self. Machado's protagonists are able to fashion the public presentation of their selves by imagining alternatives to their origins, desires, and social predicaments. They have in their pasts a burden they need to overcome, and while doing so they find themselves in conditions of freedom and harm. Evil then arises as a consequence of moral dynamism, in so far as it becomes a project for undoing the other. The genesis of a radical conception of free will and evil in Machado's narratives goes back to his translation of Victor Hugo's The Toilers of the Sea (1866). His concern with a more meticulous characterization of inwardness deepens between Iaiá Garcia (1878) and Dom Casmurro (1899), when adopting the structure of a confessional narrative he arrives at a balance between disguised motives (malice), double chronology (nostalgia), and human life as an unfolding, reversible, and self-aware process (metamorphosis). To frame Machado's strategy for depicting moral change, I take from Augustine's Confessions the suggestion that retrospection is the only way of restoring the identity of someone whose self is marked by his or her sense of dissimilarity with the past. Finally, from Kant and Paul Ricoeur I draw the elements for a further consideration of evil as an invitation to think differently about seeing, judging, and narrating human life.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>por</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>&lt;bold&gt;Trabalhos Citados&lt;/bold&gt;</title>
         <ref id="d894e116a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e120" publication-type="other">
Agostinho. Confissões. Trad. J. Oliveira Santos e A. Ambrósio de Pina. São Paulo:
Editora Nova Cultural, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e130a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e134" publication-type="other">
Borges, Dain. "The Relevance of Machado de Assis." Imagining Brazil. Ed. Jessé
Souza and Valter Sinder. Oxford: Lexington Books, 2005. 235-50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e144a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e148" publication-type="other">
Bosi, Alfredo. Machado de Assis: o enigma do olhar. São Paulo: Editora Ática, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e155a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e159" publication-type="other">
Dixon, Paul. Retired Dreams: Dom Casmurro, Myth and Modernity. West Lafayette:
Purdue University Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e170a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e174" publication-type="other">
Hugo, Victor. Os trabalhadores do mar. Trad. Machado de Assis. Rio de Janeiro:
Abril Cultural, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e184a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e188" publication-type="other">
Kant, Immanuel. "Religion within the Boundaries of Mere Reason/' Religion and
Rational Theology. The Cambridge Edition of the Works of Immanuel Kant.
Ed. Allen W. Wood and George Di Giovanni. New York: Cambridge University
Press, 1996. 39-216.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e204a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e208" publication-type="other">
Machado de Assis, Joaquim Maria. Dom Casmurro. Edições críticas de obras de
Machado de Assis. 2 ed. Rio de Janeiro: Civilização Brasileira; Instituto Nacional
do Livro, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e225" publication-type="other">
-. laiá Garcia. Edições críticas de obras de Machado de Assis. 2 ed. Rio de
Janeiro: Civilização Brasileira; Instituto Nacional do Livro, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e235a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e239" publication-type="other">
Meyer, Augusto. Machado de Assis, 1935-1958. 4 ed. Pref. Alberto da Costa e Silva.
Rio de Janeiro: José Olympio Editora; Academia Brasileira de Letras, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e249a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e253" publication-type="other">
Monteiro, Pedro Meira. "O futuro abolido: anotações sobre o tempo no Memo-
rial de Aires." Machado de Assis em linha 1 (2008): 17pp., Jun. 2008 &lt;http://www
.machadodeassis.net/download/O futuro abolido.pdf/&gt;.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e267a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e271" publication-type="other">
Morris, Herbert. On Guilt and Innocence: Essays in Legal Philosophy and Moral Psy-
chology. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1976.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e281a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e285" publication-type="other">
Nunes, Benedito. "Machado de Assis e a filosofia." No tempo do niilismo e outros
ensaios. São Paulo: Editora Ática, 1993.129-44.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e295a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e299" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. Evil: A Challenge to Philosophy and Theology. Trans. John Bowden.
London: Continuum, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e309a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e313" publication-type="other">
-. The Symbolism of Evil. Trans. Emerson Buchanan. Boston: Beacon Press,
1969.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e327" publication-type="other">
Shakespeare, William. Othello. Ed. E.A.J. Honigmann. The Arden Shakespeare.
3 ed. London: Thomas Nelson &amp; Sons Ltd, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e337a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e341" publication-type="other">
Silva, Francisco Vaz da. Metamorphosis: The Dynamics of Symbolism in European
Fairy Tales. New York: Peter Lang, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d894e352a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d894e356" publication-type="other">
Velho, Gilberto. Projeto e metamorfose: antropologia das sociedades complexas. Rio
de Janeiro: Jorge Zahar Editor, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
