<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">utopianstudies</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Utopian Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">1045991X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21549648</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">utopianstudies.23.1.0113</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/utopianstudies.23.1.0113</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Rhetorical Function of Utopia:</article-title>
            <subtitle>An Exploration of the Concept of Utopia in Rhetorical Theory</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Marlana Portolano</string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <bold>Marlana Portolano</bold>is an associate professor and the director of the Master of Arts in Humanities program at Towson University in Maryland. She teaches rhetoric from ancient to contemporary times as well as literature courses that overlap with the rhetorical tradition, and she is the author of<italic>The Passionate Empiricist: The Eloquence of John Quincy Adams in the Service of Science</italic>(State University of New York Press, 2009). She is currently working on a study of rhetorical issues in Deaf culture.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">23</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">utopianstudies.23.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>113</fpage>
         <lpage>141</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/utopianstudies.23.1.0113"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>During the past fifty years, utopian studies solidified a functional definition of utopia in the Marxist tradition, which has encouraged a broad focus on social process rather than on content. In the liberal-humanist tradition, however, utopia is often treated as strictly a matter of form and content, particularly genre. I argue that the key to a functional definition of utopia in the liberal-humanist tradition is the Western tradition of rhetoric. Since its beginnings in ancient culture, rhetoric has been concerned with verbal or symbolic persuasion using values and ideals of the audience. I explain how the utopian impulse is inherent in rhetorical theory from ancient to modern times, including examples from Plato, Cicero, eighteenth-century rhetoricians Hugh Blair and George Campbell, and modern rhetorician Kenneth Burke. I give a rhetorical reading of Mannheim and Bloch and suggest other areas of cross-pollination between rhetoric and utopian studies.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title/>
         <p>According to Ruth Levitas, author of perhaps the most complete history of the concept of utopia to date, there have been three different bases for defining utopia as an academic area of study: content, form, and function.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>This type of division has been relatively consistent since Lyman Tower Sargent's early articles in the first issues of<italic>Utopian Studies</italic>.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>Of these three areas of study, the theoretical function of utopia remains least developed. However, during the past fifty years, utopists have begun to solidify a positive, functional definition of the concept in the Marxist tradition. Even so, as Levitas points out, “utopia” in the older, liberal-humanist tradition neglects function and focuses on matters of form and content, especially in terms of genre and various canons of utopian works. This seems to be a serious gap in the field of knowledge claimed by utopists, but one that is easily remedied by taking a closer look at the history of rhetoric. This article suggests that the concept of utopia found in traditional theories of rhetoric constitutes the functional definition of utopia in the liberal-humanist tradition that Levitas has claimed missing.</p>
         <p>In order for utopian studies to develop a broad understanding of utopia that liberal humanists and Marxists can share, a functional definition should be available for both of these traditions or any hybrid of the two. Making the liberal-humanist tradition of rhetoric a basic feature in the developing discourse of utopian studies will solve this problem and lead to fruitful explorations in both fields. In its classical origins rhetoric is a highly developed art for finding or inventing all available means to persuade an audience. For those who have studied rhetoric deeply, a psychological and political understanding of persuasion would suggest an imagined better world existing in the minds of both speaker (rhetor) and audience. Without naming it “utopia,” rhetorical theorists have consistently referred to an imagined, often idealized aspect of place as a part of<italic>ethos</italic>, the artistic rhetorical proof that is drawn from an audience's collective character. In a corresponding vein, rhetorical practices are inherent in what utopian theorists Herbert Marcuse and Ernst Bloch have called the “utopian impulse.” For these writers, and as a working definition for this article, utopia is treated as a function of human social thought and communication. For the purposes of my argument, “utopia” is not an impossible political dream or a philosophical ideal but, rather, any kind of symbolic expression of hope for a better world, whether in a concrete future or in fictional or spiritual realms, and no matter if that expression is considered in a positive or negative light.</p>
         <p>Rhetoric, like utopian studies, is a discipline with perpetual disagreement over the basic definition of its subject. Rhetoric has been explored both as a body of theories on how to influence people through spoken or written language and as a practice or<italic>techne</italic>of eloquence and power in communication. Some scholars define rhetoric as the systematic art of inducing belief (James Murphy, Erika Lindeman); some, as a constitutive process of cultural formation (Marc Fumaroli, Paulo Valensio). There are modern rhetoricians who focus almost exclusively on language used in particular situations (Kenneth Burke, Lloyd Bitzer), while others expand the scope of rhetoric beyond language to any symbolic media (Sonja and Karen Foss, Charles Bazerman). This essay proceeds with the traditional assumption that rhetoric means nothing if it claims to be everything. In this vein, rhetoric is not synonymous with all communication. It is a mental and symbolic art with an aim of persuasion or, more broadly, identification with an audience so that it might be predisposed over time to act in certain ways. This is a postmodern point of view that borrows freely, but not exclusively, from classical rhetorical theories and is influenced strongly by the work of Kenneth Burke.</p>
         <p>This essay considers some general connections between utopian thought in the recently developed discipline of utopian studies and in the study of rhetoric as it has existed for approximately 2,500 years. I begin with a brief introduction to the concept of utopia as a figure of thought in rhetorical theory in general, along with an attempt to define a “utopian rhetoric.” This is followed by examples of utopian thought in canonical texts of classical rhetorical theory and in important works on rhetoric and preaching in the Enlightenment, especially those by Hugh Blair and George Campbell. The next section attempts a rhetorical interpretation of utopian thought in Marxist-influenced cultural theory. In particular, I review Mannheim, Marcuse, and Bloch to show the similarity of their ideas to certain aspects of traditional rhetoric. In the final section I briefly touch on modern and postmodern rhetorical theory, particularly the work of Kenneth Burke, and propose a functional view of utopia in the liberal-humanist tradition: one that is founded in classical ideas but influenced by all of these threads of thought, including aspects of Marxist historical philosophy.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>The Function of Utopia in Rhetoric-as-Persuasion</title>
         <p>Utopian studies have evolved to the point of establishing a history of the concept of utopia. However, what is often left out in utopian studies is how this concept is communicated or mediated via symbols and communicative conventions. This is specifically the province of rhetoric. From this perspective, we might define a utopian rhetoric as the use of symbolic communication in an attempt to move the actual state of human affairs into alignment with an imagined, better state of affairs—that is, a utopia, either one shared by the community or one invented by the speaker or both. All sorts of utopia, then, are forms of rhetoric, but the reverse is not always true. Rhetoric that functions only to sell a product or win a court case at any cost, rhetoric that uses any means necessary to win something transient, will not necessarily reach for a culture's highest ideas of what is good—unless personal gain is itself the highest good. This latter type of rhetoric simply aims at immediate effect in the audience and can be defined as pragmatic. Utopian rhetoric, on the other hand, appeals to broad cultural ideals and organizing principles. It can be equated with what the rhetorical tradition has called “philosophical rhetoric,” and it generally presumes an ethical intention. This type of rhetoric can be both culturally formative and potentially devastating if misused.</p>
         <p>In the classical tradition of philosophical rhetoric from which liberal humanism derived so many of its ideas, utopian thought appears as an ideal<italic>topos</italic>. In their own field of study, utopists have also been faced with the question of “where” utopia is located. It may be an alternate world in the mind of an individual; it may be a fictional or mythical place shared or built in the imaginations of many; it may be actualized in the material world in a geographical place; or it may be some progressive combination of these physical and nonphysical locations. Recent works such as Philip Wegner's<italic>Imaginary Communities</italic>attest to the contemporary renewal of interest in spatial imagination as a topos of utopia.<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>The discipline of rhetoric, beginning with classical treatises on the subject, has much to lend utopian studies in terms of vocabulary for theorizing about the encounter between mental geographies and material, actualized societies located in space and time. Of the five canons of traditional rhetorical study (invention, arrangement, memory, delivery, and style), the canons of memory (<italic>memoria</italic>) and invention (<italic>inventio</italic>) are perhaps most remarkable for their systematized handling of imagined places and imagined temporal realities.</p>
         <p>Early teachers of rhetoric in Greece and Rome taught students to memorize speeches that lasted for up to several hours by imagining the speech's content as symbolic objects arranged in an architectural dwelling. The first step was to imprint on the memory a set of<italic>loci</italic>or places in this imagined architecture. Cicero gave a clear description of such a device: “These forms and bodies, like all things that come under our view, require an abode, inasmuch as a material object without a locality is inconceivable. Consequently, one must employ a large number of localities which must be clear and defined and at moderate intervals apart, and images that are effective and sharply outlined and distinctive, with the capacity of encountering and speedily penetrating the mind; the ability to use these will be supplied by practice, which engenders habit.”<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>The ancient orator would then move in his imagination through this architecture of memory while he was delivering his speech, visiting each locus in a predetermined order so that his speech would have the structure and arrangement he had composed. The architecture was at first a physical building visited and impressed on the memory of the student, but later imagined architecture might take its place because of the limitless variations available to the creative mind. The more unusual the arches, features, decorations, markings, and even blemishes that might occur in such a building, the more memorable it would be to the orator. Likewise, the more unusual the objects were that were placed in the imagination at each locus, the more likely the orator would remember each idea associated with the object. This method was not designed for exact memorization of words (<italic>verba</italic>) but, rather, the subject matter of a composition (<italic>res</italic>). Some orators were renowned for their extraordinary powers of memory when trained by this method, such as Seneca the Elder, who after hearing two hundred students each speak a line of poetry could recite back the entire composition in order.<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>While the function of these imagined places has been replaced by modern textual and electronic storehouses, there is much for utopists to consider in these early systems of imaginative place-building, with their function of structuring memories for communication. Because the speeches that resulted could then be recorded for historical memory, these mental models incorporated the use of metaphor and analogy in history-building and social formation.<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>The rhetorical canon concerning the invention of arguments (inventio) also speaks of loci (or Gr.<italic>topoi</italic>). Specifically, the lines of argument or commonplaces of deductive reasoning used in rhetoric, derived from the ancient system of dialectical reasoning, were often memorized by students as mental “places” where the orator could go to invent a plethora of rhetorical backing from which to pick and choose in composing a speech. The common Aristotelian topoi included pairs of opposites for use in public argumentation, such as better or worse, more or less, possible or impossible, and advantageous or disadvantageous. More specialized topoi existed for each area of discourse. This use of loci or topoi is more figurative here than in the classical art of memory, but the terms are worth noting.</p>
         <p>What is more pertinent to utopian studies in classical rhetorical inventio is the division of compositions into three main genres: forensic, deliberative, and epideictic. The division is a matter of<italic>when</italic>the event in question has taken place. Deliberative rhetoric urges plans or policies for the future. Forensic rhetoric makes a judgment about past events. And epideictic, the rhetoric of praise and blame, celebrates the values of the audience in order to meld people together into a whole—for example, a nation or a community. As with any system of genres, a single text may overlap in two or more categories. A utopian rhetoric can be defined with reference to these terms as well. Because utopia is an imagined society that currently resides in no time and no place, except perhaps as a fiction, it lends itself to use in deliberative rhetoric about reform: The future imagined as a utopia can be used in arguments for shaping the future. On the other hand, if utopia is imagined in the past, like the subject matter of judicial rhetoric, we may have a golden age place, a conservative utopia. But perhaps most pervasively, utopia is the playground of epideictic persuasion, the category that includes ceremonial speeches, preaching, and a great deal of campaign rhetoric. For some scholars of rhetoric, epideictic also includes teaching.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>All of these types of rhetoric praise values that are considered the ideals of a society or group and blame competing values that would cause divisiveness.</p>
         <p>The rhetorical canon of style (<italic>elocutio</italic>) contains some elements of imagination in traditional figures of thought that were taught to students not only as a means for ornamenting persuasive speech but also for causing ideas to be apprehended by the audience as if they were present to their senses.<italic>Enargia</italic>, for example, is the name given collectively to figures of speech that describe people, places, or actions in such vivid detail that the subject seems present to the mind's eye. Rhetorical delivery (<italic>actio</italic>), too, must be situated in time and space, and though it takes place in the material world and for real audiences rather than imagined ones, the communicative event itself may reference any of the imagined times and places discussed above. The result is the intersection of an imagined society and the material, current society during the act of communication.</p>
         <p>In the practice of rhetoric—in speeches and articles and films and conversations that aim to persuade—utopia may not always take the form of a literal description of an imagined place. It might be inherent, a kind of ideology or mythos that lies behind plans, projects, judgments, praises, or blame. Utopia, in other words, is a functional quality of rhetoric: It aims to make a better society by first imagining it. Seen this way, it matters little what genre of rhetoric a given text falls into. What is common to all three genres is the presence of utopian constructs behind certain rhetorical practices or, put another way, the rhetorical function of the concept of utopia.</p>
         <p>In rhetorical communication, an implied utopia may be present as the imagined better city or society for the rhetor or the audience; or it can be the setting of an imagined rhetorical situation. Either way it partakes of both audience-based ethos and speaker-based ethos in a complex cultural construct. (By<italic>ethos</italic>, I mean the persuasive appeal of character, which is in classical rhetoric a conventional ordering of “higher passions” or good habits.) Gregory Claeys explains that utopia, even if it is imagined as a critical alternative to the present social structure, is always a product of the culture from which it springs. Of course it is conceived as a radical departure from current social practices, but that is because the author espouses critical thoughts about those practices, thoughts that ironically are drawn from and nurtured in the very society he or she imaginatively reinvents.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Because utopia is an imagined symbolic better world, it implies an aim or ideal by which conditions can be judged “better or worse.” Specific utopian fictions or proposals may use utopian comparisons with the present society for critical or even satirical purposes, but an underlying ideal seems ingrained in the very function of persuasive language. Rhetorical theory has also consistently evoked ideals throughout its history and into the present: Plato (when he wasn't warning against rhetoric) gave rhetors the ideal Good to strive for in dialogues such as<italic>Phaedrus</italic>and<italic>Republic</italic>. Cicero's theory gave rhetoric the<italic>orator perfectus</italic>as a personal model of perfect civic leadership to strive for in the mind of the speaker. In the mid–twentieth century revival of rhetoric, Kenneth Burke and Richard Weaver theorized hierarchies of “god-terms”—that is, the ultimate ideals of value-based argument in any given culture. Chaim Perelman was a rhetorical theorist who described the universal audience, an ideal and culturally transcendent audience as it is imagined by any particular speaker from within his or her particular culture. Each of these ideals might be seen as part of an imagined rhetorical situation in the minds of the speaker and the audience. It might be said that Aristotle's classic “rhetorical triangle”—the speaker, the audience, and the subject—is often haloed by a dream triangle that points to one or more ideals of each element of the rhetorical situation. In contemporary philosophies of discourse, this notion calls to mind Habermas's ideal speech situation, in which speaker and hearers are free to express or question any assertion whatsoever, so long as certain implicit social rules are followed. This invocation of ideals is not to suggest that utopian aspects of rhetoric lack a critical function. The opposite may be more accurate if we define critical thought as rhetorician Kenneth Burke does, as “equipment for going beyond the criticism of experience to a criticism of criticism.”<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Another way utopian rhetoric might be explained is by reference to the classical rhetorical concept of<italic>stasis</italic>—the stand a rhetor takes in order to form his or her perspective on an issue. This is a concept that implies both place (a<italic>status</italic>or stand) and a pervasive act of critical thinking. This theory was introduced during the Roman Republic by Hermagoras and was widely used as a way of defining an issue for legal argumentation. Metaphorically, by viewing a staged event from different locations in the arena surrounding it, the orator may see the situation from multiple points of view and better apprehend the reality of what is at issue. Perhaps the broadest critical thought may be gained by seeking a theoretical stasis, which is metaphorically comparable to the highest ring of seats in the bleachers overlooking any given situation in human affairs. Utopia, then, might be defined as an ethically framed view of what a rhetor imagines or sees from those highest seats.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>Some Examples of Utopian Thought in Traditional Rhetorical Theory</title>
         <p>American rhetoric from Winthrop's “City on a Hill” to Reagan's “shining city” to Barack Obama's rhetoric of hope relies on underlying utopian metaphors. In campaign rhetoric, the use of such strategies is pervasive and often transcends political party. Some contemporary theorists might define the function of utopia in terms of cognitive metaphor or cognitive narrative, areas that have overlapped with rhetoric of late.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>10</sup>
            </xref>However, for rhetoric to fulfill a functional definition of utopia for liberal humanists in utopian studies, utopia needs to be present not only in speeches and other forms of public persuasion but also in the canon of classical and liberal-humanist treatises on rhetorical theory—for this is where rhetoric itself is defined. And in fact, these theories do imply or even directly illustrate utopian societies as part of the underlying motive for practicing rhetoric.</p>
         <p>Utopian narratives, in the form of myths and speculations, have been foundational to the tradition of Western rhetoric. Ancient Greek and Roman rhetoricians often grounded their subject by narrating a myth of human nature speculating about the origins of civilized society. Cicero's<italic>De Inventione</italic>contains this well-developed example:<disp-quote>
               <p>There was a time when men wandered at large in the fields like animals and lived on wild fare; they did nothing by the guidance of reason, but relied chiefly on physical strength; there was as yet no ordered system of religious worship nor of social duties; no one had seen legitimate marriage nor had anyone looked upon children whom he knew to be his own; nor had they learned the advantage of an equitable code of law…. At this juncture a man—great and wise I am sure—became aware of the power offered by his mind for great achievements if one could develop and improve it by instruction. Men were scattered in the fields and hidden in sylvan retreats when he assembled and gathered them in accordance with a plan; he introduced them to every useful and honorable occupation, though they cried out against it at first because of its novelty, and then when through reason and eloquence they had listened with greater attention, he transformed them from wild savages into a kind and gentle folk.<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>11</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Classically influenced rhetoricians of the Renaissance and Enlightenment continued Cicero's tradition of teaching the civilizing effects of rhetoric via utopian myth. As the Enlightenment and nineteenth-century worlds embraced democratic ideals, “savage-to-sophisticate” fables provided both a historical pedigree and a vehicle for Christianized and empiricized understandings of human nature and rhetoric. No complete history of this commonplace of rhetorical teaching exists in print, although many historians of rhetoric have noted it in passing. Two of the most enduring textbooks in English were<italic>Lectures on Rhetoric and Belles Lettres</italic>(1803) by Hugh Blair and<italic>The Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>(1776) by George Campbell. Both were used not only for Anglophile academic strivings in eighteenth-century Scotland but also into the nineteenth century in America, for example, at Harvard and Princeton. Both were extensively popular, with Blair's book printed in sixty-two editions and fifty-two abridgments in the first one hundred years of publication and Campbell's having twenty-one complete editions within the same time frame.<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>12</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Hugh Blair, easily the most influential rhetorician of the Enlightenment, evokes a utopian myth to urge the cultivation of taste; in this way his Scottish students at Edinburgh might separate themselves from their identification with the world of colonial roughnecks and become educated and cultured citizens of a legitimate European nation. The principles of taste were what dictated Blair's utopia, just as they justified his views of human nature. In his first lecture on taste, Blair begins to sound very much like Cicero in a description of what might be considered, if not the ideal orator, then the ideal rhetorical critic, who would be the perfect judge of beauty and therefore the determiner of a natural standard of taste:<disp-quote>
               <p>Now were there any one person who possessed in full perfection all the powers of human nature, whose internal senses were in every instance exquisite and just, and whose reason was unerring and sure, the determinations of such a person concerning beauty would, beyond doubt, be a perfect standard for the taste of all others. Wherever their taste differed from his, it could be imputed only to some imperfection in their natural powers. But as there is no such living standard, no one person to whom all mankind will allow such submission to be due, what is there sufficient authority to be the standard? … Most certainly there is nothing but the taste, as far as it can be gathered, of human nature. That which men concur the most in admiring must be held to be beautiful.<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>13</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>Ultimately, there is not much difference in the basic narrative of Cicero's mythic, civilizing orator-leader—itself a kind of ideal Platonic standard, unreachable by everyday political or judicial events—and Blair's impossibly perfect man of taste, also an ideal of Truth with a capital<italic>T</italic>.</p>
         <p>For George Campbell, also an eighteenth-century rhetorician and Protestant clergyman from Scotland, preaching is defined as “the reformation of mankind.” What could be more utopian than that? “Reformation of life and manners—of all tasks ever attempted by persuasion, that which has the most frequently baffled its power.”<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>14</sup>
            </xref>For Campbell, the Christian preacher is closest to being Cicero's ideal orator, and he is closest to being a divine agent in bringing about a utopian society with revealed Truth as its underlying pattern of organization.</p>
         <p>Campbell's treatment of the ends of Christian oratory, preaching, is different from the three ancient genres of rhetoric in that it imagines a new human society according to new, revealed rules for social order. Because of this change, Campbell is drawn toward shared civilizing narratives to establish belief in his principles. This divine inspiration, which Augustine taught as required for persuasion and for the morality of the orator, seems to draw even more deeply than Blair on the idealized, Platonic quality of the myth. Specifically, in Campbell's chapter 10, a hypothetical dialogue involving one of Christ's apostles depicts a divinely inspired orator having all the qualities of the orator perfectus who is the main character in the “civilizing myth.” In a discussion of genres of public speaking, Campbell writes:<disp-quote>
               <p>An apostle or evangelist might have thus addressed the celebrated Athenian [Demosthenes], “You do, indeed, succeed to admiration, and the address and genius which you display in speaking justly entitle you to our praise. But however great the consequences may be of the measures to which, by your eloquence, they are determined, the change produced in the people is nothing, or next to nothing. If you would be ascertained of the truth of this, allow the assembly to disperse immediately after hearing you; give them time to cool, and then collect their votes, and it is a thousand to one you shall find that the charm has dissolved.”<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>15</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The story here is not of an ideal apostle converting multitudes through his divine persuasive gift but, rather, an ideal rhetorical critic with the practical and moral judgment of God himself, who suggests that emotionally driven rhetorical techniques would fail to steer an audience to higher truths. The implication is that if only the apostle spoke and people listened to the word of God through him, their very human nature would be altered. This would occur not by transient emotions, or even through mere rational persuasion like that of the Serpent in the tree, but by infusion with the Truth or the Ideal itself. The ideal preacher offers a return to a golden age before the Fall.</p>
         <p>In another of Campbell's explanations in<italic>The Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>, history becomes the representative empirical data for projecting a prototypical pattern across all of human nature. In this way, the arc of Christian history, including the Crusades and the Reformation, is seen as the archetypal story of social renewal, first through misused rhetoric and then through the utopian rhetorical force that truly civilizes and reforms:<disp-quote>
               <p>At one time you see Europe nearly depopulated at the persuasion of a fanatical monk [Innocent III], its inhabitants rushing armed into Asia, in order to fight for Jesus Christ, as they termed it, but as it proved in fact to disgrace as far as lay in them, the name of Christ and of all Christians among infidels; to butcher those who never injured them, and to whose lands they had at least no better title than those whom they intended, by all possible means, to dispossess; and to give the world a melancholy proof, that there is no pitch of brutality and rapacity to which the passions of avarice and ambition, consecrated and inflamed by religious enthusiasm, will not drive mankind.<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>16</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>What follows is a glowing report of the Protestant preacher's role in the Reformation. This version of the rhetorical civilizing myth alters the classical origin model by adding the events of oppression and liberation to the narrative, leading up to a utopian-inspired and rhetorically constructed social contract.</p>
         <p>In his book<italic>Exodus and Revolution</italic>, Michael Walzer describes a similar story of Moses leading the children of Israel out of Egypt as a historical myth that has had a profound impact on Western societies. He writes: “Since late medieval or early modern times, there has existed in the West a characteristic way of thinking about political change, a pattern that we commonly impose upon events, a story that we repeat to one another. The story has roughly this form: oppression, liberation, social contract, political struggle, and new society…. This isn't a story told everywhere; it isn't a universal pattern; it belongs to the West, more particularly to Jews and Christians in the West, and its source, its original version, is the exodus of Israel from Egypt.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>17</sup>
            </xref>This is essentially the story of Campbell's ideal Reformation preacher. The orator perfectus becomes a liberator, and the utopian myth turns messianic.</p>
         <p>In this light, preaching can be seen as one way to resolve an unfinished “deliberative narrative,” symbolically projecting man's political turmoil, and either his destruction or his cure, into the future. The addition of oppression and liberation to the initial brutish and uncouth condition of mankind in the classical myth transforms the story from a golden age explanation of the civilizing uses of persuasive reasoning into a progressive story of throwing off old orders for the sake of social change. Blair's underlying story of rhetoric blends the classical civilizing myth with the new concepts of taste as inherent to human nature, which seems appropriate to his belletristic approach. This gives him a judgmental or critical function similar to that of the classical forensic rhetorician. Campbell's story of the Crusades and Christian Reformation rhetoric combines an emblematic historical narrative with the original myth, blending in a generalized story of social reform that would be important not only to Protestant demographics in Europe and America but also to historical themes of reform in politics and economics—for instance, in the American jeremiad tradition, a preacherly form of political rhetoric that contributed to Puritan utopian rhetoric and to American protest and campaign rhetoric in general. While the classical origin myth is not future-oriented, the role of the belletristic preacher-orator is, and the combination gives this practice of rhetoric the function of utopian reform rather than an older and simpler model of Golden Age utopianism.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>Rhetoric, Utopia, and Philosophies of Human History</title>
         <p>Traditionally, liberal-humanist veins of utopian studies have been confined to describing the content of texts, categorizing their genre or genres, and listing works that might constitute canons, either old or new. It is the Marxist tradition that has added to utopian studies a definition of utopia in terms of historical function and an overall social process. This expansion of the concept during the twentieth century, particularly after World War II, opened up the field to theoretical ways of looking at history. Utopists who combined both traditions also began to emerge on the scene. Interestingly, these hybrid theorists such as Mannheim and Bloch identified the “utopian impulse” as a basic feature in the nature of man. In their works, utopia is the imaginative means by which material culture is propelled to social change. This is an alteration of the older Marxist position on utopianism: rejection of utopia as “unrealistic,” a position aligning with the “no place” interpretation of More's coined word. This later position is strongly rooted in Karl Marx's own rejection of a merely propagandistic or symbolic transition from capitalist to communist society. Because Marx espoused a materialist, descriptive theory of society that emphasized the inevitability of revolution and struggle, he criticized his contemporaries who were “utopian socialist” community-builders such as Owen and Fourier. These small-community builders seemed to Marx to be potential throwbacks inhibiting the progress of society as a whole. Communitarian socialists, from Marx's point of view, were really reactionaries adhering to a static model of society, not progressives at all.<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>18</sup>
            </xref>For Mannheim and Bloch, however, utopias of this type are valid illustrations of the hope for a better world.</p>
         <p>In some ways, a rejection of utopia would be a rejection of the humanist tradition of rhetoric, which is not propaganda but an art emphasizing reason, personal freedom in the audience, and the development of goodwill: in essence, the practical use of ideals and idealism rather than a pure materialism. In the liberal-humanist tradition, rhetoric and politics have worked toward ideals extracted from the people of the time. This idealism adds an inherently ethical stance in the arts of persuasion and statecraft. Here we are moving out of a limited view of utopia in terms of content and genre and toward a much broader, yet still liberal humanist view of the utopian impulse as a function of the human condition. Utopian studies has tended to rely on sociologists and political scientists for groundwork in this branch of their field, and most of these theorists are Marxist-influenced, although some seem to evolve from liberal humanism in their embracing of aesthetic ideals.</p>
         <p>Karl Mannheim viewed social dreaming not as static and reactionary but as having a positive function of promoting social change. For Mannheim, “utopia” was any group's deeply willed beliefs, which have the potential of actually bringing about change in society. In this way, Mannheim is talking about what I have defined as “utopian rhetoric,” in particular the ethos drawn from an audience's expectations of character and used to persuade them. In his controversial book,<italic>Ideology and Utopia</italic>(1939), he makes a distinction between ideologies and utopias based on their social function. Both are ideas that transcend the actual situation, but ideologies operate to sustain the existing state of things, while utopia functions to change it. Mannheim describes utopias as tending to shatter the current order when they become actual practice, a view more in line with the “good place” interpretation of More's word—that is, an imagined better state, actualized. Utopia in this sense is not a literary genre or a vision of an ideal society with certain traits, because describing utopia in terms of form or content would function to maintain a society rather than change it by means of ideas. Also, literary utopias are individual expressions; only group expressions are truly utopian for Mannheim.<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>19</sup>
            </xref>This utopia is a conceptual construct or mythos not limited to any single text.</p>
         <p>Mannheim's distinction of different types of utopia is functionally a tool for interpreting history, one that can only be applied after the events have passed and settled. From his analytical viewpoint, there are four types of utopian mentalities or impulses, each organized based on the utopia's orientation to time:<list list-type="order">
               <list-item>
                  <label>1.</label>
                  <p>Chiliasm, the leap into the millennial future, whether a messianic religious future or a political future of a new world order. Here, rhetorically, the time orientation is<italic>kairos</italic>, a fulfilled moment in time, such as the theologian Paul Tillich's “eternal now.” This form of utopia is a pursuit of mystical consciousness rather than a political drive.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>2.</label>
                  <p>The liberal-humanist idea of utopia. The time orientation here is a goal set in the future toward which it proceeds in a gradual process. Here utopia is seen as having an educational function, forming the minds of people in a society through developing traditions.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>3.</label>
                  <p>The conservative idea of utopia aims to preserve tradition and is thus a reenactment of the past. Ideology (with its negative connotations, especially Hitler) would be equivalent to the reactionary, making this perspective not a true utopia at all, since utopia envisions change.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>4.</label>
                  <p>The socialist view of utopia is a series of progressive points in history, adjusting to what is realistically possible at each stage. It is not a transcendent ideal that regulates events or educational programs from the outside but, rather, a tendency that adjusts periodically with reference to reality. Historical progress through this utopian process involves gradual “approximation to real life of a utopia that at one time completely transcended history.”<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
                        <sup>20</sup>
                     </xref>
                  </p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>As utopists often recall, Mannheim believed that without utopia, “man would lose his will to shape history and therewith his ability to understand it.”<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>21</sup>
            </xref>It is interesting to note that Mannheim's socialist utopia is not just an imagined vision; it requires some practical enactment of the idea's content. Utopia is an idea that is meant to be realized. Of course, this is difficult to prove since the presumed cause is an idea. His liberal-humanist utopia, on the other hand, is a transcendent ideal that could probably never be reached. However, even a liberal-humanist utopia, one attempted through education in developing traditions, is productive for Mannheim because it indicates a hope for change. Forced stagnation and reaction are, for Mannheim, tantamount to totalitarianism.</p>
         <p>Several aspects of Mannheim's utopia align with classical concepts of rhetoric, and I would like to touch on those here, though a fuller exploration of rhetoric's utopian function will come later. His description of utopia as arising from a social group, rather than an individual, aligns with my description of utopia as a topos of the audience's character stemming from rhetorical ethos. It is essentially a momentary consensus that brings about a new form of society—an entirely classical notion when it appears in rhetorical theory. Mannheim's four types of utopian mentalities are organized based on their relationship to time, in very much the same way that traditional rhetoric is divided into different purposes for persuasion:<list list-type="order">
               <list-item>
                  <label>1.</label>
                  <p>Chiliasm aligns with the rhetorical tradition's theory on<italic>preaching</italic>, as I explained it above, with the utopian mind envisioning a new society sprung suddenly from revealed truth.<italic>Kairos</italic>, the fulfilled moment, is not the only time orientation given to preaching in rhetorical theory, but it certainly figures prominently in Christian millennialism. Moreover, particularly in America, preaching is an important formal ancestor of many types of political rhetoric, from the Puritans to Martin Luther King Jr. Campaign rhetoric especially can fall into this category.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>2.</label>
                  <p>The liberal-humanist idea of utopia focuses on linear progress toward a goal set sometime in the future. This aligns with traditional notions of<italic>deliberative rhetoric</italic>, such as parliamentary models and the gradual process of policy debate.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>3.</label>
                  <p>The conservative utopia reenacts the past. Here there are overtones of<italic>forensic rhetoric</italic>, judging the events of recent history as either good or bad and aiming for a future that is modeled on the “good” constructs.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>4.</label>
                  <p>Socialist utopia is a tendency to arrive at utopias that, at one time, transcended history. Mannheim insists that this is not a purely ideal construct but, rather, a natural, organic evolution. An example would be the progressive integration of socialism and democracy. However, it is impossible to tell the difference between an ideal and an imagined transformation in the future if that transcendent future is perceived as the good society. Therefore, what Mannheim calls the socialist utopia would be roughly equivalent to<italic>epideictic</italic>functions of rhetoric—the use of ideals to bind a social group together in the present moment and ready them to accept realizations of those ideals sometime in the future.</p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>I am not the first to give a rhetorical reading to Mannheim. Paul Ricoeur, in<italic>Lectures on Ideology and Utopia</italic>, also offers a reinterpretation of Mannheim's concept that makes it seem part of rhetorical theory. For Ricoeur, the function of utopia is criticism of systems of authority rather than change itself. Ideology, then, would function to legitimize systems of authority, and utopia would function to challenge systems of authority. At its best, utopia could offer possibilities for the future, but at its worst it would be the unrealizable vision, merely an escape from reality into illusion or fantasy.<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>22</sup>
            </xref>Ricoeur adds a dimension that is particularly attractive to the rhetorician: the screen of symbolic reality rather than only what is materially real and unmediated. This addition would seem to confirm that Ricoeur sees utopia as a type of rhetoric. In particular, his concept of utopia is relevant to the interpretive function of rhetorical theory. The critic cannot exist outside of historical progress (which involves ideology), but to engage in criticism at all one must presume what is utopian—the viewpoint of what is ideal for humankind.<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>23</sup>
            </xref>Mannheim also makes clear in<italic>Ideology and Utopia</italic>that utopia can only be seen as an interpretation of historical events. This is because he sees knowledge as partial and dependent on the social location of the observer—a condition that his idea of utopia shares with contemporary understandings of the rhetorical situation (the social and temporal locations of the rhetor and the audience).</p>
         <p>Ernst Bloch has gained attention in English-speaking scholarship on utopia lately because of translation of his works. Bloch's three-volume utopian work<italic>The Principle of Hope</italic>(trans. 1986) claims to reestablish a lost Marxist idea of utopia. His description of the idea, however, proves to be a mixture of liberal-humanist and Marxist approaches. In particular, he develops an idea of utopia that stems from mysticism and the romantic tradition. This definition of utopia is much broader than what might be encompassed by a concept of utopia in rhetorical theory. It is social dreaming in the broadest sense, including daydreams, myths, fairy tales, and fantastic traveler's tales in addition to the literary utopias that Mannheim had rejected for his socialist utopian categories. As in Ricoeur, however, the emphasis on a mediated, symbolic realm is clear, and Bloch describes the creative arts, literature, music, and architecture as important vehicles for utopia in any given age. However, what is utopian is not just a literary genre but, rather, a function within these arts.</p>
         <p>In the first volume of<italic>The Principle of Hope</italic>, Bloch defines utopia as an “anticipatory consciousness”—the “Not Yet Conscious” as opposed to the “Now.” This is not limited to the content of the unconscious mind but, rather, is refined to mean the creative impulse of what is potentially about to become conscious or actual. This leads in material reality to what Bloch calls the “Not Yet Become.” For Bloch, the material world, like the conscious mind, is constantly in a process of undetermined change and is full of possibility. The utopian dream of a better life is, moreover, a fundamental aspect of being human for Bloch.<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>24</sup>
            </xref>Like modern, psychological understandings of rhetoric in the twentieth century, the function of utopia for Bloch is the anticipation of a transformed future. This seems to have much to do with identification and motivation, two psychological mechanisms that are behind the workings of rhetoric according to modern rhetorician Kenneth Burke, as we shall see in the next section. For Bloch, utopia is the expression of hope not only as an emotion but as an aspect of collective will and goal-making. Its function is not overtly critical, but it is expressive and instrumental—aligning it with rhetorical praxis and the changing of attitudes. Of course, because it aims to change things for the better, it necessarily draws attention to the shortcomings of current reality, so in this sense it is also critical and ethical.</p>
         <p>Like Ricoeur, Bloch distinguishes between utopias that are possibilities and those that are not. The abstract utopia is not possible, so it constitutes fantasy or what he calls “quixotry” after the divine ravings of Don Quixote.<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>25</sup>
            </xref>Bloch tends to be more critical of the abstract function of utopia but nevertheless sees it as interwoven with the more concrete kind of utopia—an anticipatory impulse that is Marxist and more turned toward the material world. It is Bloch's understanding of the Marxist idea of utopia, then, that is equivalent in many ways to the mediated processes that contemporary rhetoricians study. In other words, the anticipatory impulse is what changes attitudes, what impels self-identification with a cause or a group, what persuades people to action—all of which are definitions of rhetoric in contemporary theories authored by rhetoricians such as Kenneth Burke, Chaim Perelman, Stanley Fish, and others. This concept of utopia is essentially the same thing as constitutive rhetoric: It is a way of interpreting textual and symbolic events as they contribute to the realization of cultural norms. In Marxist terms, Bloch would say that human builders have works that already exist ideally, planned out in the imagination, before they exist materially. In this sense, Bloch sees his version of Marxism as a fully developed humanism, resolving historical and cultural conflicts of all kinds: “Precisely this is characteristic of Marxism, as the … quartermaster of the future: it removes the frozen solid antithesis between sobriety and enthusiasm by bringing both to something New and causing both to work together within it—for exact anticipation, concrete utopia.”<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>26</sup>
            </xref>For Bloch, socialism is the ultimate and proper utopian function, though many other kinds of social dreaming must necessarily come before that in the human process of utopia.</p>
         <p>As he expresses in his reading of<italic>Don Quixote</italic>, the idea of faith is central to Bloch's conception of utopia in the West. He sees a positive aspect in religion, which is faith having a goal when reality falls short of material fulfillment. Bloch sees the biblical Judeo-Christian tradition as the historical source of utopian ideation in the West, at least in its mystical, rather than dogmatic, emphasis on transformation (a view he shares with theologian Paul Tillich). For this reason, he can be sympathetic to religion—another way in which he resembles a traditional liberal humanist more than a typical Marxist would.</p>
         <p>The last twentieth-century utopist I will discuss is perhaps the most influential. Herbert Marcuse, a German immigrant of the Frankfurt school, wrote several books that explore utopian ideas. Although his ideas are Marxist, he draws most of his vocabulary from Freud and is considered a psychological utopian critic. He makes his claim, that capitalism causes dystopia, by using Freudian vocabulary to explain how social happiness would include more pleasure and the drive of<italic>eros</italic>in living, not only the fulfillment of a work ethic for its own sake. As a result, the key to Marcuse's positive utopia is the reeducation of desire: Individuals would then want a new lifestyle focusing on quality of life rather than quantity.<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>27</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Marcuse's attitudes about utopia changed over the course of his career, and he remained ambivalent about the chance of realizing a utopian society. At the beginning of his career, his book<italic>Eros and Civilization</italic>(1955) defined utopia as the classic notion of an unachievable but desirable no-place outside of history, but by the end of his career, in his last book,<italic>The Aesthetic Dimension</italic>(1978), he had somewhat accepted Bloch's idea of the socialist “concrete utopia.” The emphases on quality and eros turn Marcuse's theory toward aesthetics, and as a result he favors arts and letters as vehicles for social change in the process of educating human desire. Clearly these are areas that touch on the function of rhetoric as well. Utopia for Marcuse is seen in relation to the progress of social change, and art's role is to keep alive the possibility of social and cultural transformation—the idea of utopia as a possible aim.<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>28</sup>
            </xref>In this way he resembles Bloch; both of them have a rhetorical role for utopian art and mediated productions of all kinds. However, Marcuse's utopia differs from Bloch's in that the present and the future are greatly separated, instead of one continually emerging from the other in an unfolding process. Utopia is a kind of natural, interpersonal eros that could sprout from the ashes of a formerly repressed society—something more chiastic than progressive, to use Mannheim's terms. In the meantime, false needs, such as those evoked through advertising, must be exposed, and true needs should be cultivated in their place. The work ethic would be replaced by a principle of receptivity and nonviolence (i.e., eros), and the highest value would be sufficiency rather than superabundance.<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>29</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>The focus on arts and letters in Marcuse has made him a favorite among literary and cultural critics, and he is inviting to contemporary rhetoricians as well. A rhetorical reading of Marcuse would point out his insistence on the mediated means of communication necessary to convey hope in a future utopia. The engine of social change, one might say, is dependent on a rhetorical, utopian imagination: the art of inventing utopian topics and using them in linguistic, artistic, or architectural works to persuade others in an ethical way to improve and fulfill human desire—rather than pervert it by generating more and more desire for its own sake. In particular, Marcuse's “education of desire” resembles Kenneth Burke's explanation of literary or artistic form as the evocation and fulfillment of desire (more on this presently). There are many ways in which, at first glance, Marcuse's and the other historical theorists' ideas depend on principles of rhetoric, whether they name them as such or not. While there is no consideration of specific rhetorical proofs, reference to utopia itself could be considered a trope or a metaphorical construct. There must always be a consideration of audience in the historical theorists' understanding of points in time and in the transformation of society by means of cultural production and reception. But most strikingly, Marcuse's ethical stance resembles a liberal-humanist mainstay in rhetorical theory, one that stems back to Plato and Aristotle in ancient rhetoric. Rhetoric in the liberal-humanist tradition has always worked hand in hand with considerations of ethics in a human naturist sense. To persuade an audience or to move attitudes in a society, the good of human beings, individual or collective, must be first and foremost in the mind that produces utopian creative output (whether the good is objective or relative). This utopian topos in arts and letters is presented in a way that specifically appeals to, and draws from, the audience, whose mental and emotional state needs to be led to a more transcendent level. Platonic ideals of the good and the true especially resemble Marcuse's Freudian connotations of a return to a previously repressed state of eros, a loving goodwill among mankind. For Plato, the ideal is something that was once known but is forgotten, and the processes of dialectic and rhetoric at their best will lead the repressed audience to a transcendent understanding of the true and the good that are more closely aligned with the higher natural state of humanity. So, while Marcuse and Bloch have embraced the material or “concrete utopia” of the Marxists, there is still an infusion of preconceived ideals that cannot be escaped. It is this early stage of rhetorical invention, amounting to a rhetorical function of utopia, that both Marxist and liberal-humanist traditions can share in a cohesive understanding of utopian studies as a mature and well-defined discipline.</p>
         <p>What is meant by “rhetorical invention” that might enhance utopian studies' array of interpretive tools? Traditionally, it is the artistic creation of all the emotional, ethical, rational, and imaginative means of persuasion possible for a particular social group—the discovery of how to move an audience to psychological cohesion and, eventually, to action. Because rhetoric is usually understood as a civic art, like politics, this kind of invention is essential to any civic utopia.</p>
         <p>Perhaps the resemblance between rhetorical invention and utopia is best illustrated in Plato's dialogue<italic>Phaedrus</italic>. Plato disparaged rhetoric in his earlier philosophical writings, particularly in the<italic>Gorgias</italic>, where he claims that rhetoric is nothing but flattery; it panders to the public and works only to have power for the moment, by showing off with glamour and stirring up desire. For Plato, rhetoric, like the concept of utopia to most twentieth-century Marxists, was an unrealistic waste of time and a useless dream of escape. But in his later works, Plato changed his mind about rhetoric, just as Marcuse changed his about the usefulness of utopia as a concept in history. In the<italic>Phaedrus</italic>, Socrates is in love with the interlocutor in his dialogue, a young man who is intelligent but easily swayed by shows of verbal/symbolic skill and emotional power—the very propagandistic techniques that Marcuse would scrutinize in the need for a reeducation of desire. Socrates, voicing Plato's mature understanding of the function of rhetoric when it is used for the betterment of society, tells the young Phaedrus that “the function of oratory is to influence men's souls.”<xref rid="r030" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>30</sup>
            </xref>For the wisest of orators, who would be the best of political and cultural leaders, the art of rhetoric is one that is informed by long study of human nature but also by a divine inspiration. The inventor in this type of rhetorical work is possessed with a kind of love, a divine Eros, by which he or she leads the multitudes to the good, tempered by self-control. In effect, he conceives of rhetoric as a kind of erotic love that seeks to persuade the beloved (that is, the audience, whether an individual or the social collective in a state). The function of Plato's rhetoric in the<italic>Phaedrus</italic>, like Marcuse's and Bloch's function of utopia, is to use imagination and emotion to lead constituents toward belief in a fuller humanity, a true expression of the good in human nature.</p>
         <p>To further establish the common chords in Plato and Marcuse, there is Socrates's analogy of rhetoric to painting, a comparison that is compatible with Marcuse's and Bloch's emphasis on artistic production. Specifically, Socrates is speaking of rhetoric in the media of writing. He says, “You know, Phaedrus, that's the strange thing about writing, which makes it truly analogous to painting. The painter's products stand before us as though they were alive, but if you question them, they maintain a most majestic silence.”<xref rid="r031" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>31</sup>
            </xref>Even the setting of the dialogue reverberates with utopian concepts. Socrates and Phaedrus walk outside the city walls in a kind of nowhere to have this dialectical conversation about rhetoric, the function of which is actual progress inside the walls of Athens. In this same way, Marcuse's utopian function for the arts refers to a forgotten and repressed good in the city, one that can only be nourished for material growth through nonmaterial, symbolic communication and persuasion in transcendent goodwill.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s05">
         <title>Utopia in Postmodern Rhetorical Theory</title>
         <p>So many twentieth-century rhetorical theories can be said to have utopian aims that just a list may be enough to persuade utopian studies scholars of the theoretical and interpretive potential available to them in this thriving discipline. Any rhetorical theorist who claims that rhetoric may be the answer to avoiding physical violence or war, or that it may be the cure for ills in society that result from ideological differences, has utopian ideas about rhetoric's function. The theories of Chaim Perelman, Richard Weaver, Stephen Toulmin, Mikhail Bakhtin, Wayne Booth, Stanley Fish, and others all seem to fit into this model to a greater or lesser degree. Twentieth-century theories of rhetoric often arose from historical circumstances involving war and what the theorists saw as the abuse of rhetoric, so understanding social processes and substituting a “good rhetoric” in order to build a better society is something they see as an antidote. Rhetoric, like utopia, is inherently an ethical concern from this point of view. The fact that several of these rhetoricians have been influenced by the Marxist utopists I just discussed is evidence of cross-pollination in the two contemporary fields—or perhaps more accurately, the lack of distinct differences between them at all. Like all areas that seem to be lumped under “cultural studies,” there is so much borrowing and generalizing that it is a struggle to speak of distinct disciplines. Nevertheless, there are creative and interpretive benefits to the mix, including a wealth of terminologies from which to choose.</p>
         <p>To delve into the foundations of some of these views, the most obvious representative is Kenneth Burke—who is a veritable field of study in himself. Because he has been so foundational and influential in contemporary rhetorical studies, it will serve my purpose (that is, to introduce rhetorical studies to utopists) only to comment on the utopian aspects of his work. Like many others in rhetorical studies and utopian studies, Burke is difficult to pigeonhole in a single discipline. His ideas have been used in literary criticism, political theory, sociology, and all manner of textual and cultural studies. Burke saw rhetoric as having a curative and peacekeeping function at its best and as the root cause of war at its worst. Symbols, he argues in<italic>A Rhetoric of Motives</italic>(1950), are tools that cause people to identify with others individually or in groups. The concept has Freudian roots: When one person identifies with another person, or with a particular cause or country, that person becomes consubstantially one with the other person or cause. Rhetoric, for Burke, is this process of identification, which he says does not replace the classical notion of persuasion but, rather, expands it for modern understanding. The utopian aspect of his thought has to do with the integration of dialectic, rhetoric, and poetic myth in a function of discourse that he called “dialectical-rhetorical transcendence.” This process was most recently explored by James Zappen.<xref rid="r032" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>32</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>In Burke's<italic>A Rhetoric of Motives</italic>, he explains this quality of discourse as it functions in the course of history. His influences are Hegelian and Marxist but finally Platonic, as he ultimately sees the Hegelian and Marxist ideas as “part of the problem of competing ideologies” that needs to be transcended in order to reach a more perfect human condition.<xref rid="r033" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>33</sup>
            </xref>Burke sees dialectic and rhetoric as fundamentally oppositional. The Hegelian and Marxist positions, for instance, he sees as an oppositional shift from older approaches stressing spiritual agency to materialist approaches stressing historical outcomes. He is careful to distinguish his own approach as one of “linguistic transcendence” rather than historical theory. He is essentially concerned with symbolic communication and symbolic action. In Platonic dialogues, the dialectical process operates by alternating division and unification. The perspective at the end of the dialogue transcends the position at the beginning; the initial position can then be seen from the perspective of someone with a transcended motive. Similarly, in his<italic>Rhetoric</italic>, Burke offers a model of exchange in dialogue among competing partisans so that both sides achieve transcendence in the form of dialectical generalizations. Because the process is also poetic and creative, it results in mythic images. Rhetoric is the next step in this process. Burke defines rhetoric as the use of symbols enabling people to “identify” with one another and become “consubstantial.” In this way, rhetoric is a process of building communities, but it also entails excluding others who are not identified with the symbolic nature of the community. The solution to this problem Burke finds in recapturing the dialectical myth of the earlier, pre-partisan stage. In this way, individual and partisan advantages would be transcended in a utopian ideal. This he sees as a special kind of rhetoric, a “pure persuasion” leading to a somewhat mystical form of “ultimate identification” and universal order. This transcended community would place the competing ideologies in a hierarchical order so that each step of the hierarchy fulfills and transcends to the next. The process resembles Karl Mannheim's views of a socialist utopia with its successive, transcended points in history, but Burke would say that socialism itself, in our current understanding of it, would also be an ideology to overcome.</p>
         <p>Although Burke had not read Bloch when he formulated his theory of dialectical-rhetorical transcendence, the similarities between the two theorists are remarkable. In particular, both Burke and Bloch emphasize the important role that art and creative letters play in this function of utopia/transcendent rhetoric. For Burke, there are two ways that political and social opposition can be transcended. One, which he says is exemplified by Mannheim, would still think in politically partisan terms. The other is Burke's own reinvention of Plato's dialectical process as an interpretive and generative tool. This way would transcend political partisanship at the level of poetic myth: Myth bursts into the discourse to reveal something out of the ordinary context, and we move beyond the limitations of reason into the potentialities of imagination. He illustrates this process with a reading of Castiglione's<italic>The Courtier</italic>. “By gradations,” writes Burke, “it builds a ladder of courtship dialectically, into a grand design that, in its ultimate stage, would transcend the social mystery, ending Platonically on a mystic, mythic vision of celestial mystery.”<xref rid="r034" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>34</sup>
            </xref>The handbook is usually studied as a book of manners, but Burke suggests that it had a strong rhetorical influence—perhaps a utopian-rhetorical influence—on the motives of Elizabethan poets and other courtiers of the period. The ultimate aim seems to be merging as closely with the ideal of a perfect courtier as possible and then to become the instructor of a prince (Aristotle and Alexander are cited as examples of this motive).</p>
         <p>An obvious criticism of Burke's idea of rhetorical transcendence is that it is utopian in the unrealistic sense. It seems so abstract in its focus on generalized terminology and images that it may have no possible concrete object. Burke realized this utopian quality reminiscent of the lack of actualized topos in More's utopian “no-place.” As rhetorician James Zappen explains, “These acts of pure persuasion are devoid of partisan advantage-seeking but also devoid of persuasive purpose. As such, they might not even exist.”<xref rid="r035" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>35</sup>
            </xref>The important thing to take away from Burke's ramblings, though, is the humanistic sense that the search for perfection is inherent in human nature and that understanding this utopian impulse can only help us to live and to seek happiness in a world of competing power and advantage: “Let us observe, all about us, forever goading us, though it be in fragments, the motive that attains its ultimate identification in the thought, not of the universal holocaust, but of the universal order…. [E]ach kind strives toward the perfection of its kind, and so toward the kind next above it, while the strivings of the entire series head in God as the beloved cynosure and ninecure, the end of all desire.”<xref rid="r036" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>36</sup>
            </xref>By<italic>God</italic>Burke means an ultimate ideal transcending all other symbols and fulfilling all desire—the kind of nirvana that would eliminate the need for further utopia-making altogether. This, of course, is not achievable in the course of history, but the mythic experience of it would activate a downward movement in the process, bringing the transcendent ideals back into the pragmatic world of discourse and human affairs. This would be the function of utopia in Burkean terms, and it would result in a habit of mind that would amount to a large-scale educational scheme—dare I say, the education of desires. If the young were informed of the dialectical-rhetorical process of transcendence from the beginning, they would be able to see it occurring in the process of history as it came about. This solution is primarily Western, as rhetorician Michelle Condit has observed,<xref rid="r037" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>37</sup>
            </xref>but it also contains a self-critical vein that suggests that it might be applied in a broader view of utopian studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s06">
         <title>Conclusion: Looking Ahead to a Rhetorical Utopian Studies</title>
         <p>As Ruth Levitas has explained, a liberal-humanist understanding of the function of utopia is underrepresented in critical literature in utopian studies. Marxist interpretations of utopia's function in human history are currently the dominant paradigm for explaining the function of utopia. However, the discipline of rhetoric offers utopists a well-established tradition of theorizing about the encounter between symbolic, aesthetically mediated expressions of hope and actualized societies. Rhetoric, a field that was an original and essential foundation of the liberal-humanist tradition, is replete with examples of utopian ideation and imagery. From its origins in classical Greece, through its practice as a tool of transformation during the Reformation, and into its use as a twentieth-century critical tool for explaining the constitutive nature of discourse, the art of rhetoric inherently evokes the concept of utopia to persuade a civic audience. Modern rhetorical theory continues to overlap with the work of utopists of both liberal-humanist and Marxist philosophies. The continuity of this approach is demonstrated in the way that Marxist theorists who are usually considered utopists—Mannheim, Bloch, Marcuse—can be read as rhetorical theorists in the parts of their works that focus on the aesthetic and symbolic mediation of utopia. The art (<italic>techne</italic>) of rhetorical invention explored by rhetorical theorists is essentially the same as the anticipatory impulse explored by Bloch and Marcuse.</p>
         <p>The reevaluation and inclusion of related disciplines is essential to the growth of understanding in an interdisciplinary field such as utopian studies. Rhetorical theory fulfills the need for a functional definition of utopia in the liberal-humanist tradition. Utopists can freely borrow the terminologies of classical and contemporary rhetorical theories in ways that will make clear the rhetorical function of utopia. This cross-pollination of fields could also help to facilitate new dimensions of utopian studies: For example, twentieth-century rhetorical humanists such as Burke suggest that utopianism is a function of discourse itself. This focus on the nature of human communication and mediation is worth expanding in utopian studies.</p>
         <p>What is left unsaid in this article about the relationship between utopia and rhetoric could certainly fill the pages of many books. The range is especially rich when we turn to contemporary rhetorical theorists who specifically address society as a value to be combined with a remembered or imagined better place, as in Nedra Reynolds's<italic>Geographies of Writing</italic>or bell hooks's<italic>Belonging: A Culture of Place</italic>.<xref rid="r038" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>38</sup>
            </xref>Just as constitutive rhetoric (that is, cumulative discourse that contributes to building the structure of human society) has been important in the works of theorists often cited by utopists as crucial to their work, so the utopian impulse continues to be inherent in the way rhetoricians see their subject. To persuade verbally or visually, we must have our own idea of what is socially better, and we must also be able to imagine what our audience believes to be better. The function of utopia, then, may be less philosophical and ideological at its root than it is linguistic in a pragmatic sense. As Kenneth Burke has written of human beings, we are “the symbol-making, symbol-using, symbol-misusing animal … rotten with perfection.”<xref rid="r039" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>39</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ruth Levitas,<italic>The Concept of Utopia</italic>(Hertfordshire: Syracuse University Press, 1990).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Lyman Tower Sargent, “The Three Faces of Utopianism Revisited,”<italic>Utopian Studies</italic>5 (1994): 1–37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Philip Wegner,<italic>Imaginary Communities: Utopia, the Nation, and the Spatial Histories of Modernity</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 2002).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marcus Tullius Cicero,<italic>De Oratore Books I–II</italic>, trans. E. W. Sutton (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1948), II.lxxxvi.358.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a discussion of classical systems of memory taught as part of rhetoric, see Frances Y. Yates,<italic>The Art of Memory</italic>(1966; Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2001), 3–17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>To compare the productive role of memory in Marcuse, see Frederic Jameson,<italic>Marxism and Form: Twentieth Century Dialectical Theories of Literature</italic>(Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1971), 106–16.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For example, see Chaim Perelman and L. Olbrechts-Tyteca,<italic>The New Rhetoric: A Treatise on Argumentation</italic>, trans. John Wilkinson and Prucell Weaver (Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1969).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gregory Claeys, introduction to<italic>The Utopia Reader</italic>, ed. Gregory Claeys and Lyman Tower Sargent (New York: New York University Press, 1999), 1–5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kenneth Burke,<italic>Permanence and Change</italic>, 2nd ed., rev. (New York: Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1954), 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For example, see George Lakoff and Mark Johnson,<italic>Metaphors We Live By</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2003).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Harry Mortimer Hubbel, trans.,<italic>Cicero's “De Inventione”</italic>(Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1949), 5–7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>James L. Golden and P. J. Corbett, eds.,<italic>The Rhetorics of Blair, Campbell, and Whately</italic>(Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press, 1990).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Hugh Blair,<italic>Lectures on Rhetoric and Belles Lettres</italic>, 9th ed., vol. 1 (London: A. Strahan, 1803), 34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>George Campbell,<italic>The Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>(1776), in<italic>The Rhetorics of Blair, Campbell, and Whately</italic>, ed. James L. Golden and Edward P. J. Corbett (Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press, 1990), 234.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r015">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r016">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r017">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Michael Walzer,<italic>Exodus and Revolution</italic>(New York: Basic Books, 1985), 133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r018">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marx's position on communitarian socialists is explained well by Ruth Levitas (<italic>Concept of Utopia</italic>, 75).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r019">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Karl Mannheim,<italic>Ideology and Utopia: An Introduction to the Sociology of Knowledge</italic>, trans. Louis Wirth and Edward Shils (New York: Harcourt, Brace and World, 1966), 96–97, 133, 236.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r020">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 96–97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r021">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 236.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r022">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Lectures on Ideology and Utopia</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1986), 15–17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r023">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 251–53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r024">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Levitas,<italic>Concept of Utopia</italic>, 86–87.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r025">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ernst Bloch,<italic>The Principle of Hope</italic>, 3 vols., trans. Neville Plaice, Steven Plaice, and Paul Knight (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1986).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r026">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 1368.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r027">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Herbert Marcuse,<italic>Eros and Civilization: A Philosophical Inquiry into Freud</italic>(London: Penguin Press, 1969).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r028">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Herbert Marcuse,<italic>The Aesthetic Dimension: Toward a Critique of Marxist Aesthetics</italic>(Boston: Beacon Press, 1978), 71–73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r029">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Levitas,<italic>Concept of Utopia</italic>, 137.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r030">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Plato,<italic>Phaedrus</italic>, trans. R. Hackforth, in<italic>Plato: Collected Dialogues</italic>, ed. Ed. Edith Hamilton and Huntington Cairns (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1961), 517.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r031">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 520.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r032">
            <label>32.</label>
            <mixed-citation>James Zappen, “Kenneth Burke on Dialectical-Rhetorical Transcendence,”<italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>42, no. 3 (2009): 279–97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r033">
            <label>33.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 280.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r034">
            <label>34.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kenneth Burke,<italic>A Rhetoric of Motives</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1969), 221.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r035">
            <label>35.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Zappen, “Kenneth Burke on Dialectical-Rhetorical Transcendence,” 293.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r036">
            <label>36.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Burke,<italic>Rhetoric of Motives</italic>, 333.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r037">
            <label>37.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Michelle Celeste Condit, “Post-Burke: Transcending the Sub-Stance of Dramatism,”<italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>78 (1992): 352.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r038">
            <label>38.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Nedra Reynolds,<italic>Geographies of Writing: Inhabiting Places and Encountering Differences</italic>(Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press, 2004); bell hooks,<italic>Belonging: A Culture of Place</italic>(New York: Routledge, 2008).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r039">
            <label>39.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kenneth Burke,<italic>Language as Symbolic Action</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1966), 16.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
