<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerjsoci</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>American Journal of Sociology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00029602</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375390</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3081199</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/316983</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">AJS106216</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Georgia</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Warnke</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of California, Riverside</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2000</year>
            <string-date>September 2000</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>106</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>ajs.2000.106.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>535</fpage>
         <lpage>537</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Moral Textures: Feminist Narratives in the Public Sphere</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Maria Pia</given-names>
               <surname>Lara</surname>
            </string-name>. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1999. Pp. 238. $45.00 (cloth); $19.95 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/316983"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Maria Pia Lara’s<italic>Moral Textures: Feminist Narratives in the Public Sphere</italic>focuses on the relationship between morality, identity, and narrative. In particular, Lara is concerned to amend Jürgen Habermas’s discourse ethics by showing the way in which normative discourse on issues of justice is intertwined with aesthetic forms of communication and discussions of good. In his account of communicative rationality, Habermas distinguishes normative claims to validity from aesthetic ones. While discourse over moral norms appeals to reason and looks to a universal consensus, aesthetic discussions are devoted to making intelligible a certain sensibility and judgment of the good life. Rather than anticipating a universal consensus, aesthetic claims to validity depend upon a commonality in value and identity within groups and cultures for which a given judgment or life project can make sense.</p>
      <p>Lara follows others in questioning how sharp the distinction is. Commentators such as Thomas McCarthy have focused on the relation between the moral aspects of discourse, concerned with questions of justice, and ethical aspects, concerned with values and conceptions of good. Lara focuses on the relation between discourse over norms and narrative structure. She first expands Habermas’s account of illocutionary force to include not only well‐argued reasons but also “powerfully imaginative speech” (p. 2), and she then associates imaginative speech with narratives that are revealing in their effects. Coming to an agreement with others over the validity of norms is not a question simply of raising and redeeming validity claims. Moral claims have the capacity to engage us, instead, insofar as they are parts of narratives of power and oppression, indignity and response, indifference and the articulation of authentic identities. Lara shows how this reconceived notion of illocutionary force figures in struggles for recognition in the public sphere: citizens present to one another conceptions of subjectivity, notions of morality, and expectations about the good life and restructure them together.</p>
      <p>This account of illocutionary force is particularly suited to illuminating struggles for recognition on the part of women who have often entered the public sphere only through the narrative form, in novels, biographies, and autobiographies. Lara is particularly interested in the way in which women take up each other’s lives to make moral claims and to fashion and refashion identities. Hannah Arendt looks at the life of Rahel Varnhagen in order to assume her own identity as a pariah, as a Jew, and as a woman; later, contemporary feminists take up Arendt’s identity as reflected in her biography of Varnhagen to fashion their own. Simone de Beauvoir creates a fictional self to sort through her lived relationship to Jean Paul Sartre, which then becomes the site for contemporary feminists to sort through their own identity and autonomy. This loop occurs repeatedly in what Lara, following Ricoeur, sees as a tripartite mimesis. In mimesis 2, Jane Austen takes up the limited life of the women of her time (mimesis 1) to construct an identity for women that is then taken up again by contemporary women in films of Jane Austen’s novels (mimesis 3) to continue to construct that identity. Moreover, what is told in these looping narratives is the way in which women are and become moral agents. Thus, while many commentators have associated Austen only with Aristotle, with an ethics of virtue, Lara is just as interested in the morality of principle that Austen’s heroines exhibit. Moreover, she emphasizes the extent to which the moral claims Austen raises are validated through the narrative structure of her novels. This is a relationship that Martha Nussbaum also articulates, as Lara notes. For both, it is through the structure of narrative and imaginative speech that moral claims become not only rationally justified but compelling as well.</p>
      <p>Lara’s book is thick with references and interwoven arguments and is sometimes hard to follow for this reason. She is concerned with showing the possibilities for a recognition of the importance of self‐fashioning narrative in Habermas’s own work, especially in his early analysis in<italic>The Structural Transformation of the Public</italic>. She takes up discussions of deliberative democracy to show how they are enriched by a recognition of the place of narrative; she takes up postmodern accounts of identity; and she pursues her argument through the work of Paul Ricoeur, Albrecht Wellmer, and Wayne Booth, as well as a host of others. Despite the density of the work, Lara succeeds in illuminating the relation between narrative, identity, and morality. If the question of how we should live is bound up with ideas of who we are, and if we shape who we are with the help of narratives of other lives, these ideas would seem to be an integral part of the normative question that Habermas asks as to how we should live with others. Lara’s book is not only a welcome addition to recent work on Habermas, but also an important participant in current discussions of the relationship between literature and morality.</p>
   </body>
</article>
