<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">globalsouth</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Global South, The</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">19328648</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19328656</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">globalsouth.6.2.130</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2979/globalsouth.6.2.130</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Articles</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Among Spectators and Agents of History: Navigating through the Memory Sites of the Panama Canal</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Davidson</surname>
                  <given-names>Emily F.</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>Fall 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>6</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>globalsouth.6.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>130</fpage>
         <lpage>153</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2012 The University of Mississippi</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2979/globalsouth.6.2.130"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>ABSTRACT</label>
            <p>Public history sites like the West Indian Museum of Panama and the Miraflores Visitors Center have different approaches to narrating the Panama Canal story, ranging from tales of man’s triumph over nature and celebratory discourses of nationalist victories, to testimonies of the racial histories silenced by official renderings of the past. Given the important role of museums as educational institutions, sites that inform public opinion, and representational platforms for national tourism, this article explores the relationship these institutions forge between visitors and canal history. Through a comparative analysis of the narratives and experiential strategies at each site, I evaluate the degree to which Panamanians are cast as spectators in grandiose histories of triumph, or as agents, responsible for shaping the past, present and future. In contrast to these physical sites, I consider how The Society of Friends of the West Indian Museum of Panama constructs a living past through memory practices that challenge the petrified histories traditionally found in museums.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">According to Castillero Calvo, the majority of Panamanians share “a profoundly traditionalist, conservative and up to a certain point static notion of history: traditionalist, because it favors anecdotes over analyses and confuses history with timelines; conservative, because it shies away from revisionist approaches that question the tenets of an alleged national identity free of shadows and doubts; static, because it seems as if the past is framed as a finished event and that we cannot discover anything new” (translation mine, 1).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pierre Nora posits that memory sites can be physical places, such as museums or cemeteries, practices, like commemorations or mottos, and even objects, like texts and symbols.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">José Quiroga writes about the teleology of the Cuban Revolution as a “managed history” that comes to an abrupt and devastating halt in the Post-Soviet Era. This idea of the managed construction of nationalist historical narratives and chronologies, oriented toward a specific revolutionary or liberating end, is helpful to understanding how the canal's 1999 transfer is rendered as the culminating moment of Panama's struggle for sovereignty.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I examine a third museum,<italic>El Museo del Canal Interoceánico de Panamá</italic>(The Museum of the Inter-Oceanic Canal), in my dissertation, “Canal Memories: Race, Space and the Construction of Modern Panama.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">In a recent interview, Jelin reflected positively on the widespread use of her term “memory entrepreneurs.” This concept is intended to recognize the agency and subjectivity of social actors and movements often deemed as ephemeral: “with this idea I tried to go against a frequent posture in the most dominant or fashionable trends in cultural studies, in which cultural productions seem to circulate in a loud, without references, without actors who lead concrete projects. Cultural productions are analyzed as if they were in a cloud, eliminating historical subjects. My book is inclined exactly in the opposite direction, toward the study of concrete subjects over time” (translation mine, 108).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">As Sturken elaborates, “American national identity, and the telling of American history, has been fundamentally based on a disavowal of the role played in world politics by the U.S. not simply as a world power, but as a nation with imperialist policies and aspirations to empire. This disavowal of the U.S. as an empire has allowed for the nation's dominant self-image as perennially innocent” (7).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">All photographs taken by Emily F. Davidson (2011, 2012). The images of the Miraflores Visitor's Center are featured courtesy of the Panama Canal Authority. Photographs of the West Indian Museum of Panama are featured with permission from Panama's Office of Historical Patrimony.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For Arcadio Díaz Quiñones, reinterpretations of infamous dates are of utmost importance, and the crux of the matter is language. He argues that the title “The Spanish American War,” globally associated with 1898, serves to simplify or erase the fact that all aspects of life in Spain, Cuba, the Philippines, Puerto Rico and the United States were profoundly affected by the cultural and geopolitical implications of this date. In the case at hand, notorious dates like 1903, associated with Roosevelt's “taking” of Panama, or 1989, associated with “Operation Just Cause” and the removal of General Manuel Noriega, need to be reinterpreted and retold from multiple perspectives.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferdinand de Lesseps (<year>1805</year>–<year>1894</year>), the developer of the Suez Canal and President of the Panama Canal Company during the French construction era, and U.S. President Theodore Roosevelt (<year>1858</year>–<year>1919</year>), are frequently presented as the founding fathers of the Panama Canal. Standard canal timelines start with Lessep's failure to construct a sea-level passage, followed by Roosevelt's tenacious plight to ensure the triumph of North American engineering. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>David McCullough</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Julie Greene</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Phillipe Bunau-Varilla</string-name>
               </person-group>(<year>1859</year>–<year>1940</year>) was a French engineer who lobbied against the construction of a Nicaraguan canal and negotiated, on Panama's behalf, the 1903 Hay-Bunau-Varilla treaty, which granted the U.S. permission to build the canal. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>David McCullough</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Julie Greene</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">William Crawford Gorgas (1854–1920) was a physician for the U.S. Army and chief sanitary officer of the canal project. He is lauded for his research on the role of mosquitoes in the transmission of yellow-fever and malaria. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>David McCullough</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Julie Greene</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Declared a World Heritage Site in 1997, Panama's colonial Old Town was founded by the Spanish in 1673 (“Archaeological Site”).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Müller House, popularly referred to as “La Casa Miller” or the “Mullah Building,” was a tenement house built in Calidonia in 1910. The house is known for its peculiar triangular shape, fashioned after the transatlantic ships that traversed the canal. See Roberto Reid. In Pulido Ritter's novel<italic>Recuerdo Panamá</italic>(I Remember Panama), the narrator describes a panicked group of kids who franticly run to watch the 1972 demolition of the house. At one point in the narration, the building acquires its own voice, describing the people from all over the world who shared the universe between her walls: “I've given them the universe, I've protected them beneath my zinc roof, and my rooms never covered their ears so that men, originating from such different parts of the world, could speak the same language. Antilleans, Chinese, Hindis, Arabs, Greeks, Jews, Italians, and many more. And my wooden floors are not stained with a single drop of blood. Don't they realize that I am this city?” (translation mine, 116).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jamaican activist, journalist, and entrepreneur,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Marcus Garvey</string-name>
               </person-group>(<year>1887–1940</year>) was a leader in the Pan-Africanism and Black Nationalism movements and the founder of the Universal Negro Improvement Association and the African Communities League. He advocated for the unification of African diaspora throughout the world in the struggle for racial equality, socioeconomic progress, and nationhood. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Edmund David Cronon</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Son of a Barbadian father and a St. Lucian mother,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>George Westerman</string-name>
               </person-group>(<year>1910–1988</year>) was born in the Canal Zone in Colón. His leadership in the National Civic League, an organization loosely modeled after the NAACP, was key in movements against the Gold and Silver Roll segregation in the Canal Zone, and in reversing the aforementioned constitutional amendment (<year>1941</year>) that denied citizenship to West Indians born in Panama. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Michael L. Conniff</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">An English/Spanish informational pamphlet distributed at the museum explains: “Membership in SAMAAP is open to any person residing in Panamá, or overseas, without distinction of race, creed or social status. The primary requirement is to have an interest in working to realize and/or finance the goals of the society” (The Society).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Aleida Samaniego C.</string-name>
               </person-group>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Former Defense Forces general, politician, and CIA informant, Manuel Antonio Noriega (1934–) was a Panamanian strongman, whose removal from power was a primary objective of the North American Invasion of Panama. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>John Dinges</string-name>
               </person-group>. In December 2011, after spending more than 20 years in prison in the U.S. and France, Noriega was extradited to Panama to serve sentences for embezzlement, corruption and murder. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Scott Sayare</string-name>
               </person-group>. Former members of the opposition group, the Civilian Crusade, victims advocacy groups from El Chorrillo, and families of former military officers (executed by Noriega for treason), are just a few of the groups who brought up unresolved questions about the Invasion upon the strongman's return.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">On<italic>Día de las trenzas</italic>(5–21–2012), Panamanians of diverse ethnic backgrounds defied school regulations and challenged the public pressure to straighten “bad” hair by proudly wearing cornrows and braids. See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Roberto Quintero</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ángel López Guía</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <article-title>“Archeological Site of Panamá Viejo and Historic District of Panamá.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>UNESCO World Heritage List</italic>
               </source>.<publisher-name>UNESCO World Heritage Centre</publisher-name>,<fpage>1992</fpage>–<lpage>2013</lpage>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>11</day>
               <month>Feb.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bilbija, Ksenija</string-name>
               </person-group>, and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Leigh A. Payne</string-name>
               </person-group>. Introduction.<source>
                  <italic>Accounting for Violence: Marketing Memory in Latin America</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2011</year>.<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Castillero Calvo, Alfredo</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“El centenario y Panamá la Vieja como patrimonio mundial.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Tareas</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>115</fpage>(<year>2003</year>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.<comment>Web</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Conniff, Michael L.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“George Westerman: A Barbadian Descendant in Panama.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Human Tradition in Latin America</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>William Beezley</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Judith Ewell</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Scholarly Resources</publisher-name>,<year>1987</year>.<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Cronon, Edmund David.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Black Moses: The Story of Marcus Garvey and the Universal Negro Improvement Association</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher-name>,<year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Davidson, Emily F.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“Canal Memories: Race, Space and the Construction of Modern Panama.”</article-title>
               <source>Diss.</source>
               <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>,.<year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Díaz-Quiñones, Arcadio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“1898.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Hispanic American Historical Review</italic>
               </source>.<volume>78</volume>.<issue>4</issue>(<year>1998</year>).<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Dinges, John</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Our Man in Panama</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>,<year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <article-title>“The 45 Places to Go in 2012.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>New York Times</italic>
               </source>.<day>6</day>
               <month>Jan.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>7</day>
               <month>Jan.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>García Canclini, Néstor</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Hybrid Cultures: Strategies for Entering and Leaving Modernity</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>,<year>1995</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Greene, Julie</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Canal Builders: Making America's Empire at the Panama Canal</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>The Penguin Press</publisher-name>,<year>2009</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Jelin, Elizabeth</string-name>
               </person-group>. Interview by<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Máximo Badaró</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Repensando la relación entre memoria y democracia: entrevista a la socióloga argentina Elizabeth Jelin.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Stockholm Review L.A.S</italic>
               </source>.<fpage>7</fpage>(<year>2011</year>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Jelin, Elizabeth</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>State Repression and the Labors of Memory</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Judy Rein</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Marcial Godoy-Anativia</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>,<year>2003</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>James-Grant</string-name>
               </person-group>,. Personal interview.<day>6</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>James-Grant</string-name>
               </person-group>,.<article-title>“Mensaje del Lic. Glenroy O. James-Grant, Presidente de SAMAAP.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Boletín Informativo de la Sociedad de Amigos del Museo Afroantillano de Panamá: 1 de febrero 2010–31 de enero 2011</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>SAMAAP</publisher-name>,<year>2011</year>:<fpage>3</fpage>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>
                  <italic>La sociedad de amigos del Museo Afro-antillano de Panamá</italic>
               </source>.<collab>SAMAAP</collab>. &lt;<uri xlink:href="http://www.samaap.org/">http://www.samaap.org/</uri>&gt;.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>8</day>
               <month>Sept.</month>
               <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lombardo, Romualda</string-name>
               </person-group>. Personal interview.<day>6</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>López Guía, Ángel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Su hija no puede venir a la escuela con ese peinado.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>La prensa</italic>
               </source>.,<day>2</day>
               <month>Abril</month>
               <year>2012</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>14</day>
               <month>Sept.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lasaosa Rogers, Sebastian</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Conozca su Canal. Vimeo</italic>
               </source>.<day>13</day>
               <month>August</month>
               <year>2011</year>. &lt;<uri xlink:href="http://vimeo.com/27656752">http://vimeo.com/27656752</uri>&gt;. Film.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>10</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lowe de Goodin, Melva</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>De/From Barbados a/to Panamá</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Editora Géminis</publisher-name>,<year>1999</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lowe de Goodin, Melva</string-name>
               </person-group>. Personal interview.<day>10</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>McCullough, David</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Path Between the Seas: The Creation of the Panama Canal 1870–1914</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>,<year>1977</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <article-title>“Miraflores Visitor's Center.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Panama Canal</italic>
               </source>.<collab>Panama Canal Authority</collab>,<fpage>1998</fpage>–<lpage>2011</lpage>. &lt;<uri xlink:href="http://www.pancanal.com/eng/anuncios/cvm/index.html">http://www.pancanal.com/eng/anuncios/cvm/index.html</uri>&gt;.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>8</day>
               <month>Sept.</month>
               <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <article-title>“Museo Afro Antillano de Panamá.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Red centroamericana de museos</italic>
               </source>.<collab>Redcamus</collab>,<fpage>2005</fpage>–<lpage>2012</lpage>. &lt;<uri xlink:href="http://www.museoscentroamericanos.net">http://www.museoscentroamericanos.net</uri>&gt;.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>8</day>
               <month>Sept.</month>
               <year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <article-title>“Museums.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Focus Panamá</italic>
               </source>.<publisher-name>Focus Publications International S.A.</publisher-name>,<day>26</day>
               <month>Aug.</month>
               <year>2012</year>. &lt;<uri xlink:href="http://www.focuspublicationsint.com/focuspma/?p=195">http://www.focuspublicationsint.com/focuspma/?p=195</uri>&gt;.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>11</day>
               <month>Feb.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <article-title>“Panama City Sites: Museo Afroantillano (Afro-Antillean Museum).”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Fodor's Travel Intelligence</italic>
               </source>. Fodors Travel,<year>2012</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>11</day>
               <month>Feb.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Pulido, Ritter L.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Recuerdo Panamá</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Olalla Ediciones</publisher-name>,<year>1998</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Quintero, Roberto</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“La revuelta de las trenzas en Panamá.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Otramérica: de sur a norte</italic>
               </source>.<day>20</day>
               <month>May</month>
               <year>2012</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>14</day>
               <month>Sept.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Quiroga, Jos</string-name>
               </person-group>é.<source>
                  <italic>Cuban Palimpsests</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>,<year>2005</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <source>
                  <italic>Realms of Memory: Rethinking the French Past</italic>
               </source>. Dir.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Pierre Nora</string-name>
               </person-group>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Lawrence D. Kritzman</string-name>
               </person-group>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Arthur Goldhammer</string-name>
               </person-group>. Vol.<volume>1</volume>.:<publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>,<year>1996</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Reid, Roberto</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Casa Muller/‘Mullah’ Building.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Silver People Chronicle</italic>
               </source>.<day>12</day>
               <month>Oct.</month>
               <year>2008</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>30</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>
               </person-group>. Vol.<volume>3</volume>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>,<year>1984</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Samaniego C., Aleida</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“9.2% de los censados se declaró afrodescendiente.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>La prensa</italic>
               </source>.<day>30</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2010</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>30</day>
               <month>Dec.</month>
               <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Sánchez Laws, A. L.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Panamanian Museums and Historical Memory</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>,<year>2011</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Sayare, Scott</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“France: Noriega to Be Extradited.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>New York Times</italic>
               </source>.<day>23</day>
               <month>Nov.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.<comment>Web</comment>.<day>23</day>
               <month>Nov.</month>
               <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <collab>The Society of Friends of the West Indian Museum of Panama (SAMAAP)</collab>.<source>
                  <italic>West Indian Museum Brochure</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>SAMAAP</publisher-name>, n.d.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Sturken, Marita</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Tourists of History: Memory, Kitsch, and Consumerism from Oklahoma City to Ground Zero</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2007</year>.<comment>Print</comment>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
