<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="por">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">reviportfilo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000595</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08705283</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">2183461X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26197005</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Experienciar Deus</article-title>
            <subtitle>Gabriel Marcel, na Contramão da Teodiceia</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>DE FREITAS DA SILVA</surname>
                  <given-names>CLAUDINEI APARECIDO</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">
               <label>*</label>Universidade Estadual do Oeste do Paraná, Brasil.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2017</year>
            <string-date>2017</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">73</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26196983</issue-id>
         <fpage>839</fpage>
         <lpage>864</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia Copyright © 2017 Aletheia – Associação Científica e Cultural</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26197005"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>Abstract</label>
            <p>From the perspective of Gabriel Marcel’s juvenile writings, most notably<italic>Fragments Philosophiques</italic>(1909-1914) and<italic>Journal Métaphysique</italic>(1914-1923), this study discuss the first theoretical statute of the experience of God. This reflexive movement, strictly speaking, phenomenological-existential is based (as background) on the critique of absolute knowledge (modern idealism and scientism) which, according to Marcel, is an unavoidable contradiction: at the same time, it affirms the being, it denies the being. What draws attention is the fact that such explanatory model is transposed and, therefore, applied using the classical formulation of the so-called problem of the existence of God, of which theodicy has one of the most eloquent and emblematic metaphysical discourses. For the young French thinker, God cannot be verified or justified as an ontological proof: God is the Inverifiable Absolute, since it has to be experienced in the act of faith, in the expression of love and grace.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <label>Keywords:</label>
            <kwd>experience</kwd>
            <kwd>faith</kwd>
            <kwd>Gabriel Marcel</kwd>
            <kwd>God</kwd>
            <kwd>theodicy</kwd>
            <kwd>unverifiable</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>por</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Referências</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carmona, Feliciano Blazquez. La filosofia de Gabriel Marcel: de la dialéctica a la invocación. Madrid: Encuentro, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grassi, Martín. “O Deus da fé na filosofia concreta de Gabriel Marcel”. In Encarnação e transcendência: Gabriel Marcel, 40 anos depois, edited by Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da Silva, 19-42. Cascavel (PR): Edunioeste, 2013.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm. Essais de théodicée. Paris: GF-Flammarion, 1969.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm. Discurso de Metafísica e outros textos. Tradução e notas de Tessa Moura Lacerda. São Paulo: Martins Fontes, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lotz, Johannes Baptist. “Von der Gotteserfahrung im Denken unserer Zeit”. Stimmen der Zeit, 172 (1963), Heft 11, p. 321-334.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. “Les conditions dialectiques de la philosophie de l’intuition”. Revue de Métaphysique et de Morale, t. XX, n°5, 1912, p. 638-652.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Le palais de sable. In: Le seuil invisible. Paris: Bernard Grasset, 1914.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Journal métaphysique. Paris: Gallimard, 1927.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Être et avoir. Paris: Aubier/Montaigne, 1935.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. “Notes pour une philosophie de l’amour”. Revue de Métaphysique et de Morale 59, n°4 (Oct-Déc/1954), p. 374-379.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Fragments philosophiques (1909-1914). Paris/Louvain: Vrin/Nauwelaerts, 1961.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Les hommes contre l’humain. Préface de Paul Ricoeur. Paris: Editions Universitaires, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Homo viator. Paris: Association Présence de Gabriel Marcel, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcel, Gabriel. Essai de philosophie concrète. Paris: Gallimard, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Prini, Pietro. Gabriel Marcel et la méthodologie de l’invérifiable. Paris: Desclée de Brouwer, 1953.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. “O corpo em cena: Gabriel Marcel”. In Corporeidade e educação: tecendo sentidos, edited by Damiano, Gilberto Aparecido, Pereira, Lucia Helena Pena and Oliveira, Wanderley Cardoso, 93-112. São Paulo: Cultura Acadêmica/Fundação Editora UNESP, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. Entre o “ser” e o “ter”: a hiperfenomenologia de Gabriel Marcel. In Origens e caminhos da fenomenologia, edited by Tourinho, Carlos Diógenes Côrtes, 160-176. Rio de Janeiro: Booklink, 2014.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. ‘“A mordedura do real’: Gabriel Marcel e o gesto transcendental”. In A filosofia transcendental e a sua crítica: idealismo, fenomenologia e hermenêutica, edited by Ferrer, Diogo and Utteich, Luciano Carlos, 323-356. Coimbra: Imprensa da Universidade de Coimbra/Coimbra University Press, 2015a. http://dx.doi. org/10.14195/978-989-26-1049-8_11</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. “Intuição e dialética: Gabriel Marcel, no limiar da ontologia”. In Fenomenologia, religião e psicanálise, edited by Carvalho, Marcelo, Tourinho, Carlos Diógenes, Savian Filho, Juvenal and Carone, André, 115-133. São Paulo: ANPOF, 2015b. http://www.anpof.org/portal/images/Colecao_XVI_Encontro_ANPOF/Fenomenologia_Religio_e_Psicanlise.pdf</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. “Gabriel Marcel e a teoria da participação ontológica”. Revista de Filosofia Moderna e Contemporânea (UNB), v. 3, p. 123-137, 2015c. http://periodicos.unb.br/index.php/fmc/article/view/17684/12961</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da. “A pessoa, em carne e osso: Gabriel Marcel, para além do personalismo”. In Festschrift aos 20 anos do Simpósio de Filosofia Moderna e Contemporânea da UNIOESTE, edited by Silva, Claudinei Aparecido de Freitas da; Cardoso Neto, Libanio and Kahlmeyer-Mertens, Roberto Saraiva, 161-197. Cascavel (PR): Edunioeste, 2016.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wahl , Jean. Vers le concret. Paris: Vrin, 1932.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
