<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerjsoci</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>American Journal of Sociology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00029602</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375390</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">2782934</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/231294</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">AJSv103p962</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>What Is Agency?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Mustafa</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Emirbayer</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Ann</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Mische</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">New School for Social Research</aff>
            <x xml:space="preserve"/>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>1998</year>
            <string-date>January 1998</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>103</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>ajs.1998.103.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>962</fpage>
         <lpage>1023</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review in this section may be obtained only from the review's author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/231294"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article aims (1) to analytically disaggregate agency into its several component elements (though these are interrelated empirically), (2) to demonstrate the ways in which these agentic dimensions interpenetrate with forms of structure, and (3) to point out the implications of such a conception of agency for empirical research. The authors conceptualize agency as a temporally embedded process of social engagement, informed by the past (in its “iterational” or habitual aspect) but also oriented toward the future (as a “projective” capacity to imagine alternative possibilities) and toward the present (as a “practical‐evaluative” capacity to contextualize past habits and future projects within the contingencies of the moment).</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>This is a fully coauthored article. Earlier drafts were presented at the Paul F. Lazars‐feld Center for the Social Sciences at Columbia University, the Workshop on Politics, Power, and Protest at New York University, the Colloquium on Culture and Politics at the New School for Social Research, the meeting of the American Sociological Association at Los Angeles, and various seminars at the New School for Social Research and Princeton University. We would like to thank the participants in those forums for their many useful comments. We would also like to thank Jeffrey Alexander, Bernard Barber, Richard Bernstein, Donald Black, Mary Blair‐Loy, David Gibson, Chad Goldberg, Jeff Goodwin, Michael Hanagan, Hans Joas, Michele Lamont, Edward Lehman, Calvin Morrill, Michael Muhlhaus, Shepley Orr, Margarita Palacios, Mimi Sheller, Charles Tilly, Diane Vaughan, Loi'c Wacquant, and Harrison White for their many illuminating insights, criticisms, and suggestions. Direct correspondence to Mustafa Emirbayer, Department of Sociology, New School for Social Research, 65 Fifth Avenue, New York, New York 10003.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
</article>
