<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">isis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Isis</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00211753</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456994</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/597725</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">ISIS00026015</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Modern (Nineteenth Century to 1950)</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Leucha</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Veneer</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>December 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>99</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>597753</issue-id>
         <fpage>862</fpage>
         <lpage>864</lpage>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Virginia</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
               <surname>Zimmerman</surname>
            </string-name>.<source>Excavating Victorians</source>. (Studies in the Long Nineteenth Century.) x + 231 pp., figs., bibl., index.<publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>,<year>2007</year>. $65 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The History of Science Society. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The History of Science Society</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/597725"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This interesting work presents fragments and traces from geological and archaeological practices in nineteenth-century Britain and considers their connections with and influence on Victorian literature.<italic>Excavating Victorians</italic>is not exactly history of science but, rather, a work of literary criticism that draws very heavily on the history of science. Virginia Zimmerman underscores the disjunction between scientific and literary writing as an artifact of our view from the twenty-first century, drawing on Gillian Beer's<italic>Darwin's Plots</italic>(Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1983) for useful context and analysis. She identifies the writings of Charles Lyell and Charles Dickens, along with those of their contemporaries, as part of a single body of literature, written in response to the newly discovered vastness of time and to emphasize the authority of the individual to interpret (and thus reclaim) the past. Zimmerman uses the notion of the “trace,” as defined by Paul Ricoeur, to indicate “an object's origin in the past but also its duration into the present” (p. 8); the strategies the Victorians used to cope with this confused temporality is the major resonating theme, along with the continual conjunction of construction and destruction. This juxtaposition of preservation and decay is emphasized throughout: in geology, with the fossil remains of long-extinct species; in archaeology, with the action of Vesuvius that at once destroyed Pompeii and forever preserved its remains (which would otherwise have been lost); and in Victorian London, with the continual building projects that uncovered the traces of Roman occupation.</p>
      <p>The Victorian geologist is highly important here, writing the narrative of time and thus rescuing both the individual and the human species from apparently inevitable destruction by claiming the authority to interpret deep time. The abyss of time may dwarf the individual, but it is also meaningless without the geologist-narrator, who thus claims the authority to control the past. Zimmerman focuses very much on the work of Lyell here, though she also brings in Gideon Mantell, the connections between the work of those two geologists being well known. The brief encapsulation of early and mid-Victorian geology appears, to the eye of the specialist historian of geology, a little lightweight. Nevertheless, it leads nicely into the discussion of the effects of Victorian geology on Tennyson's poetry. Nature “red in tooth and claw” is the oft-used example of the influence of geological writings on Tennyson, and Zimmerman does look at<italic>In Memoriam</italic>; her main focus, however, is a more unusual case study. She examines<italic>The Princess</italic>, tracing the use of both catastrophist and uniformitarian language throughout the poem and emphasizing that the fairy tale, in this case, does have a happy ending, providing some comfort to those Victorians lost in the great expanse of time.</p>
      <p>The centrality of excavations and traces reappears in the discussion of archaeology, which focuses on London and Pompeii, and Zimmerman once again emphasizes the need for an authoritative writer to interpret remains in order to give them meaning. Charles Roach Smith is an important figure here, as is Henry Layard, and Zimmerman also explores the correlations between geology and archaeology, both of which she characterizes as excavatory sciences dependent on careful fieldwork and interpretive narrative reconstruction. The examination of Pompeii looks at Victorian efforts to reanimate Pompeii through historical writing, fictional or otherwise, concentrating on the works of Edward Bulwer-Lytton, and also at Victorian recreations of Pompeian daily life, which blended past and present. It is, however, the regeneration of Victorian London, which revealed the urban archaeological sites so important to Roach Smith, that leads into the discussion of Dickens's<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>and<italic>Our Mutual Friend</italic>. Zimmerman explores and explains how, in both of these works, Dickens uses explicitly archaeological language and his characters endeavor to excavate the past in order to understand and control the present. Though not all Dickens's characters can master the march of time, those who do achieve their happy ending, as did Ida and the Prince in<italic>The Princess</italic>. Even so, Dickens does not give his plots the completion and closure that the reader might expect, and the characters are sometimes unable to excavate their own pasts completely.</p>
      <p>
         <italic>Excavating Victorians</italic>brings out very clearly the discomfort the newly discovered vast expanse of geological time gave the Victorians and examines some of the writings that helped shape responses to it. Though the book may not be of particular relevance to the historian focusing closely on Victorian geology or archaeology, for the historian of science who examines wider cultural or literary phenomena it is an important guide to the stimulus that the writings of geologists and archaeologists gave other mid-Victorian writers. Nevertheless, the specialist or narrowly focused historian of science will probably find it frustrating rather than helpful, since the overviews of Victorian geology and archaeology are brief and there are distracting errors, such as the attribution of the<italic>Ninth Bridgewater Treatise</italic>to William Buckland rather than to Charles Babbage (p. 18). The chapters on Tennyson and Dickens are both interesting and illuminating, although a reader accustomed to historical argument and with limited knowledge of the techniques of literary criticism may find them faintly bewildering in places. Nonetheless, it is in this part of the analysis that the work provides valuable guidance to the historian of science.</p>
   </body>
</article>
