<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">gregorianum</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50008730</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Gregorianum</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>PONTIFICIA UNIVERSITAS GREGORIANA</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00174114</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23574177</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Les responsabilités de l'Université moderne</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Hervé</given-names>
                  <surname>Carrier</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1969</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>50</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23568596</issue-id>
         <fpage>463</fpage>
         <lpage>483</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/23574177"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article studies the institutional context of recent reforms in ecclesiastical faculties, with special attention to the transformation of modern Universities. Four major problems are raised in this period of University renewal. 1) Should Universities stress research or teaching functions? 2) Should they admit the mass of students or be reserved to an elite? 3) How can they organize efficiently the University community? 4) What is their responsibility towards the collectivity? With regard to the first question, the author notes the current emphasis on research as compared to teaching. A reasonable balance between these two functions may be attained by drawing from philosophies of education within the English, French, German and American traditions. A rewarding survey of recent University legislation in various countries is made. The post-industrial era calls for a stress on research in such a way as to link it more effectively with the teaching function of the University. As to the second question, youth today assumes its right to a University education. Universities can neither receive all candidates nor, on the other hand, systematically impose a « numerus clausus ». Selectivity is necessary. A system of diversified Colleges, Universities and Faculties would permit everyone with the prerequisite aptitudes to receive a University training. Planning would be necessary among the institutions of a given region. A system of gradual and qualified selection is suggested. The third problem concerns the University as a community. Recent reforms require effective collaboration among all the components of the University: administrators, professors, students. All should have some voice in university government. More important than structures is the mentality which will effect a genuine solidarity and consensus among all members of the University community. The fourth problem regards the University's relationship to the collectivity. The University must protect its academic freedom. This task becomes increasingly difficult in so far as Universities are largely supported by the state, industry and the general public. On the other hand the University cannot disregard urgent social questions. The social function of the University must be achieved in the context of a developing world in quest of justice. The author shows how the trends of contemporary University reform are manifested within the Catholic University system and ecclesiastical faculties. The new statutes and programs of the Gregorian University afford examples.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>fre</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d2808e107a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e114" publication-type="other">
J. Drèze et J. De-
belle, Conceptions de l'Università, Paris: Editions Universitaires, 1968.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2808e124a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e131" publication-type="other">
Voir: Westdeutsche Rektorenkonferenz (Documents concernant la
réforme de l'enseignement supérieur). Bad Godesberg, 1969, pp. 10-11.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2808e141a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e148" publication-type="other">
Voir Quelques problèmes de développement de l'enseignement supé-
rieur en Europe. Paris: Ministèri; de l'Education Nationale, 1969.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2808e158a1310">
            <label>β</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e165" publication-type="other">
W. G. Moore, The Tutorial System. Oxford: Pergamon Press, 1968.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2808e173a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e180" publication-type="other">
J. McLeish,
The Lecture Method, Cambridge Institute of Education, 1968.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2808e189" publication-type="other">
Moore, The Tutorial System</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
