<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">jnarrtechnique</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j50000414</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Narrative Technique</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Eastern Michigan University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222925</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">30225416</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>"Lost in Their Mazes": Framing Facts and Fictions in "Benito Cereno"</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Mark A.</given-names>
                  <surname>Eaton</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>1994</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>24</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>i30225411</issue-id>
         <fpage>212</fpage>
         <lpage>236</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1994 The Journal of Narrative Technique</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30225416"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="d11468e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e114" publication-type="other">
Melville may have been reminded of the former incident by an article describing the
history of Santo Domingo up to the bloody insurrection of 1799 that was published in
Putnams in January 1854</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e126" publication-type="other">
Benito Cereno first appeared from
October through December of the following year (Newman 103)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e136a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e143" publication-type="other">
Sundquist's two articles, "Slavery, Revolution, and the American Renaissance" and
"Suspense and Tautology in 'Benito Cereno.' "</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e152" publication-type="other">
Benito Cereno in Sundquist's recent book,
To Wake the Nations: Race in the Making of American Literature</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e161" publication-type="other">
Rogin, Levine,
and Thomas</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e171a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e178" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur's Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences: Essays on Language,
Action, and Interpretation</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e187" publication-type="other">
"The Value of Narrativity in the Representation of Reality," rpt. in On Narrative</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e194a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e201" publication-type="other">
"Melville's Fist:
The Execution of Billy Budd."</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e212a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e219" publication-type="other">
Louis Montrose nicely elaborates this point in his article from a recent collection of
essays: "[W]e can have no access to a full and authentic past, a lived material existence,
unmediated by the surviving textual traces of the society in question-traces whose
survival we cannot assume to be merely contingent but must rather presume to be at least
partially consequent upon complex and subtle social processes of preservation and
effacement; and secondly, that those textual traces are themselves subject to subsequent
textual mediations when they are construed as the 'documents' upon which historians
ground their own texts, called 'histories' " (The New Historicism 20).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e248a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e255" publication-type="other">
James H. Kavanagh, who is anomalous in this respect,
"criticism has at times pondered Delano's 'bafflement' with a humourlessness similar to
his, often ignoring passages where the text becomes unmistakably comic, and dissolves
Delano's sense of self-importance by making him a butt of its humor. In the scene, for
example, where the 'not unbewildered' Delano falls through the San Dominick's railing,
a reader with the least pictorial imagination might find it difficult to keep from laughing
at Delano" (363)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e281a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e288" publication-type="other">
Gennette, Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method, 27, 27n</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e294" publication-type="other">
Narrative
Discourse Revisited</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e304a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e311" publication-type="other">
Kavanagh has interestingly elaborated the implications of subsequent (re)readings of
Benito Cereno: "Because the reader is usually 'deceived' along with Delano on first
reading, this extrication [from Delano's ideological maze] requires a second reading that
is not so much a rereading of the text 'itself as a reading of one's first spontaneous
relation to the text.... By making us 'follow the leader' through the ironic unfolding of
Delano's ideology, the text becomes that ideology's immanent critique, bringing us up
against the complex of violence and death that subvene that ideology, and allowing us to
break from it" (358).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e340a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e347" publication-type="other">
Billy Budd, Sailor (An Inside Narrative), when Captain Vere announces that
Billy must be executed, "the word mutiny was not named in what he said" (368; emphasis
in original)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e360a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e367" publication-type="other">
Kavanagh points to Cereno as a kind of double for Delano; his remarks are worth quoting
at length:
Cereno functions as a kind of mirror for Delano in the text: The similarity
of their names and their tendency always to confront each other face-to-
face suggest Cereno's 'imaginary' status. The puzzle of Cereno, then,
becomes the puzzle of what Delano sees in his mirror, how it reflects his
own image back to him; and Delano sees many disturbing things:
arbitrary cruelty, decadence, weak-mindedness, and so on. But most
disturbing, he sees his own ultimate vulnerability, an image that seems
to be dissolving before his eyes-a nightmare image indeed. (364-65)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e403a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e410" publication-type="other">
Yellin, "Black Masks: Melville's 'Benito
Cereno,' " as well as The Intricate Knot: Black Figures in American Literature, 1776-
1863</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e422" publication-type="other">
Karcher,
Kavanagh, and Rogin</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e432a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e439" publication-type="other">
Mizruchi, 276</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e445" publication-type="other">
Amasa Delano would have been
somewhat removed from these changes in the ethnic and racial character of his country,
but he nevertheless would have come in contact while at sea with individuals from
different racial groups, and the perplexity he shows in this circumstance provides little
indication that he is prepared to adapt to a country that is fast becoming more racially
diverse. These implications seem applicable to this passage because of its emphasis on
language barriers-the broken English-and because Atufal, confiscating the old
sailor's knot, "ferreted into it like a detective custom-house officer after smuggled laces"
(203)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e477a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e484" publication-type="other">
To Wake the Nations 28</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e491a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e498" publication-type="other">
Hayden White speculates that historical writing may have as one of its most basic
impulses the desire to "moralize upon," in Delano's phrase, the past. White further
suggests that historical narratives may supplement the legal system where it fails to
supply such a sense of moral closure, and that both fiction and history might share this
impulse:
If every fully realized story, however we define that familiar but
conceptually elusive entity, is a kind of allegory, points to a moral, or
endows events, whether real or imaginary, with a significance that they
do not possess as a mere sequence, then it seems possible to conclude that
every historical narrative has as its latent or manifest purpose the desire
to moralize the events of which it treats. Where there is ambiguity or
ambivalence regarding the status of the legal system, which is the form
in which the subject encounters most immediately the social system in
which he is enjoined to achieve a full humanity, the ground on which any
closure of a story one might wish to tell about a past, whether it be a
public or a private past, is lacking. And this suggests that narrativity,
certainly in factual storytelling and probably in fictional storytelling as
well, is intimately related to, if not a function of, the impulse to moralize
reality, that is, to identify it with the social system that is the source of
any morality that we can imagine. (13-14)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e565a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e572" publication-type="other">
Melville (Kavanagh 375, 383n)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e579a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e586" publication-type="other">
Delano's ignorance: "Delano survives only because he does not come to understand
that the ship has been taken over by the slaves. Exactly his innocence, his unwillingness
to be suspicious, his optimism-all of which make him unable to see-save his life. He
would be killed at once if it were thought that he suspected. Likewise, he would be killed
if he interfered" ("Democratic Social Space" 99)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e606a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e613" publication-type="other">
Benjamin for
what he calls a "constellation," where historical facts are not connected one-by-one in a
linear narrative but rather allowed to cross-reference others dialectically across time and
space: "Historicism contents itself with establishing a causal connection. But no fact that
is a cause is for that very reason historical. It became historical posthumously, as it were,
through events that may be separated from it by thousands of years. A historian who takes
this as his point of departure stops telling the sequence of events like the beads of a rosary.
Instead, he grasps the constellation which his own era has formed with a definite earlier
one" (263)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e645a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e652" publication-type="other">
Simon Schama's latest book, Dead Certainties, follows the unfolding of two historical
events, the second of which is the alleged (but never conclusively proven) murder of
George Parkman, a Harvard professor and uncle of the historian Francis Parkman, Jr., in
1849.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e667" publication-type="other">
Delbanco 41</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e673" publication-type="other">
Melville had dedicated his first book, Typee, to Shaw in the same year (1849)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e680" publication-type="other">
Brook Thomas 202-06</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e686" publication-type="other">
Somers in 1842</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e692" publication-type="other">
Thomas 206-14</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e698" publication-type="other">
Rogin 294-316</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e704" publication-type="other">
Rogin 6</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e710" publication-type="other">
Delbanco 40</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="d11468e726a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e730" publication-type="other">
Adorno, Theodore W. Aesthetic Theory. 1970. Trans. C. Lenhardt. New York: Routledge &amp;
Kegan Paul, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e740a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e744" publication-type="other">
Benjamin, Walter. "Theses on the Philosophy of History." In Illuminations. Trans. Harry
Zohn. New York: Schocken Books, 1968.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e754a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e758" publication-type="other">
Branch, Watson G., ed. Melville: The Critical Heritage. New York: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul,
1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e768a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e772" publication-type="other">
Conrad, Joseph. "Henry James: An Appreciation." Notes on Life and Letters. Rpt. in Heart
of Darkness. Ed. Robert Kimbrough. New York: Norton, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e783a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e787" publication-type="other">
Delbanco, Andrew. "The Fog of History." The New Republic 3 June 1991: 39-41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e794a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e798" publication-type="other">
Fisher, Marvin. Going Under: Melville's Short Fiction and the American 1850s. Baton
Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e808a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e812" publication-type="other">
Fisher, Philip. "Democratic Social Space: Whitman, Melville, and the Promise of American
Transparency." Representations 24 (Fall 1988): 60-101. Rpt. in The New American
Studies: Essays from "Representations." Ed. Philip Fisher. Berkeley: University of
California Press, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e828a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e832" publication-type="other">
Fuentes, Carlos. Myself with Others. New York: Farrar, Strauss, Giroux, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e843" publication-type="other">
Gennette, Gerard. Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method. Trans. Jane E. Lewin. Ithaca:
Cornell University Press, 1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e853a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e857" publication-type="other">
---. Narrative Discourse Revisited. Trans. Jane E. Lewin. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e865a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e869" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Barbara. "Melville's Fist: The Execution of Billy Budd." In The Critical Difference.
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e879a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e883" publication-type="other">
Karcher, Carolyn L. Shadows over the Promised Land: Slavery, Race, and Violence in
Melville's America. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e893a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e897" publication-type="other">
Kavanagh, James H. "That Hive of Subtlety: 'Benito Cereno' and the Liberal Hero." In
Ideology and Classic American Literature. Eds. Sacvan Bercovitch and Myra Jehlen.
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e910a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e914" publication-type="other">
Levine, Robert S. Conspiracy andRomance: Studies in Brockden Brown, Cooper, Hawthorne,
and Melville. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e924a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e928" publication-type="other">
Matthews, John T. "Framing in Wuthering Heights." Texas Studies in Literature and
Language 27.1 (1985): 25-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e938a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e942" publication-type="other">
---. "Intertextual Frameworks: The Ideology of Parody in John Barth." In Intertextuality
and Contemporary Fiction. Eds. Patrick O'Donnell and Robert Con Davis. Baltimore:
Johns Hopkins University Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e956a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e960" publication-type="other">
Melville, Herman. Benito Cereno. 1855. In Billy Buddand Other Stories. New York: Penguin
Books, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e970a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e974" publication-type="other">
---. Billy Budd, Sailor (An Inside Narrative). In Billy Budd and Other Stories. New York:
Penguin Books, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e984a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e988" publication-type="other">
Mizruchi, Susan. "Cataloguing Creatures of the Deep: 'Billy Budd, Sailor' and the Rise of
Sociology." boundary 2 17.1 (Spring 1990): 272-304.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e998a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1002" publication-type="other">
Newman, Lea Bertani Vozar. A Reader's Guide to the Short Stories of Herman Melville.
Boston: G.K. Hall, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1012a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1016" publication-type="other">
Pahl, Dennis. Architects of the Abyss: The Indeterminate Fictions of Poe, Hawthorne, and
Melville. Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1026a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1030" publication-type="other">
Pearson, John H. "The Politics of Framing in the Late Nineteenth Century." Mosaic 23.1
(1990): 15-30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1041a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1045" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences: Essays on Language, Action, and
Interpretation. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1055a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1059" publication-type="other">
---. Time and Narrative. 3 Vols. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1066a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1070" publication-type="other">
Rogin, Michael Paul. Subversive Genealogy: The Politics and Art of Herman Melville.
Berkeley: University of California Press, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1080a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1084" publication-type="other">
Schama, Simon. Dead Certainties. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1091a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1095" publication-type="other">
Sundquist, Eric J. "Slavery, Revolution, and the American Renaissance." The American
Renaissance Reconsidered. Eds. Walter Benn Michaels and Donald E. Pease. Balti-
more: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1108a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1112" publication-type="other">
---. "Suspense and Tautology in 'Benito Cereno.' " Glyph 8 (1981): 103-26. Rpt. in
Modern Critical Views: Herman Melville's 'Billy Budd, ' 'Benito Cereno, ' 'Bartleby the
Scrivener' and Other Tales. Ed. Harold Bloom. New York: Chelsea, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1126a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1130" publication-type="other">
---. To Wake the Nations: Race in the Making of American Literature. Cambridge:
Belknap Press/Harvard University Press, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1140a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1144" publication-type="other">
Thomas, Brook. Cross-Examinations of Law and Literature: Cooper, Hawthorne, Stowe,
and Melville. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1154a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1158" publication-type="other">
Trilling, Lionel. The Liberal Imagination. New York: Doubleday/Anchor Books, 1953.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1165a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1169" publication-type="other">
Veeser, H. Aram, ed. The New Historicism. New York: Routledge, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1176a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1180" publication-type="other">
White, Hayden. "The Value of Narrativity in the Representation of Reality. In On Narrative.
Ed. W.J.T. Mitchell. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1190a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1194" publication-type="other">
Yellin, Jean Fagin. "Black Masks: Melville's 'Benito Cereno.' " American Quarterly 22.3
(Fall 1970): 678-89.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11468e1205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11468e1209" publication-type="other">
---. The Intricate Knot: Black Figures in American Literature, 1776-1863. New York:
New York University Press, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
