<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">enviphil</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50016367</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Environmental Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Philosophy Documentation Center</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">17180198</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21538905</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26167884</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>FEATURES</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Heidegger's Concept of the Environment in<italic>Being and Time</italic>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Cameron</surname>
                  <given-names>W. S. K.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Dept. of Philosophy Loyola Marymount University Los Angeles, CA 90045</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26167879</issue-id>
         <fpage>34</fpage>
         <lpage>46</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26167884"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Heidegger's characterization of Dasein as Being-in-the-world suggests a natural relation to environmental philosophy. Among environmentalists, however, closer inspection must raise alarm, both since Heidegger's approach is in some senses inescapably anthropocentric and since Dasein discovers its environment through its usability, serviceability, and accessibility. Yet Heidegger does not simply adopt a traditionally modern, instrumental view. The conditions under which the environment appears imply neither that the environment consists only of tools, nor that what is true of the parts is also true of the whole, nor that an orientation to use—where appropriate—precludes any other orientation. Heidegger's anthropocentric commitments thus do not rule out the possibility of a non-instrumental perspective on the natural world.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aristotle. 1996. Aristotle's Metaphysics. trans. Hippocrates G. Apostle. Grinnell, IA: Peripatetic Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gadamer, Hans-Georg. 1991. Truth and Method, 2ndRev. Ed., trans. W. Glen-Doepel, ed. J. Cumming and G. Barden, rev. J. Weinsheimer and D. G. Marshall. New York: Crossroads.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heidegger, Martin. 1962. Being and Time, trans. John Macquarrie and Edward Robinson. New York: Harper and Row. [1927; 7th German ed., 1953]</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heidegger, Martin. 1966. Discourse on Thinking, trans. John M. Anderson and E. Hans Freund. New York: Harper and Row.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heidegger, Martin. 1976 "Only a God can save us: Der Spiegel's interview with Martin Heidegger," trans. Maria P. Alter and John D. Caputo. Philosophy Today 20:267-84.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heidegger, Martin. 1977. "The Question concerning Technology," in The Question concerning Technology and other Essays, trans. by William Lovitt (New York: Harper Torchbooks.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heidegger, Martin. 1993. "Letter on Humanism" in Basic Writings, Revised and Expanded Edition. ed. David Farrell Krell. New York: Harper Collins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kant, Immanuel. 1992. Grounding for the Metaphysics of Morals, with "On a Supposed Right to Lie because of Philanthropic Concerns," 3rd Ed., trans. James W. Ellington. Indianapolis: Hackett Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Regan, Tom. 1983. The Case for Animal Rights Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Singer, Peter. 1975. Animal Liberation. New York: Random House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Skirbekk, Gunnar. 1999. "Discourse-Ethical Gradualism: Beyond Anthropocentrism and Biocentrism?" Proceedings of the Twentieth World Congress of Philosophy, Volume 1: Ethics. Ed. Klaus Brinkmann. Bowling Green, OH: Philosophy Documentation Center.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sterba, James P. 2001. Three Challenges to Ethics: Environmentalism, Feminism, and Multiculturalism Oxford: Oxford University Press</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
