<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">victperiodrev</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000128</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Victorian Periodicals Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">07094698</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24642959</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dickens's "Pious Fraud": The Popular Press and the Moral Suasion of Fictional Narrative</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>JESSICA</given-names>
                  <surname>VALDEZ</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>44</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24642953</issue-id>
         <fpage>377</fpage>
         <lpage>400</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>©2011 The Research Society for Victorian Periodicals</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24642959"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="d694e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e114" publication-type="other">
[W.H. Wills]"The Appetite for News." Household Words, i June 1850,
238-240.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e124a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e131" publication-type="other">
Walter Bagehot, Literary Studies (New York: Longman, Green, and Co.,
1891), 197.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e141a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e148" publication-type="other">
John M. L. Drew, Dickens the Journalist (New York: Palgrave Macmillan,
2004), 194.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e158a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e165" publication-type="other">
This account does not characterize Dickens as opposed to journalistic form,
which is highly varied and often includes fiction as well as non-fiction in
its generic content. Rather, I argue that Dickens espouses a greater use of
fictional plottedness in journalistic reports, rather than those practices that
privilege quantified reports and experiential information over knowledge
and truth.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e189a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e196" publication-type="other">
Some recent scholars of periodical studies have argued that the generic
divide between journalism and literature is anachronistic when applied to
the nineteenth century, and Matthew Rubery makes a related argument
in The Novelty of Newspapers. Rubery points out that the generic divide
makes little sense at a time when much of the prose written by Victorian
novelists bore some relationship to the periodical press in terms of style,
subject, or source. While I agree that distinguishing between journalistic
and novelistic form is difficult, particularly due to the indefinable and var-
ied quality of newspapers, I do see in Dickens's writings a clear awareness
of the generic differences between factual reports and narrative form. See
Matthew Rubery, The Novelty of Newspapers: Victorian Fiction After the
Invention of News (New York: Oxford University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e238a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e245" publication-type="other">
I am not arguing that the overall structure of Household Words forms a
single narrative across articles, stories and poetry. Rather, I am claiming that
Dickens uses narrative methods and figurative language to control readers'
experiences of the journal and to create a heterogeneous thematic unity
across the journal as a whole. Although I focus on prose in my account, my
claims also apply to the journal's poetry, which works intertextually with
the prose writing and often include narratives within themselves.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e271a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e278" publication-type="other">
Patrick Joyce suggests that Victorians understood themselves as acting sub-
jects in the world in terms of their place in various stories. They created a
self out of the roles they found in their reading, and these roles also took
their force from being part of narratives in which they could feel a part.
Joyce's study concerns, in particular, the ways in which social narrative
conferred collective identity. He writes, "To be human, personally and col-
lectively, was to be emplotted in a story about humanity... Both men, but
especially Edwin Waugh, were made into acting subjects by subscription to
this second narrative, the autodidact story of knowledge's self-realization in
the shape of the all-powerful spirit of 'improvement'" (148). Patrick Joyce,
Democratic Subjects: The Self and the Social in Nineteenth-Century Eng-
land (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e320a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e329" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur also suggests that the novel's fictional quality gives the reader
greater access into the psychological processes of the human mind, both
because it is focused on an actor around which a series of events circulate
and because the thought process is fictionalized and not restricted to inter-
preting exterior signs. Paul Ricoeur, Time and Narrative (Chicago: Univer-
sity of Chicago Press, 1990).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e352a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e359" publication-type="other">
In his famous analysis of Bleak House, D. A. Miller distinguishes the struc-
ture of Bleak House from that of the Chancery suit by its teleological nar-
rative and fulfilled promise of a meaningful ending. Although the Chancery
suit does eventually end, it provides only an endpoint rather than an ending:
Miller argues, "the vulgar evidence of an endpoint can never amount to the
assurance of an ending, that is, the presence of a complex of narrative sum-
mations that would match or motivate the external termination of discourse
with its internal closure" (Miller 90). According to Miller, the novel's end-
ing and its meaning are closely intertwined in a narrative like Bleak House,
so much so that to eliminate one would be to eliminate the other (86). In
this sense, I argue, the narrative and its ending not only organize the seem-
ing miscellany of Bleak House, but they also provide a framework of mean-
ing and social and moral being for the reader. D. A. Miller, The Novel and
the Police (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1988), 83-93.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e407a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e414" publication-type="other">
In some ways, the very structure of news is resistant to prolonged narra-
tive order. News is defined by facticity and recentness, and its structure is
focused on change and the anxiety to know what has happened. As soon
as new information emerges, the news no longer qualifies as news and
is demoted to explanatory information. News is not condensed into one
account but rather imparted in staged parts, leaving the reader ignorant at
any time of the state of the situation and of the potential for closure. Lucy
Brown, Victorian News and Newspapers (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1985).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e444a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e451" publication-type="other">
Patrick Brantlinger, The Reading Lesson: The Threat of Mass Literacy in
Nineteenth-Century British Fiction (Indianapolis: Indiana University Press,
1998), 90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e464a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e471" publication-type="other">
"A Preliminary Word," Household Words, 30 March 1850, 1.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e478a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e485" publication-type="other">
Richard Altick, English Common Reader: A Social History of the Mass
Reading Public, 1800-1900 (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1957),
162</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e498a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e507" publication-type="other">
Frances Ferguson puts forth an understanding of Bentham and Utilitarian-
ism that differs from the interpretations associated with Michel Foucault
and his reiteration of Bentham's panopticon. She argues that Utilitarian-
ism did not subordinate the individual to the interests of the collective. She
writes, "For the crucial insight behind the modern utilitarian social systems
that both Sade and Bentham devised was that it was inadequate to look
to beliefs in order to explain and predict what people would do, and that
it was also inadequate to try to derive people's beliefs from their actions.
Instead, they focused on the contributions of social systems in enabling
people to act without benefit of belief and without continually feeling
compelled to regard their actions with the suspicion that Marx and Freud
urged on us" (XVI). Ferguson understands the Utilitarians' greatest contri-
bution to be the introduction of information, rather than knowledge, into
the social world, which offered an alternative or supplement that allowed
people to sidestep the question of knowledge and instead obtain the regular
experience of information. Her reading of Utilitarianism is very different
from what I am arguing to be that of Dickens. Frances Ferguson, Pornogra-
phy, the Theory: What Utilitarianism Did to Action (Chicago: The Univer-
sity of Chicago Press, 2004).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e571a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e578" publication-type="other">
Drew suggests that Dickens exhibits a sense that the reader can be con-
vinced or swayed by the rhetoric of the text. His critical approach rests not
in discussing the intrinsic merits of a text but in its ability to create emo-
tional effects and change belief in the reader (Drew 164). I think this per-
spective is helpful, but the introduction to Household Words suggests that it
is not only rhetoric but also fictional plottedness that enable this effect upon
readers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e604a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e611" publication-type="other">
It's useful to consider Dickens in contrast to Trollope in this valorization
of the end. As Lynette Felber suggests, Trollope's novels are not about the
ending; rather, his novels' endings are often only a movement into the next
novel in the sequence, such that Trollope is about the extension of the
reading experience rather than the holistic movement to a satisfying end
that provides coherence to the events that preceded. Linda Hughes and
Michael Lund have argued that Victorians looked forward in their readings
toward endings that only provided jumping off points to other stories, but
certainly Dickens does not fulfill this demand. Lynette Felber, "Trollope's
Phineas Diptych as Sequel and Sequence Novel," Part Two: Reflections on
the Sequel, Ed. Paul Budra and Betty A. Schellenberg (Buffalo: University of
Toronto Press, 1998).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e654a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e661" publication-type="other">
Lorna Huett, "Among the Unknown Public: Household Words, All the Year
Round and the Mass-Market Weekly Periodical in the Mid-Nineteenth Cen-
tury," Victorian Periodicals Review 38 (spring 2005): 61-82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e674a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e681" publication-type="other">
Dickens, who first became an editor in August 1836 when he took on the
editorship of Bentley's Miscellany, had a volatile relationship with publisher
and owner Richard Bentley. Dickens demanded a more active and dominant
role for himself and regarded the publication as a "projection of his tastes
and his abilities" whereas Bentley wanted it to showcase writer talent. Dick-
ens resigned in early 1839 because of these tensions. Sabine Clemm, Dick-
ens, Journalism, and Nationhood: Mapping the World in Household Words
(New York: Routledge, 2009), 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e710a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e717" publication-type="other">
"A Detective Police Party," Household Words, 27 July 1850, 409.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e724a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e731" publication-type="other">
"The Modern Science of Thief-Taking," Household Words, 10 Aug. 1850,
368.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e741a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e748" publication-type="other">
"Valentine's Day at the Post Office," Household Words, 30 Mar. 1850, 9.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e755a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e762" publication-type="other">
"A Paris Newspaper," Household Words, 1 May 1850, 164.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e770a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e777" publication-type="other">
In a recent article published in Victorian Periodicals Review, Jonathan V.
Farina makes a related argument that Dickens's Household Words uses
stylistic features of fictional characterization to describe new abstractions
and technologies as if they, like fictional characters, were repositories of
deep character available for readers (393). He suggests that this method is
in contrast to alternative genres of representation, such as statistics, to vali-
date abstract social phenomena that could not be seen. He writes, "While
others claimed to offer value-neutral, non-interpretative facts, Dickens
aspired to offer characters, things with shadows and depths, inconsistencies
and inscrutabilities" (393). One such example, for Farina, is the "Shadow"
behind Household Words, which Farina says appeals to an emergent epis-
temology of character, a way of knowing everything as divided and irre-
ducible to systematization or simple description. This account is related to
what I read to be Dickens's anxiety regarding newspaper coverage, that is
the effort to reduce an event to a one-dimensional chronologically written
account. Fictional narrative allows for the expression of inconsistencies and
complexities that are reduced and lost within a newspaper account of an
event. In this paper, I am focusing more on plottedness and narrative, but
character also plays an integral role in Dickens's use of narrative. See Jona-
than V. Farina, "'A Certain Shadow': Personified Abstractions and the Form
of Household Words," Victorian Periodicals Review 42 (winter 2009):
392-415.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e850a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e857" publication-type="other">
Matthew Rubery argues that we can see journalism's influence on the novel
by the way in which novels import journalistic narratives or directly repre-
sent newspapers in their pages. He writes that novels used newspapers as
"one of the primary tactics by which novelists sought to keep their work
from becoming yesterday's news. Novelists used newspapers in a variety of
ways: retelling events, reported by the press; reproducing journalistic voices,
styles, and features; the pastiche of news items through headlines and quo-
tations; recording the process of news production; and, most dramatically,
portraying the individual reader's reaction to the news" (Rubery 11). How-
ever, I am arguing that Dickens has a more direct dialogue with newspaper
form, by which I mean the miscellany of forms available. See Matthew
Rubery, The Novelty of Newspapers: Victorian Fiction After the Invention
of News (New York: Oxford University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e902a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e909" publication-type="other">
He adds, "The surprising fact is that very few legitimate writers besides
Dickens have ever felt there was any virtue in these devices.... pious
frauds, where the purpose of the deception is to benefit the person being
deceived, are astoundingly hard to find" (57). Edwin M. Eigner, The Dick-
ens Pantomime (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1989).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e928a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e937" publication-type="other">
Rosemary Mundhenk makes a related argument in her article, "The Educa-
tion of the Reader in Our Mutual Friend." She suggests that what Boffin
does for Bella is what the novel does for the reader. She argues that Dickens
limits the reader's knowledge of the Boffin deception, but informs the reader
of the Harmon deception, in order to show the reader that his perception is
limited and his knowledge is partial (42), While I agree with Mundhenk's
reading of the Bella/reader parallel, I am arguing that Dickens instills in the
reader a mode of discriminative insight and control rather than a sense that
knowledge and perception is fragmentary and must be put together by each
individual observer. Rosemary Mundhenk, "The Education of the Reader in
Our Mutual Friend," Nineteenth-Century Fiction 34 (spring 1979): 41-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e975a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e982" publication-type="other">
Charles Dickens, Our Mutual Friend (New York: Penguin Classics, 1998),
751-</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e992a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e999" publication-type="other">
Harmon becomes particularly aligned with Dickens's narrator when he has
to decide whether to "come alive" again and announce his identity, and
thereby also decide the movement of the novel's plot. He is sensitive to the
negative effects that his self-pronouncements could have upon his audience.
His determination is in strict contrast to the newspapers that have rigidly
proclaimed his death and that are impervious to considering the results that
this claim may cause, including its effect on the Boffins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1026a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1033" publication-type="other">
Walter Benjamin's famous essay, "The Storyteller," suggests that contem-
porary society and print culture have lost the storyteller inherent in oral
culture and the value for imparting counsel and experience from the story-
teller to the listener. Benjamin suggests that oral storytelling maintains the
presence of the storyteller in each telling of the story and, moreover, that
it adapts new events to traditional understandings and frameworks. In an
oral culture, storytelling enables people to adapt to contemporary changes
without feeling dislocated and disrupted. In contrast, print culture erases
the storyteller and his relationship to the audience: the value for counsel is
replaced by sheer desire for information and the audience is no longer able
to adapt via storytelling to new ways of living. For Benjamin, it is the print
nature of the forms that make them what they are; but for Dickens, the
fictional quality of the novel provides a sort of substitute for the oral sto-
ryteller. See Walter Benjamin, "The Storyteller," in Theory of the Novel: A
Historical Approach, ed. Michael McKeon (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins
University Press, 2000), 77-93.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1087a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1094" publication-type="other">
"Murderer's Fame," Lloyd's Weekly Newspaper, 18 Sept. 1864.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1101a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1108" publication-type="other">
"Arrival of Müller: The Voyage to England," Lloyd's Weekly Newspaper,
18 Sept. 1864.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1118a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1127" publication-type="other">
The debate over public executions came down to questions of representa-
tion. Opponents argued that public executions failed to change the behavior
of the criminal classes and instead elicited bestial pleasure in the spectacle
of watching another person die at the state's behest. Supporters insisted that
this direct representation of state power and of the consequences of moral
and social infraction would discourage the public from breaking accepted
social codes. At question was not the morality of such a method but the
method's representative effectiveness in influencing the audience, both view-
ing and otherwise. For more information, see V.A.C. Gattrell, The Hanging
Tree: Execution and the English People 1770-1868 (New York: Oxford
University Press, 1994).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1165a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1172" publication-type="other">
Charles Dickens, letter to the Times, 17 November 1849, The Letters of
Charles Dickens, Ed., Madeline House, Graham Storey, and Kathleen Til-
lotson (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1965), 653.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1185a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1192" publication-type="other">
"A New Page for the Crimes Célèbres," All the Year Round, 26 Oct. 1864,
286.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d694e1203a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d694e1210" publication-type="other">
See Dickens, letters to the Times, 13 November 1849, The Letters of
Charles Dickens, 645-646.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
