<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">discoursestudies</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50011056</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Discourse Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">14614456</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14617080</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24049950</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Commentary</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Text as action, action as text? Ricoeur, λογοσ and the affirmative search for meaning in the 'universe of discourse'</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                  <surname>Scott-Baumann</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>13</volume>
         <issue>5</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24049943</issue-id>
         <fpage>593</fpage>
         <lpage>600</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2011 SAGE Publications Ltd.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24049950"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Ricoeur placed a great deal of importance upon text and the interpretation of text. Bell accepts this by virtue of his extended analysis of the story of Babel, and I hope to offer ways of extending and developing Bell's arguments to incorporate the ethical demands that Ricoeur placed upon text, upon our interpretation of text and upon action as a form of readable text. This will not include a commentary on discourse analysis, which I am not qualified to give. Ricoeur differed from the structuralist tradition in that he saw the relationship between language and life as taking a dialectical form: debate that presumes the possibility of altering one's position by grappling with different views, and often taking inspiration from Hegelian dialectics, with their contrasting polarized views and the eventual attempt at affirmative common ground. The term λογοσ (logos) was first used in a philosophical way by Heraclitus to give us the principle of order and knowledge, and yet for Heraclitus the world was dominated by conflict and change. Ricoeur studied this tension within logos between order and disorder, partly by his writing about language and his work on signs and symbols, partly through metaphor and narrative and also through his insights on translation. For him, all these are facets of the need for both Explaining and Understanding as forms of interpretation of language, ethics and action. Ricoeur's work on logos provides us with an approach that asks whether ethics controls language or vice versa or both and how this fits in with structuralism and later movements. For Ricoeur, signs (words, texts) are not the centres of our perceptual experience. At the heart of our perception are our motivations and our actions, for which we must take responsibility in a sort of provisional affirmation that we will keep trying. In so doing we must doubt (be suspicious of) our own motives just as much as those of others, and see action as a form of readable text.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d17583e123a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e127" publication-type="other">
Dosse F (1997) The History of Structuralism, vols 1 and 2, trans. Glassman D. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e141" publication-type="other">
Hegel F (1807/1977) Phenomenology of Spirit, trans. Miller AV. New York, Oxford: Oxford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e155" publication-type="other">
LaCocque A and Ricoeur P (1998) Thinking Biblically, trans. Pellauer D. Chicago, IL: Chicago
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e165a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e169" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1950/1966) Freedom and Nature, trans. Kohak E. Evanston, IL: Northwestern
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e180a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e184" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1950/1967) Husserl: An Analysis of His Phenomenology, trans. Ballard EG and
Embree LE. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e198" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1960/1967) The Symbolism of Evil, trans. Buchanan E. Boston, MA: Beacon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e209" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1969/1974) The Conflict of Interpretations, trans. Ihde D. Evanston, IL: Northwestern
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e219a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e223" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1975) Biblical hermeneutics. Semeia 4: 29-148.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e230a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e234" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1975/1977) The Rule of Metaphor: Multi-disciplinary Studies of the Creation of
Meaning in Language, trans. Czerny R. Toronto and Buffalo, NY : University of Toronto Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e244a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e248" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1976a) Interpretation Theory: Discourse and the Surplus of Meaning. Fort Worth:
Texas Christian University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e259a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e263" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1976b) Philosophical hermeneutics and theological hermeneutics: Ideology, Utopia
and faith in Protocol Series of the Colloquies of the Center for Hermeneutical Studies in
Hellenistic and Modern Culture, 17. Berkeley, CA: The Graduate Theological Union and the
University of California, 1-28, 29-37, 40-56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e279a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e283" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1981) Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences. Essays on Language, Action and
Interpretation, ed. and trans. Thompson JB. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e293a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e297" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1983,1985,1988) Time and Narrative, vols 1-3.Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e304a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e308" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1986/1997) Lectures on Ideology and Utopia. New York: Columbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e315a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e319" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1986/1991) From Text to Action: Essays in Hermeneutics II, trans. Blarney K and
Thompson JB. London: The Athlone Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e329a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e333" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1990/1992) Oneself As Another, trans. Blarney K. Chicago, IL: Chicago University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e344a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e348" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (1996) The Hermeneutics of Action, ed. Kearney R. London: SAGE.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e355a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e359" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (2000/2004) Memory, History, Forgetting. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e366a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e370" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (2004/2005) The Course of Recognition, trans. Pellauer D. Cambridge, MA: Harvard
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e380a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e384" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur P (2004/2006) On Translation, trans. Brennan E. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e391a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e395" publication-type="other">
Scott-Baumann A (2009) Ricoeur and the Hermeneutics of Suspicion. Continuum Studies in
Continental Philosophy. New York and London: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e405a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e409" publication-type="other">
Scott-Baumann A (2010) Ricoeur's translation model as a mutual labour of understanding. Theory,
Culture &amp; Society, special section on Ricoeur under editorship of Prof. Stephen Clark 27: 5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e420a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e424" publication-type="other">
Scott-Baumann A (2012) Ricoeur and the Negation of Happiness. Continuum Studies in
Continental Philosophy. New York and London: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d17583e434a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d17583e438" publication-type="other">
Smith JE (1995) 'Freud, Philosophy and Interpretation' and 'Reply to John E Smith'. In: Hahn LE
(ed.) The Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur. Chicago and La Salle, IL: Open Court, 147-168.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
