<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591470</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/430555</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR85222</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>William</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Schweiker</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of Chicago.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>April 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>334</fpage>
         <lpage>335</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mandry, </surname>
               <given-names>Christof</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Ethische Identität und Christlicher Glaube: Theologische Ethik im Spannungsfeld von Theologie und Philosopie</source>. Mainz: Matthias Grünewald Verlag, 2002. 314 pp. $36.00 (paper).</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/430555"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Some years ago there arose a rather heated debate among theologians in Europe, the United Kingdom, and the United States about the distinctiveness of Christian ethics in relation to “autonomous morality” specified on philosophical grounds. This was part of a longer standing agenda in modern philosophical Western ethics at least since the Enlightenment to isolate a unique domain of the “moral” free from the resources of historical traditions, especially religious traditions. What concerned a wide range of theologians in the later third of the twentieth century was to clarify, if possible, the precise relations between Christian faith and an autonomous morality. Does Christianity add anything to moral reason, and if so, what? In what does the distinctiveness of the Christian moral outlook consist? These questions touched deeper impulses in the Christian tradition insofar as forms of Christian ethics, say natural law ethics, always granted some autonomy to moral reason outside of other resources, revealed and otherwise. Throughout the late 1960s and the early 1980s a host of Roman Catholic and Protestant theologians weighed in on the debate.</p>
      <p>Christof Mandry’s recent book reopens this debate about Christian ethics, explores some of the terrain of the historical debate, and then tries to press the discussion forward. Originally written as a thesis under the direction of Dietmar Mieth, himself a contributor to this debate, Mandry's book provides a solid, if somewhat schematic, account of the lines of contention even as he makes an important contribution to the discussion within the European, especially German, context by drawing on fresh resources. Thematically, the book is divided into two parts. Part 1 explores the question of theological and philosophical ethics by examining in some detail exemplary positions. Mandry explores within Roman Catholic theology both the work of Franz Böckles, whose<italic>Fundamentalmoral</italic>(New York: Pueblo Publishing, 1980) offered a transcendental account of the theonomous autonomy, and that of Klaus Demmers, who insists on the “effective history” of faith on reason. Mandry then examines an analogous debate among Protestants by examining, specifically, Gerhard Ebeling’s account of moral conscience and Wolfhart Pannenberg’s argument for a distinctly theological grounding of ethics. The fact that thinkers from the various sides of the Christian tradition could reach such starkly different positions while drawing on strands of their own communions is of course important to note. Throughout, Mandry’s readings are fair and insightful.</p>
      <p>Granting the important historical work of part 1 of this book, it is in part 2 that Mandry begins to make some innovative moves. The gambit is to shift the discussion from the relations that can and ought to obtain between theology and philosophy toward a consideration of the ethical self. In order to make that move, Mandry draws on the recent work of Paul Ricoeur, especially<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992). This is important because, while Ricoeur’s thought has had considerable impact in the United States and in France, his work has not been used nearly so much within German theology. To be sure there are some theologians, like Dietmar Mieth, who have engaged in hermeneutical reflection and, further, work of Jürgen Habermas, Hans‐Georg Gadamer, and other German thinkers is certainly well known. But the contribution of Ricoeur to theological reflection is just now gaining interest. Happily, with the work of Mandry and others this development will continue.</p>
      <p>Mandry offers a relatively concise and convincing reading of Ricoeur on the ethical self and its relation to ethical aims for the good life and the moral demand for justice. Mandry’s concern is to clarify what is meant by “ethical identity” and how this idea might aid theological ethics. The principle contribution is to show the place of religious conviction (<italic>Überzeugung</italic>) in relation to ethical aims, moral duties, and practical reasoning. Mandry’s contention is that philosophy and theology offer different perspectives on the ethical subject which can fruitfully engage each other. The question then becomes, of course, whether or not the question that provoked the discussion in the first case has simply been pushed back one further step in reflection. What provides the warrant for multiple perspectives on the ethical subject? Is it a philosophical warrant or a theological one?</p>
      <p>This is an engaging book for specialists in theological ethics and especially for those interested in the contributions of hermeneutical thinking to ethics. One can only hope that Mandry will continue to develop this line of reflection.</p>
   </body>
</article>
