<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerhistrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The American Historical Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00028762</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19375239</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4136200</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/ahr.111.2.429</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Reviews of Books</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Methods/Theory</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Rudolf</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Dekker</surname>
               </string-name>
               <aff id="a1">Erasmus University, Rotterdam</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>April 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>111</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>527516</issue-id>
         <fpage>429</fpage>
         <lpage>430</lpage>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Jeremy D.</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
               <surname>Popkin</surname>
            </string-name>.<source>History, Historians, and Autobiography.</source>:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.<year>2005</year>. Pp. x, 339. $35.00.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 American Historical Association. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>American Historical Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/ahr.111.2.429"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In recent years autobiographies have become ever more highly esteemed as sources for historical research. At the same time, more and more historians have themselves published their life stories. Jeremy D. Popkin analyzes both tendencies in this study on history, historians, and autobiography. He has read more than 300 autobiographies, mainly by English and American historians but also including French, German, Dutch, and Italian works. Popkin makes clear that this is a very interesting body of texts, because historians who have turned into autobiographers unconsciously demolish the existing wall between historiography and autobiography. When in the nineteenth century truth and objectivity became the professional standard among historians, the genre of autobiography fell into disgrace and was left to literary critics. Historians writing their life stories are, on the one hand, bound to the rules of this narrative and literary form, but, on the other hand, they are dedicated to the professional standards of their discipline. In fact, they are aware that their autobiographies are likely to be read more critically than those written by members of other professions. Their own life story should reinforce their historical work by showing truth and credibility.</p>
      <p>Popkin starts by positioning himself within the current debate on narrative theory. In an interesting and informative chapter he criticizes in particular Hayden White and Paul Ricoeur for largely ignoring autobiographical writing while discussing the problem of history and fiction. He concludes that the hybrid genre of autobiography does not fit into their approach. Autobiography is, as he writes, both historical and fictional, both private and public, both truthful and imagined. The genre must therefore be distinguished from both history and fiction. Popkin, citing David Carr, stresses that autobiography is primarily making sense of experience by giving it narrative form.</p>
      <p>The value of Popkin's approach becomes clear in his chapter on two historians whose autobiographies have been included in the literary canon for many years: Edward Gibbon and Henry Adams. By reading them as historians, Popkin offers new insights to an already great body of literature on these authors, for instance by showing that both Gibbon and Adams believed that their personal experiences helped them in understanding the past. Not all 327 autobiographers listed in the bibliography are discussed in depth, and in chapters on vocation and career their works serve to sketch an impression of the historical profession in the twentieth century. Bookish children from middle‐class backgrounds, as most historians have been, often picked up their vocation from parents or teachers. They were also often inspired by children's books like those by Jules Verne and Karl May, which is interesting, because despite these literary models they chose to write nonfiction. For Popkin this is a telling detail, as he concludes that historians are obviously motivated by a wish to tell stories. With few exceptions historians are reluctant to write about their careers. Most are silent about their academic successes, failures, and frustrations, and few pages are spent on the daily life of teaching courses and doing administrative work. On the contrary, most authors want to show that they had another life besides their profession. Therefore they often describe their own lives against the background of great events. Since Jean‐Jacques Rousseau's<italic>Confessions</italic>, autobiography has been seen as a genre that should focus on the innermost experience and not world events, but many historians simply could not cast off their professional background. Often only those historians who were involved in politics became aware of how little an individual could accomplish, or lost faith in the ideas they once had believed. Holocaust memoirs are discussed in a separate chapter, in which Popkin concludes that these authors more than others came to realize how much personal narrative contributes to understanding the past. The testimony of first‐person accounts also have great importance in view of the campaign to deny the reality of the Holocaust.</p>
      <p>At some places it could have been useful to set this body of texts in an even wider perspective. The silence about careers, for instance, is surprising when contrasted with academic novels in which university life is described as a theater of politics and passions. And the positive tone of most of these autobiographies may also have been enhanced by the current pressure to produce positive resumés.</p>
      <p>This book is a very original and important contribution to both the study of autobiography and that of historiography. In addition to his analysis of autobiographies of historians, Popkin gives new insights about the relationship between narrative and history. Maybe every historian should write an autobiography at some stage as an essential step in his or her professional development.</p>
   </body>
</article>
