<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">philrhet</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Philosophy &amp; Rhetoric</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318213</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15272079</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">philrhet.45.4.0406</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/philrhet.45.4.0406</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Recovering Hyperbole:</article-title>
            <subtitle>Rethinking the Limits of Rhetoric for an Age of Excess</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Joshua R. Ritter</string-name>
               <aff>Department of English, University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">45</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">philrhet.45.4.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>406</fpage>
         <lpage>428</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/philrhet.45.4.0406"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Hyperbole is an easily misunderstood and misused trope, and it is largely unexplored in current rhetorical studies. Yet, at moments within thought and discourse, the excessiveness of hyperbole elicits a constructive, transformative ambiguity that can reveal alternative epistemological and ontological insights. Indeed, hyperbole is often the most effective way of trying to express seemingly impossible and inexpressible positions. I argue for the reexploration and critical examination of hyperbole, and I offer a theoretical framework from which to view texts and discourse from a hyperbolic perspective. I identify the metafunction of hyperbole, and I offer two specific functions of hyperbole. Hyperbole is more than simply an obvious and intentional exaggeration and thus can benefit from an exploration that considers it beyond its traditional tropological limits. It can be engaged as a mode of inquiry in order to delve into the complexities and paradoxes of theo-philosophical discourse, and it can also be appropriated as a critical position from which one might, for example, propose interpretations of various textual expressions that differ from their more normative interpretations.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
         <disp-quote content-type="epi">
            <p>In Linnaean terms,<italic>excess</italic>is the order,<italic>bombast</italic>and<italic>hyperbole</italic>the genera, and within the genus<italic>hyperbole</italic>, one finds various species: metaphoric hyperbole, discursive hyperbole, hyperbole ruled by allegory, hyperbole as litotes, and hyperbole that verges on irony, catachresis, or paradox.</p>
            <attrib>—Christopher D. Johnson,<italic>Hyperboles</italic>
            </attrib>
         </disp-quote>Hyperbole is an exaggeration, an excess, literally meaning to “throw beyond” (from “υπερ,” meaning “over and above, beyond” and “βολή,” meaning “to throw”). It is a familiar and often used trope, and it is often dismissed for its seeming obviousness. Left out of Giambattista Vico's, and later Kenneth Burke's, influential account of the four master tropes, hyperbole is largely a misunderstood trope today. A handful of contemporary scholars have explored hyperbole as the master trope, or the “trope-producing trope,” and they use it to describe a mode of thought or a form of philosophical inquiry that transcends its more technical uses as a linguistic trope. Yet, within current rhetorical theory, the topic of hyperbole lacks extended critical exploration. This is unfortunate because the contradictory and complex functions of hyperbole have particular importance for rhetorical theorists and critics, as these functions can provide epistemological and ontological insights.</p>
      <p>Hyperbole is one of the most effective ways of trying to express the often confounding and inexpressible positions that characterize the litigious discussions of impossibility and the struggle with transcendence and immanence, the conceptual (re)articulation of subjectivity, and the destabilization of systems of knowledge and economy. It is employed when language or thought must transcend epistemological and ontological boundaries in order to describe the magnitude of an extraordinary perspective or situation. It stretches language to its breaking point and responds in abundance, in<italic>copia</italic>. Hyperbole is more than a stylistic figure of speech. It is a “sophisticated, discursive figure of thought” (Johnson<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 44), an “inordinate movement and a violent impulsion” (Webb<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">1993a</xref>, 18), that canbe a generator of thought and meaning (Stanivukovic<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), a mental phenomenon (Holmqvist and Pluciennik<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), a propelling toward transcendence from an immanent exigency (Simpson<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), a tool of philosophical and religious inquiry (Ettenhuber<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) as well as an argumentative form (Ricoeur<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Schlueter<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Perelman and Olbrechts-Tyteca<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Hyperbole is not simply the “overreacher” or “<italic>lowd lyer</italic>” (Sidney 2010; Puttenham<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), and it is not merely a distortion or an obvious exaggeration. More often than is typically recognized, hyperbole is necessary for communicating grand and complex ideas, and it can be, as Hayden White says of other tropes, a “<italic>mode of comprehension</italic>” (1990, 3). It dramatically holds the real and the ideal in irresolvable tension and reveals the impossible distance between the ineptitude and the infinite multiplicity of language to describe that which is indescribable.</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, hyperboles are not usually considered to be that complex (for example, “It's a million degrees outside,” “From his mouth speech flowed sweeter than honey,” or “His arms reached for miles”). Rather, they are dismissed as simplistic or easily identified and interpreted, a characterization that largely accounts for why hyperbole is misunderstood today. As Louis Wirth Marvick writes of hyperbole's low standing, “If twentieth-century critics have not appreciated the full meaning of hyperbole, it is doubtless because they have clung too tenaciously to their ability to see through it” (1986, 61). Stephen H. Webb similarly asserts that “at best, when we hear hyperbole at all today it sounds ridiculous, foolish, absurd, even fanatical” (1993a, xii). However, I contend that as either figure of speech or figure of thought it forcefully beckons the hearer to “throw beyond” convention and discover a new and perhaps surprising insight or perspective. As some scholars I discuss suggest, it is a practice of excess, an event, an act of becoming, a mode of thought, and a strategy of polemic. More than other tropes, hyperbole is an intense heightening and an exaggeration of the literal with the intent of undermining and/or throwing beyond it.</p>
      <p>In order to make my argument that hyperbole is a creative, transformative trope in need of reexploration and to show how it can contribute to contemporary rhetorical theory and criticism, I offer an explication of hyperbole's functions. Various authors I discuss draw on general characteristics of hyperbole in order to evaluate and/or describe a mode of thought or an argumentative form, but they do not fully demarcate its specific rhetorical functions. Identifying these functions as the modus operandi of hyperbole, then, serves to further clarify how it is used within thought and discourse. In turn, this can allow rhetorical theorists and critics to explore hyperbole beyond its stylistic limits and identify those less obvious instances in which it is being used as a discursive figure of thought. Such an analysis can help us view texts from a hyperbolic perspective, perhaps a perspective by incongruity.</p>
      <p>I first briefly present some general positions regarding hyperbole. I then discuss more particular views about hyperbole in order to show its metafunction, its global purpose, that is, a reorientation out of disorientation. Next, I explicate its two specific functions: problematizing impossibility and possibility and disrupting hermeneutical boundaries, that is, serving as a lie on the side of truth(s). These two specific functions constitute the basic tropological parts of hyperbole. As topoi, they guide and structure my argument and offer a framework by which to identify and to evaluate the different ways hyperbole operates within texts and discourse. This evaluation reveals the duplicity of hyperbole's paradoxical formations; through its explicit uses of exaggeration and excess, it pushes interpretation and thought beyond its normative limits.</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>THE SUBJECT OF HYPERBOLE</title>
         <p>Approaching hyperbole is a difficult task, since it is and was so often dismissed as an obvious, offensive, and simplistic trope offering little to no theoretical insights. To use one of Quintilian's examples, “As he [Antony] vomited, he filled his lap and the whole platform with gobbets of food” (2001, 8.6.68). For many, there is no more to hyperbole than this type of obvious exaggeration, which is confirmed by its contentious history. Aristotle, for example, considers hyperbole “adolescent,” describing it as an aspect of metaphor in<italic>On Rhetoric</italic>, and he offers a significant critique of various types of excess in the<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>. Demetrius regards it as being oftentimes “frigid,” that is, indecorous (1995, 427), though he does highlight its utility for expressing the impossible. Although Pseudo-Longinus favors hyperbole—he places it in the elevated style, characterizing it as a useful trope for putting a “strain on the facts” and transporting one's audience to the sublime through intense<italic>pathos</italic>—he asserts that it may easily be “ruined by overshooting the mark” (1995, 285, 281). Hyperbole was often considered bombastic, associated only with epideictic rhetoric (where it functions quite well), and was aligned with excessive stylistic vices of the sophists.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>Indeed, hyperbole was often accused of<italic>cacozelia</italic>, or “perverse affectation,” which results from insincerity or poor judgment and is “the worst faults of all eloquence” (Quintilian 8.3.56).</p>
         <p>On the other hand, certain definitions and conceptions of hyperbole indicate that it can serve as a significant epistemological force within language. Despite his emphasis on moderation, in<italic>De oratore</italic>, Cicero defines hyperbole (which he refers to using the Latin word “superlatio”) as “exaggeration and overstatement of the truth for the sake of amplification or diminution” (2001, 3.203), which indicates a special consideration for the decorous use of hyperbole in opportune moments. The author of<italic>Rhetorica ad Herennium</italic>states that “emphasis is produced through Hyperbole [<italic>exsuperationem</italic>] when more is said than the truth warrants” (2004, 4.53.67). Similarly, Quintilian suggests that hyperbole (the Latin word he uses is “superiectio”) is “an appropriate [or elegant] exaggeration [or surpassing] of the truth” (2001, 8.6.67). These are interesting and complex passages that point to the epistemological play of hyperbole at the limits of “truth,” and this idea of it as meaningful play is further developed by Renaissance rhetors such as Desiderius Erasmus, especially in his influential system of<italic>copia</italic>. Indeed, Renaissance writing offers a rich terrain for hyperbole's imaginative uses. The key, according to Renaissance writers, is to use hyperbole in order to attempt to communicate the extraordinary “beyond” of thought and language—to make the transcendent immanent and to express the ineffable. These varied historical views of hyperbole present an interesting tension regarding the trope, and the debate surrounding the question of its usefulness continues today.</p>
         <p>What I am suggesting is that it is the less obvious, nuanced hyperboles that are significant and that deserve further critical attention, for example, philosophical, discursive, prophetic, ironic, or polemical hyperboles. What I show in discussing some of these types of hyperbole is that hyperbole can and does operate as more than just a simplistic, intentional, and commonplace exaggeration. According to Jean-Pierre Mileur, Paul de Man “suggests, variously, that hyperbole is the trope of tropes, the trope that governs the formation of tropes, the trope that governs the transformation of tropes into texts or, most important, that hyperbole is the (non)trope that exceeds the limits of all tropologies, the situation out of and against which tropes arise and are generalized into texts, the shape of our being-in-the-world, not reducible to rhetorical terms” (1986, 125). Mileur's more extreme claims about de Man's thought regarding hyperbole as a (non)trope or as irreducible to rhetorical terms notwithstanding, what Mileur may be driving at in this audacious, perhaps exaggerated, statement is the significance that hyperbole has as a movement within discourse and in relation to the interpretation of meaning. It is a figure of thought that can highlight the limits of figuration and representation (Bloom<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>), operate as a vehicle for the sublime (Marvick<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>), destabilize norms and conventions, and encourage active reflection on “the different ways in which meaning is constructed and communicated” (Ettenhuber<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, 210).</p>
         <p>Hyperbole can offer a way of playing with meaning at the extreme boundaries of thought where no synthesis or middle ground is sought or desired. It is “an incredible, exaggerated utterance [that] interrupts the language and logic of the existing argument” by shifting “one level of meaning to another, re-invented meaning” (Stanivukovic<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, 20). The question for hyperbole is the one posed by Gerard Genette in his essay “Hyperboles”: “Does not this hyperbolic mode of thought (wit) have its reasons, which commonsense ignores and which reason wishes to know?” (Johnson<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 4).What these statements indicate is that hyperbole is a complex trope in relation to language and thought and that it can offer epistemological insight through its interruption of logic and as a “hyperbolic mode of thought.”</p>
         <p>The purpose of hyperbole is to open up other horizons for meaning and being. As Mikhail Bakhtin suggests when discussing the carnival grotesque, by its transgression of convention “hyperbolization” can be an “act of becoming,” and transgressing its own limits is “the very nature of exaggeration” (1984, 317, 307). Drawing from his work regarding hyperbolic parody within the folk tradition, one can argue that this act of becoming is vital for hyperbole—it provides a way of transitioning out of paradoxical excess and exaggeration, enabling a new insight or perspective to be revealed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>THE GLOBAL PURPOSE</title>
         <p>Hyperbole can offer one alternative perceptions of meaning and being, both psychologically and phenomenologically (Johnson<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), through the way of excess and exaggeration, and this is its global purpose—it reorients by disorienting. Once a perplexing and sometimes disturbing disorienting perception occurs, this<italic>vertige de l'hyperbole</italic>as Baudelaire refers to it, one is ready for a perspectival reorientation—a paradoxical movement leading toward insight and partial apprehension. By generating confusion through excess, hyperbole alters and creates meaning.</p>
         <p>This operative impetus of hyperbole is not one historically ascribed to it. It is somewhat implied but never fully articulated. Paul Ricoeur offers an understanding of this metafunction of hyperbole, but he does not elaborate on his statements in any detail or discuss their implications.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>He posits that hyperbole “reorients by first disorienting [the law of paradox and hyperbole] … [and] makes the extraordinary break forth in the ordinary [the law of extravagance]” (1995, 229).<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>Hyperbolic paradox stretches the imagination through its extravagance and in one's ambiguous apprehension of it, because it is only in the obscure space of “para” that one is disoriented enough to surrender presuppositions about thought and reality, thereby preparing the way for a newly reimagined perspective.</p>
         <p>For example, both Stephen H. Webb and Ricoeur identify hyperbole as operating paradoxically in Emmanuel Levinas's thought. In<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>, Ricoeur states, “By hyperbole it must be strongly underscored, we are not to understand a figure of style, a literary trope, but the systematic practice of<italic>excess</italic>in philosophical argumentation” (1992, 337). Ricoeur shows how this practice of excess is at work in Levinas's discussion of absolute otherness, and he describes hyperbole as a strategy suited to produce “the effect of a break with regard to the idea of exteriority.” He argues, for instance, that in Levinas's thought hyperbole paradoxically reaches, to the point of paroxysm, the poles of the same and the other simultaneously through the “hyperbole of separation” and the “hyperbole of epiphany.” In like manner, Webb views hyperbole in vertical terms, and he identifies the language of height in Levinas's thought. What Webb suggests is that Levinas employs a variety of hyperbolic concepts in order to communicate his complex ideas, and he argues that hyperbole is “the perfect trope for a project that tries to say what cannot be said” (1999, 4). What Ricoeur and Webb posit overall is that Levinas is approaching ethics from a complex, perplexing hyperbolic perspective whereby he may reveal those problematic places within philosophical discourse that he may not have discovered or been able to communicate in any other way except through excess and exaggeration.</p>
         <p>Webb actually takes this approach with several different thinkers. He has a fairly radical conception of hyperbole and rarely, if at all, views it as a figure of speech. For him, hyperbole is neither intentional nor unintentional. It is an inherent, fundamental force functioning within discourse that cannot be reduced “to simple declarative statements” (1993b, 89). It is a performative and dramatic trope that abruptly interrupts “ordinary discourse,” pushing it beyond its limits, and it always operates as a figure of thought through what he calls the “hyperbolic imagination” (1993a). He argues, for example, that hyperbole is “an inherent temptation within language … against the structures that make communication reasonable, ordered, and trustworthy” (2000, 281). Hyperbole in his view is more than simply emphasis; it is “the drive toward magnification and intensification that comprises all of rhetoric” (2000, 282).</p>
         <p>Webb identifies hyperbole as operating within the thought of a number of philosophers and writers, including William James, Friedrich Nietzsche, Søren Kierkegaard, Georges Bataille, Flannery O'Connor, G. K. Chesterton, and Karl Barth (1993a, 1993b, 1995).<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>As a theologian, Webb also views certain theological concepts such as charity, grace, ethics, the gift, and love as hyperbolic (1996, 2000). He suggests, and I agree with him, that religious language and the project of theology itself are hyperbolic—for example, the assertion of Christ's divinity is hyperbolic, and “the eschatological imagination is a dramatic exaggeration of the basic human desire for satisfaction and harmony” (1999, 13). Hyperbole is not simply a ridiculous utterance that is easily dismissed. What Ricoeur and Webb each confirm is that hyperbole is a mode of thought and a practice of excess that can reveal theo-philosophical insight and express what cannot be expressed in any other way. It is a play with extremity at the boundaries of reason and rationality whereby logical thought forms are opened up to radical perspectival expressions; it is a “consent to a perspective from which certain views would not otherwise exist” (Webb<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">1993a</xref>, 20). Identifying or adopting a hyperbolic perspective, however, is more than a theoretical mode of thought, just as it is more than a simple and obvious trope.</p>
         <p>Hyperboles are a contextual response to an exigence just as much as they are a way of perceiving and approaching meaning and being in general. Often creating intense<italic>affectus</italic>in the audience, Johnson suggests, “the hyperbolist perceives an extraordinary, outrageous, ridiculous, or ineffable<italic>res</italic>(thing, event, feeling, idea), while his or her<italic>verba</italic>(words, speech, language) strain discursive limits, analogical frameworks, and literary and rhetorical conventions, to represent that<italic>res</italic>” (2010, 2). Here Johnson indicates that one would not use hyperbole or adopt a hyperbolic perspective unless the magnitude of some event or experience called for and justified its use. To be sure, those such as Levinas are responding to an extraordinary, contextualized experience or event, though it may not be readily apparent that their response is a hyperbolic one, and so the next question for hyperbole thus becomes one of intent. It is often presumed that hyperbole must be intentional, but as Ricoeur and Webb indicate, that is not necessarily the case, since one may be engaging in a practice of excess in philosophical argumentation in response to some extraordinary exigence without being fully aware that one is assuming a hyperbolic mode of thought.</p>
         <p>Chaim Perelman and Lucie Olbrechts-Tyteca assert that hyperbole may be intentionally “fired with brutality,” but they also imply that hyperbole may be operating unintentionally within what they call an argument of “unlimited development”—and in such a context, it should not be reduced “to a mere figure of style” (1969, 291). This type of argument is one that continues, goes further, and attempts to pass beyond. It is used “to define certain ‘purified’ notions,” and they argue that the role of hyperbole is to push realizable terms toward an unrealizable ideal (1969, 288, 289). Its role “is to give a direction to thought, to guide it toward a favorable evaluation of this direction, and only by a return shock is it intended to give an indication of the significant term” (1969, 290). Hyperbole “draws the mind in a certain direction … to the extreme limit” and gives force and direction to an argument of unlimited development (1969, 291). It is the driving impetus behind this type of argument, and its functions give shape and form to an ideal thought, concept, or term.</p>
         <p>For example, Saint Anselm of Canterbury posits in<italic>Proslogion</italic>, and more extensively in<italic>Liber apologeticus contra Gaunilonem</italic>, that “God is that than which nothing greater can be conceived.” One might suggest that he is here engaging in a hyperbolic mode of thought in his argument of unlimited development for the ontological proof of God's existence. Other than for his satisfaction theory of atonement offered in<italic>Cur deus homo</italic>, Anselm is most known for this proof. Responding, in many ways, to nominalists such as Roscellin, abbot of Compiegne, who argued that universals are only words and have no actual existence, Anselm sought to prove God's existence through reason alone. For Anselm, God is a “universal substance,” which exists in both intellect and reality, and is the rule against which all is measured. In his argument he pushes toward this ultimate term, which he takes to dizzying heights through his use of<italic>amplificatio</italic>. Employing<italic>incrementum</italic>by asserting what has no superior at all (Quintilian 8.4.7), Anselm presents his argument of intense degree—“that than which nothing greater can be conceived.” Although it is doubtful his explicit intent is to approach his discussion of God from a hyperbolic standpoint, in order to address the exigence of such an extraordinary subject matter he argues in the most effective way possible—through the practice of excess. Drawing the mind to the extreme limit, as Perelman and Olbrechts-Tyteca say, Anselm stretches the limits of reason through the hyperbolic within an argument of unlimited development in order to express what is inconceivable.</p>
         <p>Derrida, on the other hand, takes hyperbole in a different direction than Perelman and Olbrechts-Tyteca do in<italic>On the Name</italic>, where he discusses hyperbole in various ways in terms of negative theology. Debates on the relation/distinction between<italic>apophasis</italic>and<italic>kataphasis</italic>as well as considerations regarding negative theology and deconstruction notwithstanding, Derrida's view of hyperbole in terms of negative theology—as well as hyper-critique, hyper-impossibility, and hyper-responsibility—is quite illuminating. He translates “hyperbole” as “the movement of transcendence that carries or transports beyond being or beingness” (1995, 64), a definition he derives from Plato's<italic>Republic</italic>. In this excessive movement of “paradoxical hyperbole,” “X ‘is’ beyond what ‘is.’” X<italic>is</italic>without being (X), and this event of hyperbole “<italic>announces</italic>” in a double sense of signaling or revealing an openness and of provoking the opening of the possibility (64). Although for Derrida negative theology ultimately undermines itself through its own reasoning and always leads back to an absolute presence, the driving force of this theo-philosophical movement to communicate the incommunicable at the disorienting limits of figuration—at the beyond of “what is”—is still attempted through the paradox of hyperbole.</p>
         <p>In a similar line of reasoning, John D. Caputo (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>) discusses the “hyperbolic alterity of God.” Pushing Rudolf Otto's notion beyond itself, Caputo states that “wholly other” is a hypernym. Again, hyperbole is being used in an argument of unlimited development that represents God as (beyond) X, a characterization that Caputo suggests indicates an expenditure without reserve. He posits that a variety of hyperbolic “God is …” statements push toward the unrealizable term of “wholly other,” and for him, the ultimate term “wholly other” is also a hyperbole. The danger, he suggests, is that utter alterity can present one with and be overtaken by “<italic>another</italic>Wholly Other” and collapse into anonymity, undermining the very hypernym meant to indicate what is other than being, beyond being, or without being. What Caputo misses and what Derrida highlights is that hyperbole is an impossible<italic>signal</italic>or<italic>provocation</italic>for that which might be possible. Viewing alterity from a hyperbolic perspective is not simply signifying an endless chain of other “wholly others” to the point of meaninglessness. Alterity is a philosophical position that is the opening up to possibilities through the bewilderment of the impossible, and hyperbole is the mode of thought that allows for this thinking in and through extremity.</p>
         <p>What the discussion reveals thus far is that hyperbole is more than a figure of speech. It is a complex perspective and mode of thought that generates meaning, offers various ways from which to generate that meaning, and communicates through paradox. Hyperbole functions in this way at a metalevel by disorienting the audience or subject, by straining thought and stretching language beyond its limits, in order to communicate the magnitude of an extraordinary event or experience. What is also clear is that hyperbole is inexorably tied to both possibility and impossibility, and moving through the difficulty of impossibility is one of the two main functions of hyperbole.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>THROUGH IMPOSSIBILITY, TOWARD POSSIBILITY</title>
         <p>Current theorists, as we have seen, are eager to highlight the fact that hyperbole poses an impossible exaggeration, but they do not specifically elucidate how hyperbolic impossibility drives one toward other perspectival possibilities or how it destabilizes the very impossibility/possibility binary thinking it engages. Yet in the current context of postmodern and poststructuralist thought with its predisposition for deconstructive criticism and its inclination to abandon moderation and aesthetic proportionality, this is an important function of hyperbole that should not be overlooked. Thus, the topos of impossibility and possibility is one that needs explicit development if a theoretical framework through which a hyperbolic perspective might be employed in critical analysis is to be established.</p>
         <p>The disorienting movement through the difficulty of the impossible toward the possible is particularly evident in Seneca's theory of hyperbole. In<italic>On Benefits</italic>, he writes, “Exaggeration never hopes all its daring flights to be believed, but affirms what is incredible, that thereby it may convey what is credible” (1905, 7.23). Through exaggeration one asserts “what could not possibly be in order that they might be thought to be as much so as possible.” Seneca posits that hyperbole is well suited to express the inexpressible, which leads to a realization of other possibilities. Johnson suggests that, for Seneca, as one pushes the bounds of belief for the purpose of transition “in the larger pursuit of ‘truth,’ hyperbole's provisional violence against belief and reason becomes necessary and fitting,” and the extraordinary becomes a “driving cognitive force” (2010, 292, 293). Through a momentarily violent teleological suspension of belief and reason, one is able to experience and to move through the difficulty of the impossible and thereby tentatively apprehend and even alter what might be, or become, credible and possible. The brutal contradiction between reality and ideality fosters a transition from one perspective to another.</p>
         <p>What Seneca does not address is the intense strain hyperbolic impossibility places on the audience/subject as it moves toward its bewildering idealized heights. It “both invites and distances the audience from the height of an apparently unreasonable position” (Webb<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 3). Through a type of “functional ignorance” regarding the incredible, hyperbole emphasizes the limits of figuration in order to disrupt them and to offer a “perspectival mobility” (Ettenhuber<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, 210, 212). Noel Malcolm writes that hyperbole “makes reference to impossible things not because it is trying to describe an impossible world … but as a rhetorical figure, to emphasize and dramatize impossibility itself” (1997, 84). Malcolm stresses that what is important about hyperbole is not that it offers an “impossible world” but that it dramatically (re)presents a world reimagined through impossibility. Hyperbolic impossibility is not an absurdity. It signals and reveals the opening and limits of possibility, and it discloses the implications that impossibility may have for meaning itself.</p>
         <p>For example, Derrida's overall project may be considered a hyperbolic one, as operating within a hyperbolic mode of discourse where writing as such is identified with the “daemonizing trope of hyperbole” (de Bolla<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>, 51).<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>At exigent philosophical moments, he offers excessive concepts, such as the trace, dissemination,<italic>pharmakon</italic>,<italic>différance</italic>, and even “the impossible” itself, and he strains discursive limits and analogical frameworks (<italic>verba</italic>) in order to shift one level of meaning to another and resist the closure of impossibility (a reimagined<italic>res</italic>). Although Derrida privileges irony over other tropes, Mileur argues that for him “the hyperbolic situation … creates the necessity of interpretation (1990, 80).<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>Out of his disorienting hyperbolic language that commits provisional violence against interpretation, belief, and reason comes other epistemological and ontological possibilities. Derrida's hyperbolic mode of thought reveals the complexity of impossibility itself.</p>
         <p>More specifically, Derrida considers<italic>daimonias hyperboles</italic>to be “marvelous transcendence,” or “paradoxical hyperboles,” and he describes his project as the “attempt-to-say-the-demonic-hyperbole from whose heights thought is announced to itself,<italic>frightens</italic>itself, and<italic>reassures</italic>itself against being annihilated or wretched in madness or in death” (1978, 61). One may be annihilated in the impossibility of madness, but it is madness, the insanity of hyperbolic doubt, that drives his project of possible impossibilities. Derrida asserts that hyperbole functions to open and found the world by exceeding it “only<italic>within</italic>the space opened by demonic hyperbole.” This is the impossible task Derrida must move through toward the “very possibility” of the project of thinking, which moves “only in the direction of infinity or nothingness” (1978, 56). To attempt this project of madness is an impossible possibility facilitated through the “hybris” of “demonic hyperbole.” Out of a disorienting hyperbolic movement through the difficulty of impossibility, a reorientation occurs that is a transition toward possibility, even if that possibility is impossibility itself.</p>
         <p>I have thus far offered a general movement of this function of hyperbole. What is now crucial to demonstrate is its more specific movement through amplification. Hyperbole is the extreme form of amplification, and Quintilian suggests that, as a species of<italic>amplificatio</italic>, hyperbole falls under the purview of its four categories:<italic>incrementum</italic>(increment),<italic>comparatio</italic>(comparison),<italic>ratiocinatio</italic>(inference), and<italic>congeries</italic>(accumulation), which is closely aligned with<italic>ratio minunendi</italic>(attenuation). For example, one might offer a disproportionate name, an appropriate word replaced with a stronger one, such as “alterity” for “otherness.” Indeed, the hypernym “alterity” is the hyperbolic endeavor to communicate the incommunicable, thereby elevating its status as a critical conceptual stance, since stating “otherness,” or even the absolute otherness of the other, does not fully indicate the philosophical magnitude of what one is attempting to convey.</p>
         <p>In terms of the four categories of amplification, hyperbole is commonly expressed through<italic>incrementum</italic>, for instance, which is quite similar in structure to an argument of unlimited development. There are different types of incremental amplification. The first type proceeds, as Quintilian explains, “either by one step or by several” to the “top” and sometimes goes beyond it (2001, 8.4.4); for example, “God is (not) …” statements may lead up to and go beyond the impossible “wholly other.” The second type gives the “highest point” and then something more, such as “God is omnipotent … and certainly (beyond) ineffable.” The third type is one in which what is stated is “not the stage above the greatest, but something which has no superior at all” (2001, 8.4.7), for instance, Anselm's statement that God has no superior.</p>
         <p>Another form of<italic>incrementum</italic>is when “a succession of details, each stronger than the last, occurs in a continuous passage without any break in the sentence,” for example, “Vomiting is revolting even when not in an assembly, … even if not an assembly of the people, … even if it were not, … if he was doing, … if he was doing, … even if it were not” (2001, 8.4.8–8.4.9). In a more extreme form, Derrida states: “Even if the totality of what I think, … even if the totality of the world, … even if nonmeaning….Even if I do not<italic>in fact</italic>grasp the totality” (1978, 56–57). Each “even if” statement incrementally builds on the previous one until finally culminating in the excessive impossibility of “madness” and “the demonic.” Hyperbole is also expressed through the other forms of amplification, but<italic>incrementum</italic>offers a ready example based on the hyperbolic arguments I have already presented. Hyperbole is a specific movement of amplification toward impossible heights and depths when expressed in terms of excess and extremity. It is, of course, a matter of degree.</p>
         <p>Approaching Mark C. Taylor's<italic>copia</italic>of a/theological discourse from a hyperbolic perspective, for example, reveals this movement of hyperbole well. Taylor, especially in his earlier work, reads the radical theology of Thomas J. J. Althizer through a postmodern lens, constructing his own hyperbolic and paradoxical a/theological arguments. Through the practice of excess as a mode of thought, he radically (de)constructs a hybridity of theology and un-theology while tracing excessive, exaggerated concepts, for instance, the “not,” “erring,” the “Divine Milieu,” or “altar-ity,” along the disorienting margins of (un)thought that “mark” the openings within discourse, where an astonishing (re)apprehension may be gleaned. Taylor's most effective option in his attempt to write “beyond the end of theology,” which reveals the lack of language that is “inscribed in and as the failure of words” (1990, 223), is to write with/in this lack through the language of excess. Responding to the exigence of the current theological struggle with representation, methodology, and what he identifies as the end of theology, he argues through excess in order to communicate the magnitude of his subject matter.</p>
         <p>Stretching<italic>verba</italic>to its breaking point, he dramatically attempts to communicate and re-present an extraordinary<italic>res</italic>through the disorienting and performative twists and turns of hyperbolic<italic>incrementum</italic>and<italic>congeries</italic>. In a representative example, he writes:<disp-quote>
               <p>The trace of the fugitive gods is the nonabsent absence of the Holy. This trace is a different trace, the trace of difference itself, which can never be expressed directly, revealed totally, or known completely. It is ever elusive, evasive, excessive. Irreducibly ex-orbitant, the Holy eternally returns to interrupt the circulation of knowledge and to disrupt every form of reciprocal exchange. To hear the “inhuman,” “anonymous,” “uncanny” murmur of the Holy is to become open to that which cannot be conceived, grasped, mastered, or controlled. (1990, 119)</p>
            </disp-quote>Amid this teeming sea of paradoxical complexities and discursive amalgamations, Taylor's excessive thought regarding “the Holy” that is “irreducibly ex-orbitant” and interrupts the “circulation of knowledge” reveals the use of hyperbole at work as he navigates across an ambiguous theo-philosophical topography. Incrementally augmenting, accumulating, and building toward this unrealizable term, he “throws beyond” incongruities in order to push toward the apprehension that “the Holy” is “that which cannot be conceived.” He is making the attempt to communicate the inconceivable through his language of excess and exaggeration, which is the only way he could make the attempt effectively, and the insight gleaned from his work is that the disorienting movement of theology and a/theology, beyond the end of theology, is equally and inevitably an impossible possibility.</p>
         <p>Approaching Taylor's discourse from a hyperbolic perspective, it becomes evident that, to an extreme degree, the paradoxical maneuvering of his hyperbolic imagination both relies on and is in excess, which is a necessity if his project is to provide effective insight that pertains to his extraordinary subject matter. Taylor is sometimes accused of opaque and nonsensical writing, namely,<italic>cacozelia</italic>, but when viewed from a hyperbolic perspective, his project reveals a skilled hyperbolist responding to an exorbitant exigence that calls for and justifies the extensive use of ambiguity, excess, and exaggeration.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>A LIE ON THE SIDE OF TRUTH(S)</title>
         <p>Just as with possibility and impossibility, the productive contradictory connection between truth(s) and lie as another hyperbolic function is a complex one. As Johnson states, “To hyperbolize is to tell and not to tell enormous truths in one eloquent breath” (2010, 85). This is perhaps hyperbole's most intriguing and understated function. Contemporary scholars, as I have noted, tend to focus solely on impossibility in relation to hyperbole and do not explore its function of “arriv[ing] at the truth by falsehood” (Seneca<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">1905</xref>, 7.23). That is, this function is not typically discussed explicitly or positively in current theories regarding this trope (notable exceptions include Stanivukovic and Ettenhuber). However, there are those, such as Quintilian, who offer keen insight into the truth/lie function.</p>
         <p>Quintilian is quite equivocal in his stance toward hyperbole. He is hesitant to fully embrace it, but he acknowledges the propensity for excess and deceit within everyday thought and language. He further suggests that hyperbole may often be the most appropriate expression of the tension between truth and falsehood. He states that when one must express the inexpressible and speak of something that “transcends the normal limits of nature,” it is better to go too far than not far enough since “no one is satisfied with the truth” (2001, 8.6.76). Additionally, he defines hyperbole by pointing out that hyperbole is “a liar, but does not lie to deceive” (8.6.74). On its face, this claim is a complete non sequitur because a lie is by definition always intended to deceive, to keep hidden. However, what his stance on hyperbole reveals is that hyperbole is inexorably tied to epistemological questions concerning language and the expression of meaning, for example, representation, method, invention, or even motive. His position also suggests that a hyperbolic lie is different from a lie in its general sense of the term. It is not intended to deceive but to reveal. Hyperbole speaks a double language of transcendence at the limits of figuration, a language that offers a different way of perceiving and thinking about convention and normative frameworks of knowledge. It is duplicitous—a double cross for the purpose of transition.</p>
         <p>When hyperbole functions in this way it presents a falsehood that is not intended to be deceptive and takes on the form of errancy, that is, possessing “the<italic>structure</italic>of error without being an<italic>error</italic>” (Mileur<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>, 113), whereby one can move the audience toward alternate perceptions of truth(s) and reality through the paradox of “erring” (Taylor<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>). Hyperbole is “the language of detours, of errancy, extravagance, and even errantry” (Magnus, Stewart, and Mileur<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>, 139). It is disorienting to view possible alternate interpretations of truth(s) through this errancy, but as Goran V. Stanivukovic boldly argues, “A [hyperbolic] lie, expressed in linguistic terms, becomes truth on a hermeneutical level” (2007, 17). This lie, or errant formation, presents one with such a radical, exaggerated falsehood that one's attention is arrested. One is not able to resolve the conflict immediately or easily, but the suspicion that something more is being said is heightened.</p>
         <p>For example, if one reads the polemical hyperbolic statement “It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for someone who is rich to enter the kingdom of God” (Mark 10:25, NRSV), then one hears a physical impossibility and an errant statement.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>Of course, there are several exegetical issues here, but in general, it will commonly be acknowledged that it is physically impossible for a camel to perform this task. Yet it is assumed by many that rich people can and do participate within the kingdom of God, in which case the claim that it is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for someone who is rich to enter the kingdom of God is not only an impossibility but a lie that is not intended to deceive. In the face of such a shocking or surprising incongruity, one is forced to look beyond the exaggeration for other truth(s) that might be indicated by the errancy, that is, to the idea that it is extremely difficult to enter the kingdom of God if one is driven by wealth alone.</p>
         <p>Within this story, however, is also an errant subject. The wandering and wondering subject within the text—which is also to say beyond the text—who is “greatly astounded” (Mark 10:26) is left to wrestle with his or her subjectivity on a hermeneutical level and err toward an insight indicated through the disorienting hyperbole, for example, one's relation to God and to money as well as one's conception of the kingdom of God. Hyperbolic errancy, then, is not only a rhetorical strategy of exaggeration. To arrive at the truth by falsehood is also a mode of thought and an act of becoming, as noted by Genette and Bakhtin. The lie of hyperbole presents one with an opportunity to explore the hermeneutical possibilities for expanding one's conception of truth(s) beyond its conventional bounds.</p>
         <p>In a somewhat Nietzschean line of reasoning, the excess of the exaggerated falsehood, the hyperbolic lie, is the lie in/of the “truth,” which forces one into the violence of errant subjective (re)interpretation, the truth(s) in/of the lie. Hyperbole's figural expression exceeds the literal thing expressed, thereby marking the literal (in excess) as figure, and this errancy produces real, contextual change, for example, as “hyperbolic praxis” (Webb<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">1993a</xref>), by dramatically moving toward a psychological and/or phenomenological transition. The errant formation reveals the instability at the center of what is attempting to be expressed. As Suzanne Guerlac (1990) suggests, hyperbole throws beyond the signified but also renders the signified a signifier, which signifies excess itself. It heightens the literal, exaggerates it, and throws beyond it in order to reveal its errancy and show its figurative nature, thereby allowing for a disruptive hermeneutical mode of thought that offers a transition from one way of perceiving the world to another.</p>
         <p>An example of this function within philosophical discourse can be found in Derrida's<italic>Writing and Difference</italic>, which also happens to be the work of his that contains the most explicit discussion of hyperbole. He writes:<disp-quote>
               <p>
                  <italic>At its height</italic>hyperbole, the absolute opening, the uneconomic expenditure, is always reembraced by an<italic>economy</italic>and is overcome by economy. The relationship between reason, madness, and death is an economy, a structure of deferral whose irreducible originality must be respected. This attempt-to-say-the-demonic-hyperbole is not an attempt among others; it is not an attempt which would occasionally and eventually be completed by the saying of it, or by its object, the direct object of a willful subjectivity. This attempt to say, which is not, moreover, the antagonism of silence, but rather the condition for it, is the original profundity of will in general. (1978, 61–62)</p>
            </disp-quote>He further asserts that hyperbole “cannot be enclosed in a factual and determined historical structure, for it is the project of exceeding every finite and determined totality” (1978, 60). First, Derrida uses hyperbole to make his argument. Through<italic>incrementum</italic>, he builds his position with three “(it) is not” statements and two “this attempt to say” statements. This use of<italic>amplificatio</italic>culminates in suggesting that the attempt-to-say-the-demonic-hyperbole is the “original profundity of will in general.” Second, as a figure of thought, Derrida invokes the attempt-to-say-the-demonic-hyperbole as the overall project of uneconomic expenditure. Paradoxically, even though he posits that hyperbole exceeds “every finite and determined totality,” he also argues that it is always reeconomized even “<italic>at its heights</italic>.” This is a stark contradiction, and it is one that is supported by the function of hyperbolic errancy.</p>
         <p>Derrida is specifically addressing the role of hyperbole within his thought, but his argument is also driven by the hyperbolic through a practice of excess. He exaggerates the lie of exceeding the totality in order to “announce” the opening of the possibility, which paradoxically precipitates the structure of deferral it attempts to escape but is always entrenched within. Demonic, duplicitous hyperbole will always reach beyond its own economy of signification, but it will never succeed in exceeding because the heights of hyperbole always descend back into reeconomization, a point Derrida also makes in his discussion of hyperbole and negative theology. This highlights two characteristics of “demonic hyperbole” for Derrida that further reveal its errant structure: 1) its infinite deferral within a system it attempts to exceed and 2) its necessary force of repetition.</p>
         <p>Derrida states that hyperbole is “the uneconomic expenditure,” which both can and cannot exceed economy. His statement has the structure of error without being an error. He speaks the language of extremity and of exceeding economy in order to emphasize the repetitive necessity of making the attempt to “throw beyond.” Through hyperbolic errancy, the repetition of the attempt-to-say-the-demonic-hyperbole, the signifier exceeds the signified that is already in excess. The attempt will never be completed but is always necessary. Thus, Derrida engages in a hyperbolic mode of thought regarding hyperbole itself in order to reveal that the radical attempt to throw beyond the economy of writing is an impossible possibility that must always be attempted but will never arrive.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s05">
         <title>CONCLUSION</title>
         <p>More than a simple and obvious trope, hyperbole is a perspective that allows one to view the world otherwise through the use of excess and exaggeration. It is a mode of thought, a practice of excess, and an act of becoming. It can operate discursively, polemically, prophetically, paradoxically, and philosophically. It is a generator of meaning and being and a lens through which to view the world and the limits of knowledge differently. It is a disruptive force within language that always attempts to move beyond the insufficiency of thought and language while at the same time revealing the errant multiplicity and exorbitance of discourse through the abundance of excess. Hyperbole is a different kind of speech; through it a lie that is not a deception can be employed on the side of truth(s), which is always lacking and unstable, necessitating the abundance of excess.</p>
         <p>The enormity of a particular exigence may be such that one of the only tropes capable of communicating the incommunicable is the one that so adamantly risks miscommunication. Hyperbole stirs one's emotions through the convergence of power and luminosity in a transcendental display of immanental insight that extends beyond the purview of logic and reason, thereby creating the intensity of<italic>vertige de l'hyperbole</italic>, which threatens to dismantle conventions of reason and rationality. Revealing that reason is madness and madness is reason through its “mad audacity,” this vertigo is precisely the disorienting crux of hyperbole's function of expressing the inexpressible and momentarily suspending presuppositions before they are re-oriented toward daring phenomenological and psychological reformulations.</p>
         <p>There are several contemporary theorists who explore and offer significant insight into hyperbole, but they do not fully identify its specific rhetorical functions. They each offer important characteristics of hyperbole but do not demarcate both its global purpose and its figural limits. In this article, I have outlined two specific functions of hyperbole, and I have shown how they operate within discourse. I have also identified the metafunction of hyperbole and revealed that it may operate as a figure of thought beyond its traditional tropological limits. I have not abandoned these limitations but expanded on them by grounding hyperbole as a mode of thought within its specific stylistic formations. As such, hyperbole can be used to delve into the complexities and paradoxes of ethics and theo-philosophical argumentation—the intricacies of negative theology and ascetical theology, the problematic role of subjectivity, and the difficulty of representation. It can also be used discursively to read various philosophical texts—those of Friedrich Nietzsche, Slavoj Zizek, Søren Kierkegaard, Emmanuel Levinas, and Michel Foucault, for example—in ways other than they are typically read or to explicate concepts such as the “event,” the “spectacular,”<italic>jouissance</italic>, alterity, the real, and<italic>différance</italic>.</p>
         <p>Adopting a hyperbolic perspective is also certainly a way to argue as well as a way to examine other “texts” because it is a trope and figure of thought that reveals those moments within discourse when one is attempting to transcend the bounds of reality because the extraordinary nature of a given situation or subject matter requires the use of an excessive prophetic voice or an ardent polemical exaggeration. As Mileur posits, “The work is a hyperbole, the intersection of other hyperboles, and the subject is, insofar as he can be written about at all, another hyperbole” (1990, 86). Rather than circumventing it, understanding hyperbole as the focus of thought and action can create significant moments of<italic>inventio</italic>as well as<italic>elocutio</italic>for the hyperbolist and critic alike. By approaching a particular text, a critical term, and even a piece of criticism itself from a hyperbolic perspective, one might (re)consider and (re)interpret these “texts” as a stretching of discursive limits that leads one toward a re-presentation of the extraordinary—an attempt to communicate the ineffable or transgress the expressible.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Although hyperbole is explicitly connected to epideictic throughout Greco-Roman times, the Middle Ages, and the Renaissance, it is surprisingly absent from current epideictic literature.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Katrin Ettenhuber (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) also suggests that one purpose of hyperbole in Renaissance sacred rhetorics is to offer one the possibility for a spiritual reorientation.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>) also compares this movement of disorientation and reorientation to the logic of superabundance that he connects to love as hyperethical and hypermoral in contradistinction to the logic of equivalence, which he associates with justice.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Alexander Nehamas also sees the hyperbolic operating in Nietzsche's thought and states that his writing is “irreducibly hyperbolic” and that his “writing, and his thinking, is<italic>essentially</italic>hyperbolic” (1987, 22, 31). See also Magnus, Stewart, and Mileur (<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Allan Megill (<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>) also suggests that Derrida, along with Friedrich Nietzsche, Martin Heidegger, and Michel Foucault, all rely on and communicate through excess and exaggeration, though he does not once mention hyperbole in his analysis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Today, irony is privileged over most other tropes, but this is a detrimental position to take. Paul de Man, for example, suggests that irony actually tends toward hyperbole. Discussing Baudelaire, he posits that irony often begins as litotes and moves toward the absolute through and beyond hyperbole, and he suggests that irony is the “unrelieved<italic>vertige</italic>” of “<italic>vertige de l'hyperbole</italic>” (1983, 215). Mileur suggests that for de Man, irony is a form of hyperbole operating within a hyperbolic situation. Webb also contrasts hyperbole with irony and claims that “something fundamental is lost when the manipulative desire to turn reality against itself is allowed to displace and overwhelm the basic need to see further than appearances alone permit” (1993a, xvii). By placing hyperbole at the center of language and action, this project may move one “further away from Western metaphysics than the privileging of philosophy's old ally, irony” (150).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>John Prideaux also cites this passage in<italic>Sacred Eloquence</italic>(1659) when discussing such notions as “Sublime Hyperboles” (see Ettenhuber<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, 205-206). For further examples of hyperbole used in the gospels as well as in Paul's writings, see Stein<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>and Schlueter<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>. Additionally, hyperbole is often used in the rabbinical and prophetic traditions.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation>Aristotle. 1991.<italic>On Rhetoric: A Theory of Civic Discourse</italic>. Trans. George A. Kennedy. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation>Aristotle. 1999.<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>. 2nd ed. Trans. Terence Irwin. Indianapolis, IN: Hackett.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation>Bakhtin, Mikhail. 1984.<italic>Rabelais and His World</italic>. Trans. Helene Iswolsky. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation>Bloom, Harold. 2003.<italic>A Map of Misreading</italic>. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation>Caputo, John D. 1998. “God Is Wholly Other—Almost: ‘Différance’ and the Hyperbolic Alterity of God.” In<italic>The Otherness of God</italic>, ed. Orrin F. Summerell, 190–205. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation>Cicero. 2001.<italic>De oratore</italic>. Trans. James M. May and Jakob Wisse. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation>Cicero. 2004.<italic>Rhetorica ad Herennium</italic>. Trans. Harry Caplan. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation>De Bolla, Peter. 1988.<italic>Harold Bloom: Towards Historical Rhetorics</italic>. New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation>De Man, Paul. 1983.<italic>Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism</italic>. 2nd ed. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation>Demetrius. 1995.<italic>On Style</italic>. Trans. Doreen C. Innes. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation>Derrida, Jacques. 1978.<italic>Writing and Difference</italic>. Trans. Alan Bass. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation>Derrida, Jacques. 1995.<italic>On the Name</italic>. Trans. David Wood. Palo Alto, CA: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r13">
            <mixed-citation>Ettenhuber, Katrin. 2007. Hyperbole: Exceeding Similitude. In<italic>Renaissance Figures of Speech</italic>, ed. Sylvia Adamson, Gavin Alexander, and Katrin Ettenhuber, 197–216. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r14">
            <mixed-citation>Holmqvist, Kenneth, and Jaroslaw Pluciennik. 2008.<italic>Infinity in Language: Conceptualization of the Experience of the Sublime</italic>. New Castle upon Tyne, UK: Cambridge Scholars Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r15">
            <mixed-citation>Johnson, Christopher D. 2010.<italic>Hyperboles: The Rhetoric of Excess in Baroque Literature and Thought</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r16">
            <mixed-citation>Longinus. 1995.<italic>On the Sublime</italic>. Trans. W. H. Fyfe. Ed. G. P. Goold. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r17">
            <mixed-citation>Magnus, Bernd, Stanley Stewart, and Jean-Pierre Mileur. 1993.<italic>Nietzsche's Case</italic>. New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r18">
            <mixed-citation>Malcolm, Noel. 1997.<italic>The Origins of English Nonsense</italic>. London: HarperCollins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r19">
            <mixed-citation>Marvick, Louis Wirth. 1986.<italic>Mallarme and the Sublime</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r20">
            <mixed-citation>Megill, Allan. 1985.<italic>Prophets of Extremity: Nietzsche, Heidegger, Foucault, Derrida</italic>. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r21">
            <mixed-citation>Mileur, Jean-Pierre. 1986. Allegory and Irony: ‘The Rhetoric of Temporality’ Re-Examined.”<italic>Comparative Literature</italic>38 (4): 329–36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r22">
            <mixed-citation>Mileur, Jean-Pierre. 1990.<italic>The Critical Romance: The Critic as Reader, Writer, Hero</italic>. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r23">
            <mixed-citation>Nehamas, Alexander. 1987.<italic>Nietzsche: Life as Literature</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r24">
            <mixed-citation>Perelman, Chaim, and Lucie Olbrechts-Tyteca. 2003.<italic>The New Rhetoric: A Treatise on Argumentation</italic>. Trans. John Wilkinson and Purcell Weaver. Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r25">
            <mixed-citation>Puttenham, George. 2007.<italic>The Art of English Poesy</italic>. Ed. Frank Whigham and Wayne A. Rebhorn. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r26">
            <mixed-citation>Quintilian. 2001.<italic>The Orator's Education</italic>. Ed. and trans. Donald A. Russell. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r27">
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur, Paul. 1991. “Love and Justice.” In<italic>Radical Pluralism and Truth: David Tracy and the Hermeneutics of Religion</italic>, ed. Werner G. Jeanrond and Jennifer L. Rike, 187–202. New York: Crossroad.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r28">
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur, Paul. 1992.<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>. Trans. Kathleen Blamey. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r29">
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur, Paul. 1995.<italic>Figuring the Sacred: Religion, Narrative, and Imagination</italic>. Trans. David Pellauer. Minneapolis, MN: Fortress Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r30">
            <mixed-citation>Schlueter, Carol J. 1994.<italic>Filling up the Measure: Polemical Hyperbole in 1 Thessalonians 2.14–16</italic>. Sheffield, UK: JSOT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r31">
            <mixed-citation>Seneca. 1905.<italic>On Benefits</italic>. Trans. Aubrey Stewart. London: George Bell and Sons.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r32">
            <mixed-citation>Simpson, Christopher Ben. 2009.<italic>Religion, Metaphysics, and the Postmodern: William Desmond and John D. Caputo</italic>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r33">
            <mixed-citation>Stanivukovic, Goran V. 2007. “Mounting above the Truthe”: On Hyperbole in English Renaissance Literature.<italic>Forum for Modern Language Studies</italic>43 (1): 9–33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r34">
            <mixed-citation>Stein, Robert H. 1985.<italic>Difficult Sayings in the Gospels: Jesus's Use of Overstatement and Hyperbole</italic>. Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r35">
            <mixed-citation>Taylor, Mark C. 1984.<italic>Erring: A Postmodern A/Theology</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r36">
            <mixed-citation>Taylor, Mark C. 1990.<italic>Tears</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r37">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1991.<italic>Re-Figuring Theology: The Rhetoric of Karl Barth</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r38">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1993a.<italic>Blessed Excess: Religion and the Hyperbolic Imagination</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r39">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1993b. “A Hyperbolic Imagination: Theology and the Rhetoric of Excess.”<italic>Theology Today</italic>50 (1): 56–67.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r40">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1995. “The Rhetoric of and About Excess in William James's<italic>The Varieties of Religious Experience</italic>.”<italic>Religion and Literature</italic>27 (2): 27–45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r41">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1996.<italic>The Gifting God: A Trinitarian Ethics of Excess</italic>. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r42">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 1999. “The Rhetoric of Ethics as Excess: A Christian Theological Response to Emmanuel Levinas.”<italic>Modern Theology</italic>15 (1): 1–16.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r43">
            <mixed-citation>Webb, Stephen H. 2000. “Theological Reflections on the Hyperbolic Imagination.” In<italic>Rhetorical Invention and Religious Inquiry: New Perspectives</italic>, ed. Walter Jost and Wendy Olmsted, 279–300. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r44">
            <mixed-citation>White, Hayden. 1990.<italic>Tropics of Discourse: Essays in Cultural Criticism</italic>. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
