<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philstud</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50008991</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philippine Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Ateneo de Manila University</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00317837</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">20122489</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">42633941</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bourdieu, Historical Forgetting, and the Problem of English in the Philippines</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>T. RUANNI F.</given-names>
                  <surname>TUPAS</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2008</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>56</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40098104</issue-id>
         <fpage>47</fpage>
         <lpage>67</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2008 Ateneo de Manila University</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/42633941"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article explores the nature of historical forgetting in the Philippines through the lens of Pierre Bourdieu's notion of forgetting as misrecognition, which is invested with power and struggle. The notion is concretized in the context of Reynaldo Ileto's discussion of the Schurman Commission, which was tasked to gather information about the Philippines as part of the United States' pacification campaign. Because historical forgetting is rooted in the structure of society itself, policies concerning language and education are imbued with power and class dimensions. The necessity of change in consciousness is enmeshed in the broader politics of social change, which is thus the context of the debate on the critical role of English in the Philippines. The political imperative to forget is inherent in—and partly sustains—the fundamental structure of social relations in the Philippines.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="d12723e114a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e121" publication-type="other">
Tupas 2003</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e127" publication-type="other">
Tupas 2004;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e133" publication-type="other">
Tollefson 1991, 1986</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e140" publication-type="other">
Tupas 2002;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e146" publication-type="other">
Pennycook 1992</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e152" publication-type="other">
Lorente and Tupas 2002</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e158" publication-type="other">
Tupas 2001;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e164" publication-type="other">
Phillipson 1992</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d12723e180a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e184" publication-type="other">
Alzona, Encarnacion. 1932. A history of education in the Philippines, 1565-1930. Manila: University
of the Philippines Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e198" publication-type="other">
Barrows, David P. 1907. History of the Philippines. Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e209" publication-type="other">
Bourdieu, Pierre. 1973. Cultural reproduction and social reproduction. In Knowledge, education and
cultural change: Papers on the sociology of education, ed. Richard Brown, 71-112. London:
Tavistock.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e222a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e226" publication-type="other">
---. 1988. Homo academicus, trans. Peter Collier. Cambridge: Polity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e234a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e238" publication-type="other">
---. 1990a. Language and symbolic power, ed. John Thompson. Cambridge: Polity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e245a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e249" publication-type="other">
---. 1990b. The logic of practice, trans. Richard Nice. Cambridge: Polity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e260" publication-type="other">
---. 1996. The state nobility–Elite schools in the field of power, trans. Lauretta C. Clough.
Cambridge: Polity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e274" publication-type="other">
---. 2000. Pascalian meditations, trans. Richard Nice. Cambridge: Polity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e281a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e285" publication-type="other">
Canieso-Doronila, Maria Luisa. 1998. The emergence of schools of the people and the transformation
of the Philippine education system. UP-CIDS Chronicle 3(1): 63-97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e295a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e299" publication-type="other">
Constantino, Letizia R. 1982. World Bank textbooks: Scenario for deception. Quezon City: Foundation
for Nationalist Studies.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e310a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e314" publication-type="other">
Constantino, Renato. 1970. The mis-education of the Filipino people. Journal of Contemporary Asia
1(1): 20-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e324a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e328" publication-type="other">
---, with Letizia Constantino. 1975. A history of the Philippines: From the Spanish colonization to
the Second World War. New York and London: Monthly Review Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e338a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e342" publication-type="other">
Enriquez, Virgilio. 1988. From colonial to liberation psychology: The indigeneous perspective in
Philippine psychology. Report No. 3, Southeast Asian Studies Program Teaching and Research
Exchange Fellowships, Institute of Southeast Asian Studies, Singapore.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e355a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e359" publication-type="other">
--- and Elizabeth Protaction-Marcelino. 1989. Neo-colonial politics and language struggle in the
Philippines: National consciousness and language in Philippine psychology (1971-1983). Quezon
City: Akademya ng Sokolohiyang Pilipino.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e372a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e376" publication-type="other">
Frei, Ernest J. 1949. The historical development of the Philippine national language (Chap. 1).
Philippine Social Sciences and Humanities Review 14(40): 367-400.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e386a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e390" publication-type="other">
---. 1950. The historical development of the Philippine national language (Chap. 3). Philippine
Social Sciences and Humanities Review 14(40): 45-79.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e401a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e405" publication-type="other">
Freire, Paulo and Ira Shor. 1987. A pedagogy for liberation: Dialogues on transforming education.
Westport and London: Bergin and Garvey.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e415a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e419" publication-type="other">
Fullante, Luis Cruz. 1983. The national language question in the Philippines, 1936 to the present.
Ph.D. diss., University of California in Los Angeles.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e429a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e433" publication-type="other">
Gonzalez, Andrew. 1994. Language and nationalism in the Philippines: An update. In Language
planning in Southeast Asia, comp. Abdullah Hassan, 253-67. Kuala Lumpur: Ministry of
Education.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e446a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e450" publication-type="other">
Graff, Henry F. 1969. American imperialism and the Philippine insurrection. Boston: Little, Brown.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e457a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e461" publication-type="other">
Hau, Caroline S. 1998. Literature, nationalism and the problem of consciousness. Diliman Review
46(3/4): 3-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e471a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e475" publication-type="other">
Ileto, Reynaldo C. 1999. Knowing America's colony–A hundred years from the Philippine War. Center
for Philippine Studies, Occasional Papers 13. Manoa: University of Hawai'i.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e486a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e490" publication-type="other">
Isidro, Antonio 1949. The Philippine educational system. Manila: Bookman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e497a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e501" publication-type="other">
Lopez, Salvador P. 1966. The colonial relationship. In Philippine-American relations, ed. Frank F.
Golay, 7-31. Manila: Solidaridad Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e511a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e515" publication-type="other">
Lorente, Beatriz P. In press. Packaging English-speaking products: Maid agencies in Singapore.
In Language and the market, ed. Helen Kelly-Holmes and Gerlinde Mautner. Basingstoke:
Palgrave-Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e528a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e532" publication-type="other">
--- and T. Ruanni F. Tupas. 2002. Demythologizing English as an economic asset: The case of
Filipina domestic workers in Singapore. ACELT Journal 6(2): 20-32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e542a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e546" publication-type="other">
Lusk, Hugh H. 1898. The problem of the Philippines. North American Review 167(502): 267-77.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e553a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e557" publication-type="other">
McKinley, William. 1900. Instructions of the President to the Philippine Commission, 7 April 1900.
Washington, D.C.: Bureau of Insular Affairs.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e568a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e572" publication-type="other">
Mojares, Resil B. 1999. The war against the Americans: Resistance and collaboration in Cebu,
1899-1906. Quezon City: Ateneo de Manila University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e582a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e586" publication-type="other">
Monroe, Paul. 1925. A survey of the educational system of the Philippine Islands: Created under
Acts 3162 and 3196 of the Philippine Legislature. Board of Educational Survey. Manila: Bureau
of Printing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e599a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e603" publication-type="other">
Mulder, Niels 1990. Philippine textbooks and the national self-image. Philippine Studies
38:84-102.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e617" publication-type="other">
Murphy, John W. and Jung Min Choi. 1997. Postmodernism, unraveling racism and democratic
institutions. London: Praeger.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e627a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e631" publication-type="other">
Peet, Richard, with Elaine Hartwick. 1999. Theories of development. New York: Guildford.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e638a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e642" publication-type="other">
Pennycook, Alastair. 1994. The cultural politics of English as an international language. London:
Longman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e653a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e657" publication-type="other">
Phillipson, Robert. 1992. Linguistic imperialism. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e664a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e668" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1999. Memory and forgetting. In Questioning ethics: Contemporary debates in
philosophy, ed. Richard Kearney and Mark Dooley, 5-11. London and New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e678a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e682" publication-type="other">
San Juan, E. Jr. 1998. One hundred years of reproducing and reproducing the 'Filipino.' Amerasia
Journal 24(2): 1-35.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e692a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e696" publication-type="other">
Schirmer, Daniel B. and Stephen Rosskam Shalom, eds. 1987. The Philippines reader: A history of
colonialism, neocolonialism, dictatorship, and resistance. Quezon City: KEN.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e706a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e710" publication-type="other">
Sibayan, Bonifacio P. and Andrew Gonzalez. 1996. Post-imperial English in the Philippines. In
Post-imperial English: Status change in former British and American colonies, 1940-1990, ed.
Joshua A. Fishman, Andrew W. Conrad, and Alma Rubal-Lopez, 139-72. Berlin and New York:
Mouton de Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e726a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e730" publication-type="other">
Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty. 1998. Cultural talks in the hot peace: Revisiting the "global village."
In Cosmopolites: Thinking and feeling beyond the nation, ed. Pheng Cheah and Bruce Robbins,
329-50. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e744a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e748" publication-type="other">
Sta. Maria, Felixberto C. 1999. On the teaching of English. Journal of Asian English Studies 2(1/2):
84-89.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e758a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e762" publication-type="other">
Swartz, David. 1997. Culture and power: The sociology of Pierre Bourdieu. Chicago: University of
Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e772a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e776" publication-type="other">
Tiongson, Antonio T. Jr. 2006. Introduction: Critical considerations. In Positively no Filipinos allowed:
Building communities and discourse, ed. Antonio T. Tiongson Jr., Edgardo V. Gutierrez, and
Ricardo V. Gutierrez, 1-14. Philadelphia: Temple University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e789a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e793" publication-type="other">
Tollefson, James W. 1986. Language policy and the radical left in the Philippines: The New People's
Army and its antecedents. Language Problems and Language Planning 10(2): 177-89.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e803a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e807" publication-type="other">
---. 1991. Planning language, planning inequality: Language policy in the community. London and
New York: Longman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e817a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e823" publication-type="other">
Tupas. T. Ruanni F. 2000. Viva kay Señor Sto. Niño!: Some notes towards critical language studies
in English in the Philippines. Journal of English Studies and Comparative Literature 6(1):
126-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e837a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e841" publication-type="other">
---. 2001. Linguistic imperialism in the Philippines: Reflections of an English language teacher of
Filipino Overseas Workers. Asia-Pacific Education Researcher 10(1): 1-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e851a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e855" publication-type="other">
---. 2002. A century of errors: English language teaching and a political history of Philippine-
American relations. In Ruptures and departures: Language and culture in Southeast Asia, ed.
Corazon D. Villareal, Lily Rose Tope, and Patricia May B. Jurilla, 137-75. Quezon City: University
of the Philippines Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e871a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e875" publication-type="other">
---. 2003. History, language planners, and strategies of forgetting: The problem of consciousness
in the Philippines. Language Problems and Language Planning 27(1): 1-25.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e885a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e889" publication-type="other">
---. 2004. The politics of Philippine English: Neocolonialism, global politics, and the problem of
postcolonialism. World Englishes 23(1): 47-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e899a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e903" publication-type="other">
---, ed. 2007. (Re)making society: The politics of language, discourse and identity in the Philippines.
Quezon City: University of the Philippines Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e913a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e917" publication-type="other">
UNESCO-Philippine Educational Foundation. 1953. Fifty years of education for freedom, 1901-1975.
Manila: National Printing Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e928a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e932" publication-type="other">
Valencia, E. M. 1981a. Towards a Philippine political economy. Diliman Review (May-June): 7-14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e939a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e943" publication-type="other">
---. 1981b. Towards a Philippine political economy. Diliman Review (July-August): 43-45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12723e950a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12723e954" publication-type="other">
Villareal, Corazon D. 2002. Re-searching language teaching. ACELT Journal (6)2: 33-37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
