<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">resephen</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018136</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Research in Phenomenology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill Academic Publishers, Inc.</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00855553</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15691640</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24721816</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>TOPIC: Immanence and Transcendence</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A PRESENT FOLDED BACK ON THE PAST (BERGSON)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>RUDOLF</given-names>
                  <surname>BERNET</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Basil</given-names>
                  <surname>Vassilicos</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>35</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24721810</issue-id>
         <fpage>55</fpage>
         <lpage>76</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2005 Koninklijke Brill NV</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24721816"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>In Matter and Memory, Bergson examines the relationship between perception and memory, the status of consciousness in its relation to the brain, and more generally, a possible conjunction of matter and mind. Our reading focuses in particular on his understanding of the evanescent presence of the present and of its debt vis-à-vis the "unconscious" consciousness of a "virtual" past. We wish to show that the Bergsonian version of a critique of "the metaphysics of presence" is, for all that, an offshoot of a Platonic type of metaphysics. It is true that Bergson departs from traditional stand-points on the side of a self-sufficient and original present and a form of presence to which the transparency of consciousness would confer the character of immediate evidence. All the same, it can hardly be claimed that his rehabilitation of the past and the unconscious opens up new perspectives on how forgetting and death are bound up with the work of memory.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="d1385e135a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e142" publication-type="other">
G. Deleuze, Bergsonism, trans. H. Tomlinson and B. Habberjam (New York: Zone
Books, 1988), 55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e152a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e159" publication-type="other">
H. Bergson, Matter and Memory, trans. N. M. Paul and W. S. Palmer (New York:
Zone Books, 1991; originally published as Œuvres, Edition du Centenaire (Paris:
Presses Universitaires de France, 1959). Hereafter cited as AIM, followed by page
references first to the English translation, and then to the French edition.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e175a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e182" publication-type="other">
"Everything will happen as if we allowed to filter through us that action of external
things which is real, in order to arrest and retain that which is virtual: this vir-
tual action of things upon our body and of our body on things is our perception
itself" (MM, 232/363). Cf. also MM, 58/206.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e198a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e205" publication-type="other">
"[Ejvery perception is already memory. Practically, we perceiae only the past, the pure
present being the invisible progress of the past gnawing into the future" (MM,
150/291).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e219a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e226" publication-type="other">
G. Deleuze, Difference and Repetition, trans. P. Patton (London: Continuum Press,
1994), 9Off.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e236a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e243" publication-type="other">
One should not, however, confuse this distinction between retentional memory and
a memory that recalls remembrances of the past, with the celebrated Bergsonian
distinction between recollection-memory and habit-memory (MM, 79ff./225ff). The
latter distinction in effect only concerns memory of the past under its double form
of a reactivation of a memory in its original context and the role of memories in
the immediate recognition of the present object of a concrete perception. Retentional
memory is neither a contemplation of the past nor its habitual repetition in a pre-
sent comportment.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e272a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e279" publication-type="other">
"In fact, this is just what consciousness bears witness to whenever, in order to ana-
lyze memory, it follows the movement of memory at work. Whenever we are try-
ing to recover a recollection to call up some period of our history, we become
conscious of an act sui generis by which we detach ourselves from the present in
order to replace ourselves, first, in the past in general, then in a certain region of
the past—a work of adjustment, something like the focusing of a camera. But our
recollection still remains virtual; we simply prepare ourselves to receive it by adopt-
ing the appropriate attitude. Little by little, it comes into view like a condensing
cloud; from the virtual state it passes into the actual; and as its outlines become
more distinct and its surface takes on color, it tends to imitate perception. But it
remains attached to the past by its deepest roots; and if, when once realized, it
did not retain something of its virtuality, if, being a present state, it were not also
something which stands out distinct from the present, we should never know it for
a memory" (MM, 133f./276f.).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e327a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e334" publication-type="other">
P. Ricoeur, Memory, History, Forgetting, trans. K. Blarney and D. Pellauer (Chicago:
University of Chicago Press, 2004), 52.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e344a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e351" publication-type="other">
MM, 95/241. Cf. also MM, 101/247, 107/252, 129f./274.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e358a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e365" publication-type="other">
MM, 168/307. Cf. also MM, 237/367, 239/369.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e373a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e380" publication-type="other">
P. Ricœur, op. cit., 417 and 442.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e387a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e394" publication-type="other">
P. Ricoeur, op. cit., 440.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e401a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e408" publication-type="other">
G. Deleuze, Bergsonism, 59.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e415a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e422" publication-type="other">
L. Lawlor, The Challenge of Bergsonism. Phenomenology, Ontology, Ethics (London: Continuum,
2003), 54ff.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e432a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e439" publication-type="other">
Lawlor, op. cit., 57: "The Bergsonian reversal of Platonism consists in this: Bergsonian
reminiscence is Platonic forgetfulness."</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e449a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e456" publication-type="other">
Lawlor, op. cit., 59: "That the experience of pure memory must be an experience
of death...."</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1385e467a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d1385e474" publication-type="other">
E. Levinas, Time and the Other, trans. R. Cohen (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University
Press, 1987), 80 (trans, modified). (Lawlor also cites this text.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
