<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">criticalinquiry</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Critical Inquiry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00931896</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15397858</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/655207</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">CI360405</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Literary Unrest: Blanchot, Lévinas, and the Proximity of Judaism</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Hammerschlag</surname>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fnu1"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>8</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>36</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>655202</issue-id>
         <fpage>652</fpage>
         <lpage>672</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2010 by The University of Chicago. 00093-1896/10/3604-0003$10.00. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/655207"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fnu1">
               <p>S<sc>arah</sc>H<sc>ammerschlag</sc>is assistant professor of religion at Williams College and currently a senior fellow at the Martin Marty Center at the University of Chicago Divinity School. Author of<italic>The Figural Jew: Politics and Identity in Postwar French Thought</italic>(2010), she is currently working on a second book entitled<italic>Sowers and Sages: The Renaissance of Judaism in Postwar Paris.</italic>
               </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fnu2">
               <p>All translations, unless otherwise noted, are my own.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc-1">
         <title>1. An Unspeakable Proximity</title>
         <p>In 1988,<italic>L'Arche,</italic>a popular French Jewish monthly, ran the headline “Maurice Blanchot Expresses Himself on Judaism for the First Time.” In the essay, which was published as an open letter to Salomon Malka, Blanchot begins by revealing that this is exactly what he would not do.</p>
         <disp-quote>
            <p>In some sense, Judaism is so close to me that I do not feel that I possess the dignity to speak of it, except to make known this proximity and the reasons for this proximity (but even that, can I express it?). Isn't it presumptuous to hope one day to be able to speak of it? Will there ever be a day on which to express it? The answer: not in the time to come<italic>[l'avenir],</italic>but perhaps in the future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
         <p>The essay begins thus with a disavowal, a seeming refusal to speak on exactly the promised topic. And, yet, this is exactly what Blanchot, a French cultural Catholic, has to express about Judaism, that the only form proper to it is disavowal. At least, that is, until the future, at a time that should not be mistaken with a time to come.</p>
         <p>Is there anything to this claim beyond a series of enigmas? Blanchot is no stranger to negative discourse and messianic language, yet it is striking and seemingly unfitting to see it applied to terms of religious identity rather than God, death, or the disaster. Why would Blanchot suggest that Judaism, a historical tradition with a scriptural canon, could become unspeakable?</p>
         <p>We can answer this question only when we read the comment as Blanchot's response to Emmanuel Lévinas. Blanchot makes no mystery of this. In the letter to Malka, Blanchot follows his comment about his proximity to Judaism with a resumé of his relationship with Lévinas, the details of which were widely known in France by this time. Lévinas and Blanchot met at the University of Strausborg in 1926, where they became fast friends, Lévinas educating Blanchot on the phenomenology of Husserl and Heidegger and Blanchot educating Lévinas on Proust and Valery.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>During World War II Blanchot was instrumental in saving the lives of Lévinas's wife and daughter, and after 1968, when Blanchot retreated into seclusion, Lévinas was one of the few people he spoke with regularly and the only one, he recounts in the letter to Malka, with whom he used the pronoun<italic>tu</italic>. The intensity of their friendship is evident in writing from throughout their careers: in Blanchot's<italic>Writing the Disaster</italic>and<italic>The Infinite Conversation</italic>and in numerous essays by Lévinas.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Blanchot's references to Judaism are always in conjunction with Lévinas. Often it is as though Judaism could be used as another name for Lévinas's ethics and vice versa. Not only is Blanchot convinced that Lévinas's philosophy instantiates the essence of Judaism, he is persuaded by this vision and drawn to it.</p>
         <p>It is that conviction, however, that leads Blanchot ultimately to critique Lévinas, though he rarely does so outright. It is only through subtle juxtapositions of points or hardly tangible displacements that Blanchot's essays on Lévinas present his thought as betraying what for Blanchot is his central insight. Blanchot's letter to Malka seems to express great admiration for Lévinas, yet it functions similarly.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Blanchot's and Lévinas's critical relationship is marked by a long-standing debate over the respective capacities of literature and philosophy to have a political and moral impact. But, as I will show, this disagreement develops further political implications when it is a question of what literature can do<italic>to</italic>or<italic>for</italic>Judaism. For both thinkers, the act of reading is fundamental to their discussions of Judaism. For Lévinas, engagement with scripture and Talmud serves as a means to reclaim Judaism both in terms of its meaning and significance for the modern world and as a form of communal identity. In contrast, for Blanchot, the importance of reading and writing arises from literature's ability to upset the structures of our identity, exiling us from ourselves. Literature becomes a political force when, as a mode of discourse woven from figurative language, it disenables easy and triumphant identification with a present community and disrupts our allegiances. For Blanchot, this importance is redoubled when thought in relation to Lévinas's retrieved conception of Judaism, for it is Lévinas himself who defines Judaism as a teaching of exile. Blanchot thus performs a literary operation on Lévinas's thought by repeating it and altering it through commentary. His aim is to signal the difference between Lévinas's definition of Judaism and his political deployment of the category, highlighting the tension between Lévinas's desire to build up Judaism's presence in the world and his articulation of Judaism as a teaching of deracination.</p>
         <p>At stake here are four factors: (1) Lévinas's conception of Judaism, (2) the role that textual practices have in that conception, (3) Blanchot's interpretation of Lévinas's representation of Judaism, and finally (4) Blanchot's own notion of literature. Revealing the interrelation of these four elements can help us understand both the differences between the two thinkers and how Blanchot's own position on Judaism can be understood as a critical intervention in Lévinas's thought, one made possible by his conception of how literature relates to philosophy.</p>
         <p>First I will clarify what leads me to see an implicit critique in Blanchot's letter. Blanchot begins with the phrase “d'une certaine manière.” As insignificant as this phase may seem, it is in fact the form or manner of proximity that Judaism takes that disallows Blanchot from speaking in its name. He continues, “I do not feel that I possess the dignity to speak of it, except to make known this proximity.” This can be read as a statement of humility, acquiescence before something he admires. But there is something odd about the logic. One would not expect Blanchot's proximity to Judaism to make him feel that he is lacking the dignity to speak of it. Rather, we would assume that proximity would in fact bestow dignity or perhaps the responsibility to speak. Usually the closer one is to an authority or an institution, the greater one's right to speak in its name.</p>
         <p>Blanchot suggests here that there is something about Judaism that reverses that logic. Proximity to Judaism would seem to undermine the dignity that accompanies self-avowal, the confession of belonging. Does this tell us something about Blanchot or about Judaism? It is striking that in the last three sentences of the passage the language becomes impersonal. There is an absence of personal pronouns to the point of awkwardness. It is as though Blanchot has subtly shifted from speaking about himself to offering general propositions about the relation of<italic>any</italic>speaker to Judaism. A note follows. It clearly turns our attention away from Blanchot and toward Judaism. He quotes Lévinas: “Judaism is an essential modality of every human being.” Lévinas makes such a statement in various contexts. He insists that Judasim—beyond its manifestation as the historical tradition of a particular people—is in fact also universalizable. Such statements would seem to enable Blanchot to make known his proximity to it, a proximity, given the halakhic definition of Judaism, that Blanchot, as an unconverted Catholic, would not be able to claim. But Blanchot responds to Lévinas: “an essential modality but most often unrecognized, buried or worse perverted and finally recused.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>Blanchot's reply to Lévinas does not discount Judaism's universality; rather it discounts only its ability to appear as recognizable. He suggests that Judaism is universalizable only insofar as it cannot be taken up, claimed, or inhabited as an identity. Thus we begin to get a sense of Blanchot's critique, although it may not appear as a critique just yet. For, of course, Blanchot's comment that Judaism is most often unrecognized, attacked, or buried appears first and foremost as a judgment on a world that responds to the prophetic Jewish voice by suppressing it. But this explanation does not explain why the comment is a note to Blanchot's statement about Judaism's proximity and unspeakablity. For this statement suggests that there is something intrinsic to Judaism that makes it unspeakable. Blanchot's comment emerges only as a critique when we consider that Lévinas's own claim about Judaism's universality is part of a greater strategy to announce Judaism's world-historical importance in the twentieth century. This is a project that on one level Blanchot clearly supports. However, the political ends that each see implied by this claim are deeply at odds with one another. For Lévinas this endeavor will imply augmenting the tradition's voice on crucial political and moral issues and internally strengthening the tradition through Jewish education.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>For Blanchot, on the contrary, it will imply developing something of an antipolitics whose very function is to call into question communitarianism of any sort. Blanchot, however, does not assert the difference. Rather he exploits the unresolvable tensions in Lévinas's hermeneutical position in order to imply that Lévinas's own aims are at odds with the essence of Judaism as he has himself defined it.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Maurice Blanchot, “N'oubliez pas,”<italic>Écrits politiques: 1958–1993</italic>(Paris, 2003), p. 165.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>See Marie-Anne Lescourret,<italic>Emmanuel Lévinas</italic>(Paris, 1994), p. 68.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>It should be noted that much has been made of Blanchot's alignment with the far Right and a number of studies have attempted to read in his work an element of anti-Semitism, not only in his early political writings, but even buried within the philo-Semitism that characterizes his later work. This interpretation does not bear out in relation to either period. While it is clear that Blanchot wrote for publications in the 1930s that published anti-Semitic perspectives, he did not himself express anti-Semitic positions. His associations with the far Right movement can certainly be tied to its critique of capitalism, one that was often conflated with anti-Semitism, but as far as his own writings attest Blanchot himself did not participate in that conflation. For more on this issue and Blanchot's friendship with Lévinas, see Lescourret,<italic>Emmanuel Lévinas</italic>, pp. 64–65, 113–16. For a summary of the attacks and an explanation and defense of Blanchot's activities in the 1930s, see Leslie Hill,<italic>Blanchot, Extreme Contemporary</italic>(New York, 1997), pp. 36–46 and “La Pensée politique,”<italic>Magazine Littéraire</italic>, no. 424 (Oct. 2003): 35–38. For the case against Blanchot, see Jeffrey Mehlman,<italic>Legacies of Anti-Semitism in France</italic>(Minneapolis, 1983), pp. 6–22, 107–9, and Steven Ungar,<italic>Scandal and Aftereffect: The Study of France Since 1930</italic>(Minneapolis, 1995), pp. 60–80.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>The way in which Blanchot appropriates<italic>and</italic>distorts Lévinas's work seems to have been missed by most scholars. Either they tend to take Blanchot at his word, thus assuming that Blanchot's admiration and support of Lévinas's project is almost completely untainted by critique, or they miss altogether the allusion to Lévinas in Blanchot's descriptions of Judaism, thus reading them as mere simplification and allegorization. For an example of the former, see Georges Hansel, “Maurice Blanchot, son ami, son allié,” in<italic>Emmanuel Lévinas-Maurice Blanchot, penser la différence</italic>, ed. Éric Hoppenot and Alain Milon (Paris, 2008), pp. 285–97. For an example of the latter, see Kevin Hart,<italic>The Dark Gaze</italic>:<italic>Maurice Blanchot and the Sacred</italic>(Chicago, 2004), p. 187, where he suggests that Blanchot's description of Judaism in the section entitled “Being Jewish” in<italic>The Infinite Conversation</italic>, discussed below, “is ultimately Hegelian. Judaism belongs to a dialectical movement: things happen<italic>so that</italic>other things might be generated in turn.” Hart even gives Hegel more credit as a philosopher of religion, adding that “Hegel would pay a little more attention to the specifics of religious practice” (ibid.). Blanchot exposes himself to this misreading by not<italic>always</italic>being explicit about his method of commentary. It is nonetheless surprising that his practice of repetition and distortion is so often missed by critiques given his own frequent statements about the practice of commentary and repetition as a mode of writing.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Blanchot, “N'oubliez pas,” p. 165.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Lévinas's pedagogical concerns are demonstrated by his activities as the director of the École Normale Israélite Orientale, which he treated as an institution for training the future elites of the Jewish community. He emphasized Hebrew language instruction and knowledge of the tradition along with its relation to the Western canon. As his students attest, he was preparing his students to move comfortably between these two worlds and to be able successfully to translate the learning from one into the learning of the other. See Salomon Malka,<italic>Emmanuel Lévinas: La Vie et la trace</italic>(Paris, 2002), pp. 99–120. See also additional information gathered from the Archives of Alliance Israélite Universelle, Files AM France E 001–003. Lévinas's larger political concerns are best demonstrated by his intense and consistent involvement in the Colloque des Intellectuels Juifs de Langue Française whose yearly meetings were aimed both at strengthening the community and at demonstrating the capacity of the Jewish tradition to provide responses to current and pressing political issues. See, for example,<italic>La Conscience juive</italic>, ed. Éliane Amado Lévy-Valensi and Jean Halpérin, 2 vols. (Paris, 1963–65).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>2. Lévinasian Hermeneutics and Judaism's World-Historical Importance</title>
         <p>From the 1930s forward, the political dimension of Lévinas's work is tied to the claim that the time has come for Judaism to announce its universal significance. Our age needs Judaism, he declared, “the humanism of the suffering servant—the History of Israel—invites us to create a new anthropology, a new historiography, and perhaps, by bringing about the end of Western ‘triumphalism,' a new history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Already in 1939 Lévinas had written that Jews “have the obscure feeling that Hitlerism is like a call to their vocation and to their destiny,” a destiny defined not by monotheism but by a “resistance to the cult of power and earthly greatness.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>Against what Lévinas identified as a Nietzschean valorization of nobility and strength, “the message of Judaism is a paradox and an insanity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>Conversely, however, if Judaism appeared as weakness and passivity before the “morality of the masters,” then the morality of the masters could be exposed as brutish and bullying in the light cast by Judaism. Lévinas proclaims this light as necessary in the thirties when he fears that Christianity had failed to protect Europe from the return of a “primitive mentality” and in the 1960s in response to the cold war and the postcolonial birth of new nations. “At the dawning of the new world,” Lévinas wrote in 1961, “Judaism has the consciousness to possess, through its own permanence, a function in the general economy of Being. No one can replace it. Someone has to exist in the world who is as old as the world.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This vision of Judaism as opposed to paganism, as a no to the discourse of blood and soil is perhaps best expressed in a little essay also from 1961, “Heidegger, Gagarin, and Us.” Here Judaism emerges less as a positive tradition than as a rejection of other alternatives. Lévinas plays on the French anti-Semitism of the late nineteenth and twentieth century that linked Jews to cosmopolitanism, technology, and universalism in order to reclaim these qualities as a part of Judaism's mission in the world, a mission that calls into question loyalty to land. “One's implementation in a landscape, one's attachment to<italic>Place</italic>,” Lévinas writes, “is the very splitting of humanity into natives and strangers.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>Judaism's passivity and weakness are figured as the source of its importance, an importance that Lévinas uses the model of Gagarin's flight into space to symbolize. Gagarin's brief freedom from the earth is compared to what he refers to as Judaism's freedom with regard to place.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>This little essay, which is transparently a response to some of Heidegger's postwar writings against technology, such as his 1950 essay “Das Ding,” focuses on the metaphor of rootlessness as a way to signal that Judaism offers an alternative message to Heideggerian nostalgia. It is this vision of Judaism that Blanchot clearly found so compelling, and it is a vision to which he will try to press Lévinas to remain loyal, a loyalty that for Blanchot entails revoking paradoxically an attachment to Judaism itself.</p>
         <p>If Lévinas himself could not see how his vision might call into question his own loyalty to Judaism, this is partly because he first had to show that the message he was expounding derived from Judaism. He found his clearest source in Franz Rosenzweig's<italic>The</italic>
            <italic>Star of Redemption</italic>, but he also needed to legitimate his vision through an engagement with the tradition itself. It was ultimately in his Talmudic readings that he emerges as a voice speaking for Judaism and in the Babylonian Talmud that he finds his vision.</p>
         <p>The process of reading and interpreting the Talmud provided Lévinas with the appropriate medium through which he was able to name the essence of Judaism and to act as its spokesperson. The irony is that Lévinas is ultimately unable in his own interpretations to demonstrate the very principle that authorizes his engagement with the rabbinic corpus. While it is the fecundity of the text that accommodates untraditional meanings, his desire to disseminate a particular interpretation of Judaism disallows him from upholding the text's plurivocity.</p>
         <p>It is well known that Lévinas came to the Talmud late in life. Despite his Orthodox upbringing and his knowledge of Hebrew, he began studying Talmud only when he was in his forties, through his relationship with the mysterious Chouchani, the man to whom he would refer most often not by name but as his eminent master, his intransigent master, or his unpitying master.</p>
         <p>Despite his lack of traditional training with the Talmud, Lévinas served as the interpreter of the rabbinic corpus and ultimately of Judaism for many of his contemporaries and students. The Talmudic readings, before being published collectively, were given at meetings of Le Colloque des Inellectuels Juifs de Langue Française<italic>.</italic>Lévinas used these occasions to encourage France's Jewish intellectuals to return to the Hebrew, to those “square letters” as he called them. A revival of the reading practices of the rabbis, Lévinas suggested, could reinvigorate Judaism. “It is through reading,” he wrote, “that references take on reality; through reading, in a way, we come to inhabit a place. The volume of the book can provide the<italic>espace vital!</italic>In this sense too the people of Israel are the people of the Book, whose relationship to the Revelation is unique.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>Through the reading of Talmud, Lévinas forged his connection to the Jewish tradition. It was the plurivocity of the text that made the connection possible both for him and for other Jews.</p>
         <p>In the essay “Revelation in the Jewish tradition,” from which the lines above are excerpted, Lévinas refers twice to the volume of the book as a kind of dwelling place. He calls it an “<italic>espace vital”</italic>and speaks of it as inhabitable. Given Lévinas's resistance to the language of homecoming in his ethics, his unrelenting insistence that ethical subjectivity is a form of uprooting, it is striking that he uses this language. On the one hand, it is a common trope to refer to the book as the Jewish homeland, one that valorizes the culture's mobility. On the other hand, it is a trope that replaces one form of homecoming with another. Throughout his philosophical corpus Lévinas opposes Abraham to Odysseus in order to emphasize the Hebrew tradition as the source for a model of ethical subjectivity, one in which the uprooting of the subject does not culminate in the satisfaction of homecoming.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>Given Lévinas's insistence on the parallel between the structure of ethical subjectivity and the teachings of Judaism, there is an inconsistency here, at least in Lévinas's choice of metaphors, which may reveal as well a tension at the heart of his conception of Judaism. As we'll see in a moment, this is an inconsistency that Blanchot will try to exploit.</p>
         <p>For Lévinas, it is clear that rabbinic reading practices invest the biblical text with a kind of fecundity. The Bible and the Talmud show themselves to be divinely inspired because they have the power to invoke new responses in their readers. In their polyvalence they can support multiple interpretations and can be infinitely renewed. Where Blanchot will see polyvalence as one way in which literature refuses the reader a place to rest, Lévinas will see the same feature as an enrichment and a hospitality in the text. In this sense, Lévinas's hermeneutic theory is closer to Paul Ricoeur's than to Blanchot's. If we consider literary language, following Ricoeur, as that language that increases the multiplicity of meaning toward a redescription of reality, then it is indeed the rabbis' respect for the literary quality of scripture that Lévinas finds most valuable. He will not, however, put it in these terms.</p>
         <p>Rather, the category of literature is troubling for Lévinas. On the one hand, it is clear that a number of Lévinas's most important influences are literary. His recently published<italic>Carnets de captivité</italic>devotes considerable attention to Proust as a source for his analysis of sociality and even include notes and plans for his own novel.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>In later works he quotes Alyosha Karamazov almost as frequently as Descartes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>On the other hand, he is also at times quite damning of literature as an aesthetic pursuit. His most critical statements about literature appear in “Reality and Its Shadow.” Published at the end of 1948, ten months after Blanchot's “Literature and the Right to Death,” this essay is a response to both Blanchot and Sartre's “What Is Literature?” Lévinas condemns literature here as fundamentally escapist. “The poet exiles himself from the city,” he writes. Speaking of artistic pleasure more generally, he adds, “There are times when one could be ashamed of it, as if carousing in a town struck by the plague.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>He does not have much sympathy for catharsis.</p>
         <p>Nonetheless, Lévinas finds a parallel between rabbinic hermeneutics and his philosophy. He suggests that the Jewish conception of revelation correlates with his own validation of “the saying”—the dimension of address—over the “said,” its discursive meaning. Rabbinic interpretation reinvigorated the spoken word. It emphasized the potential for speech to affirm the ethical face-to-face encounter. Lévinas saw this dynamic particularly in the yeshiva practice of reading out loud and working as a<italic>havruta</italic>, in pairs. He thus encouraged French Jews to renew such practices.</p>
         <p>This solicitation had its effect, not only on his students at the École Normale Israélite Orientale, where his weekly<italic>cours rachi</italic>became a highlight of the school's curriculum, but on many who came to ENIO on Saturdays merely to attend these lessons. Benny Lévy, most famously, turned away from secular existence and became a<italic>baal teshuva</italic>in response to Lévinas's influence.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>Yet Lévinas's drive to rejuvenate Judaism did not culminate in a revival of France's Jewish community. It was more ambitious. Lévinas argued for the universal significance of the Jewish message. It was the plurivocity of the text that allowed him to claim that this message was already in the Talmud, but it was also this message that led him to offer readings of the Talmudic text that themselves reduce the text's plurivocity to a singular interpretation. In order to specify Judaism's message as one that is universally communicable Lévinas must ultimately claim one meaning as primary—the philosophical core buried beneath a multifaceted surface. The model Lévinas invokes looks much like Kant's in<italic>Religion within the Limits</italic>
            <italic>of Reason Alone</italic>or Maimonides's in the<italic>Guide for the Perplexed</italic>, where we find a hierarchy of meaning. Philosophical meaning is cloaked by an outward mythology. Scripture's truth is not arrived at by discovering its seventy faces of meaning but in the location of the text's philosophical essence.</p>
         <p>This is evident already in Lévinas's introduction to<italic>Quatre Lectures talmudiques.</italic>Lévinas's claim here is that the Talmud harbors philosophical arguments but hides them in “apologues” and “adages” that require the philosopher's reformulation. The reader must “retrieve the initial design of its force, even when it is enveloped and made more palatable by thoughts that want only to be pious.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The truth can be recovered through rubbing and digging, Lévinas suggests, in images that recall Heidegger's own metaphors of destruction. The consequence of this mode of reading is that it reduces polyvalence to a vehicle, making of the text's opacity a nut to be cracked, an occasion for clarification. In “Judaism and Revolution” for example, a Mishnaic passage discussing whether fair practices of payment should be derived from a general principle or from the custom of the land “reveals that the other man's right is practically an infinite right.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>In another reading, Tractate Shabbat 88, a midrash on Exodus 19:17, appears to be a commendation of the Israelites for their absolute obedience to God's commandments. Lévinas rereads it to reveal a Lévinasean lesson: “The Torah,” he writes, “is given in the Light of a face. The epiphany of an other person is ipso facto my responsibility toward him: seeing the other is already an obligation toward him.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>
         </p>
         <p>One of the payoffs of this mode of interpretation for Lévinas is that it burns off the particularism of these texts, like strong sun over a thin layer of clouds, making visible their underlying universal message. As a consequence of these readings, Judaism appears as a message that must speak to every man. Lévinas is often at pains to make this point, particularly when the Talmud itself seems to be distinguishing between the rights owed to the people Israel and the rights owed to the stranger. Lévinas insists that Israel in fact stands for “every man.” Here he calls on his teacher Chouchani to authorize the move. “I have it from an eminent master,” he says in one Talmud reading, that to interpret the term Israel as referring to a particular ethnic group would be “to forget that Israel means a people who has received the Law and, as a result, a human nature which has reached the fullness of its responsibility and self-consciousness.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The function of Lévinas's universalization of Talmud is two-fold. First Lévinas can only assert Judaism's importance in the contemporary world if its message speaks to everyone. Additionally Lévinas has to defend against the reading that Judaism is itself another tribalism or nationalism. The quotation above appears in the context of a Talmudic passage that discusses to whom one owes the equivalent of overtime wages. The text itself is clear. The law refers to the people Israel. Given the fact that Lévinas has defined Judaism in such a way that it is opposed to any distinction between “natives” and “strangers,” he is at great pains to protect Judaism from any interpretation that would allow it to appear tribalistic or exclusionary. He does not dispute the literal meaning of the passage, but insists that the more universal meaning is the source of the passage's truth; it is the philosophical core that must be unearthed. The problem is that Lévinas's philosophical model of reading Talmud forces him to make statements that are at odds with his own validation of the plurivocity of the scriptural text.</p>
         <p>There are two reasons for this. The first is that he is trying to protect his own interpretation as foundational and fundamental. Second, the strain between Lévinas's two strategies of reading is indicative of a more fundamental tension between building up the Jewish community and the impulse to make Judaism universally applicable. When Lévinas emphasizes the plurivocity of the text, he consistently speaks of the renewal of the Jewish people. In these passages there is no mention of the universalization of Judaism. When he universalizes the category, he also deemphasizes the text's plurivocity, prioritizing its philosophical essence. As Moshe Halbertal has shown, the emphasis on rabbinic plurivocity goes hand in hand with other strategies of policing the border of the community. Without a clear demarcation of who has the authority to engage in interpretation, the principle of interpretive openness threatens to disrupt community cohesion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>Conversely, Lévinas's universalization of Judaism can only function meaningfully if agreement can be established concerning the tradition's core teachings. Otherwise, there can be no clear criteria for association or identification.</p>
         <p>It is exactly the power of literature's plurivocity to decentralize meaning, to disenable the closure of certain types of communities that makes literature for Blanchot a powerful political tool. It is exactly this quality as well that makes literature expressive of Judaism. Both Judaism and literature for Blanchot point toward the desert of exile.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Emmanuel Lévinas, “Jacob Gordin,”<italic>Difficult Freedom: Essays on Judaism</italic>, trans. Seán Hand (Baltimore, 1990), p. 171.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “A propos de la mort du pape Pie XI,”<italic>L'Herne</italic>, no. 60 (1991): 152.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “Le Pensée juive aujourd'hui,”<italic>Difficile Liberté</italic>(Paris, 1963), p. 296; trans. Hand under the title “Jewish Thought Today,”<italic>Difficult Freedom</italic>, p. 166.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “Heidegger, Gagarine, et Nous,”<italic>Difficile Liberté</italic>, p. 257; trans. Hand under the title “Heidegger, Gagarin, and Us,”<italic>Difficult Freedom</italic>, p. 232.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>See ibid.; p. 233.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “La Revelation dans la tradition juive,”<italic>L'Au-delà du verset: Lectures et Discours Talmudiques</italic>(Paris, 1982), p. 159. See also Lévinas, “Revelation in the Jewish Tradition,”<italic>Beyond the Verse: Talmudic Readings and Lectures</italic>, trans. Gary D. Mole (Bloomington, Ind., 1994), p. 130.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>See, for example, Lévinas, “La Trace de L'Autre,”<italic>Tijdschrift voor Philosophie</italic>25 (Sept. 1963): 605–23; trans. Alfonso Lingis under the title “The Trace of the Other,” in<italic>Deconstruction in Context: Literature and Philosophy</italic>, ed. Mark C. Taylor (Chicago, 1986), pp. 345–59.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Lévinas apparently had plans for two novels, entitled<italic>La Dame de chez Wepler</italic>and<italic>Eros</italic>. Only the notes for the latter are included in the first volume of the complete works; see Lévinas,<italic>Carnets de captivité, suivi de ecrits sur la captivité, et notes philosophiques diverses</italic>, ed. Rodolphe Calin and Catherine Chalier (Paris, 2009), pp. 14–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>As Oona Eisenstadt pointed out to me, the passage that Lévinas most often attributes to Alyosha, “we are all guilty toward others, and I am the guiltiest of all,” is not recounted in<italic>The Brothers Karamozov</italic>as a direct quotation of Alyosha's (Fyodor Dostoyevsky,<italic>The Brothers Karamazov</italic>, trans. Andrew R. MacAndrew [New York, 1970], p. 384). In fact it is Alyosha's retelling of the life of Father Zossima, who attributes these lines to his long-deceased brother Markel.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “La Réalité et son ombre,”<italic>Les Imprévus de l'histoire</italic>(Paris, 1994), p. 119; trans. Nidra Poller under the title “Reality and Its Shadow,”<italic>Unforeseen History</italic>(Urbana, Ill., 2004), p. 90.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>The term<italic>baal teshuva</italic>literally means “master of return” and refers most often to Jews who embrace halakhic or orthodox practice after having lived a less observant life previously.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Lévinas, introduction to<italic>Quatre Lectures talmudiques</italic>(Paris, 1968), p. 13. See also Lévinas, introduction to<italic>Nine Talmudic Readings</italic>, trans. Annette Aronowicz (Bloomington, Ind., 1990), p. 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “Leçon talmudique,” in<italic>Jeunesse et révolution dans la conscience juive: Données et débats</italic>, ed. Halpérin and Georges Levitte (Paris, 1972), p. 62. See also Lévinas, “Judaism and Revolution,”<italic>Nine Talmudic Readings</italic>, p. 98.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “La Tentation de la tentation,”<italic>Quatre Lectures talmudiques</italic>, pp. 103–4. See also Lévinas, “The Temptation of Temptation,”<italic>Nine Talmudic Readings</italic>, p. 47.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “Leçon talmudique,” p. 62; “Judaism and Revolution,” p. 98.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>See Moshe Halbertal,<italic>People of the Book</italic>:<italic>Canon, Meaning, and Authority</italic>(Cambridge, Mass., 1997), p. 7.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>3. Writing the Distance: Blanchot's Exilic Commentary</title>
         <p>Unlike Lévinas, Blanchot's concern for Judaism is not motivated by the practical concerns of reviving the tradition in the postwar context. He is free of the necessities of community leadership, free from any pragmatics concerning the tradition. For Blanchot, Judaism is a concept, one he has discovered through reading Lévinas along with Edmond Jabès and Franz Kafka. Its message is encapsulated in the commandment to Abraham in Genesis 12:<italic>Lech Lecha</italic>, “Go forth from your father's house.” Blanchot reads this commandment as a prohibition against putting down roots, not only in a particular place but also in any statement of the truth. Like Lévinas, Blanchot sees this counsel of dispersion as having fundamental importance in the post-World War II world, an importance that has little to do with the lived tradition and everything to do with developing a political position antithetical to fascism. Blanchot accepts Lévinas's depiction of Judaism and takes the idea a step further by reading Lévinas's principle of moral deracination as advocating absolute disappropriation. He writes in<italic>The Infinite Conversation</italic>,<disp-quote>
               <p>there is a truth of exile and there is a vocation of exile; and if being Jewish is being destined to dispersion—just as it is a call to a sojourn without place, just as it ruins every fixed relation of force with<italic>one</italic>individual,<italic>one</italic>group, or<italic>one</italic>state—it is because dispersion, faced with the exigency of the whole, also clears the way for a different exigency and finally forbids the temptation of Unity-Identity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The language here is similar to Lévinas's in “Heidegger, Gagarin, and Us.” Blanchot follows Lévinas in referring to Judaism as a teaching allergic to force, resistant to the call of land. But exile is not a principle that refers only to land for Blanchot. It is a principle of resistance to communitarianism and accompanying claims to exemplarity. Judaism for Blanchot teaches the value of being an outsider, an outsider to a nation, to a fixed community, and ultimately to the truth. Judaism as a teaching of exile also calls us to resist the forces of group identification, to question the nature of our allegiances and our self-certainty. In this way, for Blanchot, Judaism is in fact parallel to communism.</p>
         <p>Blanchot reads both communism and Judaism as sharing a critique of ownership. Marx's rejection of private property becomes in Blanchot's writing a critique of the structure of the proper. This definition of communism was particularly important to Blanchot in 1968 when he was theorizing about the political significance of the student protests. In a text called “Communism without Heritage,” written during the student protests and published anonymously, Blanchot describes communism, just as he did Judaism, as an ideology that resists the political movement of unity through identity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>Blanchot describes Judaism and communism as adverse to patriotism. The danger of patriotism for Blanchot (as opposed to Marx) is not that it might divert us from recognizing our state of subjugation but that it encourages a model of communitarianism that has fusion or immanence as its ideal. The danger of such political modes is their penchant for self-satisfaction and the aggressive drive toward replication and cultural imperialism that for Blanchot is the inevitable consequence of cultural self-affirmation, the claim to instantiate the ideal, to possess the truth. “Everything,” Blanchot writes, “which roots men by values, by sentiment, in one time, in one history, in one language, is the principle of alienation that constitutes man so that he sees himself as privileged . . . such that he encloses himself in satisfaction with his reality and is thus driven to propose it as exemplary or to impose it as a conquering affirmation.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>
         </p>
         <p>For Blanchot, Judaism and communism are thus the antitotalitarian discourses par excellence. This does not mean, however, that he sees in the historical configuration of either Judaism or communism the instantiation of the principle of disappropriation. Rather, both represent this ideal by means of the fact that they cannot coincide with themselves. That is to say, no form of Judaism and no form of communism can appear that would fulfill the ideal of disappropriation. The moment that Judaism or communism claims to instantiate the discourse of disappropriation, it has failed to do so by the very fact that it has claimed to represent this ideal as its own. Both thus represent for Blanchot an ideal of community whose importance rests in the visibility of its nonappearance.</p>
         <p>In this sense both Judaism and communism constitute messianic forms of community, communities that can only articulate themselves in the acknowledgement that their time is indeed<italic>not now</italic>. The source for Blanchot's identification of Judaism with this structure of deracination and disappropriation is clearly Lévinas's own essays on Judaism. Lévinas's own conception of Jewish universalism would also seem to imply the lack of self-coincidence that Blanchot emphasized. For if it is indeed the case that to apply the term<italic>Israel</italic>ethnically involves forgetting “that Israel means a people . . . which has reached the fullness of its responsibility and self-consciousness,” then it would seem that Israel represents an ideal and not a reality, a goal and not a fact. Yet the question remains as to the relation between this ideal and the Jewish people. Insofar as Lévinas does not in his political writings cultivate the element of disappropriation that is so crucial to Blanchot, his political writings run the risk of indulging the impulse toward exemplarity or self-affirmation of which Blanchot is so wary.</p>
         <p>This tendency is encapsulated by a statement of Lévinas's from 1960 in a speech composed to commemorate the one-hundredth anniversary of the foundation of the Alliance Israélite Universelle, in which he asked, “are not certain civilizations teachers in relation to others? Is not anything in this world classic anymore?” His response: “The point where Hebraism entered the world is a summit.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Lévinas maintains throughout his writings on Judaism the classical claim that Jerusalem will be “a light to the nations” (Isaiah 51:4). The way in which this sentiment leads to a politics of exemplarity is perhaps most at issue when we consider Lévinas's position on Israel. As is evident from a recently published exchange in the days following the announcement of Israel's independence, the idea of Judaism discussed between Lévinas and Blanchot was clearly at odds with the fact of a Jewish state.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>Yet both maintained support of the state to the point that Blanchot broke with the extreme Left after May '68 as a result of its anti-Israeli rhetoric.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>For both it is certainly clear that Israel's existence needed no more justification than the fact of the Holocaust. Yet the question remains of how to handle the tension between a deracinating conception of Judaism and a Jewish state. Lévinas argues that Israel offers<italic>the</italic>privileged opportunity to instantiate the moral teaching of Judaism, writing in the essay “The State of Israel and the Religion of Israel” that “the State of Israel will be religious because of the intelligence of its great books which it is not free to forget.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>This position provides the resources for critiquing Israel when it does not live up to its moral vision but just as easily bestows Israel with the status of being unconditionally exceptional by virtue of its potential. Ultimately for Lévinas, Israel represents the unique promise of prophetic politics. It consequently should be defended and protected even when its actions, if performed by another state, would warrant critique and sanction.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>Blanchot has been interpreted as being less critical of Israel, in fact, but this is not a consequence of his unconditional support for the nation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>Rather, by separating out the exigency of “being Jewish” from the Jewish people, Blanchot maintains the principle that being Jewish calls into question<italic>every</italic>nation,<italic>every</italic>claim to allegiance. Consequently, Israel must account for its valuing loyalty and allegiance over justice, as must any other nation. The consequence of this approach is that the state of Israel is neither treated as exemplary nor as exceptionally blameworthy.</p>
         <p>To return then to Blanchot's comments in his letter to Malka, it is now apparent that Blanchot's insistence on the unspeakability of his proximity to Judaism, his insistence that he will be able to speak of it only in the future, is part and parcel of Blanchot's conviction that Judaism, understood in its Lévinasian sense, ought to have built into it the impossibility of self-affirmation. We can see then that these lines, which seem straightforwardly to honor Lévinas, also involve a critique.</p>
         <p>If indeed the letter to Malka was meant to prod Lévinas, to push him to recognize the inconsistency in his own thought, we might ask after the remedy. How could Lévinas disclose the Jewish message in the world and simultaneously disown it? One answer to this question is that he could not, neither on philosophical nor political grounds, for that would require a disavowal of both his philosophical and political commitments. Blanchot, however, as a literary critic and a thinker with profoundly different political aims, will accomplish this task for him. He thus exposes Lévinas to a reading that capitalizes on both the tensions in Lévinas's own work and the more radical demands implied by his philosophy of deracination. To do so he transforms Lévinas's philosophy into its literary double.</p>
         <p>The importance of literature as a political tool is revealed most clearly when we differentiate it from what Jean-Luc Nancy and Phillipe Lacoue-Labarthe, influenced by Blanchot, come to define as myth. They configure myth as “a fiction, in the strong, active sense of ‘fashioning,' . . . whose role is to propose, if not to impose, models or types . . . , types in imitation of which an individual, or a city, or an entire people, can grasp themselves and identify themselves.” Myth creates community by providing a narrative of origin and installs the nexus for the political subject's identification with that community. Myth is thus the mechanism by which social fusion is created. It serves its function when it produces, as Lacoue-Labarthe and Nancy write, “a total belief, an immediate, unreserved adhesion to the dreamed figure. . . . It is both the model of identity<italic>and</italic>its present, effective,<italic>formed</italic>reality.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>In contrast, literature, as Blanchot defines it, would be that mode of speech that mocks any mythic claim to fusion by expressing disjunction. Most importantly it disallows the act of identification that is a form of self-presencing. From its very beginnings, Blanchot's theory of literature zeros in on the capacity of figurative language to disrupt identification.</p>
         <p>The term that Blanchot uses to describe the operation of disidentification or noncoincidence is<italic>désouevrement</italic>(unworking). This term, which arises from Blanchot's engagement with Alexandre Kojève's lectures on Hegel, describes both the political act of disappropriation and the literary movement toward the improper. Literature, like Judaism, is a movement toward the outside, a force of uprooting, of restlessness.</p>
         <p>This is already clear in “Literature and the Right to Death,” the essay to which Lévinas was responding in “Reality and Its Shadow.” There Blanchot writes, “where is literature's power? It plays at working in the world, and the world regards its work as a worthless or dangerous game.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>Blanchot's rhetoric here is once again remarkably similar to Lévinas's in “Reality and Its Shadow” and is seemingly as negative. Yet what condemns literature for Lévinas redeems it for Blanchot. Ultimately it is the way in which literature deforms action into inaction that gives it its importance. Its function first appears as a resistance to the philosophical concept.</p>
         <p>This notion of literature develops from Blanchot's reading of Mallarmé as well as his encounter with the Hegelian description of comprehension. Drawing from Kojève's seminars, Blanchot begins with the notion that language involves the absence (the annihilation or death) of the object, such that for one to possess the idea of cat, one must annihilate the uniquely real cat in its existence.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>“Common language,” Blanchot writes, recognizes this operation as unproblematic or at least productive. For in killing the real cat, I have gained something much more secure, the idea of cat, which cannot die. Literary language differs from common language not in the act itself, for by the very fact that it is language it must also enact a negation of the object. “But literary language,” Blanchot suggests, “is made of uneasiness” (“L,” p. 315; “LRD,” p. 325). Literary language draws attention back to the negativity of the operation, focusing on the fact that the word expresses the nonexistence of the cat and that what it has given us as a replacement is a word. Literature dramatizes the operation of replacement by offering “an endless sliding of ‘turns of phrase' which do not lead anywhere. Thus is born,” Blanchot writes, “the image that does not designate the thing but, rather, what the thing is not” (“L,” p. 315; “LRD,” p. 326). The mark of the literary is the mark of the trope, a turn. A figure of speech is a turn that multiplies the absence between the object and the word, for now what we have is a word that refers not to the object but to another word.</p>
         <p>Where the capacity of figurative language to multiply meaning appears as a kind of generosity in Lévinas's analysis of the Jewish conception of revelation, in Blanchot it is a site of slippage and anonymity. Literary language is “<italic>my</italic>consciousness<italic>without me</italic>, the radiant passivity of mineral substances, the lucidity of the depths of torpor” (“L,” p. 317; “LRD,” p. 328).</p>
         <p>Literature for Blanchot is defined by its being a nonplace, a site of erring. It acts by mimicking activity and in this doubling it creates a space of instability where valences are multiplied; nothing is as it seems. For even in its gesture back toward the original object, in its turning, which is effected through the multiplication of images and the animation of language's materiality, what is achieved is not greater clarity or another form of possession—the rendering of presence—but rather an instability that creates ambiguity at every level such that one does not know when language is expressing or representing. “If it is a thing or means that thing . . . obscure because it says too much, opaque because it says nothing” (“L,” p. 329; “LRD,” pp. 341–42).</p>
         <p>Literary language is itself deracinating. It destabilizes every assertion by upsetting the relationship between signifier and signified. This is a language, Blanchot argues, of the outside, likening it in its wandering to the biblical exile. Writing and Judaism are thus parallel modes. Their resemblance is key for Blanchot particularly in his reading of Kafka. Kafka's own writing serves as a way of being Jewish, making the desert of writing the only destination in an exile that eschews the goal of the promised land.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Writing</italic>, a word Blanchot uses to replace<italic>literature</italic>in<italic>The Infinite Conversation,</italic>is finally for Blanchot the only way to remain true to the idea of Judaism. It is also the only way, Blanchot will argue, to remain true to the impulse of estrangement that he locates at the heart of Lévinas's philosophy. For Blanchot, insofar as the relation to the other is one of infinite distance between myself and the Other, inaugurating “a relation of impossibility and strangeness,” the language that invokes this relation must be one unsupported by presence; that is, it must be writing (<italic>EI</italic>, p. 101;<italic>IC</italic>, p. 71). Blanchot suggests further that as a mode of communication philosophy itself fails to be faithful to the relation with the Other because it requires a language that prioritizes clarity. “How can one say inequality by means of what tends to equalize?” Blanchot asks. The only speech that “would speak without leveling . . . without tending toward the identity implied by satisfaction and full understanding” is a speech that can speak of difference without grasping it or capturing it, for even when it represents its relation toward a referent it is characterized by a turn (<italic>EI</italic>, p. 90;<italic>IC</italic>, p. 63).</p>
         <p>Blanchot's response to the inadequacy he recognizes in Lévinas's philosophy is to rewrite it through the production of commentary. In the prefatory note to<italic>The Infinite Conversation</italic>Blanchot suggests that the volume should itself be understood as participating in the<italic>désoeuvrement</italic>that characterizes writing. This is a writing that “is called upon to undo the discourse in which, however unhappy we believe ourselves to be, we who have it at our disposal remain comfortably installed” (<italic>EI</italic>, p. viii;<italic>IC</italic>, p. xii). Insofar as Blanchot's essays on Lévinas also participate in the activity of writing, these essays deform Lévinas's thought by doubling it through commentary. Commentary, as Blanchot understands it, participates in literature by repeating the work. Blanchot describes his method as one that leaves the text empty by “translating it in its ambiguity through an interrogation henceforth still more ambiguous since it bears this ambiguity, bears upon it, and ends by becoming dissipated in it” (<italic>EI</italic>, p. 571;<italic>IC</italic>, p. 390).</p>
         <p>By describing Lévinas's work in terms that insist on the capacity of this thought to dismantle subjectivity, Blanchot reads Lévinas in such a way that Lévinas's concerns come to appear very close to Blanchot's own. As most readers of Lévinas would have to admit, there is something of a disharmony between this reading and most straightforward interpretations of Lévinas's texts. Even Derrida, who tends to read texts against the grain, doubts the claims of similarity that Blanchot's reading seems to assert, arguing that between Lévinas's thought and Blanchot's affinities only arise in relation to the critical and negative moments in Lévinas's texts.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>Blanchot's interpretation is thus a doubling that unworks Lévinas's thought and pushes it to its extremes.</p>
         <p>Nowhere is this clearer than in Blanchot's responses to Lévinas's Jewish writings. What we find in the texts in which Blanchot speaks of Judaism is never a critique of Lévinas. Often he doesn't even mention Lévinas's name. Rather he repeats Lévinas's own characterizations of Judaism with just the subtlest shades of alteration or distortion. One way in which Blanchot echoes Lévinas's characterization of Judaism is by adopting the schema that appears in Lévinas's Jewish writings. Paganism is represented as a thinking of the proper, Christianity as a form of escapism, and Judaism as the prophetic interruption of history. When Blanchot adopts this schema, however, he shifts the placement of the structures. What appears, at least on the surface, as a cultural commentary in Lévinas's essays appears in Blanchot's recasting as a series of tropes, metaphors for human tendencies that can be disengaged from their proper referent. Once again, we see Blanchot writing in Lévinas's margins and reorienting his thought so that even when Blanchot seems to be merely repeating Lévinas's characterizations the significance has somehow shifted. This shift is particularly clear in Blanchot's own response to Gagarin's flight.</p>
         <p>In his 1988 letter to Malka, Blanchot spoke of his relationship to Judaism as one of unspeakable proximity. Twenty-seven years earlier he had performed the meaning of this statement in an essay that reproduced almost exactly the text of Lévinas's “Heidegger, Gagarin, and Us.”</p>
         <p>Written in the same year (1961), but published three years later, Blanchot's “The Conquest of Space” is a subtle commentary on Lévinas's essay, paraphrasing it in places almost word for word. The only mention of Lévinas, however, is in the footnote where Blanchot credits Lévinas as a major source for his reflections. In Blanchot's text, Lévinas's subtle references to Heidegger are further defaced and transposed so that what Lévinas refers to as a Heideggerian/pagan thinking now appears more generally as human thought:<disp-quote>
               <p>Man does not want to leave his own place. He says that technology is dangerous, that it detracts from our relationship with the world, that true civilizations are those of a stable nature, that the nomad is incapable of acquisition. Who is this man? It is each one of us, at the times we give in to lethargy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The mode that is attributed to the Jew in Lévinas's essay is here called merely nomadic. It is nevertheless clear that the relationship between “man” and the “nomad” mirrors the relation of the anti-Semite to the Jew, as the “nomad” is presented as tied to technology and as such represents a threat to “man.” At the same time that it generalizes Lévinas's text, the opening of Blanchot's essay nonetheless manages to parallel the first paragraph of Lévinas's, even alluding obliquely to Heidegger's critique of flight in “Das Ding.” Within the body of the essay, Blanchot does take up specifically the category of the pagan, declaring that Gagarin's space flight is a threat to the pagan in all of us: he who is tied to enrootedness, to tradition, to his biological race, he who consoles himself among the trees over the evil of mankind. The Jew, however, is not mentioned. Even when Lévinas is paraphrased in the essay it is without specific citation, and he is referred to not as someone who speaks in the name of Judaism but as “the man with no fixed abode,” as a representative of the nomads (“C,” p. 13; “CS,” p. 269). In repeating Lévinas, Blanchot has insisted on resisting the move back to the proper, which Lévinas's essay performs in its emphasis on Judaism's message. Lévinas uses Gagarin's flight to lead back to the truth of Judaism, concluding his own essay with the claim that, like technology, Judaism “has demystified the universe” and, moreover, “has discovered man in the nudity of the face” (“H,” p. 259; “HGU,” p. 234). Blanchot uses Lévinas's essay to remind us that Gagarin tears us away from the proper in<italic>every sense</italic>. His omission of both Lévinas's name and of Judaism underscores the point that deracination as a moral concept would prohibit reappropriation of any kind. The message of Gagarin's speech from space is for no one to claim and for no one to own, that is, that “truth is nomadic” (“C,” p. 13; “CS,” p. 271). Blanchot has thus doubly displaced Lévinas's terminology, eliding even the reference to exile, a mode historically associated with Judaism and characterized by an attachment to a particular place.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Just as literature effaces the proper meaning of words, imposing a slippage that leaves the reader with no firm ground to stand on, so this essay effaces the proper meaning of Lévinas's text. To return to Blanchot's letter to Malka, it reveals to us finally what Blanchot meant when he said that in a<italic>certain</italic>way Judaism was so close to him that he could not speak of it. In what way is Judaism close to Blanchot? This proximity is one that must be announced as a distance. In maintaining that distance is not Blanchot declaring himself more loyal than Lévinas to the teaching of deracination, of which Blanchot considers Lévinas to be the teacher? In his letter to Malka and in his rewriting of Lévinas's essay “Heidegger, Gagarin, and Us,” Blanchot is answering Lévinas's call for Judaism to announce a new teaching to the postwar world. Undoubtedly Lévinas intended this call to strengthen both the Jewish community and the broader perception of Judaism's message. Blanchot's interpretation could be interpreted as doing the opposite. At the very least, it ignores the pragmatics of Lévinas's concerns. Yet, for Blanchot, Judaism's political power is only realized in renunciation. Its highest teaching, he suggests, is that there must be a gap between the call and the one in whose name the call is made. This is a space that literature discloses, offering us a mode of political speech that does not operate on the principle of mythical identification but rather ceaselessly interrupts itself, reminding us that fulfillment is not yet.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Blanchot,<italic>L'Entretien infini</italic>(Paris, 1969), p. 184, hereafter abbreviated<italic>EI</italic>; trans. Susan Hanson under the title<italic>The Infinite Conversation</italic>(Minneapolis, 1993), pp. 125–26, hereafter abbreviated<italic>IC</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>See Blanchot, “Le Communisme sans héritage,”<italic>Écrits politiques: 1958–1993</italic>(Paris, 2003), p. 113; trans. Christopher C. Stevens under the title, “Communism without a Heritage,”<italic>The Blanchot Reader</italic>, ed. Michael Holland (Cambridge, 1995), pp. 202–4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Ibid., p. 113; p. 202; trans. mod.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “L'École Normale Israélite Orientale perspectives D'avenir,” in<italic>Les Droits de l'homme et l'éducation: Actes du Congrès du centenaire</italic>, ed. Alliance Israélite Universelle (Paris, 1961), p. 79.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>A few days following the announcement of Israel's independence, Blanchot wrote to Lévinas to ask after his reaction given that Lévinas had in earlier discussions emphasized his position that Zionism did not seem to be in accordance with Judaism's destiny. Lévinas responds by explaining his current ambivalence, one that is punctuated, on the one side, by a sense of the miraculous and, on the other, by the feeling that such an event reduces Judaism to the level of the mundane, to the “thirst of ministers, ambassadors, functionaries, and military officers who will finally have their protocols” (Lévinas, “Lettre à Maurice Blanchot sur la création de l'État d'Israël,”<italic>La Règle du Jeu</italic>, no. 41 [Oct. 2009]: 249). See the English translation of this letter in this issue of<italic>Critical Inquiry</italic>, p. XXX.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Blanchot's letter to Lévinas explaining his decision on this point is quoted by Lévinas in<italic>Du Sacré au Saint</italic>(Paris, 1977), pp. 1948–49.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Lévinas, “Etat d'Israel et religion d'Israel,”<italic>Difficile Liberté</italic>, p. 245; trans. Hand under the title “The State of Israel and the Religion of Israel,”<italic>Difficult Freedom</italic>, p. 219.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>See, in particular, Lévinas, foreward to<italic>L'Au-delà du verset</italic>, p. 14; foreward to<italic>Beyond the Verse</italic>, p. xvii.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>See Joëlle Hansel, “‘Être Juif' selon Lévinas et Blanchot,” in<italic>Emmanuel Lévinas-Maurice Blanchot, penser la difference</italic>, p. 353.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Philippe Lacoue-Labarthe and Jean-Luc Nancy,<italic>Le Mythe Nazi</italic>(Paris, 1991), pp. 34, 56; trans. Brian Holmes under the title “The Nazi Myth,”<italic>Critical Inquiry</italic>16 (Winter 1990): 297, 306.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>Blanchot, “La Littérature et le droit à la mort,”<italic>La Part du feu</italic>(Paris, 1949), p. 328, hereafter abbreviated “L”; trans. Lydia Davis under the title “Literature and the Right to Death,”<italic>The Work of Fire</italic>(Stanford, Calif., 1995), p. 340–41, hereafter abbreviated “LRD.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>See Jean-Paul Sartre, “What Is Literature?” trans. Bernard Frechtman,<italic>“What Is Literature?” and Other Essays</italic>(Cambridge, Mass., 1988), pp. 21–245.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>See Jacques Derrida, “Violence et metaphysique: Essai sur la pensée d'Emmanuel Lévinas,”<italic>L'Ecriture et la difference</italic>(Paris, 1967), p. 152; trans. Alan Bass under the title “Violence and Metaphysics: An Essay on the Thought of Emmanuel Lévinas,”<italic>Writing and Difference</italic>(Chicago, 1978), p. 103.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Blanchot, “La conquista dello spazio,”<italic>Il Menabò</italic>7 (1964): 13, hereafter abbreviated “C”; trans. Stevens under the title “The Conquest of Space,”<italic>The Blanchot Reader</italic>, p. 269, hereafter abbreviated “CS.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Thanks to Clark Gilpin for helping me to see this double displacement.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
