<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207292</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/587599</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR88221</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Kelly</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Brotzman</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Boston College.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>April 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>88</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>522214</issue-id>
         <fpage>255</fpage>
         <lpage>256</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Reynolds, </surname>
               <given-names>Thomas E.</given-names>
            </string-name>
            <source>The Broken Whole: Philosophical Steps toward a Theology of Global Solidarity</source>. SUNY Series in Theology and Continental Thought. Albany: SUNY Press, 2006. viii+243 pp. $70.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The University of Chicago Press. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago Press</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/587599"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In<italic>The Broken Whole</italic>, Thomas Reynolds argues that postmodern “pluralistic consciousness” invites a stance of nontotalizing, nonpolemical availability and trust toward others and deepens our understanding of identity and tradition, which are themselves constituted by polycentrism and difference. In the book’s concluding chapters, Reynolds attempts to show how religion—at least in theory—exemplifies this thesis, and he outlines a corresponding theological paradigm.</p>
      <p>This book will be read from cover to cover by very few people. It can be considered required reading for even fewer. Scholars interested in Continental philosophy and postmodern theology will appreciate Reynolds’s treatment of key themes and thinkers, although few of his arguments are novel. The strengths of the book are chiefly expository and topical. Reynolds does a good job of “teaching” his favorite thinkers to the uninitiated. His explanation of Richard Rorty’s concept of irony, for example, is quite useful. Furthermore, the issues that drive Reynolds’s argument (presumably, the possibility of peaceful coexistence in a world of profound difference) have genuine urgency.</p>
      <p>Still, the book has significant shortcomings. First, it suffers from a bad case of sprawl. Reynolds attempts to engage the following thinkers at some length: Jacques Derrida, Michel Foucault, Hans‐Georg Gadamer, Jürgen Habermas, Gottfried Herder, Emmanuel Levinas, Jean‐Francois Lyotard, Gabriel Marcel, Paul Ricoeur, Richard Rorty, Friedrich Schleiermacher, Charles Taylor, Paul Tillich, and Ludwig Wittgenstein. Dozens more receive passing mention. This, however, is nothing compared to the book’s many arguments. Reynolds forwards vast theses not only in philosophical theology and the theory of religion but also in hermeneutics, epistemology, and ethics. For good measure, we also get a typology of world religions (162) and an interpretation of the Enlightenment (22–41). Sheer breadth, of course, is not necessarily a weakness. It can be an impressive sign of intellectual power and agility. In this case, however, it comes at the expense of nuance. Consequently,<italic>The Broken Whole</italic>sometimes reads more like a term paper for a graduate survey course than a focused monograph.</p>
      <p>Another problem is the book’s unrelenting abstractness. As noted above, issues of nonviolence, solidarity, and dialogue seem to be hovering in the background, but never once does Reynolds mention any actual situation where real communities have confronted these issues. His argument stringently avoids any reference to concrete historical examples. Reynolds also exhibits the dismaying tendency of using simple declarative sentences like these: “The other is a presence who solicits my response by signaling a promise precisely in its distance. Its call is not anonymous, but signifies the trace of something that invites recognition and bids me to pay attention to it. I respond. My world is adjusted. I am transposed, tilted toward the exterior” (113). Where, when, and how are these things actually happening? Only in a vague, theoretical stratosphere? Or in real life? If the latter, why not dwell on a few specific examples? Jargon and underdefined catchphrases further obscure matters: “Thus, meaningful vitality is the constitutive affirmation of being‐with, an affirmation that reflects a presentiment of surplus value intrinsic to the we‐relation” (123).</p>
      <p>Airy theoretical statements like these begin to sound downright saccharine when the subject turns to religion. Consider the following statement: “Presence [oddly, this term is sometimes capitalized by Reynolds, sometimes not] is an inescapable existential presupposition, a kind of eschatological affirmation built into the praxis of availability. … When we encounter the presence of the other, we cannot help but say ‘it is good’” (147). One wants to know how these sentences would be received by a Palestinian attempting to negotiate an Israeli checkpoint or by a student at one of the stricter jihadist‐leaning madrassas in Pakistan. For approximately two pages (150–52), Reynolds dwells on the darker realities of pluralism and difference: violence, mistrust, fear, imperialism, and domination. Undeterred, however, he moves swiftly to “the recovery of trust,” arguing that despite all appearances to the contrary, “religious faith [is] a ‘saving’ performance” that “places us … in a trustworthy and gratuitous ultimate environment, one that resists falsification by the conditions of finitude” (158). One senses that reality is not receiving due attention.</p>
      <p>Theorizing for theory’s sake certainly has its place, and not every book needs to be focused on practical issues. Nonetheless, even the most gymnastic theoretician needs some grounding connection to relevant cases. Reynolds is profoundly uninterested in this level of analysis. While he flies through the theoretical air with great speed in<italic>The Broken Whole</italic>, it is unclear whether the book can make any sort of stable or decisive landing.</p>
   </body>
</article>
