<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">historyreligions</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">HR</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>History of Religions</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00182710</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456935</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/669654</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">HR520411</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Manuel A. Vásquez,<italic>More Than Belief: A Materialist Theory of Religion</italic>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af1" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Tim</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Murphy</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">University of Alabama</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2013</year>
            <string-date>May 2013</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>52</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>669643</issue-id>
         <fpage>422</fpage>
         <lpage>425</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>More Than Belief: A Materialist Theory of Religion</source>. By<string-name>
               <given-names>Manuel A.</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
               <surname>Vásquez</surname>
            </string-name>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2011. Pp. 382. $29.95 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/669654"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>There is a broad rift in the work on theory in the academy generally between realism, favored by scholars (often scholar activists), who typically work with concrete communities, and constructivism, typically favored by more philosophically inclined scholars, whose primary work is the analysis of texts and textual traditions. Marxist sociology is a paradigmatic example of the former; deconstruction is a classic case of the latter.</p>
      <p>This debate boils down to a moral debate. Realists claim that a moral commitment to a concrete group of real-life persons supervenes the infinite play of the signifier. They see constructionists as occupying a privileged, distanced, ocular place which ultimately devalues real world conditions, thus leading to political quietism. Constructionists are committed to an ideal of allowing the Other to be other. They see the very definitiveness which realists cherish as at least potentially the scholar’s own will to power, that is, the imposition of one’s own meaning onto the subsequently elided Other.</p>
      <p>Clearly, this is an oversimplified, almost melodramatic way of presenting this debate. However, it is very often in this oversimplified, melodramatic way that it is played out in the field of “theory” as it exists in many disciplines. It is also very much the way it plays out in Manuel Vásquez’s text. This is, in part, because this book is really three books in one: a critical genealogy of the study of religion, a distinct theory of religion, and a (nonvitriolic) polemic aimed at certain rival theories. Each of these is a worthy pursuit, and, although performed unevenly throughout the text, each makes a real contribution to the task of theorizing religion. However, one may wonder if it would have been better to write two books, one on theory and a genealogy.</p>
      <p>The threefold arrangement allows Vásquez to present his arguments by deeply embedding them in extended exegeses of important theoretical problems and texts in the history of the study of religion. His theory is developed in and by a back-and-forth, dialogical-polemical interaction with an impressive array of key theorists and theories (indeed, Vásquez seems never to have met a theory he would not exposit). As such, the polemical element tends to define his positive position. His theory is, as it is worked out in the text, something of an antitheory, or at least a reaction to the weaknesses of other theories. His realism is directly pit against constructivism. In fact, much of the book expresses his animus toward constructivism.</p>
      <p>When viewed against his background and his prior research—and I mean this in no way as either reductive or an ad hominem—it is not surprising that Vásquez would opt for realism. Born in El Salvador, he attended the<italic>Colegio</italic>
         <italic>Externado San José</italic>, a secondary school run by Jesuits seeking to implement the more radical social teachings of Vatican II. As he relates in the preface to his first book,<italic>The Brazilian Popular Church and the Crisis of Modernity</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), his education at this a radical time proved a formative influence on his outlook. This first book is a sociological study of a specific group of people participating in the “popular church” movement in Brazil. His more recent work<italic>Globalizing the Sacred: Religion across the Americas</italic>(New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 2003), which he coauthored with Marie F. Marquardt, looks again at concrete groups as they perform their religion in a variety of contexts and as these contexts are affected by the processes of globalization. The place theory holds for him and his theoretical disposition follow logically from his training as a sociologist. He is a realist as described above (he describes his position in this debate as “cultural realism” [6]). He engages in theory because: “I do theory for a more ‘therapeutic’ purpose: to disentangle some of the epistemological knots that have characterized the discipline of religion as [a] way to provide fallible yet effective tools to explore the rich and diverse everyday activities of situated actors who have come to identify what they do as religious” (9). Theory, then, is a tool, that is, a secondary element that comes after the solid research is completed.</p>
      <p>Vásquez’s overall project is to “rematerialize” (as he puts it) the study of religion, and the key to his positive theoretical position lies in the way he conceptualizes materialism. His focus on this rematerialization is on three areas: the body, practice, and emplacement. The book is divided into three parts, each corresponding to these domains. However, it is indicative of his interests and intentions that part 1 on embodiment contains seven chapters, while parts 2 and 3 contain two chapters each. He chooses materialism “because it approaches religion as it is lived by human beings, not angels” (5).</p>
      <p>When he formulates the basis for his materialism he does something very interesting. Rather than engage the Marxist tradition, with its issue of the relation between an economic base and a cultural superstructure, he turns of all places to phenomenology: “My aim is to recover alternative materialist currents within phenomenology which challenges somatophobic internalism and idealism. These alternative phenomenological currents stress historicity, facticity, enfleshment, and embeddedness in everyday life as the inescapable conditions for [the] construction of selfhood” (59). Several chapters in part 1 offer an extensive reinterpretation of Husserl and Merleau-Ponty in whom Vásquez finds support for a “non-reductive materialism.” As a theorist, Vásquez is a synthetic thinker, artfully blending an array of ideas into a single whole. This makes the book a richly informative work, yet one which sustains a single argument throughout.</p>
      <p>However, one could argue that there is a serious problem with his core theory. The problem is this: despite all the polemics and careful exegesis, finally he offers no substantive justification for adopting materialism as a position as opposed to any other position. So, whence comes his materialism? From politics and from political morality. In a critique of Deleuze’s approach he says it is “neither epistemologically fruitful nor politically strategic in contemporary society ” (164). Whether or not an approach is politically strategic in his sense, is a deeply misguided criterion for assessing a theory. Its presentist agenda renders it useless for evaluating theory as such. A theory of religion must be applicable to all forms of religion, not just the ones we encounter in our present. Ultimately, using such a criterion for choosing a theoretical framework makes such a choice subjective, even solipsistic. His criterion makes no sense for the study of ancient religions or for the study of textual traditions, both worthy pursuits. There may be good reasons to study angels and not human beings in the present.</p>
      <p>As is often the case, when a scholar who is trained as a descriptivist (in disciplines such as history, sociology, and ethnography) attempts to take on theoretical issues they become theoretically parochial. They understand what works for their predefined area of expertise. However, theory takes place in constituting the domains for research, prior to the act of description, not in the applying individual concepts to preexistent object-domains. As Paul Ricoeur put it, “to delimit a domain of application is a hermeneutical act,” an act “that calls for reflection in terms of a general theory of interpretation” (<italic>Figuring the Sacred</italic>[Minneapolis: Augsburg Fortress Press, 1995] 304). This kind of reflection, in my view as a scholar trained in theory, is completely lacking in Vásquez’s choice of criterion, despite his long sections of exegesis of theoretical texts. Rigorous exegesis is not the same thing as rigorous theoretical thinking. Rather, in Vásquez’s choices we find a predetermined view in search of a theory. The book becomes a justification of his choices, not a critical, reflexive, hermeneutical act. Theory happens before the explication of theory begins, and awareness of this fact is absent from this text.</p>
      <p>This situation reflects the field as a whole. Descriptivists tend to take up theory later in their careers, after they have done their solid research. This means that theory is often done by nonspecialists. Consequently, because they lack expertise in theory itself they are usually unable to work abstractly enough at the macrolevel of theory formation. It says a great deal about what we think of theory as an intellectual and scholarly enterprise when we tolerate an arrangement in this area that would be unthinkable in any other area of scholarly expertise. Theory proper cannot be understood as a set of tools or as something exterior to research, but rather as that which forms the thinking which underlies research itself.</p>
      <p>In sum: while it has it flaws, this book is one of the most comprehensive and up-to-date surveys of the field of theories of religion around. It is worth the cover price for that alone, which makes it definitely recommendable. Those who want to learn about the current state of theory, especially if they tend in the realist direction, will find this book very useful. Constructivists acquainted with theory will likely find it less so.</p>
   </body>
</article>
