<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">humastud</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j50000010</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Human Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Martinus Nijhoff Publishers</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">01638548</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1572851X</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">40270700</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="pub-doi">10.1007/s10746-009-9109-1</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Phenomenology of Falling Ill: An Explication, Critique and Improvement of Sartre's Theory of Embodiment and Alienation</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Fredrik</given-names>
                  <surname>Svenaeus</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2009</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>32</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>i40010631</issue-id>
         <fpage>53</fpage>
         <lpage>66</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2009 Springer Science+Business Media B.V.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40270700"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>In this paper I develop a phenomenology of falling ill by presenting, interpreting and developing the basic model we find in Jean-Paul Sartre's Being and Nothingness (1956). The three steps identified by Sartre in this process are analysed, developed further and brought to a five- step model: (1) pre-reflective experience of discomfort, (2) lived, bodily discomfort, (3) suffered illness, (4) disease pondering, and (5) disease state. To fall ill is to fall victim to a gradual process of alienation, and with each step this alienating process is taken to a new qualitative level. Consequently, the five steps of falling ill have not only a contingent chronological order but also a kind of logical order, in that they typically presuppose each other. I adopt Sartre's focus on embodiment as the core ground of the alienation process, but point out that the alienation of the body in illness is not only the experience of a psychic object, but an experience of the independent life of one's own body. This facticity of the body is the result neither of the gaze of the other person, nor of a reflection adopting the outer perspective of the other in an indirect way, but is a result of the very otherness of one's own body, which addresses and plagues us when we fall ill. I use examples of falling ill and being a patient to show how a phenomenology of falling ill can be helpful in educating health-care personnel (and perhaps also patients) about the ways of the lived body.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>Phenomenology</kwd>
            <kwd>Illness</kwd>
            <kwd>Sartre</kwd>
            <kwd>Embodiment</kwd>
            <kwd>Alienation</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d9027e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e141" publication-type="other">
Hardy, R. (Ed.). (1978). Sick: How people feel about being sick and what they think of those who care for
them. Chicago: Teach 'em' Inc.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e155" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, M. (1996). Being and tinte (J. Stambaugh, Trans.). Albany: State University of New York
Press, (original work published 1927).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e165a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e169" publication-type="other">
Leder, D. (1990). The absent body. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e176a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e180" publication-type="other">
Merleau-Ponty, M. (1962). Phenomenology of perception (C. Smith, Trans.). London: Routledge.
(original work published 1945).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e191a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e195" publication-type="other">
Nordenfelt, L. (1995). On the nature of health: An action-theoretic approach (second revised edition).
Dordrecht: Reidel Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e209" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. (1992). Oneself as another. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e216a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e220" publication-type="other">
Sartre, J.-P. (1956). Being and nothingness (H. E. Barnes, Trans.). New York: Washington Square Press,
(original work published 1943).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e230a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e234" publication-type="other">
Svenaeus, F. (2001). The hermeneutics of medicine and the phenomenology of health: Steps towards a
philosophy of medical practice, (second revised edition). Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e244a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e248" publication-type="other">
Toombs, S. K. (1992). The meaning of illness: A phenomenological account of the different perspectives
of physician and patient. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e258a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e262" publication-type="other">
Zahavi, D. (2003). Husserl's phenomenology. Stanford, California: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9027e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9027e274" publication-type="other">
Zaner, R. M. (1981). The context of self : A phenomenological inquiry using medicine as a clue. Athens,
Ohio: Ohio University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
