<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">polisocirevi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50003148</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Polish Sociological Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The Polish Sociological Association</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">12311413</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41969499</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bringing Habermas to Memory Studies</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>MICHAŁ</given-names>
                  <surname>ŁUCZEWSKI</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>TOMASZ</given-names>
                  <surname>MAŚLANKA</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>PAULINA</given-names>
                  <surname>BEDNARZ-ŁUCZEWSKA</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>183</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40092224</issue-id>
         <fpage>335</fpage>
         <lpage>349</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © The Polish Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41969499"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>In this paper, we attempt to show the fruitfulness of the theory of communicative action for memory studies. Specifically, we intend to demonstrate that concepts characteristic of the discipline, such as "history," "memory," and "dialogue," reflect three types of universal validity claims: "memory" formulates claims to authenticity, "history" formulates claims to truth, and "dialogue" formulates claims to Tightness. Thus, it is possible to introduce a seminal Habermasian notion of rationality that rests on validity claims. This notion can serve to integrate, enrich, and identify blind spots in memory studies. Our purpose is to demonstrate the relevance of collective memory to social cohesion (cultural reproduction, social integration, and socialization) and the public sphere (its development and atrophy, rationalization, and colonization).</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d11632e138a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e142" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey. 2003. On the Social Construction of Moral Universais: The "Holocaust" from War
Crime to Trauma Drama, in: The Meanings of Social Life. Cultural Sociology, Oxford: Oxford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e155a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e159" publication-type="other">
Assmann, Aleida. 1999. Erinnerungsräume. Formen und Wandlungen des kulturellen Gedächtnisses.
München: C. H. Beck Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e169a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e173" publication-type="other">
Assmann, Aleida. 2006. Fünf Strategien der Verdrängung, in: A. Assmann, Der lange Schatten der
Vergangenheit. Erinnerungskultur und Geschichtspolitik. München: C. H. Beck Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e183a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e187" publication-type="other">
Assmann, Aleida. 2010. From Collective Violence to a Common Future: Four Models for Dealing with
a Traumatic Past, in: Helena Gonçalves da Silva, Adriana Alves de Paula Martins, Filomena Viana
Guarda and José Miguel Sardica (eds.), Conflict, Memory Transfers and the Reshaping of Europe.
Cambridge: Cambridge Scholars Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e204a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e208" publication-type="other">
Assmann, Aleida. 2012. Cultural memory and Western civilization: Functions, media, archives. Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e218a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e222" publication-type="other">
Assmann, Jan. 1992. Das Kulturelle Gedächtnis: Schrift, Erinnerung und Politische Identität in frühen
Hochkulturen. München: C. H. Beck Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e232a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e236" publication-type="other">
Axer, Christine. 2010. Die Aufarbeitung der NS-Vergangenheit: Deutschland und Österreich im Vergleich und
im Spiegel der französischen Öffentlichkeit. Köln: Böhlau.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e250" publication-type="other">
Baer, Alejandro. 2001. Consuming History and Memory through Mass Media Products, European Journal
of Cultural Studies 4: 491-501.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e260a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e264" publication-type="other">
Blaive, Muriel; Gerbel, Christian and Lindenberge r, Thomas (eds.). 2010. Clashes in European
Memory: The Case of Communist Repression and the Holocaust. Innsbruck: Studienverlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e274a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e278" publication-type="other">
Borsò, Vittoria; Krume ich, Gerd and Witte, Bernd (eds.). 2001. Medialität und Gedächtnis. In-
terdisziplinäre Beiträge zur kulturellen Verarbeitung europäischer Krisen. M &amp; P Schriftenreihe für
Wissenschaft und Forschung. Stuttgart: Metzler.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e296" publication-type="other">
Breakwell, Glynis M., (ed.). 1996. Changing European Identities: Social Psychological Analyses of Social

              Change. 1
              
              ed. International series in Social Psychology. Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann.
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e309a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e313" publication-type="other">
Buchinger, Kristin; Gantet, Claire; Vogel, Jakob. 2009. Europäische Erinnerungsräume. Frankfurt
am Main: Campus Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e327" publication-type="other">
Chaumont, Jean-Michel. 1997. La concurrence des victimes: Génocide, identité, reconnaissance. Textes
à l'appui. Série Sociologie. Paris: Éd. La Découverte.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e337a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e341" publication-type="other">
Cole, Tim. 1999. Selling the Holocaust: From Auschwitz to Schindler, How History is Bought, Packaged and
Sold. New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e351a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e355" publication-type="other">
Crivello, Maryline; Garcia, Patrick and Offenstadt, Nicolas (eds.). 2006. Concurrence des passés.
Usages politiques du passé dans la France contemporaine. Aix-en-Provence: Publications de
l'université de Provence.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e368a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e372" publication-type="other">
Den Boer, Pim. 2008. Loci memoriae—Lieux de memoire, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar Nünning (eds.),
Cultural Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin, Nw York: de
Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e386a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e390" publication-type="other">
Dolff-Bonekämper, Gabi. 2008. Sites of Memory and Sites of Discord: Historie Monuments as
a Medium for Discussing Conflict in Europe, in: Graham J. Fairclough et al. (eds.), The Heritage
Reader. London, New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e403a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e407" publication-type="other">
Douglas, Peter. 2004. Habermas, Schelling and Nature, in: Dieter Freundlieb, Wayne Hudson and John
Rundell (eds.), Critical Theory After Habermas. Leiden-Boston: Brill.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e417a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e421" publication-type="other">
Ebbrecht, Tobias. 2011. Geschichtsbilder im medialen Gedächtnis. Bielefeld, Berlin: Transcript.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e428a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e432" publication-type="other">
Erll, Astrid. 2008. Literature, Film, and the Mediality of Cultural Memory, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar Nün-
ning (eds.), Cultural Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin: de
Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e445a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e449" publication-type="other">
Filipkowski, Piotr. 2010. Historia mówiona i wojna: doświadczenie obozu koncentracyjnego w perspek-
tywie narraeji biograficznych [Oral History and War: the Concentration Camp Experience in the
Perspective of Biographical Narrative]. Wroclaw: Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Wroctawskiego.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e462a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e466" publication-type="other">
Fleming, Marie. 1997. Emancipation and Illusion. Rationality and Gender in Habermas's Theory of Moder-
nity. Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania State University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e477a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e481" publication-type="other">
François, Etienne; Schulze, Hagen. 2002. Deutsche Erinnerungsorte. München: C. H. Beck Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e488a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e492" publication-type="other">
Garde-Hansen, Joanne. 2011. Media and Memory, Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e499a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e503" publication-type="other">
Gensburger, Sarah and Lavabre, Marie-Claire (eds.). 2012. D'une "mémoire européenne" à l'euro-
péanisation de la "mémoire. Paris: L'Harmattan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e513a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e517" publication-type="other">
Gerhards, Jürgen; Neidhardt, Friedhelm. 1991. Strukturen und Funktionen moderner Öf-
fentlichkeit, in: Stefan Müller-Dohm; Neumann-Braun, Klaus (eds.), Öffentlichkeit, Kultur, Mas-
senkommunikation. Oldenburg: Universitätsverlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e530a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e534" publication-type="other">
Ginev, Dimitri. 2003. Critical Horizons, The Pluralistic Public Sphere from an Ontological Point of
View 1 (4).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e544a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e548" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1984. The Theory of Communicative Action, vol. 1, Boston: Beacon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e556a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e560" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1987. The Theory of Communicative Action, vol. 2, Boston: Beacon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e567a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e571" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1989. The New Conservatism: Cultural Criticism and the Historians' Debate, ed. and
trans, by Shierry Weber Nicholsen, Cambridge MA: The MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e581a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e585" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1989a. Eine Art Schadensabwicklung, in: Historikerstreit: Die Dokumentation der
Kontroverse um die Einzigartigkeit der nationalistischen Judenvernichtung. München: Piper.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e595a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e599" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1989b. Vom öffentlichen Gebrauch der Historie, in: Historikerstreit: Die Dokumenta-
tion der Kontroverse um die Einzigartigkeit der nationalistischen Judenvernichtung, München: Piper.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e609a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e613" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1992. Faktizität und Geltung, Frankfurt/M.: Suhrkamp Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e620a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e624" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1995. Strukturwandel der Öffentlichkeit: Untersuchungen zu einer Kategorie der bür-
gerlichen Gesellschaft, Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e635a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e639" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1998. Die postnationale Konstellation. Politische Essays. Frankfurt am Main:
Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e649a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e653" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 2001. The Postnational Constellation Political Essays, translated, edited and with an
introduction by Max Pensky, Cambridge MA: The MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e663a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e667" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 2004. Der gespaltene Westen. Kleine politische Schriften X. Frankfurt am Main:
Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e677a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e681" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 2008. Ach, Europa. Kleine politische Schriften XI. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e688a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e692" publication-type="other">
Hudson, Wayne. 2004. Postreligious Aesthetics and Critical Theory, in: Dieter Freundlieb, Wayne Hudson
and John Rundell (eds.), Critical Theory After Habermas. Leiden-Boston: Brill.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e702a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e706" publication-type="other">
Hutton, Patrick H. 1993. History as an Art of Memory. Hanover: University Press of New England.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e714a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e718" publication-type="other">
Irwin-Zarecka, Iwona. 2007. Frames of Remembrance: The Dynamics of Collective Memory. New
Brunswick-London: Transaction Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e728a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e732" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Pauline. 2004. Irreconcilable Differences? Habermas and Feminism, in: Dieter Freundlieb, Wayne
Hudson and John Rundell (eds.), Critical Theory After Habermas. Leiden-Boston: Brill.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e742a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e746" publication-type="other">
Junker-Kenny, Maureen. 2011. Habermas and Theology. London—New York: T &amp; T Clark/Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e753a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e757" publication-type="other">
Keslassy, Eric and Rosenbaum, Alexis (eds.). 2007. Mémoires vives: Pourquoi les communautés
instrumentalisent l'Histoire. Paris: Bourin éditeur.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e767a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e771" publication-type="other">
Koller, Andreas. 2010. The public sphere and comparative historical research: An introduction, Social
Science History 34/3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e781a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e785" publication-type="other">
Kwiatkowski, Piotr; Nijakowski, Lech; Szacka, Barbara; Szpociński, Andrzej. 2010. Między
codziennošciq a wielką historiq. Druga wojna światowa w pamięci społeczeństwa polskiego. Muzeum
II Wojny Światowej [Between Everyday life and a Great history. The Second World War in Memory
of Polish Society]. Gdaňsk-Warszawa: World War II Museum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e802a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e806" publication-type="other">
Latouche, Régis and Mathien, Michel (eds.). 2009. Histoire, mémoire et médias. Bruxelles: Bruylant.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e813a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e817" publication-type="other">
Le Rider, Jacques. 2008. Mitteleuropa as a lieu de memoire, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar Nünning (ed.),
Cultural Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin: de Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e827a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e831" publication-type="other">
Leggewie, Claus. 2011. Der Kampf um die europäische Erinnerung: Ein Schlachtfeld wird besichtigt.
München: C. H. Beck Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e841a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e845" publication-type="other">
Levy, Daniel; Sznaider, Natan. 2002. Memory Unbound, European Journal of Social Theory 5 (1).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e852a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e856" publication-type="other">
Levy, Daniel; Sznaider, Natan, Erinnerung im globalen Zeitalter: Der Holocaust, Frankfurt am Main:
Suhrkamp Taschenbuch Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e866a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e870" publication-type="other">
Lübbe, Hermann.2007. Vom Parteigenossen zum Bundesbürger: Über beschwiegene und historisierte Vergan-
genheiten. München: Fink.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e881a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e885" publication-type="other">
Łuczewski Michal; Bednarz-Łuczewska, Paulina. 2011a. Polnische und deutsche Erin-
nerungskultur. Eine zusammenfassende Analyse der Fallstudien, in: Micha! Luczewski, Wied-
mann, Jutta (eds.), Erinnerungskultur des 20. Jahrhunderts in Polen und Deutschland. Analysen
deutscher und polnischer Erinnerungsorte. Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e901a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e905" publication-type="other">
Łuczewski, Michal; Wiedmann, Jutta (eds.). 201 1. Erinnerungskultur des 20. Jahrhunderts in Polen
und Deutschland. Analysen deutscher und polnischer Erinnerungsorte. Frankfurt am Main: Peter
Lang Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e918a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e922" publication-type="other">
Macdonald, Sarah (ed.). 2002. The Politics of Display: Museums, Science, Culture. London: Routledee.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e929a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e933" publication-type="other">
Maier, Charles. 1988. The Unmasterable Past. Cambridge Massachusetts: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e940a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e944" publication-type="other">

              Margalit, Avishai. 2004 [2002]. The Ethics of Memory. 3
              
              ed. Cambbridge, Mass: Harvard University
            
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e957a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e961" publication-type="other">
März, Peter. 2006. Woran erinnern? Der Kommunismus in der deutschen Erinnerungskultur. Köln: Böhlau.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e969a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e973" publication-type="other">
Maślanka, Tomasz. 2011. Racjonalność i komunikacja. Filozoficzne podstawy teorii społecznej Jürgena
Habermasa [Rationality and communication. Philosophical Foundations of social theory of Jürgen
Habermas]. Warszawa: Wydawnictwa Uniwersytetu Warszawskiego.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e986a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e990" publication-type="other">
Meier, Christian. 2010. Das Gebot zu vergessen und die Unabweisbarkeit des Erinnerns. München: Siedler.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e997a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1001" publication-type="other">
Mueller, Jan-Werner. 2006. On the Origins of Constitutional Patriotism, Contemporary Political The-
ory 3 (5).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1011a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1015" publication-type="other">
Müller, Jan Werner 2007. Constitutional Patriotism. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1022a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1026" publication-type="other">
Nolte, Ernst. 1989. Vergangenheit die nicht vergehen will, in: Historikerstreit: Die Dokumentation der Kon-
troverse um die Einzigartigkeit der nationalistischen Judenvernichtung. München: Piper.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1036a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1040" publication-type="other">
Nora, Pierre. 1989. Between Memory and History: Les Lieux de Mémoire, Representations 26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1048a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1052" publication-type="other">
olick, Jeffrey; Robbins, Joyce. 1998. Social Memory Studies: From "Collective Memory" to the His-
torical Sociology of Mnemonic Practices, Annual Review of Sociology Vol. 24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1062a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1066" publication-type="other">
Petritsch, Wolfgang and Džihić, Vedran (eds.). 2010. Conflict and Memory: Bridging Past and Future
in [South East] Europe. Southeast European Integration Perspectives 3. Baden-Baden: Nomos
Verl.-Ges.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1079a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1083" publication-type="other">
Roudometof, Victor. 2002. Collective Memory, National Identity, and Ethnic Conflict: Greece, Bulgaria,
and the Macedonian Question. Westport, Conn.: Praeger.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1093a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1097" publication-type="other">
Rüsen, Jörn. 2001. Zerbrechende Zeit. Über den Sinn der Geschichte. Köln-Wien: Böhlau Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1104a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1108" publication-type="other">
Sitton, John. 2003. Habermas and Contemporary Society. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1115a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1119" publication-type="other">
Snow, David; Morrill, Calvin; Anderson, Leon. 2003. Elaborating Analytic Ethnography. Linking
Fieldwork and Theory, Ethnography 4 (2).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1130a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1134" publication-type="other">
Spracklen, Karl. 2009. The Meaning and Purpose of Leisure. Habermas and Leisure at the End of Moder-
nity. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1144a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1148" publication-type="other">
Stråth, Bo, (ed.). 2000. Myth and Memory in the Construction of Community: Historical Patterns in Europe
and Beyond. Bruxelles: P.I.E.-Peter Lang.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1158a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1162" publication-type="other">
Szacka, Barbara. 2006. Historia i pamięć zbiorowa [The History and Collective Memory], Kultura
i Społeczeństwo 203.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1172a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1176" publication-type="other">
Szacki, Jerzy. 2011. Tradycja [Tradition]. Warszawa: Wydawnictwa Uniwersytetu Warszawskiego.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1183a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1187" publication-type="other">
Sznaider, Natan. 2008. Gedächtnisraum Europa: Die Visionen des europäischen Kosmopolitismus. Eine
jüdische Perspektive. Bielefeld: Transcript Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1197a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1201" publication-type="other">
Triandafyllidou, Anna; Wodak, Ruth and Krzyżanowski, Michal (eds.). 2009. The European
public sphere and the media: Europe in crisis. Basingstoke, Hampshire: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1212a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1216" publication-type="other">
Walkowitz, Daniel J. 2004. Memory and the Impact of Political Transformation in Public Space. Radical
perspectives. Durham, NC: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1226a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1230" publication-type="other">
Welzer, Harald; Moller, Sabine; Tschuggnall, Karoline. 2005. "Opa war kein Nazi." Nationalismus
und Holocaust im Familiengedächtnis. Frankfurt am Main: S. Fischer Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1240a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1244" publication-type="other">
Wessler, Hartmut. 2008. Transnationalization of Public Spheres, Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1251a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1255" publication-type="other">
Winter, Jay. 2008. Sites of Memory and the Shadow of War, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar Nünning (eds.),
Cultural Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin, New York: de
Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1268a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1272" publication-type="other">
Young, James. 2008. The Texture of Memory: Holocaust Memorials in History, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar
Nünning (eds.), Cultural Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin,
New York: de Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11632e1285a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11632e1289" publication-type="other">
Zierold, Martin. 2008. Memory and Media Cultures, in: Astrid Erll, Ansgar Nünning (eds.), Cultural
Memory Studies. An International and Interdisciplinary Handbook. Berlin, New York: de Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
