<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerhistrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The American Historical Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>American Historical Association</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00028762</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19375239</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3523281</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/530342</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reviews of Books</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Dolan</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>April 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>109</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>587019</issue-id>
         <fpage>471</fpage>
         <lpage>472</lpage>
         <page-range>471-472</page-range>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Reading Irish Histories: Texts, Contexts, and Memory in Modern Ireland Lawrence W. McBride</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/530342"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="index_only">
         <title/>
         <p>[[START 06A00080]] Methods/Theory from either Gibbon's or Pocock's point of view, in the making of the first volume of the Decline and Fall. In Pocock's summary of Gibbon, the Augustan principate was a system that bumped along for a quarter millennium until, following fifty years of mili- tary anarchy, the Illyrian Diocletian divided the empire into two halves ruled by two senior and two junior emperors. Diocletian himself abandoned any remain- ing pretence that the emperor was merely princeps and imperator, openly assuming virtually an Asiatic despo- tism, styled dominus and secluded from public access. This set the stage for the establishment of an entirely new kind of regime under Constantine in the next generation. The very resilience of the Augustan-Anto- nine system up to that point posed narrative and explanatory challenges for Gibbon in itself, since it occurred despite runs of weak emperors, intermittent monsters (Caligula, Nero, Domitian, Commodus, Ca- racalla), the progressive emasculation of the senate (effectively completed by Septimius Severus early in the third century), and the growing independence of the military. Gibbon's flowing recit is bracketed by peintures (the gallicisms are Pocock's) of Antonine civilization at the start and of Christianity in chapter fifteen. In between the beginning and end of his volume, Gibbon appears to have realized that he had, in a way, painted himself into a corner, given that he had over a thousand years still to narrate, and a radical shift in priorities and design proved necessary. Future volumes of the Decline and Fall would give both the foreign tribes and the Christians much greater prom- inence, and before the last volume's conclusion, a Tacitean account of the decline and fall of western antiquity would evolve into an "enlightened narrative" of the triumph of barbarism and religion, recovery from which had only really begun in Gibbon's own age of civility. This volume is every bit as persuasive as its prede- cessors and, perhaps because it is as much recit as the others were peintures, it is also rather more compelling a read. More than the first two volumes of his work, volume three of Barbarism and Religion leaves one hanging; like Gibbon and his first readers, we are only at the Milvian Bridge, pondering what will follow with Constantine. One hopes that, unlike those readers, we will not have to wait five years for the next episode. DANIEL WOOLF University of Alberta [[END 06A00080]] [[START 06A00090]] LAWRENCE W. MCBRIDE, editor. Reading Irish Histories: Texts, Contexts, and Memory in Modem Ireland. Port- land, Oreg.: Four Courts Press. 2003. Pp. 233. $55.00. The final essay of this collection closes with the following sentiment from Sean Farrell Moran: "Like Socrates and Plato who stood firmly against the influ- ence of myth in Athenian democracy, academic histo- rians will step in to attempt to correct the misconcep- tions of Irish citizens" (p. 218). In the previous essay, one such "academic historian," Ben Novick, stepped into the breach in the following fashion: "Writing, as discussed throughout this book, is a primary means of disseminating information" (p. 211). Socrates and Plato have indeed met their match. It is perhaps unfortunate that this collection, edited by Lawrence W. McBride, closes with one of the most arrogant pieces of scholarship that I have ever had the displeasure of reading. The conceit of the comparison quoted above, and the condescension of statements such as "Perhaps we should pity the peasants. They made the mistake of remembering their past incor- rectly" and "The common Irish man and woman must then be re-educated about Ireland's past and abandon their memories" (p. 218), make it difficult to commend the essay as a fine conclusion to an exceptional book. One can only hope that Moran is trying to be ironic. But it would be unfair to condemn this book on the basis of one author's misguided faith in the powers of the "academic historian." Indeed, the book, although most worthy at times, has enough problems without that. The intention of the collection is clearly estab- lished in the editor's preface: to "examine how a variety of historical narratives were delivered through the written word, but with special attention paid to how readers might have reacted to these texts" (p. 13). The difficulty is that the reader is the one consistent absentee from the essays that follow. From Paul Townend's chapter on the reading rooms of the na- tional movements of the late nineteenth century to Novick's chapter on the newspaper of the Irish Volun- teers, the reader is little more than a shadowy figure. Even the most basic details are ignored; there is no attempt to estimate circulation figures for books or newspapers. Anne Kane's attempts at "reconstructing" (p. 46) what a newspaper reader during the land war might have felt amounts to little more than an essay in speculative sociology. Paul Ricoeur and Clifford Geertz seem to get more attention than the actual people who "may have" (p. 46) and "could well have" (p. 56) responded to the newspapers examined. It also seems unlikely that any farmer facing eviction could have conceived of the land war as a "ritual process" (p. 45). But Kane's essay is not the only one at fault in this fashion. The extent of the readers' absence almost begs one to question why the editor made such a particular point of drawing "special attention" to the reader at all. This is not a fault particular to this book or to these essays. Beyond specific accounts by a reader reacting to a text, which in turn have all the inherent linguistic and interpretative pitfalls of any other text, there are very few ways to interpret the readers' response to any type of narrative. Timothy McMahon is one of the few authors in this collection who actually quotes from the men and women who attended the Gaelic Summer Colleges that he examines. His essay is one of the collection's most valuable as a result. Colin Barr's piece on university education, again valuable in its factual content, has nothing to say about the students or how the changes in the universities effected them AMERICAN HISTORICAL REVIEW 471 APRIL 2004 [[END 06A00090]] [[START 06A00090]] Reviews of Books and Films and their learning. The academic career of one Galway student, H. Fitzwalter Kirker, is traced in its entirety, but only in a footnote. The reader gets at least something approximating a lifeline in the piece by McBride on the young reader and the teaching and learning of Irish history. That "young people are by nature curious" (p. 114), however, seems an inade- quate point on which to hang a conclusion. The book is at its strongest in the essays by Jose Lanters and Gregory Castle, which focus on the work of T. W. Rolleston and Standish O'Grady, respectively. Both historians are examined in the context of their contemporaries; both essays actually attempt to fulfill the claims they make for themselves in their opening pages. The same cannot be said, however, for Eileen Reilly's piece on J. A. Froude. Its bland rehearsal of his life is punctuated with references to his visits to Ireland and quotations from some of his more offen- sive diatribes on the Irish people. She offers little or no comment on the bigotry that billowed forth from his pen. For example, one is told of Froude's dislike for Daniel O'Connell but not the reason why. Novick's piece on the military education of the Irish Volunteers begins with an interesting description, but it is rather disappointing thereafter. Although the material is fascinating, the author's conclusions are not. At one point, he deduces that "The pattern of military education seen in the Irish Volunteer and the Workers' Republic lends weight to the idea of the Rising as blood sacrifice, since the key strategist, Joseph Plunkett, never wrote military columns for the Irish Volunteer" (p. 198). At no point does it occur to Novick that the rebels might not have printed their plans in the paper because letting the authorities in Dublin Castle know in advance was not really part of the plan. How useful, indeed, is an examination of the Irish Volunteer's role in the training of the rebels when even the author concedes that details of training on urban insurrection were "left to the writers of the Workers' Republic" (p. 210); when the author gives approximately nine lines of consideration to what he adjudges to be the more important source? Through- out there is little sense of the eye of Dublin Castle watching over what was published and curtailing what could be written. This is a worthy but a frustrating book. There is a lot of value in each essay in terms of the material that is brought to light, but there is also the crushing weight of the artificial framework under which the essays are forced to labor. Like Froude, it is perhaps this book's "portion in life to please no one faction" (p. 140). ANNE DOLAN Trinity College Dublin [[END 06A00090]] [[START 06A00100]] COLIN NEWBURY. Patrons, Clients, and Empire: Chief- taincy and Over-Rule in Asia, Africa, and the Pacific. New York: Oxford University Press. 2003. Pp. xii, 328. $72.00. It is a brave historian nowadays who admits that his or her current academic preoccupations began in the 1950s, but an unrepentant Colin Newbury tells us that imperial history at Oxford University is peculiarly marked by continuity. He says that literary theory has dominated the study of discourse for too long (al- though presumably not at Oxford), and it is time to get back to the study of political discourse using the time-honored model of patron-client relations. Drawing on his extensive knowledge of African and Pacific imperial history, with the addition of material on South and Southeast Asia, Newbury presents a well researched and cogently argued case for the persis- tence of precolonial clientage networks in certain British and French colonies. Patron-client modeling was refined by social scientists in the 1960s and 1970s, when it became a useful way of explaining why inde- pendence had brought relatively little change to the administrative systems of former colonies. That polit- ical and economic relations in some colonies can be analyzed effectively using this theory is clear; whether the exercise speaks to wider debates about empire is another question. The omission of colonies of settle- ment, along with almost all of the Portuguese, Dutch, and German empires, weakens the case considerably. Newbury draws on a wide, although extremely selec- tive, range of secondary literature to supplement his own research, wisely conceding that authors may not like the use he makes of their material. He feels no need to address the epistemological and methodolog- ical concerns raised by authors whose work he mines for empirical detail. He excludes pioneering cross- disciplinary studies, such as Jean and John Comaroff, Of Revelation and Revolution (1991) and Nicholas Thomas, Colonialism's Culture: Anthropology, Travel and Government (1994), which have done so much to shape current debates in postcolonial anthropology. Newbury calls for more interaction between social scientists and historians, but he does surprisingly little to encourage it. If patron-client brokerage really is the best model, Newbury should be able to tackle other theories with confidence, demonstrating their inade- quacies through constructive engagement. Instead he revives battles won long ago, such as the critique of "collaboration" and "indirect rule" analysis. There are still some historians who work with these terms, but far more interesting is the much larger number of scholars tackling more recent debates. This book's contribution to imperial historiography is therefore difficult to assess. Newbury hopes that it will help to determine whether imperial rule suc- ceeded or failed "in 'preparing' [its colonies] for the exigencies and responsibilities of devolved govern- ment" (p. viii). One wonders whether this is still a pressing question, however. It has been a long time since independence for many of the countries Newbury discusses. Scholars posing broader questions about colonialism's legacy will wonder about the cost of Newbury's ruthlessly exclusive approach. While dis- cussing the influence of indigenous networks, Newbury AMERICAN HISTORICAL REVIEW 472 APRIL 2004 [[END 06A00100]]</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
