<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">polisocirevi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50003148</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Polish Sociological Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>THE POLISH SOCIOLOGICAL ASSOCIATION</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">12311413</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24371584</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Sociological Prelude in Theological Notations: Minor and Major</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>KIERAN</given-names>
                  <surname>FLANAGAN</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>186</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24371582</issue-id>
         <fpage>139</fpage>
         <lpage>165</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © The Polish Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24371584"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This paper explores trivial or minor issues of body parts and relics and the major matter of evil. These incongruities offer a means of reflecting on the relationships between sociology and theology as re-set by the advent of postsecularity and the fears of Benedict XVI concerning the dictatorship of relativism. Efforts to resolve these incongruities draw attention to metaphors and the limits of sociological rhetoric in handling matters pertaining to theology. A means of overcoming these dilemmas is to be found in the musical explorations of Weber who offers a way of coming to terms with the irruptive spectres of postsecularity.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d669e114a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d669e121" publication-type="other">
'Dangerous liaisons: theology, social
sciences and modernity', organised by the Centre for Thought of John Paul II and the Institute of Sociology,
the University of Warsaw, 12th April 2012</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d669e143a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e147" publication-type="other">
Anon. 2007. A 'Dictatorship of Relativism'? Symposium in Response to Cardinal Ratzinger's Last Homily,
Common Knowledge, (13) 2-3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e157a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e161" publication-type="other">
B a d i o u, Alain. 2001. Ethics: An Essay on the Understanding of Evil, trans. Peter Hallward. London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e168a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e172" publication-type="other">
B a g n o 1 i, Martina, Klein, Holger A., M a n n, C. Griffith and Robinson, James (eds.). 2011. Treasures
of Heaven: Saints, Relics and Devotion in Medieval Europe. London: The British Museum Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e182a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e186" publication-type="other">
B a 1 d o v i n, John F. 2008. Reforming the Liturgy: A Response to the Critics. Collegeville, Minn.: The Litur-
gical Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e197a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e201" publication-type="other">
Von Balthasar, Hans Urs. 1987. Truth is Symphonic: Aspects of Christian Pluralism, trans. Graham
Harrison, San Francisco: Ignatius Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e211a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e215" publication-type="other">
B a u m a n, Zygmunt. 1991. Modernity and the Holocaust. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e222a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e226" publication-type="other">
B a u m a n, Zygmunt &amp; T e s t e r, Keith. 2001. Conversations with Zygmunt Bauman. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e233a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e237" publication-type="other">
Beckford, James A. 2012. Public Religions and the Postsecular: Critical Reflections, Journal for the
Scientific Study of Religion, (51) 1: 1-19.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e247a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e251" publication-type="other">
Benedict XVI. 2010. Pilgrim in Britain: Homilies and Addresses in Great Britain. London: Catholic
Truth Society.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e261a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e265" publication-type="other">
Bennett, Alan. 1994. Writing Home. London: Faber and Faber.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e273a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e277" publication-type="other">
B o u r d i e u, Pierre. 1990. Fieldwork in Philosophy, in: Pierre Bourdieu, In Other Words: Essays Towards
a Reflexive Sociology. Cambridge: Polity Press, pp. 3-33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e287a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e291" publication-type="other">
Davis, Murray S. 1997. Georg Simmel and Erving Goffman: Legitimators of the Sociological Investigation
of Human Experience, Qualitative Sociology, (20) 3: 369-388.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e301a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e305" publication-type="other">
De Botton, Alain. 2012 Religion for Atheists: a Non-believer's Guide to the Uses of Religion. London:
Hamish Hamilton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e315a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e319" publication-type="other">
Dürkheim, Emile. 1915. The Elementary Forms of the Religious Life, trans. Joseph Ward Swain. London:
George Allen &amp; Unwin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e329a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e333" publication-type="other">
E a g 1 e t o n, Terry. 2010. On Evil. New Haven: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e340a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e344" publication-type="other">
Fessenden, Tracy. 2014. The Problem of the Postsecular, American Literary History, (26) 1:154-167.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e352a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e356" publication-type="other">
Fine, Gary Alan, Manning, Phillip &amp; S m i t h, W.H. 2000. Introduction, in: Gary Alan Fine &amp; Gregory
W.H. Smith, (eds.), Erving Goffman, vol. 1, London: Sage, pp. ix-xlv.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e366a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e370" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 1986. To be a Sociologist and Catholic: a Reflection, New Blackfriars, (67) 792:256-70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e377a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e381" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 1991. Sociology and Liturgy: Re-presentations of the Holy. Basingstoke: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e388a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e392" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 1996. The Enchantment of Sociology: A Study of Theology and Culture. Basingstoke:
Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e402a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e406" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2004. Seen and Unseen: Visual Culture, Sociology and Theology. Basingstoke: Palgrave
Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e416a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e420" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2007. Sociology in Theology: Reflexivity and Belief. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmil-
lan (a).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e431a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e435" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2007. Visual Spirituality: an Eye for Religion, in: Kieran Flanagan and Peter C. Jupp,
(eds.),A Sociology of Spirituality. Aldershot: Ashgate, pp. 219-49 (b).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e445a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e449" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2008. Sociology into Theology: The Unacceptable Leap, Theory, Culture &amp; Soci-
ety (25) 708 December: 236-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e459a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e463" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2010. A Secular Age: an Exercise in Breach-Mending, New Blackfriars (91) 1036:
699-721 (a).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e473a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e477" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2010. Bauman's Implicit Theology, in: Mark Davis and Keith Tester (eds.), Bauman's
Challenge: Sociological Issues for the 21st Century. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, pp. 92-126 (b).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e487a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e491" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2011. Secularisation and the dictatorship of relativism: Some perplexities in Light of
the World, School of Sociology, Politics and International Studies, University of Bristol, Working
Paper No. 04-11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e504a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e508" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. 2013. Bauman's travels: Metaphors of the Token and the Wilderness, in: Mark Davis
(ed.), Liquid Sociology: Metaphor in Zygmunt Bauman's Writings on Modernity. Aldershot: Ashgate,
pp. 45-66.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e522a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e526" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, Kieran. Postsecularity and Sociology: the Issue of Divine Irruptions. Aldershot: Ashgate (forth-
coming).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e536a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e540" publication-type="other">
F1 a n n e ry, Austin (ed.). 1975. Vatican Council II. The Conciliar and Post Conciliar Documents. Dublin:
Dominican Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e550a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e554" publication-type="other">
F o u r n i e r, Marcel. 2012. Emile Dürkheim: A Biography, trans. David Macey. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e561a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e565" publication-type="other">
Fulkerson, Matthew (2014). The First Sense: A Philosophical Study of Human Touch. Cambridge, Mass.:
The MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e575a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e579" publication-type="other">
Girard, René and Mishra, Pankaj. 2005. Pope Benedict and the Dictatorship of Relativism, New
Perspective Quarterly (22) 3: 43-48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e589a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e593" publication-type="other">
Goffman, Erving. 1961.Encounters. Harmondsworth: Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e601a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e605" publication-type="other">
Grimshaw, Allen D. 2000. Erving Goffman: A Personal Appreciation, in: Gary Alan Fine &amp; Gregory
W.H. Smith (eds.), Erving Goffman, vol. 1. London: Sage, pp. 5-7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e615a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e619" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen and Ratzinger, Joseph. 2006. The Dialectics of Secularization: On Reason and
Religion, trans. Brian McNeil. San Francisco: Ignatius Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e629a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e633" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 2008. Notes on Post-Secular Society, New Perspectives Quarterly (25) 4:17-29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e640a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e644" publication-type="other">
Hervieu-Léger, Danièle. 2000. Religion as a Chain of Memory, trans. Simon Lee. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e651a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e655" publication-type="other">
Huysmans, Joris Karl. 1986. Lower Depths. London: Dedalus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e662a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e666" publication-type="other">
K e e n a n, William. 2002. Post-secular Sociology: Effusions of Religion in Late Modern Settings, European
Journal of Social Theory (5) 2: 279-290.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e677a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e681" publication-type="other">
Röhrsen, Jens. 2012. How religious is the public sphere? A critical stance on the debate about public
religion and post-secularity, Acta Sociologica (55) 3: 273-288.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e691a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e695" publication-type="other">
Johansen, Birgitte Schepelern. 2013. Post-secular sociology modes, possibilities and challenges, Ap-
proaching Religion (3) 1: 4-15.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e705a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e709" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Paul. 2013. Mozart: A Life. New York: Viking.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e716a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e720" publication-type="other">
L e m e r t, Charles. 2003. Goffman's Enigma: Series Editor's Forward, in: A Javier Trevino (ed.) Goffman's
Legacy. Lanham: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, pp. xi-xvii.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e730a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e734" publication-type="other">
Martin, David. 2002. Christian Language in the Secular City. Aldershot: Ashgate.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e741a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e745" publication-type="other">
McLennan, Gregor. 2010. Uplifting Unbelief,NewBlackfriars (91) 1036: 627-45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e753a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e757" publication-type="other">
Miller, William Watts. 2012. A Durkheimian Quest: Solidarity and the Sacred. Oxford: Berghahn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e764a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e768" publication-type="other">
P a 11 i s o n, Stephen. 2007. Seeing Things: Deepening Relations with Visual Artefacts. London: SCM.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e775a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e779" publication-type="other">
Pickering, W.S.F. 2008. Looking Backwards and to the Future, in: W.S.F. Pickering and Massimo Rosati
(eds.), Suffering and Evil: the Durkheimian legacy: in commemoration of the 90th anniversary of
Durkheim's death. Oxford: Berghahn, pp. 163-177.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e792a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e796" publication-type="other">
Putnam, Robert D. and Campbell, David E. 2010. American Grace: How Religion Divides and Unites
Us. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e806a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e810" publication-type="other">
R a d k a u, Joachim. 2009. Max Weber: A Biography, trans. Patrick Camiller. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e817a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e821" publication-type="other">
R a t z i n g e r, Joseph Cardinal. 1995. The Nature and Mission of Theology, trans. Adrian Walker. San
Francisco: Ignatius.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e832a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e836" publication-type="other">
Riley, Alexander Tristan. 2010. Godless Intellectuals? The Intellectual Pursuit of the Sacred Reinvented.
New York and Oxford: Berghahn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e846a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e850" publication-type="other">
S c a f f, Lawrence A. 2011. Max Weber in America. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e857a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e861" publication-type="other">
S i m m e 1, Georg. 1997. Essays on Religion, trans. Horst Jürgen Helle. Yale: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e868a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e872" publication-type="other">
S i m m e 1, Georg. 2005. Rembrandt, Alan Scott and Helmut Staubmann, trans, and ed. New York: Rout-
ledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e882a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e886" publication-type="other">
S t o e c k i, Kristina. 2011. Defining the Postsecular. Paper presented at the Academy of Sciences, Moscow.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e893a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e897" publication-type="other">
Taylor, Charles. 2007. A Secular Age. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e905a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e909" publication-type="other">
Tester, Keith. 2013. Refleksja zarôwno socjologiczna, jak i teologiczna: rozmowa z Kieranem Flana-
ganem, przel. Karolina Mikolajewska i Stanislaw Burdziej, Stan rzeczy (5) 2: 151-172.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e919a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e923" publication-type="other">
T r u m b 1 e, Angus. 2010. The Finger: A Handbook. London: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e930a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e934" publication-type="other">
Turner, Charles. 2010. Investigating Sociological Theory. London: Sage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e941a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e945" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1958. From Max Weber, trans, and ed. H.H. Gerth and C. Wright Mills. New York: Oxford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e955a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e959" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1968. Economy and Society, vol. 2, Guenther Roth and Claus Wittich (ed.). Berkeley:
University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e969a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e973" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1978. The History of the Piano, in: Max Weber, Selections in Translation, W. G. Runciman
ed. and E. Matthews trans. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 378-382.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e984a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e988" publication-type="other">
W i e v i o r k a, Michel. 2012. Evil. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d669e995a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d669e999" publication-type="other">
Williams, Rowan. 2014. The Sunday Telegraph 27th April.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
