<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">musitheospec</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100580</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Music Theory Spectrum</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01956167</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15338339</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">90012063</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Chopin and the Romantic Sonata</article-title>
            <subtitle>The First Movement of Op. 58</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                  <given-names>ANDREW</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>FALL 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">36</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e90012057</issue-id>
         <fpage>270</fpage>
         <lpage>294</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Oxford University Press on behalf of The Society for Music Theory</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/90012063"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article proposes that Romantic sonatas exploit in their formal structures multiply directed temporal narratives, comprising a temporal stream and various other streams that can be broadly characterized as<italic>atemporal</italic>. The temporal stream articulates the principal sonata trajectory and correlates with the concept known in structural narratology as the<italic>first narrative</italic>; the atemporal streams reside on alternate temporal levels and remain external to, or disengaged from, that of the first narrative. The structural and expressive implications of this opposition, together with the view of sonata-formal conventions made available in recent work on Sonata Theory, provide a framework within which the article explicates Chopin’s robust dialogue, in the first movement of his Piano Sonata in B Minor, Op. 58, with Classical German-Austrian sonata conventions and contemporary Romantic aesthetic currents. The reading provides a foundation for reassessing Chopin’s work in the sonata genre, the norms and expressive potential of which he is often thought of as never fully apprehending.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <label>Keywords:</label>
            <kwd>Chopin</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>sonata</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>Sonata Theory</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>temporality</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>Romantic</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>Romanticism</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>narrative</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>narratology</kwd>
            <x>.</x>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abbate, Carolyn. 1991. Unsung Voices: Opera and Musical Narrative in the Nineteenth Century. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Almén, Byron. 2008. A Theory of Musical Narrative. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arnold, Janice Margaret. 1992. “The Role of Chromaticism in Chopin’s Sonata Forms: A Schenkerian View.” Ph.D. diss., Northwestern University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bakhtin, Mikhail. [1975] 1981. The Dialogic Imagination: Four Essays. Ed. Michael Holquist. Trans. Caryl Emerson and Michael Holquist. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bartel, Dietrich. 1997. Musica Poetica: Musical-Rhetorical Figures in German Baroque Music. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barthes, Roland. [1970] 1974. S/Z. Trans. Richard Miller. Preface by Richard Howard. New York: Hill and Wang.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berger, Karol. 1992. “Narrative and Lyric: Fundamental Poetic Forms of Composition.” In Musical Humanism and Its Legacy: Essays in Honor of Claude Palisca. Ed. Nancy Kovaleff Baker and Barbara Russano Hanning. 451–70. Stuyvesant [NY]: Pendragon.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berger, Karol. 1994. “Chopin’s Ballade op. 23 and the Revolution of the Intellectuals.” In Chopin Studies 2. Ed. John Rink and Jim Samson. 72–83. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berger, Karol. 2007. Bach’s Cycle, Mozart’s Arrow: An Essay on the Origins of Musical Modernity. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Buelow, George J. 2001. “Rhetoric and Music.” Section 1.2, “Baroque.” In Grove Music Online, Oxford Music Online. http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/43166 (accessed 31 August 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Caplin, William. 1998. Classical Form: A Theory of Formal Functions for the Instrumental Music of Haydn, Mozart, and Beethoven. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Caplin, William. 2004. “The Classical Cadence: Conceptions and Misconceptions.” Journal of the American Musicological Society 57 (1): 51–117.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chomiński, Józef. 1950. Preludia Chopina. Kraków: Polskie Wydawnictwo Muzyczne.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chomiński, Józef. 1960. Sonaty Chopina. Kraków: Polskie Wydawnictwo Muzyczne.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chopin, Frédéric. [1845?] Sonata pour les piano, op. 58. Leipzig: Breitkopf and Härtel. Plate no. 7260.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chopin, Frédéric. 1981. Complete Ballades, Impromptus and Sonatas: The Paderewski Edition. Ed. Ignacy Jan Paderewski, Ludwik Bronarski and Józef Turczyński. New York: Dover.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chua, Daniel K. L. 2009. “Beethoven’s Other Humanism.” Journal of the American Musicological Society 62 (3): 571–645.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cone, Edward T. 1974. The Composer’s Voice. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dahlhaus, Carl. [1980] 1989. Nineteenth-Century Music. Trans. J. Bradford Robinson. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dammeier-Kirpal, Ursula. 1973. Der Sonatensatz bei Frédéric Chopin. Wiesbaden: Breitkopf and Härtel.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Darcy, Warren. 1997. “Bruckner’s Sonata Deformations.” In Bruckner Studies. Ed. Timothy L. Jackson and Paul Hawkshaw. 256–77. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Daverio, John. 1993. Nineteenth-Century Music and the German Romantic Ideology. New York: Schirmer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Genette, Gérard. 1980. Narrative Discourse: As Essay in Method. Trans. Jane E. Lewin. Foreword by Jonathan Culler. Ithaca [NY]: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goldberg, Halina. 2004. “‘Remembering that tale of grief’: The Prophetic Voice in Chopin’s Music.” In The Age of Chopin: Interdisciplinary Inquiries. Ed. Halina Goldberg. 54–92. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gould, Peter. 1967. “Sonatas and Concertos.” In Frédéric Chopin: Profiles of the Man and the Musician. Ed. Alan Walker. 144–69. New York: Taplinger.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hatten, Robert S. 1982. “Toward a Semiotic Model of Style in Music: Epistemological and Methodological Bases.” Ph.D. diss., Indiana University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hatten, Robert S. 1994. Musical Meaning in Beethoven: Markedness, Correlation, and Interpretation. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hatten, Robert S. 2004. Interpreting Musical Gestures, Topics, and Tropes: Mozart, Beethoven, Schubert. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heineman, Michael. 2003. “Bach–Beethoven und Chopin: Zu Fryderyk Chopins Sonate Nr. 1 C-moll, op. 4.” In Chopin and His Work in the Context of Culture. Vol. 1. Ed. Irena Poniatowska. 404–10. Krakow: Polska Akademia Chopinowska.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Helman, Zofia. 2000. “Norms and Individuation in Chopin’s Sonatas.” Trans. Radosław Materka and Maja Trochimczyk. Polish Music Journal 3 (1), http://www.usc.edu/dept/polish_music/PMJ/issue/3.1.00/helman.html (accessed 11 February 2011).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James. 2001. “Back and Forth from Egmont: Beethoven, Mozart, and the Nonresolving Recapitulation.” 19th-Century Music 25 (2/3): 127–54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James. 2002. “Beyond the Sonata Principle.” Journal of the American Musicological Society 55 (1): 91–154.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James. 2004. “Beethoven Reception: The Symphonic Tradition.” In The Cambridge History of Nineteenth-Century Music. Ed. Jim Samson. 424–59. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James. 2012. “Monumentality and Formal Processes in the First Movement of Brahms’s Piano Concerto No. 1 in D Minor, op. 15.” In Expressive Intersections in Brahms: Essays in Analysis and Meaning. Ed. Heather Platt and Peter H. Smith. 217–51. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James, and Warren Darcy. 1997. “The Medial Caesura and Its Role in the Eighteenth-Century Sonata Exposition.” Music Theory Spectrum 19: 115–54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hepokoski, James, and Warren Da. 2006. Elements of Sonata Theory: Norms, Types, and Deformations in the Late-Eighteenth-Century Sonata. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huneker, James. 1900. Chopin: The Man and His Music. New York: Scribner.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Janowitz, Anne. 1998. “The Romantic Fragment.” In A Companion to Romanticism. Ed. Duncan Wu. 442–51. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kallberg, Jeffrey. 1988. “The Rhetoric of Genre: Chopin’s Nocturne in G Minor.” 19th-Century Music 11 (3): 238–61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kallberg, Jeffrey. 1990. “Hearing Poland: Chopin and Nationalism.” In Nineteenth-Century Piano Music. Ed. R. Larry Todd. 221–57. New York: Schirmer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kallberg, Jeffrey. 1996. Chopin at the Boundaries: Sex, History, and Musical Genre. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinderman, William. 1985. “Beethoven’s Symbol for the Deity in the Missa solemnis and the Ninth Symphony.” 19th-Century Music 9: 102–18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinderman, William. 1986. “Schubert’s Tragic Perspective.” In Schubert: Critical and Analytical Studies. Ed. Walter Frisch. 65–83. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinderman, William. 1988. “Thematic Contrast and Parenthetical Enclosure in the Piano Sonatas, op. 109 and 111.” In Zu Beethoven 3: Aufsätze und Dokumente. Ed. Harry Goldschmidt. 43–59. Berlin: Verlag Neue Musik.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kinderman, William. 2009. Beethoven. 2nd ed. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Klein, Michael. 2004. “Chopin’s Fourth Ballade as Musical Narrative.” Music Theory Spectrum 26 (1): 23–55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leichtentritt, Hugo. 1921. Analyse der Chopin’schen Klavierwerke. 2 vols. Berlin: M. Hesse.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leikin, Anatole. 1992. “The Sonatas.” In The Cambridge Companion to Chopin. Ed. Jim Samson. 160–87. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Levinson, Marjorie. 1986. The Romantic Fragment Poem: A Critique of a Form. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">MacFarland, Thomas. 1991. Romanticism and the Forms of Ruin: Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Modalities of Fragmentation. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marx, Adolph Bernhard. 1841. Die Lehre von der musikalischen Komposition. 2nd ed. 4 vols. Leipzig: Breitkopf and Härtel.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McKee, Eric. 1999. “Alternative Meanings in the First Movement of Beethoven’s String Quartet in E♭ Major, op. 127: Emergence and Growth from Stagnation and Decline.” Theory and Practice 24: 1–27.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Metz, Christian. 1974. Film Language: A Semiotics of the Cinema. Trans. Michael Taylor. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Milewski, Barbara. 1999. “Chopin’s Mazurkas and the Myth of the Folk.” 19th-Century Music 23 (2): 113–35.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monahan, Seth. 2007. “‘Inescapable’ Coherence and the Failure of the Novel-Symphony in the Finale of Mahler’s Sixth.” 19th-Century Music 31 (1): 53–95.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monahan, Seth. 2008. “Mahler’s Sonata Narratives.” Ph.D. diss., Yale University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monahan, Seth. 2011a. “‘I Have Tried to Capture You … ’: Rethinking the ‘Alma’ Theme from Mahler’s Sixth Symphony.” Journal of the American Musicological Society 64 (1): 119–78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monahan, Seth. 2011b. “Success and Failure in Mahler’s Sonata Recapitulations.” Music Theory Spectrum 33 (1): 37–58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monelle, Raymond. 2000. The Sense of Music: Semiotic Essays. Foreword by Robert S. Hatten. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morgan, Robert. 1969. “The Delayed Structural Downbeat and Its Effect on the Tonal and Rhythmic Structure of Sonata Form Recapitulation.” Ph.D. diss., Princeton University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Müller, Günther. [1948] 1968. “Erzählzeit und erzählte zeit.” In Günther Müller, Morphologische Poetik: Gesammelte Aufsätze. Ed. Helga Egner and Elena Müller. 247–68. Tübingen: Niemeyer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newcomb, Anthony. 1994. “The Polonaise-Fantasy and Issues of Musical Narrative.” In Chopin Studies 2. Ed. John Rink and Jim Samson. 84–101. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newman, William. 1972. The Sonata since Beethoven: The Third and Final Volume of A History of the Sonata Idea. 2nd ed. New York: Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Niecks, Friedrich. 1890. Friedrich Chopin als Mensch und als Musiker. 2 vols. Leipzig: Leuckart.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nowick, Wojciech. 1995. “Fryderyk Chopin’s Scherzo in B Minor op. 20: Form and Thematic Process.” Trans. Katharine Tylko-Hill. In Chopin Studies 5: The 2nd International Musicological Symposium Devoted to the Works of Fryderyk Chopin, Warsaw, 9–13 September 1989. 174–89. Ed. Zofia Chechlińska, Wojciech Nowik, Mieczysław Tomaszewski and Hanna Wróblewska-Straus. Warsaw: Frederick Chopin Society.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nowick, Wojciech. 2003. “Chopin’s Sonata Counter-Type: Error of Construction or Innovative Idea.” In Chopin and His Work in the Context of Culture. Vol. 1. Ed. Irena Poniatowska. 334–39. Krakow: Polska Akademia Chopinowska.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Opieński, Henryk. 1928. “Sonaty Chopina, ich oceny i ich wartość konstrukcyjna (I)” [“Chopin’s Sonatas, Their Evaluations and Their Constructive Values (I)”]. Kwartalnik Muzyczny 1–2: 59–72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Opieński, Henryk. 1929. “Sonaty Chopina, ich oceny i ich wartość konstrukcyjna (II)” [“Chopin’s Sonatas, Their Evaluations and Their Constructive Values (II)”]. Kwartalnik Muzyczny 1–2: 152–62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pekacz, Jolanta T. 2000. “Deconstructing a ‘National Composer’: Chopin and Polish Exiles in Paris, 1831–49.” 19th-Century Music 24 (2): 161–72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref70">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Petty, Wayne C. 1999. “Chopin and the Ghost of Beethoven.” 19th-Century Music 22 (3): 281–99.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref71">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, Paul. 1984. Time and Narrative. 3 vols. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref72">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Riepel, Joseph. 1754. Anfangsgründe zur musicalischen Setzkunst. 2nd ed. Regensburg: Montag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref73">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rink, John. 1992. “Tonal Architecture in the Early Music.” In The Cambridge Companion to Chopin. Ed. Jim Samson. 78–97. New York: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref74">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosen, Charles. 1988. Sonata Forms. Revised ed. New York: Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref75">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosen, Charles. 1995. The Romantic Generation. Cambridge [MA]: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref76">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rosen, Charles. 1997. The Classical Style: Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven. Expanded ed. New York: Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref77">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Samson, Jim. 1985. The Music of Chopin. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref78">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Samson, Jim. 1989. “Chopin and Genre.” Music Analysis 8 (3): 213–31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref79">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Satyendra, Ramon. 1997. “Liszt’s Open Structures and the Romantic Fragment.” Music Theory Spectrum 19 (2): 184–205.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref80">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schmalfeldt, Janet. 1992. “Cadential Processes: The Evaded Cadence and the ‘One More Time’ Technique.” Journal of Musicological Research 12: 1–51.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref81">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schumann, Robert. [1841] 1988. “Chopin’s Sonata.” In Schumann on Music: A Selection from the Writings. Trans. and ed. Henry Pleasants. 173–74. New York: Dover.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref82">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tomaszewski, Mieczysław. 1999. Frédéric Chopin und seine Zeit. Trans. Małgorzata Kozłowska and Antoni Buchner. Laaber: Laaber Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref83">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Walicki, Andrzej. 1992. Philosophy and Romantic Nationalism: The Case of Poland. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref84">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Walker, Alan. 1966. “Chopin and Musical Structure: An Analytical Approach.” In Frédéric Chopin: Profiles of the Man and the Musician. Ed. Alan Walker. 227–57. New York: Taplinger.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref85">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Webster, James. 1986. “Binary Variants of Sonata Form in Early Haydn Instrumental Music.” In Joseph Haydn: Bericht über den Internationalen Joseph Haydn Kongress, Wien, Hofburg 5–12 September 1982. Ed. Eva Badura-Skoda. 127–35. Munich: G. Henle.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref86">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Webster, James. 2001. “Sonata Form.” “Introduction” and Section 3. iii, “The Classical Period: The Recapitulation.” In Grove Music Online, Oxford Music Online. http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/26197 (accessed 23 January 2011).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
