<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">shaw</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Shaw</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">07415842</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15291480</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">shaw.34.1.0133</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/shaw.34.1.0133</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bernard Shaw and Paul Ricoeur</article-title>
            <subtitle>Emissaries of Hope, Faith, and Wellness</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Einsohn</surname>
                  <given-names>Howard Ira</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <bold>
                     <sc>howard ira einsohn</sc>
                  </bold>is an adjunct instructor in English at Middlesex Community College in Middletown, Connecticut, where he has worked in various capacities since 1974. He is also a past contributor to the<italic>SHAW</italic>and enjoys writing about Shaw in relation to one of his favorite philosophers, Paul Ricoeur. He is presently contemplating a new Shaw project.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">shaw.34.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>133</fpage>
         <lpage>161</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/shaw.34.1.0133"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Bernard Shaw and Paul Ricoeur are emissaries of hope, faith, and wellness. Wellness is a holistic concept signifying the overall health of an individual that springs from an optimum balance of mind, body, and spirit. It is a state of being unsustainable without the abiding presence of hope and faith. Hope and faith make it possible for humans to affirm life despite the hardships that ineluctably befall them. And hope and faith—together with the wellness they engender—are precisely the factors that uplift Shaw and Ricoeur in their tireless efforts to make the world a better place for everyone.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>I</title>
         <p>Studies in the social and medical sciences consistently show that “hope is key to good health, the best predictor of a meaningful existence, and an indicator of academic and athletic performance.”<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>In addition, as consultant psychiatrists emphasize in a 2010 position statement presented to England's National Health Service, hope is also crucial for recovering from mental illness. “Hope,” the statement says, “is a central aspect of Recovery as Recovery is probably impossible without hope. It is essential to sustaining motivation and supporting expectations of an individually fulfilled life.”<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>At the same time, hope is likewise excellent medicine for recuperating from physical illness, according to the distinguished professor emeritus of preventive medicine Jack Coulehan. “Hope,” he writes, “is a natural human resource that can palliate and contribute to healing.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>For him and many other palliative care providers, hope is an effective antidote to suffering, a “universal balm” in the language of the Hippocratic tradition.<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>Furthermore, hope is not just instrumental to everyday living and recuperation, but also self-reinforcing: “hopeful people tend to be more resilient, more trusting, more open, and more motivated than those less hopeful, so they are likely to receive more from the world, which in turn makes them more hopeful.”<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>In short, hope is essential to wellness; and wellness, it is important to underscore, is more than just avoiding the common cold or a sprained ankle. Wellness is a holistic concept. It signifies a balanced way of being in the world, which reflects a positive approach to living that strives for the optimal integration of body, mind, and spirit. In the words of the World Health Organization, wellness is “a state of complete physical, mental, and social well-being, and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity.”<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>Long ago, when Aristotle identified eudemonia as the telos of human life, he was speaking not of happiness in a superficial sense, but of wellness. Without hope, wellness is unattainable.</p>
         <p>Indeed, the U.S. National Institute of Mental Health reports that individuals with hope deficits experience a range of enervating feelings that include helplessness, guilt, and despair; and in extreme cases, says the institute, the hopeless may succumb to depression and suicide.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>Similarly, the American Psychological Association links hopelessness with helplessness, self-blame and, most notably, depression.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>“People who are depressed,” the association observes, “may become overwhelmed and exhausted and stop participating in certain everyday activities altogether. They may withdraw from family and friends. Some depressed individuals may have thoughts of death or suicide.”<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>Clinically speaking, the hopeless are mired in distress, immiserated. They cannot lead fulfilling lives, let alone thrive. In acute circumstances, they may even choose not to live at all. Clearly, when hopelessness metastasizes into depression, it becomes a life-threatening disease. Hence, without the therapeutic restoration of hope, the forlorn remain in grave danger of frantically treading water for a while and then, with no lifeline in sight, eventually drowning from sheer debilitation in a sea of isolation and anguish. Hope, then, is undeniably critical to wellness, and, in my judgment, hope is precisely the quality that best accounts for the buoyancy Bernard Shaw and Paul Ricoeur demonstrated throughout their long and productive lives—lives that included frustration, disappointment, and adversity along with success, satisfaction, and recognition.</p>
         <p>Two theoretical models of hope dominate the research field in psychology. The first, most closely associated with C. R. Snyder, conceptualizes hope as a cognitive construct centered on the dual capacities of individuals to strive toward personally relevant goals despite obstacles and to formulate strategies for pursuing their desired ends over time.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>10</sup>
            </xref>This approach is cognitive because it anchors the hope process in conscious intellectual activity such as willing, thinking, reasoning, and problem solving. For Snyder, “hope is the sum of the mental willpower and waypower that you have for your goals.”<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>11</sup>
            </xref>The second major paradigm, most closely associated with Anthony Scioli and Henry B. Biller, conceptualizes hope as a future-directed emotional construct with network attributes comprising four complex and interrelated subsystems.<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>12</sup>
            </xref>This approach is emotional because it ties the positive expectations of individuals to humankind's inborn animating passion for mastery (autonomy/empowerment), attachment (bonds with others), survival, and spirituality (the four subsystems). Under this view, hope is a near universal phenomenon with a deep structure rooted in the biological, psychological, and cultural evolution of the species. For Scioli and Biller, an integrative theory like theirs captures “the entire breadth, depth, and richness of the hope experience” more so than other efforts.<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>13</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Fortunately, we do not have to choose between the two reigning theories in terms of validity or comprehensiveness. Nor do we have to concern ourselves with any overlap that may exist between them. Rather, we can profitably employ them jointly as backgrounded templates for exhibiting the general contours of hope as these defining characteristics reveal themselves in the lives of Shaw and Ricoeur. When we take this approach, an eerie feeling of déjà vu ensues. It is almost as if the leading theoreticians actually studied in depth the biographical details of our principals or interviewed them periodically at length in constructing their perspectives on hope. We virtually see Shaw and Ricoeur in the particulars of the theories they provide. Hence, the thorny issue of what hope actually is—a state of mind, a galvanizing affect, or some combination of the cognitive and the emotional—is essentially moot for what we are trying to accomplish. Our focus is not primarily on the psychodynamics of hope. Professionals in the relevant disciplines can debate the merits of the competing arguments under consideration. For us, it suffices to establish that Shaw and Ricoeur are instructive exemplars, archetypes, or case studies of what hopeful individuals are like in relation to wellness, regardless of the specific theoretical stance on hope behavioral specialists can bring to bear on the endeavor.</p>
         <p>To talk about hope is difficult without bringing faith into the conversation. The two terms often accompany one another in discourse and are frequently used interchangeably. Nevertheless, we can distinguish between them in ways that make a difference to thinking and that align them—as distinct concepts—more exactly with our day-to-day experience of living. From one angle, hope is a function of want and wish, and faith is a function of trust and conviction. The former expresses the yearning that our preferred outcomes come to be as events unfold, the latter the assurance that our longings will be realized in the fullness of time. Hope, then, dwells in the optative realm, faith in the declarative realm. Furthermore, faith implies hope, but not vice versa. If faith is a phenomenological presence in us at all, it necessarily reflects a subsidiary but related hopeful intentionality directed toward a desired future state of affairs. In this sense, faith entails hope. Conceptually, the two go together conjointly; it is hard to think faith without thinking hope. On the other hand, one can have hope without any correlative faith. The condemned criminal, for example, may desperately hope for a stay of execution but lack the abiding faith that the eleventh-hour phone call will come. Similarly, the terminally ill patient may passionately hope for a last-minute medical miracle but profoundly doubt that any such saving event will ever take place. Put simply, hope may exist absent faith, albeit passively and enfeebled, whereas if faith is present, hope will be too, in a kinetic form disposed toward energized, goal-directed behavior.</p>
         <p>Faith does much more than simply indicate the presence of hope. It also endows hope with its motivational import and incipient efficacy. Without faith, hope is like a rocket without a launching pad, or a car without an engine: all potential and no actualization. Faith is the propulsive force behind a vital as opposed to a vacuous or attenuated hope. It gives hope its impetus, its directionality, its capacity to make an impact in the world. Without faith, hope devolves into halfhearted effort, lethargy, or empty wistfulness. Hope can be a potent agent of change, but only if it is driven by faith—only if faith spurs it to action in the service of an anticipated future good. Yes, faith can move mountains, but only because it fires and, through thick and thin, stokes the hope that does the heavy lifting. Nonetheless, we must always take care to hitch our wagons to the right star so that we inoculate ourselves against the harmful pathologies that stem from unexamined commitment: escapist wishful thinking in the case of utopian hope, and misplaced reliance on the fanciful in the case of ideological faith. The path to ruin, as Shaw and Ricoeur knew well, is littered with grand intentions, false prophets, and inhumane creeds. Lest we do great damage to self, others, and the planet, what we hope for, and what we trust in, must have some rational relation to reality.<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>14</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Ultimately, faith is a condition of possibility—a necessary component—for an engaged and efficacious hope. Put differently, faith is primary and hope is secondary. This is true in two senses, neither of which diminishes the significance of hope in human affairs. First, faith undergirds hope in the same way that a solid foundation supports a subsequent structure. The substratum comes first, then the library or theater. Without a firm base, hope atrophies and may even collapse entirely when the harsh winds of life reach gale force velocity—just as poorly designed buildings come tumbling down during category 1 hurricanes. Second, faith is the core of the two major comprehensive belief systems that have guided<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>' growth and development through the ages: religion and science. Respectively, one grounds faith in a transcendent or supernatural agency that guarantees order, meaning, and purpose in the cosmos; and the second grounds faith in the power of the human mind to plumb the mysteries of the universe accurately on its own through observation, measurement, and verifiable experimentation. Though often at odds with each other, these tussling worldviews have at least one attribute in common. They each engender and nourish hope, much as the sun emits radiant energy. In this schema, hope is neutral with respect to religion and science. It can spring full-blown from either source and, in a manner of speaking, does not burden itself with determining what precisely presides over the earth and sky. It simply hungers fervently after a better tomorrow, delegating the underwriting of its activities to faith. All of this is germane to our efforts here because Shaw and Ricoeur were not only apostles of hope. They were also men of devout religious faith. They possessed a deep and lasting reverence for what they took to be the numinous, in all of its manifestations.</p>
         <p>Similarly, hope can be born of faith in oneself, another, or others. But once again, as was suggested earlier, caution is in order. Individuals can err, charismatics can beguile, and nations can aggress; and when they do, as has happened with disturbing frequency throughout recorded history, disastrous consequences often follow in their wake. Misjudgment, deceit, and hubris are timeless flaws in the fabric of life, so we must use sound judgment to assess the degree of vulnerability any terrestrial object of elevated trust and unswerving loyalty may have to degenerative infection, be the worrisome scourge faulty reasoning, delusions of grandeur, overweening pride, or some equally debilitating defect. The same holds true for the gods. They too should not be beyond scrutiny, even if one of their presumed qualities is inscrutability. For many, the verdict remains untendered regarding whether deities actually exist as believers depict them and, even if they do, whether what is routinely done in their names has caused more harm than good. No one can speak with certainty about the domain of the divine; no one knows if it shelters supreme beings or supreme illusions. Unquestioning faith, then, in anyone or anything, including organized religion as well as institutional science for that matter, is always fraught with risk. Any way you conceptualize it, faith is a high-stakes gamble whose outcome is uncertain. But this doesn't mean that we shouldn't pool our collective resources, which are far from negligible, and make the wisest life-enhancing wagers we can. Of course we should; informed communal action aimed at furthering the commonweal is a self-evident necessity. To do otherwise, to fiddle when Rome is about to burn, is to court catastrophe wantonly—something our two principals would never countenance. As finite and fallible creatures, it is unlikely that we mortals will ever be in a position to dispense with faith altogether. For should we abandon faith completely or allow it to dissipate under a paralyzing fog of incertitude, no consequential residue of hope would remain to fortify us against the stresses, anxieties, and threats that hem in human existence. And that, as Shaw and Ricoeur recognized, would not bode well for the species' future.</p>
         <p>By the same token, nothing we have said thus far suggests that hope and faith are immune from the vicissitudes of existence. Under extreme conditions of deprivation, hope may wilt, and faith may wither, to the extent that those devastated by searing horrors may see little or no point at all in continuing to live. And when living becomes utterly insufferable for the grievously afflicted, suicide and other destructive acts all too often strike the traumatized psyche as the only remaining remedy. Where hope and faith are lacking, there is scarcely life, if any, beyond the bare physiological minimum of a beating pulse. Surely we can empathize with those Jewish Holocaust survivors who demur at singing the praises of the Hebraic God. The same holds true analogously for some bereft parents who have lost children to senseless acts of violence; they too are less inclined to trust in the benevolence of divine providence. Living victims of natural disasters are likewise susceptible to dark nights of the soul devoid of the sustenance that hope and trust bestow on the more fortunate. And so it goes, ineluctably. Historically, if anything has discouraged the hopeful and faithful, it is the widespread presence of evil and unjust suffering. Where the upper limit of tolerance lies varies from person to person, but everyone—with the possible exception of the unbreakable saints among us (if such a breed exists)—has just such a threshold. Shaw died at age ninety-four, Ricoeur at ninety-two. They lived long, eventful, and productive lives; their celebrated careers in the public sphere spanned roughly seven decades, many of them turbulent and unsettling; and, yes, they encountered substantial hardships along the way that tested their forbearance. Yet through it all, they retained their wellness and positive outlook on life. This, in my view, clearly demonstrates the power of hope and faith to sustain a fragile species besieged by a formidable array of forces that threatens its viability.<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>15</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>To sum up, hope and faith are crucial to human wellness, singly and in the aggregate; they are, in this respect, salutary virtues. Both are indispensable to the species' prospects for flourishing, but in the ordinary course of events, neither is indestructible. Each can wane, to one degree or another; and, in extremis, each may succumb to the experientially insurmountable. And when one expires, the other loses its efficaciousness in the process. In theory, faith is simultaneously source, foundation, and trigger whereas hope is at once derivative, dependent, and active. Without faith, hope fades to nothingness, and so too does living, leaving the race impoverished at every level. The hopeless, if they survive at all, live grim, stunted, and joyless lives. Without a therapeutic intervention, the prognosis for the hopelessly morose is bleak: unrelenting gloom, or worse. Hope—be it cognitively or emotionally based, or mixed—is the anticipation of future goods, and faith is the conviction that future goods can be realized. Faith has multiple sources, among them religion, science, esteemed others, or the self, no one of which is necessarily infallible or unconditionally trustworthy. Hence, the faith-hope nexus may exist in a healthy or a pathological state, depending on whether the forward-looking gaze is tied to objective actuality, escapist idealism, or distortive ideology. If eyes are irrevocably fixed in the wrong direction, wishes are bound to be disappointed and harm, on a grand scale, may be the result. Yet even if faith, as well as any correlative hope it generates, is firmly grounded in reality, there is no guarantee of success. Things go awry, for a variety of reasons, some predictable, some not. Faith, then, is always a wager, and a risky, sometimes perilous, one at that. Faith can stumble, fail, or disintegrate, extinguishing in its demise any lingering vestiges of hope.</p>
         <p>However, as Shaw and Ricoeur well understood, the precariousness of hope and faith does not imply that we should resign ourselves to inertia. Inaction in the face of a looming challenge or an impending calamity is not a productive strategy; it just makes it that much easier for our most dreaded fears to come to pass. Evil is liable to prevail if people of good will do nothing, says the venerable aphorism. We may not know everything, but some things we do know—and those bits of knowledge might ultimately prove decisive in tipping the scales in favor of a faltering species were they to be acted on judiciously. Besides, can anyone live, in any meaningful sense of the term, without trusting in something? Not likely; and as we will soon see, faith is an all-in bet Shaw and Ricoeur courageously make, in full awareness of the way of the world. Despite the potential for disappointment, heartbreak, or crushing defeat, they embrace faith and they embody hope, not just intermittently but persistently. Although buffeted roughly by life's inescapable headwinds, neither acquiesces to dejection; neither renounces humankind; and, to the very end, both labor to ease the lot of those society has unwisely left behind. In addition, the two view the world principally through the lens of the sacred. For them, faith and hope in tandem supply a spiritual dimension to an existence that otherwise might lack an element of awe-inspiring transcendence. For the faithful and hopeful who incline toward religion, as do Shaw and Ricoeur, the numinous persists in our midst and not only nourishes the soul but also elicits a reverence for creation's grandeur that carries with it the certitude that we live best when we serve a purpose beyond shallow self-aggrandizement. That purpose, according to Shaw and Ricoeur, is helping to bring about ever more bountiful life on an equitable, peaceful, and flourishing planet. The paradigm they choose to emulate here is the catholic Jesus—not Jesus the sacrificial scapegoat of vicarious atonement but Jesus the inspired teacher who counsels all of us not merely to live but to live abundantly.<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>16</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Fully primed, faith thrusts hope into the world with a corresponding mission, a motivating moral imperative, whose fulfillment becomes the object of intense human pursuit. The envisioned end state may be mundane or sublime, its scale may be limited or universal, and its dynamism may comprise the catalyzed aspirations of an individual, a group, a nation, or the race as a whole. For Shaw and Ricoeur, the mission is ecumenical in scope, simple in theory, and incontrovertible in substance—humbly: to give more than you take, to treat others as you would wish to be treated, to care for the defenseless, to act justly, to love mercy, to be peacemakers, and to make the world a better place than you find it. Needless to say, the task has proven extraordinarily difficult to complete even locally, let alone globally. If ever there were a “mission impossible,” implementing Jesus's social gospel seems to be it. History itself testifies to the arduousness of the enterprise. Yet, as receptive auditors of the Bible's metaphorical discourse, it is precisely to this singular calling that Shaw and Ricoeur conscientiously harken. In this connection, two things are especially noteworthy about the momentous parallel choices they make. First, they are accompanied by a commensurate hopefulness maintained over lengthy faith-driven lives. Second, they reflect shared philosophical perspectives on the nature of hope and faith, perspectives that are sometimes unreflected in scholarly explorations of these saving graces. In fact, invoking Ricoeur in this context throws a penetrating light not only on hope and faith as phenomena but also on Shaw the tragic-optimist, the Shaw who never allows the tragic dimensions of existence to overwhelm his qualified positivism about the constructive role humans can play in the promotion of life.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>II</title>
         <p>Shaw himself acknowledges the significance of hope for human wellness, in terms of both the individual and the collective. “Our will to live,” he writes, “depends on hope, for we die of despair, or as I have called it in the Methuselah cycle, discouragement.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>17</sup>
            </xref>The “we” Shaw invokes is inclusive: it encompasses anyone and everyone. No one is excluded. For him, “Defeatism is the wretchedness of policies.”<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>18</sup>
            </xref>It drains vitality and erodes willpower, empting life of any goals worth pursuing. Shaw, though, was no stranger to bitter disappointments, be they personal, professional, or cosmic. If ever a person had cause for discouragement or was ripe for defeat by circumstances, it was Shaw. His experience included stark realities such as a drunkard father, an indifferent mother, and a stultifying Irish milieu that suffocated his creativity. Moreover, even when Shaw gained a foothold in the art, music, and book reviewing circles of London, critics panned his novels; the Lord Chamberlain banned his plays, when theater owners did not close them precipitously for financial reasons; and, much to his abhorrence, the British government exploited the masses at home and abroad through its sordid sanctioning of a voracious capitalism. That Fabian socialism died stillborn in Parliament and fizzled elsewhere only intensified his apprehension. Then, of course, there was the horrifying spectacle of the “Great War,” punctuated by friends and foes alike falsely branding Shaw a traitor for his controversial<italic>Common Sense about the War</italic>.<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>19</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>To make things worse, the allied victors ignored his advocacy of a just and merciful peace treaty at the conclusion of World War I, so that the vanquished would not plot murderous revenge. Regrettably, because of this colossal myopia, the defeated did precisely what Shaw foresaw and, to our everlasting sorrow, six million souls went to the ovens amid the carnage of the Second World War (not to mention the fiery mushroom clouds that incinerated much of Hiroshima and Nagasaki). Everywhere his discerning eye turned, Shaw saw outrages perpetrated against the sanctity of the person and the integrity of the planet. This is not the stuff sanguine dreams are made of. Ironically, through it all Shaw did manage to achieve a degree of stature for his feverish efforts on behalf of a beleaguered humankind, but it was not the kind of prominence he sought. Popular opinion regarded him more as a witty jester who reduced everything to a pointless joke than as an earnest prophet who conveyed providential correctives to a wayward people. Commonly perceived as a master of the frivolous, he was not taken seriously as an artist or thinker until relatively late in life. No. Events did not transpire according to Shaw's preferences, to put it mildly. Yet Shaw never succumbed to the enticements of fashionable nihilism or the futility of abject negativity. He could hold competing conceptions in his mind without suffering the disquieting dissonance that frequently accompanies analytical thinking.</p>
         <p>For example, Shaw could agree with Schopenhauer that the world is fundamentally Will and simultaneously reject his metaphysics of unmitigated pessimism. He could concur with Nietzsche that the Judeo-Christian God is a deceased phantom and that institutionalized religion is a repressive force but still devoutly believe in a limited and liberating divine-like creative Life Force that suffuses the cosmos and drives evolution. He could also vehemently reject Darwin in favor of Lamarck on the grounds that the former banished not only mind but hope from the universe, leaving everything to fickle chance, whereas the latter accommodated will, purpose, and effort in mapping the descent of species. And he could agree with Marx that capitalism is a pestilence and deny both the determinism inherent in dialectical materialism as well as the implication that capitalists per se are wicked. In another register, he could denounce vaccines and vivisectionists and still lobby for something like a National Health Service, staffed by professionals dedicated to keeping the nation healthy through certified medical practices, in contradistinction to the unscrupulous charlatans of the day, who exploited human misery by peddling snake oil cures. Similarly, he could chide scientists for mistaking the relation of cause and effect but praise Einstein for his discovery of the curvilinear universe. He could likewise doubt the veracity of the Bible as literal truth but cherish the redemptive dimensions of its symbols, metaphors, and parables. In this connection, he could eschew the idea that Jesus died sacrificially on the cross to expiate our sins vicariously, only to rise from the dead three days later, and at the same affirm that the Nazarene embodied, in his teachings and actions, the best roadmap we have to earthly salvation. And perhaps most important of all, he could see the ubiquity of evil yet nevertheless maintain that it was a contingent rather than a necessary fact of life—more a product of ignorance than malevolence—which over time and with persistence could gradually be evolved out of existence via informed educational practice and piecemeal political action.</p>
         <p>This characteristic pattern of thought, this capacity to simultaneously contemplate jostling polarities and mediate them productively, is exactly what Eric Bentley had in mind when he described Shaw as a “both/and” as opposed to an “either/or” thinker.<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>20</sup>
            </xref>Shaw habitually saw the complexities of existence not in black and white, but in varying shades of gray. He was uncomfortable with absolutes, choosing instead to leaven his unorthodox views with nuance, jocularity, and hyperbole. Nonetheless, for all his exuberant playfulness, Shaw was deadly serious about the world's ills and what concerned individuals and their leaders ought to do to ameliorate them. He could grieve, sometimes privately, sometimes publicly, for the sorry state of human affairs, yet steadfastly refuse to bend his knee in dolorous surrender. With all of its unsightly blemishes visible to even the casual observer, Shaw, who was anything but nonchalant in his observations, could look reality in the face without turning away in implacable disgust. He could absorb the body blows and knockdowns fate might decree and get up off the mat, battered but not cowered, for another round. There was no quitting in Shaw. He might bend in the wake of the ferocious storms that pummeled the species, but he would not break in their blustery gusts. He was made of sterner mettle. He was dogged. He was resilient. He was irrepressible. He was, above all else, hopeful and imbued with faith regarding life's prospects for continuing ascent. Still, Shaw was as Alfred Turco Jr. rightly observed—bringing Bentley's profound insight to its destined conclusion—a tragic optimist.<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>21</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Tragic optimism is an oxymoron entirely consonant with Shaw's customary mode of analysis: dialectical (both/and) thinking. Shaw was well aware that the historical record revealed precious little to demonstrate that humankind had made substantive progress in reducing unwarranted pain, suffering, and injustice. As his urbane Devil so eloquently puts it in<italic>Man and Superman</italic>, if the race excels at one particular thing it is in perfecting ever more efficient means of wreaking destruction on a massive scale and not in honing the executive skills necessary for peacefully achieving the humane society. Moreover, without a vibrant socialism to vitiate the dark side of capitalism, an eventuality that with every passing day seemed to him more and more remote, Shaw saw few if any signs that the desperate conditions of the victimized, whose numbers were growing at an alarming rate, were likely to improve. Even his flirtations with the ruling dictators of the period failed to produce the consummation he devoutly desired. In the main, humans generally struck him as simply too immature, selfish, and shortsighted to manage their affairs wisely. Hence, it is not surprising that the Shavian corpus, for all its sparkling wit and polemical precision, includes a palpable strain of simmering pessimism. At the same time, however, Shaw was not one iota less optimistic that life, in strictly biological terms, would continue to evolve unabated, one species supplanting another through the eons. As Lilith—Shaw's embodiment of the Life Force—declares in her statement that concludes<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, “Of life only is there no end.”<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>22</sup>
            </xref>Barring a cataclysm of biblical proportions, Shaw believed that life was indestructible. Therefore, to his way of thinking, the best use of human energy and talent lies in doing everything possible to assist the forward movement of evolution as it wends its way through the generations. In the Shavian universe, the operative principle is that living creatures will develop indefinitely, continually transforming themselves into ever more differentiated forms, for as long as time and place endure. Thus, only a fool would think<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>represented the unsurpassable pinnacle of the evolutionary process.</p>
         <p>And this is precisely where the specifically tragic enters the equation—Shaw was no fool. Yes, left to its own devices, evolution would proceed undeterred, in an upward trajectory of increasing complexity. Shaw was certain about this, but whether humankind would be around to witness the results remained for him a very open question. What preoccupied Shaw the most about the future was not that the species seemed to be sprinting toward the abyss in a mad dash to deliver itself single-handedly into extinction, although this was quite worrisome enough in his eyes. Rather, it was the agonizing fear of a potentially lethal incapacity lurking beneath the madness that drove him to the breaking point. More than anything, Shaw was desolated by the mounting evidence that suggested human beings were innately incapable of resolving the plethora of challenges confronting them with anything approaching justice and good common sense. As the years unfolded, he became increasingly fearful that no matter what remedial efforts were undertaken in the name of the sane society, nothing would avail. In his darkest moments, he came perilously close to believing that his fellow men and women were genetically unequipped to cope coherently with the exigencies of life. These severe doubts carried apocalyptic consequences with them. For if his worst nightmare truly mirrored reality, and every indication he had pointed in that direction, then there was in principle no remedy for the insanity, no way to heal the self-inflicted wounds that augured the arrival of oblivion. Divine intervention, in the traditional Western sense, was not an authentic possibility for him. He did not believe that some heavenly redeemer was waiting expectantly in the wings to make a grand, saving entrance. Only the drunken sea captain depends, misguidedly, on Providence to keep the rocks at a safe distance. Responsible skippers navigate. They do not drift aimlessly, as storm clouds gather and ominous waves swell. They steer. Such is the austere wartime warning Shaw embeds in what is perhaps his greatest play,<italic>Heartbreak House</italic>.<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>23</sup>
            </xref>Excepting the unthinkable, then, humankind will rise or fall through its own efforts. And in Shaw's estimation, those efforts were, by every measure he could muster, likely to fail disastrously.</p>
         <p>In the face of this chilling assessment, Shaw reached the only conclusion that made logical sense to him: life's invincibility, the core of Lilith's claim, “heralds a victory for evolution that is fully compatible with a defeat for mankind.”<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>24</sup>
            </xref>However distressing it may be to contemplate in the abstract, the conjunction of evolution's victory and mankind's defeat comported perfectly with his tragic consciousness. Beneath the antic pose he often presented sardonically to an all-too-credulous public, Shaw harbored the corrosive awareness that we mortals may never be able to synthesize the dualities that inescapably circumscribe the human condition—thought and deed, wisdom and power, body and spirit—in a way that both ensures the survival of the race and enhances the plight of the downtrodden. For Shaw, at his nadir, the issue was not that we lack individuals with the requisite qualities to meet developmental imperatives. We do not; the Life Force fills this need, everlastingly. Of more concern to him was the inescapable fact that gifted visionaries never seem to gain sufficient traction to alter the downward spiral of events decisively, once and for all. Either they are ignored altogether by an otherwise engaged multitude or the presiding authorities devise ever more diabolical means of neutering them or their accomplishments. Winter, spring, summer, or fall, they are always unwelcome.<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>25</sup>
            </xref>As time marched on, the marriage of contraries Shaw longed to effect seemed less and less achievable, and this growing anxiety was reflected not just in his plays but in his prose writings as well. Bleakness enveloped him at every turn, with no reprieve in sight. In his considered judgment, if humankind was a hair's breadth away from dissolution, and this certainly seemed to be the case in his eyes, it is because we are our own worst enemy. If the species is irretrievably lost, Shaw concludes, we have no one to blame but ourselves. From a human vantage point, this is as dire as it can get, existentially.</p>
         <p>Here, though, we should pause to elaborate a crucial consideration introduced earlier. While we can say with confidence that Shaw possessed a tragic sensibility, we can also say with equal assurance that he never crossed the psychological threshold required for transforming his entrenched pessimism into an indefeasible tragic vision. Granted, the malaise Shaw endured was both chronic and caustic, but it never bludgeoned him into submission before life's unavoidable hardships and misfortunes. As the particulars of his biography make clear, he remained a working artist and an engaged intellectual in humankind's service to the very end. Under no circumstances would Shaw abjure himself or his species. He adamantly refused to do so, on any grounds. He stood firm and refused to yield, no matter what infelicities came his way. A few examples should suffice to illustrate Shaw's extraordinary tenacity. When the cognoscenti urged him in not so many words to cease his playwriting efforts because Nature had so obviously disqualified him for the profession, Shaw politely declined their impertinent requests and went on to win the Nobel Prize in Literature for<italic>St. Joan</italic>, after having authored such “trifles” as<italic>Heartbreak House</italic>,<italic>Major Barbara</italic>,<italic>John Bull's Other Island</italic>, and<italic>Man and Superman</italic>. These impolitic gestures by the critics were classic instances of adding insult to injury, inasmuch as the unsolicited vocational guidance followed closely upon nine years of futile attempts by Shaw to secure publication of his novels. And when his<italic>The Shewing-up of Blanco Posnet</italic>provoked the displeasure of the national censor, Shaw responded before a joint select government committee with an excoriating brief that both exposed the absurdity of institutional censorship and simultaneously skewered the stifling social and political conservatism of the age.</p>
         <p>In another vein, to those who claimed vociferously that his 1914 “commonsense” pamphlet about Britain's entry into the Great War was treasonous, Shaw responded with equal vigor, and then some. Where rhetorical fisticuffs were concerned, Shaw could pack quite a wallop. His imposing prowess in argument put him indisputably in the company of the heavyweight champions of debate, and he was characteristically disinclined to overlook what he took to be scurrilous accusations that questioned his motives. To no one's surprise, then, he mounted a vigorous defense. Among other things, Shaw informed his detractors that he was neither a pacifist nor a sympathizer with the kaiser. In particular, he noted that just as he could celebrate German high culture but reject Prussian military aggressiveness, he could extol the virtues of “esoteric” working-class Britishers for their demonstrative patriotism yet criticize “ostensible” England for her foolish Junkers and Militarists,<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>26</sup>
            </xref>who blundered his adoptive country into a dubious and bloody conflict (more both/and thinking).<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>27</sup>
            </xref>True, Shaw did half facetiously suggest that the senseless slaughter could be ended quickly and unceremoniously if the contesting armies simply shot their generals and returned home to their harvests and local politics. But he made it very clear that should the fighting continue, Britain rather than Germany must prevail in order to preserve the little of the world's sanity that remained. In his view, each of the major combatants shared responsibility for the gruesome inferno that engulfed Europe. No party to the hostilities was above reproach; no one's hands, he maintained, were entirely clean in this foul undertaking. However, once the cannons thundered in cadence and bomb-laden zeppelins floated menacingly in the nighttime sky, Shaw asserted that he had no qualms at all about supporting the homeland's war effort.</p>
         <p>In relatively short order, because he gave much better argumentatively than he got, Shaw was vindicated in the court of worldwide public opinion—but not without a terrible hidden cost. The smug conquering heroes ignored his plea for a Versailles peace treaty that did not vindictively punish the Germans with onerous reparations and, as a result, the Continent erupted in flames once more roughly a generation later, with no less ghastly consequences, if not more so. Confronted for a second time in less than three decades with humankind's seemingly insatiable bloodlust, Shaw was brokenhearted yet again. But, just as before, he did not slink away in denial or shrivel up in despondency. On the contrary: in his ninety-third year, a defiant Shaw produced<italic>Farfetched Fables</italic>, the preface to which offered detailed prescriptions for how the species could correct its floundering course before irreversible disaster struck in the form of biological extinction. While he may have considered these late musings mere “crumbs,” they provided readers with much food for thought and showed unmistakably that the feisty Shaw had not sheathed his hoary sword. Before an unhinged civilization gone familiarly berserk, Shaw spurned capitulation. He still had some fight left in him.</p>
         <p>Well, then, why was Shaw so indomitable? What accounts for his steely intestinal fortitude and his exceptional recuperative power? Shaw could have retired from the fray gracefully, and with earned distinction, but he chose not to. Where most would have strategically advanced to the rear, he charged forward; and when many would have raised the white flag, he persevered. What was it that gave the psychically wounded Shaw the strength to continue plying his trade, in and out of the playhouse, for a flawed species adrift in a world teetering on the edge of annihilation? Was he an egomaniac? Was he an obsessive-compulsive? Was it merely a matter of keeping a stiff upper lip or putting a smiley face on a blighted situation? Was he a diehard lover of lost causes? Was he delusional? Was he a camouflaged Pollyanna in a Jaeger suit? Was he a glutton for punishment? No: I do not think it was any of these things. I believe—along the lines suggested previously—a more satisfactory answer to the intriguing question of Shaw's remarkable endurance is available to us.</p>
         <p>We can begin filling in the specifics of this answer by considering another statement Shaw's Lilith makes at the end of<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>. “From the moment I … lose hope and faith in [humankind],” says the Life Force incarnate, “they are doomed…. I may not spare them forever.”<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>28</sup>
            </xref>This cautionary admonition is instructive not just because it declares that the jury is still out with respect to the race's fate. It is also revelatory in the sense that it gives us a privileged insight into the quintessential being of the man behind the work by way of the implicit homology it provides. The critical point is this: if for Shaw, the cosmic dramatist, “hope and faith” are efficacious in the divine sphere in deferring the species' demise, they are for Shaw, the everyday person, equally efficacious in the earthly sphere. The analogy works as follows. Lilith has not yet given up completely on humans in their present stage of development because she retains hope and faith in their capacity to change for the better. In a similar way, Shaw the individual does not give up completely on Lilith's stiff-necked people for precisely the same reason. He carries within him the unshakable belief that, despite all appearances to the contrary, humans have the permanent capability to modify their behavior in a manner that meets the Jesusian standard Lilith ordains: ever more abundant life on a just and peaceful planet. Whether they will realize this competency in action, no one can say with certainty, not even the goddess herself, for she too lacks the perspective of eternity. But this irreducible metaphysical possibility is all the breathing space Shaw needs to maintain his equilibrium, his wellness, in a world wildly out of kilter.</p>
         <p>For Shaw, the intrinsic texture of the universe guarantees that no outcome, including salvation in the terrestrial realm, is foreclosed from time immemorial. The Lilith narrative proclaims that there is nothing structural in the ether that precludes the realization of human aspirations. The future, in Shaw's judgment, is therefore accessible to those who creatively seize the initiative. To those who boldly revivify the neglected practice of navigation, in the manner so beloved by the superannuated Captain Shotover, the possibilities are immeasurable. Figuratively speaking, in the Shavian worldview the Life Force has left the door to planetary flourishing open, and the species' task is to discover effective means of walking through it altruistically. Of course, as Shaw would be the first to admit, this is very difficult to achieve in practice. Nevertheless, he never wavered in his credo that where there was the will, the morally appropriate way would be found. Despite the gnawing realities that crimped his spirits, Shaw possessed an inexhaustible reservoir of hope and faith that fortified him against adversity and impelled him to action in defense of creation. Paul Ricoeur, likewise a man of constant hope and faith, can help us understand the dynamics of the two salutary virtues that unfailingly bolstered Shaw's resolve over his long and accomplished life.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>III</title>
         <p>The aspects of Ricoeur's philosophical reflections on faith and hope that directly concern us address areas of inquiry pursued by Immanuel Kant: ethics, religion, epistemology, finitude (the notion of limits), and art. One of the main questions that intrigued Kant in the realm of ethics—the domain of practical thought that asks, what ought we to do?—is this: why does the will in its freedom so often choose as the maxim of its intended action a principle that cannot pass the test of universalization (the categorical imperative)? Why, he wanted to know, is the will bound? What holds the will captive to the extent that it cannot legislate the proper moral law? How, he wondered, can freedom be unfree? How can it be held in bondage? What force is so potent that it can render the free will servile? To this bewildering enigma, Kant offered a solution familiar to religious traditions in the West: radical evil. In his<italic>Religion within the Limits of Reason Alone</italic>, Kant argues that radical evil is the unfathomable phenomenon that prevents the actualization of human freedom. This sort of evil, says Kant, is real, irrational, and radical in the sense that it is always already there in experience. It precedes us; it is in our midst, and, to varying degrees, we contribute to it through our own behavior. Because radical evil is everywhere in history, this ubiquity places a limit on what we finite creatures can do in the world. It enslaves the will and thus far has nullified efforts to liberate it in a way that enables humans to achieve the good life—what Kant calls the kingdom of ends and we can call global wellness.</p>
         <p>For Ricoeur, Kant's corpus is essentially a philosophy of limits.<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>29</sup>
            </xref>In the Kantian universe, apart from limitations on action, there are also dimensions of reality beyond the epistemological reach of the species. Specifically, human knowing is limited to objects conditioned by time and space. We mortals, for example, cannot know a hypothesized God, his purposes and methods—or any other postulated transcendental entity—because the efficacy of speculative reason ends where the border of the unconditioned begins. Stated technically, humans can know phenomena, things that are perceived or interpreted, but not things as they are in themselves independent of the mind (noumena). This means that any notion of totalization, of obtaining absolute knowledge, in the manner articulated by, say, Hegel, is chimerical. For Kant, then, neither the theoretical nor the empirical sphere furnishes adequate grounds to support the contention that a reconciliation of freedom and nature is possible. Now, if nothing in our knowledge or experience indicates that freedom can be rehabilitated, a potentially devastating dilemma arises for Kant: how can he save his ethics, which presupposes that ought implies can, if the will is inexorably impotent in the face of omnipresent evil? How can we do what we must if we are denied autonomy? If we cannot emancipate the will, a major plank in Kant's philosophical edifice will collapse under the weight of an unresolvable aporia. Kant, of course, is well aware of the impasse and in his<italic>Critique of Judgment</italic>posits the transformative power of art as the means of mediating between actuality and freedom. Unfortunately, Kant never fully develops the idea of how symbolic expression, a product of the creative imagination, can genuinely resuscitate the vulnerable will, so the question he himself believes religion poses—what may I hope?—remains incompletely answered. However, this lacuna is all the inspiration Ricoeur needs to build on Kant's achievements in fashioning his own views on faith and hope, views that he and Shaw share, especially with respect to a mutual emphasis on the potency of poetic construction in general and narrative texts in particular to alter behavior in the direction of the good.<xref rid="r030" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>30</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>However, this does not mean that in attempting to fill the philosophical gap Kant bequeaths his interlocutors, Ricoeur accepts Kantian thought wholesale. He does not. While he endorses the notion of limits, Ricoeur rejects an ethics built exclusively on the idea of duty.<xref rid="r031" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>31</sup>
            </xref>Ricoeur does so largely because he thinks Kant mistakes the second phase of ethical theory for the first. For Ricoeur, the foundation or first phase of ethics is the teleological tilt toward ends, purposes, and the good. It is not the Kantian deontological tilt toward rules, obligations, and the right, which is derivative and comes second. A third and pivotal evaluative phase completes the ethical arc for Ricoeur: the dialectical tilt toward practical judgment in context (what Aristotle called<italic>phronesis</italic>), which requires that deontological norms be measured for degrees of compliance against the supreme (first-phase) teleological standard of meritorious living before they are implemented in concrete situations.<xref rid="r032" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>32</sup>
            </xref>On Ricoeur's view, Kant's ethics of duty does not encompass the full spectrum of moral relations. It is too narrow. Beyond the difficulties associated with its formalism and ironclad maxims, Kantian ethics acknowledges only one legitimate source of moral motivation (acting out of respect for the law), whereas Ricoeur believes there are valid springs of ethical behavior beyond unadulterated practical reason. Desires, interests, fears, and aspirations to attain basic human goods and happiness are all licit motivational factors in the ethics Ricoeur valorizes.</p>
         <p>In addition, Ricoeur believes that a purely deontological framework like Kant's is insufficiently sensitive to the asymmetry inherent in human action. Humans not only do evil, they also suffer evil at the hands of others, and disproportionately so when they are the innocent victims of ignominious power. Much to our regret, the powerful few can bring whole peoples and nations to their knees, or very nearly annihilate them altogether, if they are fanatics and lack restraint. Precisely because others may be the non-consenting recipients of our actions, Ricoeur argues, we ought to treat them with the same solicitude we treat ourselves. And we should do so graciously, he adds, not with the expectation of receiving something of equal or greater value in return, but out of a sense of gratitude for the plenitude that has been given us. Hence, for Ricoeur, the primary concern of ethics is less about honoring rigid rules and more about taking responsibility for the welfare of others. Under the aegis of the good, decency obliges us first and foremost to minimize violence against the person, in all it nefarious forms, so that we can then maximize human flourishing across the globe—all of which brings Ricoeur well within the orbit of Shaw, who shares the same priorities and whose ethics is similarly teleological.</p>
         <p>Like Ricoeur, Shaw invests his ethical capital in enhancing life, not in obeying rules. In the celebrated dream sequence of<italic>Man and Superman</italic>, Shaw includes duty as one of the seven deadly virtues that cause more detriment than benefit. For him, there is no act, however heinous, that some well-intentioned individual has not justified under the rubric of duty. The road to hell, Shaw said famously, is paved with the good intentions of those who in the aftermath of disastrous results defended themselves by claiming that duty compelled them to do what they did. For this reason, his recording angel is not keenly interested in what Kantian precepts individuals have or have not followed. What counts for the celestial Shavian bookkeeper is whether actions make the world better or worse, whether they reduce suffering and increase happiness—with happiness defined as the joy, the wellness, that comes from serving a purpose greater than narrow self-interest. “[C]onduct,” Shaw writes, “must justify itself by its effect upon life and not by its conformity to any rule or ideal.”<xref rid="r033" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>33</sup>
            </xref>And effecting life, in the sense Shaw understands it, is not a matter of dutifully genuflecting before conventional morality but of asserting the autonomous will, even if it engenders charges of immorality. “[L]ife,” he continues, “consists in the fulfilment of will”<xref rid="r034" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>34</sup>
            </xref>and not in, as he reiterates in<italic>The Sanity of Art</italic>, “the fulfilment of a moral law or of the deductions of reason.”<xref rid="r035" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>35</sup>
            </xref>Even so, Shaw makes it very clear that in crowning the will sovereign he is not championing anarchy. For every sanctioned principle his visionaries disavow, they honor nine. Shaw does not condone recklessness or wild abandon. Before the will sets events in motion, prudence and deliberative judgment, he believes, should prepare the way. He is well aware that we cannot dispense with tradition entirely and reasonably expect society to remain stable. Rather, Shaw's point is that social progress—think of Martin Luther King, Jr. and the nonviolent civil rights movement in America, for example—often requires individuals to transgress prevailing norms, and while such actions are technically immoral, they are not bad or wicked in an absolute sense. If life is to be enhanced, Shaw says, we must always be prepared to act “immorally.”<xref rid="r036" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>36</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Nevertheless, all this spirited Shavian talk of making things better may be inconsequential if radical evil can indeed neutralize the will to the good at every critical juncture in history. If we cannot adequately establish—that is, if we cannot provide at least a reasonable basis for believing in—the power of art to infuse the assailable will with enough momentum to overcome the sinister gravitational pull of its chief nemesis, as Kant avers is possible but only partially elaborates, we may never be able to remedy the ills of the world on a scale sufficient to satisfy evolution's appetite for ever more flourishing life on a thriving planet. If we cannot do what is obligatory because of a subjugated will that is beyond deliverance, it does not matter which conception of ethics is taken as authoritative. Our efforts will always fall short, and the species will assuredly go the way of other hapless creatures that have vanished from the planet, if not today, then tomorrow, or the day after. This sobering realization brings us back full circle to Ricoeur and his Kantian revitalization project.</p>
         <p>For Ricoeur, there is something more originary than evil is radical, and that something is the goodness of creation, as attested to by the Genesis narrative at 1:31: “And God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, it was very good.”<xref rid="r037" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>37</sup>
            </xref>While Ricoeur refrains from interpreting the Bible literally, he does discern in the symbolic story of creation a bedrock affirmation of the human capability for the good that precedes metaphysics and history and resides at the uppermost limit of rational thought. And this attestation is expressly the testimony he chooses to stake his life and work on, even if it cannot be verified empirically. Without such a leap into the Kantian unknowable, without this wager on the elemental goodness of being, faith, hope, and meaning itself, Ricoeur maintains, would eternally elude the grasp of humankind. Hence, Ricoeur can agree that evil is primordial and still believe that something—the good—is even more primordial. In other words, Ricoeur starts from the premise that we are predisposed toward the good but have a propensity toward evil. This means, in effect, that the will, although corruptible, is not fundamentally corrupt. It has to be seduced, led astray, before it falls victim to evil. Thus, for Ricoeur, we do not come into the world as damaged goods; rather, we damage our intrinsic goodness through the imprudent deeds we later enact. To put Ricoeur's point another way, that we have fallen implies that we fell from somewhere, and that somewhere is just our original, untainted state of goodness. Moreover, the fact that we have fallen also intimates to Ricoeur that with effort we might be able to get up, that with exertion we might become upright once again in the ontological sense of reclaiming something approaching our initial moral wholesomeness.</p>
         <p>This is very different from St. Paul's conception of original sin, which holds that through the disobedience of one man eons ago we come into life hereditarily stained—requiring a Christ to die on the cross sacrificially so that every person who ever was, is, or will be can be washed clean vicariously. For Ricoeur, contrary to Christian orthodoxy, the stain is not in us<italic>ab initio</italic>: we soil ourselves. Evil may be everywhere, Ricoeur stipulates, but not because sin is a fixed constituent of human being. Evil shadows us because the will is inscrutably errant, but nothing demonstrates to him decisively that this must always be the case. For Ricoeur, until proven otherwise, evil remains a contingent fact of existence, not a necessary one, which carries with it the possibility that what is ruptured can be mended. It is precisely the cleft between necessity and contingency, exactly this metaphysical fissure between what immutably is and what is mutable, that opens up enough fertile soil for faith and hope to take root. Simply stated, the posited anterior goodness of creation (the immutable) anchors Ricoeur's faith in the fecundity of life, and the correlative notion of evil's putative transience (the mutable) solidifies Ricoeur's hope that the indentured will can be set free. Together, faith and hope sustain Ricoeur in the struggle to retrieve a lapsed but not lost human species. And they do the same for Shaw, in the identical way.</p>
         <p>Although Shaw may be many admirable things, he is not a university-trained philosopher of hermeneutics and phenomenology. Ricoeur is. Yet when it comes to contemplating matters of faith and hope, little of consequence, if anything, separates the two, in terms of both substance and method. To begin with, the first presupposition Shaw employs to orient himself to existence is the same as Ricoeur's: the unsullied innocence of creation. Every infant, according to Shaw, is an “experiment … a fresh attempt to produce the just man made perfect: that is, to make humanity divine.”<xref rid="r038" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>38</sup>
            </xref>Each child, Shaw says, possesses a “divine spark,” a “vital impulse” that impels it “towards perfection.”<xref rid="r039" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>39</sup>
            </xref>In all children, then, latent divinity lies dormant, awaiting cultivation by the guardians of civilization. In other words, the good toward which the budding vanguards of the future instinctively aspire is not wholly outside them. It also lives within them: it is encoded on the helical strands of their DNA.<xref rid="r040" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>40</sup>
            </xref>For Shaw, the deific imprint of all that is virtuous and consecrated in the world inheres uncorrupted in the human genome.</p>
         <p>Furthermore, children come to us fully immersed in “divine mystery,” Shaw observes. They have a “conscience,” which is nothing other than the inborn urge to prefer the good over the bad and the right over the wrong.<xref rid="r041" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>41</sup>
            </xref>From the moment they make their entrance, Shaw maintains, humans naturally lean toward the commendable. For this reason, in the Shavian universe of enlightened child rearing, totalitarian haranguing from pious elders about proper conduct is both unnecessary and undesirable. To be sure, the young need appropriate nurturing in order to acquire a foundational moral code they can subsequently amend as they mature. Youths do have to be socialized developmentally; they do need to be grounded in the ways of civilized life. Otherwise, the transition to adulthood may prove difficult for them. No one denies this, including Shaw. But, he insists, youngsters come into the world with all the equipment they need to pursue rectitude. Hence, they should not be prisoners in their homes, their schools, or their places of worship. Instead, we should spare them the reign of terror that traditionally accompanies childhood by creatively harnessing their innate tendency toward the worthy. So Shaw asserts.</p>
         <p>Moreover, the astute logician in Shaw sees the newborn child as a commissioned envoy of divinity, whether that divinity is understood as the Judeo-Christian God, the Shavian Life Force, or the equivalent in some other belief system. Using the Christian sacrament of Baptism as a dispositive case in point, Shaw, always the cogent syllogist, argues that “if God is the Father of all men, and if the child is the father to man, it follows then that the true representative of God at the christening is the child itself.”<xref rid="r042" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>42</sup>
            </xref>Hence, from Shaw's considered viewpoint, if we seek the Kingdom of Heaven, we need not scour the galaxy frenetically. Instead, we should look no further than ourselves, for in each of us dwell effervescent particles of the same numen that breathes life into inert matter. In sum, for Shaw, every conception is immaculate,<xref rid="r043" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>43</sup>
            </xref>and every child is a living incarnation of the primeval goodness that bathes the universe.</p>
         <p>Furthermore, like Ricoeur, Shaw rejects the Pauline concepts of original sin and vicarious atonement. We enter the world spotless, Shaw believes, and no gentleman—Shaw's shorthand for the virtuous person, male or female—would ever allow an innocent other to pay for her misdeeds. The crux is not to ignorantly transgress to the heart's content and then brazenly appeal to a sacrificial scapegoat to wash away the dirt with unblemished blood and tears. Rather, as Jesus proclaims, the recalcitrant should have a change of heart and sin no more. For Shaw, “Christ stands in the world for that intuition of the highest humanity that we, being members of one another, must not complain, must not scold, must not strike, nor revile nor persecute nor revenge nor punish.”<xref rid="r044" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>44</sup>
            </xref>What most intrigues and inspires Shaw about Jesus is not his purported special status in the cosmic order among adherents of traditional Christianity, but the type of person he embodies in the flesh. Thus, he is, as Ricoeur views him, a paradigmatic metaphor, a timeless “intuition” in the Shavian lexicon, of precisely the kind of exemplary individual Shaw believes every child has the capacity to become in its maturity: a reverent adult who heeds Micah's (6:8)<xref rid="r045" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>45</sup>
            </xref>admonition to do justice, love mercy, and walk humbly with your God.<xref rid="r046" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>46</sup>
            </xref>In Shaw's (as well as Ricoeur's) eyes, there is no means of remedying the world's ills other than discovering practical and compassionate ways of implementing politically the core of Jesus's message, which he takes to be the basic principles of Fabian socialism.<xref rid="r047" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>47</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>In this connection, two additional Ricoeurian points are worth emphasizing. First, Shaw does not present incontestable evidence to warrant his assertion that we exit the womb untarnished. And there is a good reason for this omission. No such corroboration exists, either in speculative thought or actual experience. Shaw knows this, even if he does not explicitly cite Kant on the limits of human knowledge. For this reason, he couches his deepest feelings about the sanctity of creation and the purity of nascence in terms of a “frame of reference”<xref rid="r048" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>48</sup>
            </xref>—what we may call faith—without which our lives could easily be an endless nightmare of unrelieved pessimism. Shaw may enlist Paley and the elaborate inner workings of the famous watch to proffer the notion that there is a designer behind all of the intricate design we see in nature, but he is well aware that while argument by analogy is suggestive, it is not necessarily irrefutable.<xref rid="r049" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>49</sup>
            </xref>After all, given enough time, the counterargument goes, blind chance could have achieved the exact same results many are anxious to attribute to divine intelligence. For Shaw, then, the extrapolated likeness between the maker of a timepiece and the maker of a universe, with respect to complexity, organization, and purpose, does not constitute a rigorous proof. Nevertheless, it does provide him with sufficient grounds for a rational belief in things unseen. Shaw designates his ethereal architect the Life Force and equates it with Will, Spirit, and the mainspring of life, Creative Evolution. On this faith-based view, Shaw defines the Life Force and its ends as the paramount “good” in the ethical sense and conceives every newborn as similarly good because it comes into being already gifted with a subset of the same Will, Spirit, and Creativity that animates the world. From this angle, we can justifiably say that both Ricoeur and Shaw ground their abiding faith and the hope that flows from it in texts they deem sacred and revelatory, the former in the book of Genesis, the latter in the book of Nature.</p>
         <p>Second, like Ricoeur, Shaw posits the poetic imagination, as it reveals itself in religious and other kinds of narrative texts, as the capability best suited for mending the ailing soul and resurrecting the frangible will. The human heart may be deceitful above all things, and desperately wicked, as the prophet laments, but for Shaw (and Ricoeur) it is corrigible. Things can and do change; this is the first law of Shavian evolution. And, in Shaw's judgment, there is no more effective catalyst for provoking restorative transformation, for ridding the world of the ignorance that fuels evil, than the making of imaginative art that is aesthetically pleasing. Why is this the case? Because storytelling can break the infernal spell that enthralls the will. Telling stories, Shaw maintains, can deliver the imbecilic will from slavery, thereby restoring enlightened individual autonomy and the untrammeled capacity to act in accordance with higher rather than lower passions.<xref rid="r050" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>50</sup>
            </xref>“Fine art,” he muses, as exemplified for example in his own dramatic works, by implication, “is the only teacher except torture.”<xref rid="r051" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>51</sup>
            </xref>In this regard, Shaw is very much like the “artist” and “Bohemian” Jesus he commemorates: the sage and commiserative guide who, “when reproached for resorting to the art of fiction when teaching in parables,” justified “himself on the ground that art is the only way in which the people can be taught.”<xref rid="r052" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>52</sup>
            </xref>Consider the biblical Testaments, once more. Shaw believes they are unreliable historical documents yet nonetheless finds “in their readable parts”—that is, in their tales, fables, and legends—a treasure trove of tropes vital to the species' wellness (the same is true for Ricoeur).<xref rid="r053" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>53</sup>
            </xref>However, and this is critical, he cautions that “you cannot read the Bible if you have no sense of literary art.”<xref rid="r054" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>54</sup>
            </xref>Thus, in addition to whatever else they do, insists Shaw, educational institutions must inculcate an appreciation for both the beauty and the potency of symbolic expression. For Shaw as well as Ricoeur, narratives can unlock the manacles that shackle the species. They can galvanize people everywhere to lift the millstones communally so that unfettered spirits may soar.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>IV</title>
         <p>Yes, regrettably, the species is fallen and the will is impaired. Nevertheless, these deficiencies are remediable for Shaw and Ricoeur. The two place unwavering faith in the ineradicable goodness of creation and lodge unflagging hope in the inextirpable capacity of humans to repair the damage they have done to themselves and the planet that houses them. Things can be different. Lives need not be beggared. Tomorrow can be better than today. This is the inspiriting wager Shaw and Ricoeur make, with eyes fully open to the countless maladies that mar existence. Through the maelstroms that swirled around them, they stayed the course, undaunted: they remained faithful, hopeful, spiritual, creative, and humane; they lived long, active, and productive lives of notable achievement; they made uplifting the least advantaged the locus of their ameliorative efforts; they sought justice, equality, and reconciliation for everyone; and the world is a much better place because of them. By such benchmarks, Shaw and Ricoeur epitomize wellness. For these kindred spirits, ever the intrepid circumnavigators of the entropic regions, one touch of the divine that permeates the universe makes us all brothers and sisters under the skin. Accordingly, as harried members of a single global family under siege, it follows in their thinking that we are responsible for one another's welfare, and that we cannot save our individual selves apart from saving humankind at large. Hence, we cannot injure someone unjustly, or allow another to suffer unnecessarily, without diminishing ourselves. In the inclusive society they envision, our shared humanity elicits shared responses to life's exigencies wherever they occur.</p>
         <p>Moreover, for Shaw and Ricoeur, imaginative works of art have the power to project alternative and potentially redemptive ways of living together harmoniously, which in turn can substantially change hearts, alter beliefs, and reorient behavior in an empathetic direction that promotes vigilant concern for the other. Be they biblical narratives, plays for the stage, fictions for the page, or other forms of literary texts broadly construed, stories can portray freedom and fault reconciled in compassionate beings committed to advancing the common good. In this way, poetic making can and has instilled in us not only faith and hope but magnanimity as well. Thus, the answer to the provocative question Shaw poses at the beginning of his last major treatise,<italic>Everybody's Political What's What?</italic>—“Is Human Nature Incurably Depraved?”<xref rid="r055" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>55</sup>
            </xref>—is a resounding no: not just for him but for Ricoeur, too. Where there is faith, there is hope; and where there is hope, there is life. Life expectant.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Louise Danielle Palmer, “The Key to Wellness: Exciting Research on Hope” (20 October 2007),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://keystowellness.blogspot.com/2007/10/exciting-research-on-hope.html">http://keystowellness.blogspot.com/2007/10/exciting-research-on-hope.html</uri>(accessed 3 May 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“Recovery Is for All: Hope, Agency, and Opportunity in Psychiatry” (2010), 5,<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/pdf/Recovery%20is%20for%20all.pdf">http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/pdf/Recovery%20is%20for%20all.pdf</uri>(accessed 30 May 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jack Coulehan, “Suffering, Hope, and Healing” (2012), 728,<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.stonybrook.edu/bioethics/SufferingHopeHealing.pdf">http://www.stonybrook.edu/bioethics/SufferingHopeHealing.pdf</uri>(accessed 5 May 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 721.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Palmer, “Key to Wellness.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>World Health Organization, “Frequently Asked Questions” (2013),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.who.int/suggestions/faq/en/">http://www.who.int/suggestions/faq/en/</uri>(accessed 6 June 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>National Institute of Mental Health, “What Are the Signs and Symptoms of Depression?” (2011),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/publications/depression/what-are-the-signs-and-symptoms-of-depression.shtml">http://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/publications/depression/what-are-the-signs-and-symptoms-of-depression.shtml</uri>(accessed 5 May 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>American Psychological Association, “Understanding Depression and Effective Treatment” (2010),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.apapracticecentral.org/outreach/depression.pdf">http://www.apapracticecentral.org/outreach/depression.pdf</uri>(accessed 5 May 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>C. R. Snyder,<italic>The Psychology of Hope: You Can Get There from Here</italic>(New York: Free Press, 1994).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 5, italics in the original.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Anthony Scioli and Henry B. Biller,<italic>Hope in the Age of Anxiety</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I treat this and related themes systematically in my “Ideology, Utopia, and Faith: Shaw, Ricoeur, and the Passion for the Possible,” in<italic>SHAW: The Annual of Bernard Shaw Studies</italic>15 (University Park: Penn State University Press, 1995), 105–21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r015">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In section II, I discuss some of the hardships Shaw encountered in his life as they relate to hope and faith; these obstacles are familiar to readers of this journal. Unfortunately, I do not have the space to do the same for Ricoeur, whose biography is perhaps less well known to students of Shaw. A man of deep hope and faith like Shaw, Ricoeur likewise experienced significant suffering over time. For example, his mother died shortly after giving birth to him, and his father died two years later in the First World War's Battle of the Marne. By the age of twenty, he had also lost the grandparents who raised him, as well as his sister. In addition, he was a captive for five years in a German prisoner of war camp during World War II. Later, after his liberation, he had a professional falling out with Jacques Lacan and encountered difficulties as a university administrator in Nanterre (the west part of Paris). Perhaps most painful of all, his son Olivier committed suicide at thirty-nine, and his beloved wife predeceased him. Yet despite the tribulations that tested him severely, Ricoeur garnered international renown as a thinker, teacher, and lecturer. He also received the prestigious John W. Kluge Prize for the Study of Humanity and remained productive until his death in 2005, doing all he could to improve what he perceived to be the deplorable state of world affairs. For details on these and related matters, interested individuals can, for example, consult Charles E. Reagan's<italic>Paul Ricoeur: His Life and Work</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1996) and<italic>The Ricoeur Collection</italic>on the web at<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.fondsricoeur.fr/index.php?m=107&amp;#x0026;lang=en&amp;#x0026;rub=3&amp;#x0026;opt=107">http://www.fondsricoeur.fr/index.php?m=107&amp;lang=en&amp;rub=3&amp;opt=107</uri>(accessed 24 July 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r016">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I treat this theme extensively in my “Economies of the Gift: Shaw, Ricoeur, and the Poetics of the Ethical Life,” in<italic>SHAW: The Annual of Bernard Shaw Studies</italic>25 (University Park: Penn State University Press, 2005), 27–51.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r017">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Postscript,”<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, in<italic>Complete Plays with Prefaces</italic>, 6 vols. (New York: Dodd, Mead, 1963), 2:c; a few pages later, Shaw writes that “[d]iscouragement does in fact mean death” (cvi). All references to Shaw's prefaces, plays, and one postscript are from this edition.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r018">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Sixteen Self Sketches</italic>(New York: Dodd, Mead, 1949), 128.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r019">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The pamphlet, some thirty-five thousand words, was published as a Special War Supplement to the<italic>New Statesman</italic>on 14 November 1914. It created quite a stir, as its criticism of the British government ran counter to the country's prevailing mood. In general, the public was outraged and Shaw was ostracized. Ultimately (as noted below), Shaw was vindicated. For context and commentary on the matter, see, for example, A. M. Gibbs,<italic>Bernard Shaw: A Life</italic>(Gainesville: University Press of Florida, 2005), 346–49; for additional insight into Shaw and the World War I period, see Stanley Weintraub,<italic>Journey to Heartbreak: The Crucible Years of Bernard Shaw, 1914–1918</italic>(New York: Weybright and Talley, 1971).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r020">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Eric Bentley,<italic>Bernard Shaw</italic>(New York: Limelight Editions, 1985), 22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r021">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Alfred Turco Jr.,<italic>Shaw's Moral Vision: The Self and Salvation</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1976), 274–86.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r022">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, 2:262.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r023">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw wrote<italic>Heartbreak House</italic>in 1916–17 but deferred publication and production of the play until after World War I had concluded, in order not to appear critical of his country when soldiers and noncombatants on both sides were dying or being maimed in the fighting.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r024">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Turco,<italic>Shaw's Moral Vision</italic>, 286.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r025">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>This is the sentiment behind Joan's passionate<italic>cri de coeur</italic>at the end of Shaw's<italic>St. Joan</italic>: “O God that madest this beautiful earth, when will it be ready to receive Thy saints? How long, O Lord, how long?” (<italic>Complete Plays with Prefaces</italic>, 2:428; Cauchon anticipates Joan when he inquires, “Must then a Christ perish in torment in every age to save those that have no imagination?” [ibid., 2:423]).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r026">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I say “blundered,” but, given the somnambulant, dream-like ambience of<italic>Heartbreak House</italic>, “sleepwalked” is equally apt. The latter is suggested by Christopher Clark in his incisive study,<italic>The Sleepwalkers: How Europe Went to War in 1914</italic>(New York: Harper, 2012). Referring to Europe's prewar glibness, Clark writes that “in this sense, the protagonists of 1914 were sleepwalkers, watchful but unseeing, haunted by dreams, yet blind to the reality of the horror they were about to bring into the world” (562).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r027">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For the distinction between “esoteric” England and “ostensible” England, see Bernard Shaw, “Heartbreak House and Horseback Hall,” preface to<italic>Heartbreak House</italic>, 1:470.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r028">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw,<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, 2:262.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r029">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For an informative discussion of Ricoeur's interpretation of Kant's thought as a philosophy of limits and how this reading relates to freedom, ethics, and hope (what Ricoeur calls “a passion for the possible”), see Kevin J. Vanhoozer,<italic>Biblical Narrative in the Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur: A Study in Hermeneutics and Philosophy</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990), 38–55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r030">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On the significance of narrative for Shaw and Ricoeur, see my “Economies of the Gift.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r031">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For Ricoeur's ethical theory and his critique of Kant in this regard, see, for example, Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992), especially the Seventh, Eighth, and Ninth Studies (his “little ethics” as Ricoeur fondly referred to these three reflections).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r032">
            <label>32.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur defines the ethical intention of meritorious living as follow: “<italic>aiming at the ‘good life’ with and for others, in just institutions</italic>” (Ricoeur,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>, 172, italics original).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r033">
            <label>33.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>The Quintessence of Ibsenism</italic>, in<italic>Major Critical Essays</italic>(New York: Penguin, 1986), 149.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r034">
            <label>34.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r035">
            <label>35.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “The Sanity of Art,” in<italic>Major Critical Essays</italic>, 338.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r036">
            <label>36.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw,<italic>Quintessence of Ibsenism</italic>, 145–46ff.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r037">
            <label>37.</label>
            <mixed-citation>King James Bible (Cambridge ed.),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://biblehub.com/genesis/1-31.htm">http://biblehub.com/genesis/1-31.htm</uri>. On originary goodness, see, for example, the following sources: Paul Ricoeur,<italic>The Symbolism of Evil</italic>, trans. Emerson Buchanan (Boston: Beacon, 1969), 250–52; Ricoeur, “Ethical and Theological Considerations on the Golden Rule,” in<italic>Figuring the Sacred: Religion, Narrative, and Imagination</italic>, ed. Mark I. Wallace (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1995), 298; Ricoeur, “Love and Justice,” in<italic>Paul Ricoeur: The Hermeneutics of Action</italic>, ed. Richard Kearney (London: Sage Publications, 1996), 33; and Ricoeur, “Ethics and Human Capability: A Response,” in<italic>Paul Ricoeur and Contemporary Moral Thought</italic>, ed. John Wall, William Schweiker, and W. David Hall (New York: Routledge, 2002), 284–85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r038">
            <label>38.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Parents and Children,” preface to<italic>Misalliance</italic>, 4:7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r039">
            <label>39.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 4:95.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r040">
            <label>40.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Preface,”<italic>Androcles and the Lion</italic>, 5:412–13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r041">
            <label>41.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Parents and Children,” preface to<italic>Misalliance</italic>, 4:10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r042">
            <label>42.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 4:5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r043">
            <label>43.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In his<italic>Sixteen Self Sketches</italic>, Shaw counts as a “sacred truth” the notion that “all conceptions are immaculate,” 121.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r044">
            <label>44.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Parents and Children,” preface to<italic>Misallince</italic>, 4:52.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r045">
            <label>45.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, for example, Shaw's<italic>Sixteen Self Sketches</italic>, 123.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r046">
            <label>46.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur, as does Shaw, interprets Jesus not as a sacrificial scapegoat whose life was stolen from him scandalously but as a representation of righteous excellence who freely gives his life in a demonstration of abounding generosity so that others may live abundantly by striving, to the best of their ability, to emulate his conduct. We cannot literally know the Trinitarian Jesus, says Ricoeur, following Kant; nonetheless, the literary qualities of the New Testament, Ricoeur argues, allow us to glimpse the Nazarene's silhouette and catch sight of what a paragon of paragons might be like were he to assume the guise of mortality. See my “Economies of the Gift” for a detailed discussion of this issue.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r047">
            <label>47.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Preface,”<italic>Androcles and the Lion</italic>, 5:323. I have extensively treated this thematic and related matters in my “Economies of the Gift,” noting, among other things, that Ricoeur also embraces socialist principles (as embodied in his the notion of the gift-giving economy, for example) and that, like Shaw, he too derives his beliefs from the social gospel Jesus teaches and practices.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r048">
            <label>48.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Postscript,”<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, 1:cv.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r049">
            <label>49.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 1:xxxvii–xxxviii.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r050">
            <label>50.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I have explored the connection among will, passion, and the good life in my “The Summoned Self under Siege: Shaw, Ricoeur, and the Poetics of Personhood in Too True To Be Good,” in<italic>SHAW: The Annual of Bernard Shaw Studies</italic>28 (University Park: Penn State University Press, 2008), 112–36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r051">
            <label>51.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Parents and Children,” preface to<italic>Misalliance</italic>, 4:88.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r052">
            <label>52.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Preface,”<italic>Androcles and the Lion</italic>, 5:343.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r053">
            <label>53.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See my “Economies of the Gift” for a detailed discussion of this issue as it relates to Shaw and Ricoeur.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r054">
            <label>54.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw, “Parents and Children,” preface to<italic>Misalliance</italic>, 4:88.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r055">
            <label>55.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Everybody's Political What's What?</italic>(New York: Dodd, Mead, 1944).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
