<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591680</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/428537</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR85124</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Jeffrey L.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Kosky</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Washington and Lee University.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>January 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>146</fpage>
         <lpage>148</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Robbins, </surname>
               <given-names>Jeffrey W.</given-names>
            </string-name>
            <source>Between Faith and Thought: An Essay on the Ontotheological Condition</source>. Studies in Religion and Culture. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2003. xi+193 pp. $39.50 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/428537"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Ever since Martin Heidegger offered an operative concept of the ontotheological constitution of metaphysics, thinkers have been obsessed with overcoming it. Ontotheology has been blamed for any number of ills and its overcoming deemed the way to escape the injustice, violence, blasphemy, or manipulation from which God, self, world, and the Other suffer. According to Jeffrey Robbins, however, the project of overcoming ontotheology is not only misguided but dangerous, for, whatever form it takes, it aims at an imaginary purity.</p>
      <p>Invoking theoretical frameworks proposed by Julia Kristeva, Robbins outlines the urgency of addressing this problem of purity in three interludes that orient the book toward those nonphilosophical experiences of abject otherness that motivate it. In these interludes, Robbins poetically explores the disastrous consequences of the aim at purity in terms of borders and cosmopolitanism (immigration), final solutions and witnessing (the Holocaust), and bibliolatry and criticism (resurgent fundamentalisms).</p>
      <p>The attempt at overcoming ontotheology has pushed in two seemingly opposed directions: toward a theology purified of philosophy (Karl Barth) and toward a philosophy purified of theology (Heidegger). What both Barth and Heidegger have in common, according to Robbins, is a shared dismissal of philosophical theology (which Robbins often uses as a seeming equivalent to ontotheology) in favor of a thought that is pure (either philosophy or theology) but that in its purity renders impossible any dialogue with the other it suppresses.</p>
      <p>Robbins specifies these failures by showing how two great attempts at philosophical theology fell short. On the one hand, Dietrich Bonhoeffer pushed theology toward a philosophical theology that would repair the Barthian disjunction of theology and philosophy and avoid posing the alternative of deciding categorically between either God or world. Bonhoeffer’s attempt falls short, however, when he bases his ethics on a wisdom that sees the world through the truth of Jesus Christ. On the other hand, the path of phenomenology has gone in the opposite direction: from a transcendental idealism (the early Edmund Husserl, for whom philosophy should be pure of ontology or theology) to engagement with history and the world (Heidegger and the later Husserl, whose attention to the life‐world brings philosophy into the world of history and actuality that animates it, even if the promise of this engagement is not often seized).</p>
      <p>After this historical, critical section, Robbins develops a more constructive approach toward a philosophical theology that capitalizes on the ontotheological condition. He claims as his models Paul Ricoeur and, ultimately, Jean‐Luc Marion and Emmanuel Lévinas. Understanding Ricoeur’s hermeneutics “according to the model of religious orthodoxy in which faith and practice translate into knowledge” (p. 123), Robbins praises Ricoeur for offering a model of philosophical theology but criticizes this model because, like all orthodoxy, the philosophy remains uncritical of its foundations—that is, of the religion to which it gives conceptual formulation. Another model of philosophical theology is provided by Marion and Lévinas. In Marion, Robbins asserts, phenomenology and theology each pass into the other in such a way that there is not a confusion or reduction but a mutual criticism and modification of each by the other (p. 113). Marion’s supposed embrace of the ontotheological dialogue between philosophy and theology is foreshadowed, according to Robbins, in Lévinas, who first modeled “an alternative strategy for contemporary philosophical and theological thought … a strategy that is<italic>otherwise than overcoming</italic>” (p. 132).</p>
      <p>While these readings of Marion and Lévinas are admirable descriptions of a worthy project, objections that would strengthen Robbins’s argument can be made. Contrary to Robbins’s aim, the authors that serve as his models of philosophical theology present their work in a form that maintains the division between a theological side (Marion’s<italic>God without Being</italic>, Lévinas’s Talmudic commentaries) and a philosophical side (Marion’s phenomenology and Lévinas’s ethical philosophy). In not fully recognizing this, Robbins does not so much prove himself wrong as he overlooks an important point of his own argument. For, in order to understand how theology and philosophy relate, they must be distinguished. Only if differences remain can there be conversation and mutual, transformative indebtedness.</p>
      <p>The question then becomes: to what extent does the pattern of ontotheology permit such distinctions? For Marion, not at all, since the God of ontotheology is stigmatized as a philosopher’s God to be overcome in the search for a truly theological thought of God. When Robbins claims that Marion provides a model of philosophical theology to the extent that “[he] accepts the bounds established by the ontotheological condition” (p. 101), there is either a massive misreading of Marion or what is meant by ontotheology remains imprecise. Some clarity might be achieved by sticking to Heidegger, who offers the classic conceptualization of ontotheology. For Heidegger, ontotheology is the answer to the question “How does God enter philosophy?” As such, it would not allow conversation between philosophy and theology because the God it thinks, even theologically, is already the God of philosophy. In Robbins’s work, by contrast, ontotheology stands for a “synthesis” (p. 11), a “dialogue” (p. 14), or a “mixed discourse” (p. 15) of philosophy and theology that best resists the corrosive fragmentation and dangerous purification of thought and culture. I cannot help but feel that in the transition from overcoming ontotheology to accepting it, what is being saved or maintained is not what was being overcome.</p>
      <p>While sharing the aim of relating philosophy and theology, I do not think the project is best accomplished by thinking ontotheologically (at least, not in its Heideggerian sense). What is needed is to insist on a sharper distinction between ontotheological philosophy and religious theology so that we can better understand how they might relate. And here again, I agree with Robbins for different reasons: Ricoeur, Lévinas, and Marion are key sources in this project, for their work maintains the distinction that it calls into question.</p>
   </body>
</article>
