<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24708915</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>RECONNOITERING DOOYEWEERD'S THEORY OF MAN</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                  <surname>Blosser</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1993</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>58</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24708906</issue-id>
         <fpage>192</fpage>
         <lpage>209</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24708915"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1634e101a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e108" publication-type="other">
Author's note: a slightly different version of this article was published under the title of
"Soul and Body in the Philosophy of Herman Dooyeweerd" in Tydskrif vir christelike
wetenskap 27, no. 1 (1991), 57-82.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e121a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e128" publication-type="other">
A New Critique of Theoretical Thought, 4 vols, trans. W.S. Young, D.H. Freeman, and H. de
Jongste (Amsterdam: H.J. Paris, and Philadelphia: Presbyterian and Reformed, 1953 - 58;
repr. Jordan Station, Ont.: Paideia Press, 1984), III, 781: hereafter cited as "NC," followed by
volume number and page number.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e144a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e151" publication-type="other">
Cf. John N. Kraay, "Successive Conceptions in the Development of the Christian
Philosophy of Herman Dooyeweerd (II)," Philosophia reformata 45,(1980), p. 16, where, citing
the WdW III, p. 627, Kraay says: "In fact, Die Stellung des Menschen im Kosmos is really the
fundamental theme (het eigenlijke grondthema) of the philosophy of the cosmonomic idea."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e167a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e174" publication-type="other">
Peter J. Steen, The Structure of Dooyeweerd's Thought (Toronto: Wedge, 1983). This book is an
unrevised doctoral dissertation defended in 1970 at Westminster Theological Seminary under
the title, "The Idea of Religious Transcendence in the Philosophy of Herman Dooyeweerd,
with reference to its significance for Reformed Theology"; hereafter referred to as
"Structure."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e194a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e203" publication-type="other">
In the research I did for this paper, I was repeatedly amazed at the number of times I
found myself mentally reversing myself in some criticism of Dooyeweerd when I discovered
that his rationale resulted from a much deeper penetration of an issue that I at first could
possibly suspect. I am therefore very conscious of the possibility that I could be entirely
mistaken on certain points.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e222a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e229" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 281.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e236a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e243" publication-type="other">
For Vollenhoven, see especially "College systematiek - het probleem van de tijd,"
aantekeningen J.C. Vander Stelt (Amsterdam: mimeo, 1963); for K.J. Popma, Levens-
beschouwing, 7 vol. (Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1958-65) and numerous articles and
works on the problems of time and anthropology; for Vincent Briimmer, Transcendental
Criticism and Christian Philosophy (Franeker: T. Wever, 1961); for O.T.L. Albers, Het natuurrecht
volgens de wijsbegeerte der wetsidee (Nijmegen: Gebr. Janssen, 1955); for W.H. Velema, De leer
van de Heilige Geest bij Abraham Kuyper ('s-Gravenhage: Van Keulen, 1957); for H.G. Stoker,
Die wijsbegeerte van de skeppingsidee (Pretoria: De Bussy, 1933), esp. pp. 1-64; for M.Fr.J.
Marlet, Grundlinien der Kalvinistischen "Philosophie der Gesetzesidee" als Christlicher
Transzendentalphilosophie (Miinchen: Karl Zink, 1954), pp. 116-124; for F. Kuijper, "Een nadere
bezinning over de transcendentale critiek in de W.d.W.," Philosophia reformata 27 (1962), 6-27;
for C.A. van Peursen, "Enkele critische vragen in margine bij A New Critique of Theoretical
Thought," Philosophia reformata 24 (1959), 166; for William Young, Toward a Reformed Philosophy
(Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1953); for A.L. Conradie, The Neo-Calvinistic Concept of Philosophy
(Natal: University Press, 1960), pp. 126 - 94; for Ronald H. Nash, Dooyeweerd and the
Amsterdam Philosophy (Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1962), pp. 91-94; for Steen, op.cit.; for
Hendrik Hart, "The Problems of Time: An Essay" in The Idea of a Christian Philosophy
(Toronto: Wedge, 1973), pp. 30-42; for Kent Zigterman, "Dooyeweerd's Theory of Individu-
ality Structures as an Alternative to a Substance Position, Especially that of Aristotle,"
Master's Thesis, ICS 1977 (Toronto: AACS, 1977), ch. IV; for Harry Fernhout, "Man, Faith,
and Religion in Bavinck, Kuyper, and Dooyeweerd," Master's Thesis, ICS 1975 (Toronto:
AACS, 1977); for John Cooper, "Dualism and the biblical view of human beings," Reformed
Journal 32, Issue 9 (Sept., 1982), 13-16, and Issue 10 (Oct., 1982), 16-18; and for Gary North,
The Sinai Strategy (Tyler, TX: Institute for Christian Economics, 1986).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e323a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e330" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 280.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e337a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e344" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, "De taak ener wijsgerige antropologie en de doodlopende wegen tot
wijsgerige zelfkennis," Philosophia reformata 26, No. 1 (1961), 57.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e354a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e361" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, "De leer van de mens in de Wijsbegeerte der Wetsidee," Sola fide 7, No. 2
(1954); English trans., "The Theory of Man: Thirty-two Propositions on Anthropology"
(Toronto: ICS mimeo, n.d.), Proposition No. VIII; henceforth cited as "TM," followed by the
Roman numeral indicating the proposition.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e378a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e385" publication-type="other">
NC, III, 89 (emphasis added); quoted by John Murray, Collected Writings of John Murray,
Vol. II: Select Lectures in Systematic Theology (Edinburgh: Banner of Truth, 1977), p. 22, η. 1.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e395a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e402" publication-type="other">
NC, III, 89 (emphasis added).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e409a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e416" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 127; pp. 126-130.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e423a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e430" publication-type="other">
Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e437a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e444" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, In the Twilight of Western Thought, University Series, edited with
Introduction by R.J. Rushdoony (Nutley, NJ: Craig Press, 1960), p. 181f. Whether the human I
is "nothing in itself," as Dooyeweerd suggests here, is a question we shall address later in this
paper.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e460a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e467" publication-type="other">
Indeed, Dooyeweerd in some contexts seems to suggest this, which would conflict
fundamentally with the implications of his belief in the resurrection of the body. Reporting
on a conversation with Dooyeweerd in Amsterdam in June, 1964, Steen says that he asked
Dooyeweerd "whether he thought that the fact that Paul speaks of faith abiding in I Cor. 13
after the judgment day, had any bearing on whether the function of faith would abide after
judgment. Dooyeweerd gave an interesting reply. First he said, 'faith turns into sight and
therefore faith passes away.' When I mentioned the fact that Paul emphasizes that faith
abides, he stressed the fact that we really know nothing about the future after the judgment.
When I then asked how it would be possible to conceive of a resurrected man without all the
functions and the law spheres holding, he seemed to reconsider his previous statement and
agree that I was laying my finger on an important point." (Steen, Structure, p. 85)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e506a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e513" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, pp. 266-269, esp. p. 268f.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e520a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e527" publication-type="other">
Steen indicates that the term "above time" (boventijdelijk) was abandoned by Dooyeweerd
in his later years under intense criticism, in favor of the expression "religious transcendence."
Yet, according to Steen, this substitution by no means represented a change in Dooyeweerd's
own understanding of the whole structure to which the former term applied, but rather a
concession to what he regarded as a misunderstanding that had arisen concerning the whole
complex of ideas involved. (Structure, p. 6, n. 6).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e550a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e557" publication-type="other">
Popma's views are expressed throughout his writings; see especially Levensbeschouwing, 7
vols, (see above, n. 6), cited by Steen, Structure, p. 302, n. 37. Geertsema's views were
expressed in his paper by the title of "Homo respondens," see above.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e570a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e577" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, pp. 305-307.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e584a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e591" publication-type="other">
Steen reports that Zuidema described transcendence in this fashion to him in a personal
conversation in Amsterdam (Structure, p. 308, n. 44).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e601a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e608" publication-type="other">
I am assuming here the correlativity of what Steen calls "Word-revelation" and
"creational revelation" (Structure, p. 304), or what has been traditionally called "special
revelation" and "general revelation." One of the best accounts of this correlation I know of is
found in G.C. Berkouwer, General Revelation, Studies in Dogmatics, trans, ed. (Grand Rapids:
Eerdmans, 1955).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e628a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e635" publication-type="other">
TM, XXIX, XXXII. Steen says "it appears that Dooyeweerd is saying that the human race
as a totality represented in Adam and Eve (stamvader en stammoeder) was created by God in
the beginning. All that will unfold and be subject to the temporal process of becoming is
present here as finished creation. There would seem to be a root community of hearts
represented in the heart of the first representative root, Adam." (Structure, p. 65)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e654a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e661" publication-type="other">
Steen observes: "Dooyeweerd intimates that reality as it exists through temporal be-
coming and supra-temporal generation had a pre-existence in the Spirit of God; it exists as
created, as finished creation. It is this finished existing creation that now becomes in the great
becoming process." (Structure, p. 66f., cf. p. 52f.) One might wish to ask, then: What is the
supra-temporal existence of the soul? (On the concept of aevum, or created eternity, in
Dooyeweerd, see his "Het tijdsprobleem en zijn antinomieën op het immanentie-standpunt,"
Philosophia reformata 4 (1939), 4-5; cited by Steen, Structure, p. 132, n. 9).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e687a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e694" publication-type="other">
The fact that the generation of both soul (supra-temporally) and body (temporally) derive
from the pre-existence of the already created whole man, understood as entirely contained in
the heart or soul as the radical religious root of personality, underscores the claims of those
who, following Vollenhoven's problem-historical method, find some sort of "priority theme"
or "monarchian" element in Dooyeweerd's thinking, along with some variety of "instru-
mentalism" and "impetus theory" (see, e.g., Vollenhoven's "De consequent probleem-
historische méthode," Philosophia reformata 26 (1961), 19-22, cited in Steen, Structure, p. 43, n.
5; cf. Steen, Ibid., pp. 57-74,102-104, and Fernhout, op.cit. (see above n. 7), pp. 7, 72-109).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e723a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e730" publication-type="other">
On Boethius, see K.J. Popma, "De eeuwigheid Gods volgens Boëthius," Philosophia
reformata 22 (1957), 21-51, and Nadenken over de tijd (Amsterdam: Buijten en Schipperheijn,
1965), cited in Steen, Structure, p. 109, n. 101; on the pre-Socratics, see P.A. Meyer, Socratisch
schimmenspel. Socrates' plaats in de griekse wijsbegeerte, Christelijk perspectief, 22 (Amster-
dam: Buijten en Schipperheijn, 1974), cited by Peter J. Steen, "The Problem of Time and
Eternity in its Relation to the Nature-Grace Ground-motive" in Hearing and Doing.
Philosophical Essays Dedicated to H. Evan Runner, ed. John Kraay and Anthony Toi (Toronto:
Wedge, 1979), p. 143, n. 4; on Oscar Cullmann, see Steen, Structure, p. 110, and "Time and
Eternity" (in Hearing and Doing), p. 136, and O. Cullmann, Christus und die Zeit (Zurich: A.G.
Sollikon, 1948).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e765a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e772" publication-type="other">
In the Twilight of Western Thought, p. 181.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e779a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e786" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, "Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte," Scientia 1 (1956), 144; quoted in G.C.
Berkouwer, Man: The Image of God, Studies in Dogmatics, trans. Dirk W. Jellema (Grand
Rapids: Eerdmans, 1962), p. 258; henceforth cited as "Man." See Dooyeweerd's comparable
statement in NC, I, 21, where he uses "philosophical" instead of "theoretical" thought; and cf.
TM, VI, on the presuppositional nature of the soul in human theorizing.
The parallels with Scheler's view of the "person" are remarkable here. Much as in
Dooyeweerd's view the "soul" or "heart" can never be objectified, so for Scheler the "person"
can never become an object of analysis; much as in Dooyeweerd's view "acts" come forth out
of the soul but only function within the temporal structure of the human body, so for Scheler
the person acts into time without himself being in time. For Scheler's distinction between
"acts" and "functions," and significant differences in his view of the act-structure, see Max
Scheler, Der Formalismus in der Ethik und die Materiale Wertethik, Gesammelte Werke, Vol;. II, ed.
Maria Scheler (Bern: Francke Verlag, 1954), pp. 395ff.; translated as Formalism in Ethics and
No7t-Formal Ethics of Values (Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1973), pp. 385ff. For
the comparable views of Dooyeweerd, see TM XIV and XX, for example. It is possible that
both Dooyeweerd's and Scheler's view of the non-objectifiability of the essential selfhood of
the person is the result of a residual Kantianism.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e844a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e851" publication-type="other">
Cf. Tory Hoff, "Nephesh and the Fulfillment it Receives as Psuche" in A.H. De Graaff and
J.H. Olthuis, eds. Toward a Biblical View of Man (Toronto: AACS, 1978), pp. 71-131, esp. p.
106f.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e864a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e871" publication-type="other">
Cf. above, n. 18, for Popma's view of man as a listening, Word-receiving being. Popma
contrasts this emphasis with that of man as a seeing being in the theo-ontological tradition,
and with man as a questioning being in Heideggerian philosophy (cf. Steen, Structure, p. 302,
n. 37.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e887a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e894" publication-type="other">
Steen, despite noting Dooyeweerd's development of "a unique aversion towards citing
proof-texts in his works" as a result of his early confrontations with Reformed theologians,
and despite noting Dooyeweerd's consequent failure to appreciate the rich discovery of
Scripture in recent developments within the exegetical branches of theology, and despite
noting that this may be (ironically) part of the reason for a residuum of nature-grace
influence in his philosophy, nevertheless speaks of "the rich biblical emphasis... always
present in Dooyeweerd." (Structure, pp. 20, 272; cf. p. 127, n. 2)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e920a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e927" publication-type="other">
Cf. Martin Heidegger, Being and Time, trans, J. Macquarrie and E. Robinson (New York:
Harper and Row, 1962), p. 194f., where Heidegger rejects the view that this hermeneutical
circle is a circulus vitiosus.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e940a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e947" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 139; Steen's incisive objections against a scholastic reading of Rev. 10: 6
are particularly noteworthy (p. 138).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e957a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e964" publication-type="other">
A few examples of "acts" performed by incorporeal creatures are: Satan speaking with
God (Job 1: 6-12); his act of rebellion against God (Is. 14: 12-15); the rich man in Hades
speaking with Abraham (Lk. 16: 23-24); Moses, who was buried by the Lord (Deut. 34: 6),
speaking with Elijah and Christ on the Mount of Transfiguration (Mt, 17: 3); and creatures in
the heavenly throne room praising God (Rev. 4: 8).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e984a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e991" publication-type="other">
Although Dooyeweerd says that "all human acts have their origin in the soul," and
therefore beyond time, he holds that they function only within the temporal structure of the
human body (TM, XX; cf XIV). For this reason he opposes the phenomenology of Husserl and
Scheler, which regards acts as "incorporeal (onlichamelijk), (pure 'psychonomic') intentional
experiences" (TM, XV).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1010a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1017" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricoeur, "The Hermeneutics of Testimony," Anglican Theological Review 61, No. 4
(1979); rpt. in Essays on Biblical Interpretation, ed. Lewis S. Mudge (Philadelphia: Fortress,
1980), pp. 119-154.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1030a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1037" publication-type="other">
See above, n. 24.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1044a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1051" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 257. The fact that Dooyeweerd overtly rejects this theme, as Steen
notes, does not of itself cease to make it a problem.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1061a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1068" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, pp. 193-206; esp. p. 202. On Diemer, see an abridged translation of his
work under the title of Nature and Miracle by Wilma Bouma (Toronto: Wedge, 1977), which is
Part I of his Natuur en wonder. On Kuyper, see p. 206 of Structure, where Steen says the
"speculative lust for a totality view or a unity view was embodied among supra-lapsarian
scholastic Reformed theologians of which Kuyper reigned supreme."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1087a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1094" publication-type="other">
On the "participation idea" see Steen, Structure, p. 209; on the collapse of structure into
direction see Ibid., p. 83, where Steen writes: "It might be said that structure tends to be
reduced to direction... Structure is transcendentally-directed meaning. Meaninglessness,
nothing, and meaning loss tend to occur when this direction is lost. The structure is almost its
pointing character." Steen finds in this state of affairs what he calls the "semi-contradictory
theme" in Dooyeweerd's thought.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1118a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1125" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 83f.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1132a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1139" publication-type="other">
On Dooyeweerd and Kant, see, e.g., V. Briimmer, op.cit. (see above, n. 6), pp. 13-39, and
Jong Doo Kim, "Wissen und Glauben bei I. Kant und H. Dooyeweerd: Der Kantische
Dualismus und Dooyeweerds Versuch zu seiner Ûberwindung," Philosophia reformata 48, no.
2 (1983) special issue devoted to Kim's work).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1155a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1162" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 263.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1169a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1176" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 257; Berkouwer is quoting Dooyeweerd, "Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte," Scientia
1(1956), 144.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1186a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1193" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 258; as will be seen, this appears to flatly contradict Dooyeweerd's own words
below.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1203a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1210" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 257, n. 33; Berkouwer refers here to the article by Dooyeweerd, "Het tijds-
probleem in de Wijsbegeerte der Wetsidee," Philosophia reformata 5 (1940), 181.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1221a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1228" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, "Beroepsmisdaad en strafvergelding in 't licht der wetsidee,"
Anti-revolutionaire staatkunde 2 (1928), 430; cited by Steen, Structure, p. 160, cf. p. 159.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1238a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1245" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, "Ter nagedachtenis van mijn vriend Prof. dr. Ph. Kohnstamm,"
Mededelingen van de Vereniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte (Sept., 1952), p. 11; cited in
Steen, "Time and Eternity," p. 144, n. 16, and in Structure, p. 115, n. 129, and p. 130.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1258a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1265" publication-type="other">
See Berkouwer's discussion of relevant biblical passages in Man, pp. 264ff., and cf.
Heidelberg Catechism (Lord's Day 22).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1275a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1282" publication-type="other">
Scheler's position is precariously subtle: the "person" is neither exhausted in his "acts"
nor something subsisting through their temporal succession, but, rather, a supra-temporal
being who acts into time and who "is and experiences himself only as a being that executes
acts"; the "whole person is contained in every fully concrete act, and the whole person 'varies' in
and through every act - without being exhausted in his being in any of these acts, and
without 'changing' like a thing in time" (Formalismus, p. 395f. [English translation, p. 385]; see
above, n. 27, for full references).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1308a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1315" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 259; emphasis added.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1322a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1329" publication-type="other">
Zigterman, op.cit. (see above, n. 6), ch. 4, esp. 119-36.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1337a1310">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1344" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 258; emphasis added (cf. above, n. 44).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1351a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1358" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 263; Steen, Structure, p. 150; in another connection, Berkouwer
significantly points our that "merely positing... a duality-in-unity does not mean that we
actually have a real unity" (Ibid., p. 212).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1371a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1378" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 150.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1385a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1392" publication-type="other">
See in this volume, Stephen Evans' paper.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1399a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1406" publication-type="other">
For full references to the relevant works of H.G. Stoker and K. Zigterman, see above, n. 6.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1413a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1420" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 262, n. 44; Dooyeweerd, NC, III, 67.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1428a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1435" publication-type="other">
Zigterman, op.cit., (see above, n. 6), p. 125f. The special irony here is that Dooyeweerd's
concept of heart contains features of the kind that Dooyeweerd himself rejects as belonging
only to a metaphysics of substance when they are applied to created things, which have no
supra-temporal unity.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1451a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1458" publication-type="other">
In this connection, Berkouwer's comment is significant that "anti-dualism as such is not a
§;uarantee of a true insight into human nature" {Man, p. 222).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1468a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1475" publication-type="other">
In this context, Dooyeweerd's reading of Stoker seems misleading. When Stoker suggests
that his concept of substance gives a better expression to "the autonomous being and value of
the cosmos with respect to God" {die eien zijn en die eienwaarde van die kosmos teenover God),
Dooyeweerd fears that the radical biblical view of the dependence of all creation upon God is
somehow being threatened (NC, III, 71). But this overlooks precisely the point Stoker is
affirming: namely, the real difference instituted between the Creator and His creation by the
very act of creating. Accordingly, creation is not self-sufficient; but it is not nothing; it is
something. (Cf. Zigterman, op.cit., pp. 129,132,136.)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1504a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1511" publication-type="other">
John Cooper, op.cit. (see above, n. 6), Issue 9 (Sept., 1982), p. 13.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1518a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1525" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 122f., n. 144; p. 221.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1532a1310">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1539" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, Man, p. 230.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1634e1547a1310">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1634e1554" publication-type="other">
Steen, Structure, p. 272; cf. above, n. 30.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
