<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmodernhistory</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Modern History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222801</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375358</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3555642</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/427573</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JMH76040601</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>James Smith</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Allen</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Southern Illinois University, Carbondale</aff>
            <x xml:space="preserve"/>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>December 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>76</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>jmh.2004.76.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>934</fpage>
         <lpage>936</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>A History of Reading in the West</source>. Edited by<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Guglielmo </given-names>
               <surname>Cavallo</surname>
            </string-name>and<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Roger </given-names>
               <surname>Chartier</surname>
            </string-name>. Translated by<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Lydia G. </given-names>
               <surname>Cochrane</surname>
            </string-name>. Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press,<year>1999</year>. Pp. 488. $40.00 (cloth); $24.95 (paper).</product>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Correspondence: Models of Letter‐Writing from the Middle Ages to the Nineteenth Century</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Roger </given-names>
               <surname>Chartier</surname>
            </string-name>,<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Alain </given-names>
               <surname>Boureau</surname>
            </string-name>, and<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Cécile </given-names>
               <surname>Dauphin</surname>
            </string-name>. Translated by<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Christopher </given-names>
               <surname>Woodall</surname>
            </string-name>. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press,<year>1997</year>. Pp. vi+162. $47.50.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/427573"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Why the history of reading? What historical difference does this casual activity make? By now, historians have become accustomed to scholarly accounts of seemingly incidental matters, such as pet ownership and melodrama, which at first blush may seem rather removed from dynamics of historical change like war, revolution, and industrialization. But in the hands of historians like Roger Chartier and Robert Darnton, the history of reading has become a significant field in the social history of ideas. It has far‐reaching implications, especially in the early modern period, for the development of individual and group consciousness, of new religious beliefs and related institutions, and of the state and its bases in society, culture, and the economy. The Enlightenment, for instance, looks very different from the perspective of the consumers of printed matter. In the eighteenth century, readers took very selectively to heart the ideas of the philosophes for a host of reasons we now know: with a few exceptions—for instance, Jean‐Jacques Rousseau’s<italic>La nouvelle Héloïse</italic>(1761) and J. W. von Goethe’s<italic>The Sorrows of Young Werther</italic>(1774)—the major publications of the century’s great intellectuals were much less well circulated than those by the period’s hack writers. And readers received these texts with other things in mind than the philosophes’ challenge to think rationally, deductively, and independently of established authority. Moreover, Jürgen Habermas’s notion of the public sphere (in<italic>The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere,</italic>trans. Thomas Burger and Frederick Lawrence [Cambridge, Mass., 1989]) makes sense only if there are engaged readers as well as engaged writers to create a bourgeois civil society on the eve of the French Revolution of 1789.</p>
      <p>The two volumes under review here expand on these valuable historical insights. The first collection of essays, edited by Roger Chartier and his Italian counterpart, Guglielmo Cavallo, is very nearly a comprehensive overview of the issues, the sources, and the literature in the field from ancient Greece to the twentieth‐century Internet. Eleven prominent scholars join Chartier and Cavallo in an assessment of developments in their various specialties. Despite considerable differences in approach—linguistic, etymological, ethnographic, material, theological, social, and economic, among others—the essays share some themes, which the editors summarize well in their introduction. Historically speaking, a text written is not a text read; it does not speak for itself; readers must first give it meaning, which is often far removed from what the author had intended. As Paul Ricoeur put it in his<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>(trans. Kathleen McLaughlin and David Pellauer, 3 vols. [Chicago, 1984–88]), the world of the text and the world of the reader are not one and the same, and their relationship does not remain the same over time. Historians of the book, like Henri‐Jean Martin, have attended well to the changing modalities of the material text; historians of literacy, like François Furet and Jacques Ozouf, have also considered the limitations of textual reception; but only recently have historians pondered how historical changes in printed matter affected the way it was received, as Donald F. McKenzie recommends in his bibliographic sociology of texts. Similarly, historians have finally learned to take seriously the historical implications of Stanley Fish’s interpretive communities, whose predispositions to texts have a life of their own independent of the texts themselves in ways that can be traced over time. In this, we are at a considerable distance from the philological obsessions of nineteenth‐century literary scholarship.</p>
      <p>This collection is thus an ambitious survey of “the various ways of reading that have been characteristic of Western societies since classical antiquity” (p. 2). Using sources as varied as funeral inscriptions, classical drama, volumina and codexes, manuscript illuminations and marginal glosses, ecclesiastical directives, library layouts and furnishings, autobiographical accounts, police records, and personal interviews, as well as the material culture of written and printed objects, these historians have elucidated collectively at least five “revolutions” in Western culture’s two‐thousand‐year shift from traditional orality to mass literacy: the transition from oral to written culture in antiquity and early medieval Europe; the transition from oral to silent—or, at least, murmured—reading in the High Middle Ages; the transition from written to print culture in the late medieval, Renaissance, and Reformation periods, thanks to the printing press and the proliferation of texts; the transition from intensive to extensive reading habits during the Enlightenment and the ensuing “golden age” of a mass rage to read; and, finally, the transition from printed paper to electronic screens in the late twentieth century, which seems to mark a pervasive loss of canonical literate life. Each of the essays in this collection examines one or more of these revolutionary changes in the history of reading, either by period or by interpretive community, usually defined by a particular religious observance or by a specific social group.</p>
      <p>The second, more focused collection of essays, written by Chartier, Alain Boureau, and Cécile Dauphin, demonstrates well the complexity of the field as it is generally practiced in France. A small portion of a much larger collection of work, which appeared originally in French in 1991, this book mines the historical possibilities of one source in particular: letter‐writing manuals. These introductions to literate culture are examined in depth, from the first instances in the late eleventh century (studied by Boureau), through their appropriation by the publishers of the<italic>bibliothèque bleue</italic>in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries (examined by Chartier), to the modern how‐to guides for the socially inexperienced and insecure lower middle classes in the nineteenth century (surveyed by Dauphin). The implications extend far beyond the history of reading, but they center on the obvious disjunction between, on the one hand, the intention and content of the texts, often of ecclesiastical, courtly, and aristocratic origin, and, on the other, the multiple interests and uses of their consumers, the recently literate, urban, middle classes seeking some sense of the cultural norms among the social elite. Revealed throughout the essays is more than the tension between text and reading; it is also the tension between “strategies of domination, whether physical or symbolic, and the inventiveness of appropriation that governs the practices of everyday life” (p. 3).</p>
      <p>Scholars and their students interested in the field would do well to begin with these studies, despite some unevenness in period, place, and theme. Developments in the twentieth century, for example, are not well served, especially as their globalization bursts all traditional boundaries in the discipline, making a historical perspective essential to an understanding of ongoing transformations in literate life everywhere, not just in the West. Similarly, the absence of illustrations undermines the potential value of these books as introductions to the history of reading. Much of the work here depends on the material objects that readers actually had; without images of them, the reader develops less of a sense of the field. Finally, the exclusion of the essays on correspondence from the original collection is deeply regrettable; Chartier’s summary of their implications in the introduction hardly does justice to them, especially to the important study of the 1847 postal survey by Dauphin and two other colleagues. The translations are generally accurate, but the indexes are barely adequate.</p>
   </body>
</article>
