<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">polisocirevi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50003148</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Polish Sociological Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>THE POLISH SOCIOLOGICAL ASSOCIATION</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">12311413</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24371587</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Biography and the 20<sup>th</sup>Century Tony Judt's Project of a Political Death</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>BARTŁOMIEJ</given-names>
                  <surname>BŁESZNOWSKI</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>186</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24371582</issue-id>
         <fpage>195</fpage>
         <lpage>212</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © The Polish Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24371587"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The aim of this article is to analyse the political and mnemonic programme to be found in the last books of the British historian and thinker Tony Judt. The author of this article assumes that the final period of Judt's writing, in which he produced Ill Fares the Land, The Memory Chalet, and the posthumously published discussion with Timothy Snyder entitled Thinking the Twentieth Century, is dependent on a kind of 'art of memory'. For Judt, being terminally ill with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and thus condemned to immobility, this method became not so much—as in the case of its classic varieties—a technology of remembering, as a manner of recognizing and analyzing the contemporary world by turning to his own biography. The purpose was to construct a 'political testament' for the Western world in a time of crisis whose roots, according to Judt, can be found in the supremacy that 'economic' thinking has achieved over traditional political thought. In a gesture reminiscent of the Stoic 'techniques of the self' described by Michel Foucault, Judt, by exploiting his own no less complicated biography and identity, tries to throw light on the complicated history of the 20th century, containing the sources of 'our contemporary ills'. Biography and history thus meet here in a 'work of memory' whose horizon and catalyzer is the perspective of death, and whose stake is the idea of a political community experiencing, according to Judt, a period of inertia.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d690e117a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d690e124" publication-type="other">
Heidegger 1962: 263</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d690e131a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d690e138" publication-type="other">
The Use of Pleasure (1984)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d690e144" publication-type="other">
The Care of the Self (1984)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Bibliography</title>
         <ref id="d690e160a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e164" publication-type="other">
Benjamin, Walter. 2011. On the Concept of History, in: Idem, Selected Writings, vol. 4:1938-1940, transi.
E. Jephcott and Others. Cambridge, Massachusetts, and London, England: Harvard University
Press, pp. 389-400.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e177a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e181" publication-type="other">
D e 1 e u z e, Gilles, Guattari, Félix. 2007. A Thousand Plateaus, transi. B. Massumi. London, New York:
Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e191a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e195" publication-type="other">
Foucault, Michel. 1990. The Use of Pleasure, vol. II of The History of Sexuality, transi. R. Hurley. New
York: Vintage Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e209" publication-type="other">
Foucault, Michel. 2001. Foucault, in: Idem, Dits et écrits. 1954-1988, vol. II. Paris: Gallimard, pp. 1450-
1455.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e220a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e224" publication-type="other">
Foucault, Michel. 2005. The Hermeneutics of the Subject: Lectures at the Collège de France 1981-1982,
transi. G. Burchell. New York: Picador.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e234a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e238" publication-type="other">
Foucault, Michel. 2006. Preface to the 1961 Edition of History of Madness, transi. J. Murphy, J. Khalfa.
London, New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e248a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e252" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, Martin. 1962. Being and Time, transi. J. Macquarrie, E. Robinson. New York, Hagerstown,
San Francisco, London: Harper &amp; Row Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e262a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e266" publication-type="other">
H u 11 o n, Will. 2010. Them and Us: Changing Britain—Why We Need a Fair Society. London; Little, Brown.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e273a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e277" publication-type="other">
J u d t, Tony. 2005. Postwar: A History of Europe Since 1945. London: William Heinemann.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e284a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e288" publication-type="other">
J u d t, Tony. 2008. Reappraisals: Reflections on the Forgotten Twentieth Century. New York: The Penguin
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e299a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e303" publication-type="other">
J u d t, Tony. 2010. Ill Fares the Land. London. New York: The Penguin Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e310a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e314" publication-type="other">
J u d t, Tony. 2010a. The Memory Chalet. New York: The Penguin Press (Kindle Edition).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e321a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e325" publication-type="other">
J u d t, Tony with Snyder, Timothy. 2012. Thinking the Twentieth Century. London: William Heinemann.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e332a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e336" publication-type="other">
Kotakowski, Leszek. 2002. Kaplan i blazen (Rozwazania o teologicznym dziedzictwie wspôlczesnego
myslenia) [The Chaplain and the Fool: Reflections on the Theological Heritage of Contemporary
Thought], in: Idem, Pochwata niekonsekwencji. Pisma rozproszone sprzed roku 1968 [In Praise
of Inconsistency: Scattered Writings from 1955-1968], vol. II, selected and edited, Z. Mentzel,
London: Puis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e355a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e359" publication-type="other">
Neumann, Birgit. 2009. Literatura, pamiçc, tozsamosc [Literature, Memory, Identity], transi. A. Pelka,
in: M. Saryusz-Wolska (ed.), Pamiçc zbiorowa i kulturowa. Wspôtczesna perspektywa niemiecka
[Collective and Cultural Memory: the Contemporary German Perspective], Krakow: Universitas,
pp. 249-284.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e375a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e379" publication-type="other">
Norman, Jesse. 2010. The Big Society. The Anatomy of the New Politics. Buckingham: The University of
Buckingham Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e390a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e394" publication-type="other">
Rancière, Jacques. 2010. Dissensus: On Politics andAsthetics, transi. G. Rockhill. London, New York:
Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e404a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e408" publication-type="other">
R i c o e u r, Paul. 2006. Memory, History, Forgetting, transi. K. Blaney, D. Pellauer. Chicago: University of
Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e418a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e422" publication-type="other">
Shore, Marci. 2012. Introduction, in: Tony Judt, Historia niedokonczona. Francuscy intelektualisci
1944-1956 [Past Imperfect: French Intellectuals 1944-1956], transi. P. Marczewski. Warszawa:
Wydawnictwo Krytyki Politycznej.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e435a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e439" publication-type="other">
Welzer, Harald. 2009. Material, z ktörego zbudowane sq biografie, transi. M. Saryusz-Wolska, in:
M. Saryusz-Wolska (ed.), Pamiçc zbiorowa i kulturowa. Wspôtczesna perspektywa niemiecka [Collec-
tive and Cultural Memory: the Contemporary German Perspective], Krakow: Universitas, pp. 39-
57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d690e455a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d690e459" publication-type="other">
Yates, Frances. 1999. The Art of Memory. London and New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
