<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.26.2.0333</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0333</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Ethics and Religion in Continental Philosophy</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">26</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.26.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>333</fpage>
         <lpage>360</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0333"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s01">
         <sec-meta>
            <contrib-group>
               <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <string-name>
                     <italic>Merold Westphal</italic>
                  </string-name>
                  <aff>Fordham University</aff>
               </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
         </sec-meta>
         <title>The Second Great Revolution in Phenomenology</title>
         <p>In the early seventies I heard Bob Fogelin give a lecture to incoming first-year students. It was part of a series on current, cutting-edge developments in various disciplines. He pointed out that for some time philosophers had spent little time and effort trying to determine what was right and what was wrong, what was just and unjust, and so on. Instead they asked whether, when we make moral judgments, we are expressing emotions, evoking emotions, prescribing behavior, asserting some natural facts, asserting some nonnatural facts, and so forth. In short, normative ethics had been largely supplanted by meta-ethics. But that seemed to be changing. A guy named Rawls had written a book in which he tried to articulate principles in terms of which we could distinguish just from unjust social practices and institutions. Fogelin prophesied that Rawls had opened Pandora's box and that philosophers were likely to return to the challenging tasks of normative ethics.</p>
         <p>Without drawing an exact parallel, I want to suggest that ethics and religion have moved from a rather peripheral role<italic>then</italic>to a more central role<italic>now</italic>in Continental philosophy.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>The center of attention<italic>then</italic>was on the<italic>magna opera</italic>of Husserl, Heidegger, Sartre, and Merleau-Ponty, and these had little to say about either ethics or religion. One had to look elsewhere, and each of the following elsewheres remained peripheral.</p>
         <p>There were, of course, Kierkegaard and Nietzsche, who between them had a lot to say about ethics and religion. But one mark of the transition from<italic>then</italic>to<italic>now</italic>is the increasing importance given to them in contexts like the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy.</p>
         <p>There were also the second- and third-tier existentialists: Marcel, Jaspers, Buber, Shestov, Berdyaev, Unamuno, and so forth. There was Ricoeur's work in hermeneutical phenomenology of religion (<italic>The Symbolism of Evil</italic>, 1960) and in the hermeneutics of suspicion (<italic>Freud and Philosophy</italic>, 1970).<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>It is this hermeneutical turn to which I refer as the first revolution in phenomenology. The attempts of Sartre and Merleau-Ponty to find a political alternative to Soviet communism and American capitalism also were of significance for ethics.</p>
         <p>Finally, there was Sartre, who along with Marx, Nietzsche, and Freud was one of the great secular theologians of original sin. His analyses of how we are the desire to be God and of concrete relations with others in the light of the Look are important for both ethics and the philosophy of religion. With reference to the latter, Sartre writes, “These considerations do not exclude the possibility of an ethics of deliverance and salvation. But this can be achieved only after a radical conversion which we can not discuss here.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>Sartre points us toward radical evil only to drop the subject like a hot potato. But he had signaled, without knowing it, the second revolution.</p>
         <p>It would be foolish to deny that there are rich resources, especially for philosophy of religion, in these elsewheres. But they remained peripheral insofar as the main task was to clarify the Cartesian and anti-Cartesian dimensions of the phenomenological project and to find its existential import in time, death, and the body rather than, say, in God, the right, and the good. As already indicated, only Sartre's analysis of the other brought the conversation directly in touch with ethics and religion.</p>
         <sec id="s01_1">
            <title>Now</title>
            <p>The movement from<italic>then</italic>to<italic>now</italic>, so far as ethics and philosophy of religion are concerned, can be largely told in relation to five proper names: Ricoeur, Levinas, Kierkegaard, Derrida, and Marion. Paul Ricoeur was already part of<italic>then</italic>, but as he kept writing, so broadly and so deeply, he became more and more an inescapable part of the<italic>now</italic>. The problem is that he did this in so many different ways that he could easily take up all my time and space and then some. Not just in such collections as<italic>Thinking Biblically</italic>and<italic>Figuring the Sacred</italic>but whenever he wrote about virtually anything, be it time and narrative, memory, metaphor, interpretation, translation, ideology, evil, justice, the self (as other), recognition, or whatever, he provoked our thought about either ethics or religion or both. So, with gratitude and apologies, I'll leave him as the one who has shaped our<italic>now</italic>, so far as ethics and religion are concerned, in more different but deep ways than anyone else. He is in any case more important for the first revolution than for the second.</p>
            <p>More manageable, but not less important, is the role of Emmanuel Levinas. We can compare his contribution to normative ethics to that of Kant. Like Kant, he offers an account of the moral life in terms of unconditional (categorical), infinite (never finished, imperfect) obligation. His is a deontological theory. Like Kant, he seeks to articulate the first principle of moral obligation and offers three formulations of it (paralleling a familiar reading of Kant). You shall not commit murder.<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>4</sup>
               </xref>You shall not let me die alone.<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>5</sup>
               </xref>You shall not usurp my place in the sun.<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>6</sup>
               </xref>That the second and third formulas specify imperfect duties should be abundantly clear.</p>
            <p>But Levinas is no Kant redivivus. Unlike Kant, he does not try to derive specific, concrete duties from these principles. They provide no aid and comfort to casuistry (in the nonpejorative sense). Especially in his analyses of the third party, he emphasizes that the move to concrete specificity involves comparison and calculation.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>7</sup>
               </xref>This takes us to the realm of risky judgment, away from the immediacy, clarity, and certainty of first principles. Already in the experience of the face to face, “the free adherence to truth, an activity of knowledge … seeks a reason which does not coincide with the radiance of this clear and distinct idea itself” (TI 303). How much further from the ideals of Platonic, Cartesian, and even Kantian intuition is the comparative, calculative wisdom of politics (for with the third-party ethics becomes politics with all its ambiguity)?</p>
            <p>Again, unlike Kant, Levinas does not seek to derive his principles themselves from reason as the monological exercise of some faculty of the human mind. In terms of the classical distinction between reason and experience, they arise out of experience, two experiences in particular. First, in<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>and related works, there is the experience of the face of the other. Then, in<italic>Otherwise than Being</italic>and related works, there is the distinction between the saying and the said, pointing to the experience of being addressed by the other (the saying) independent of the content of the other's speech (the said). The mere presence of the face and voice of the other calls me from the enjoyments of egoism to responsibility. The other's face and voice have an almost Nicene quality.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>8</sup>
               </xref>They are thoroughly empirical and relative, and yet they are the bearers of something transworldly and absolute, namely, an unconditional call to moral responsibility. These two are not really all that different. For the face “is a living presence; it is expression. The life of expression consists in undoing the form in which the existent, exposed as a theme, is thereby dissimulated.<italic>The face speaks</italic>” (TI 66; emphasis added). Already in<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>Levinasian ethics has taken the linguistic turn, not as the analysis of propositions but as the attentiveness to speech acts.</p>
            <p>Once again, unlike Kant, he does not try to keep the specifically religious roots of his ethical passion, in this case Jewish, from appearing. Thus the other, whose face and voice disturb my complacency and call me to a frightening responsibility, is never so abstract as merely a rational being or someone who is always an end and not merely a means; the other is above all the widow, the orphan, and the stranger. This transparent appeal to the Hebrew scriptures, whose God regularly sides with the little people at the bottom and expects the people of God to do as well, is what enables Levinas to speak of “the overcoming of Western ontology as ‘an ethical and a prophetic cry.’”<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>9</sup>
               </xref>He refers to a passage in “God and Philosophy” in which he speaks of the modern presumption that philosophy is an ideology, a presumption that comes from outside philosophy: “It begins in a cry of ethical revolt, bearing witness to responsibility; it begins in prophecy.”<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>10</sup>
               </xref>Here we have the hermeneutical acknowledgment that philosophical reflection is not neutral and without presuppositions but always located in and shaped by traditions that have already shaped us before we have chosen them.</p>
            <p>Underlying and perhaps uniting these three ways in which Levinas's “Kantian” ethics is anti-Kantian is the way in which his phenomenology is anti-Husserlian. He insists that he is doing phenomenology in the fundamental sense of intentional analysis.<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>11</sup>
               </xref>But he has to admit, “In spite of everything what I do is phenomenology.” Why “in spite of everything”? Partly, no doubt, because it is not a transcendental phenomenology and does not rely on the phenomenological reduction.<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>12</sup>
               </xref>But the more basic reason is that precisely in the ethical relation where we are called forth to responsibility and called upon to answer at our trial, he is concerned with “an intentionality of a wholly different type” (TI 23) from the objectifying, theoretical vision that is basic to Husserl.<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>13</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>We have already encountered this “wholly different” intentionality in reference to Sartre's analysis of the Look. It is the inverted intentionality in which the tasks of constitution and<italic>Sinngebung</italic>are carried out by the gaze and the voice of the other.<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>14</sup>
               </xref>The premoral egoism that Levinas calls the same “turns to the absolutely other only on call from the Other.<italic>Revelation</italic>constitutes a veritable inversion [of]<italic>objectifying cognition</italic>” (TI 67).<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>15</sup>
               </xref>The arrows of intentionality do not emanate from me but come to me from the other. I, my identity, and my responsibility are not legislated by myself but come to me from beyond me. This is why<italic>passivity</italic>and<italic>transcendence</italic>are such keywords for Levinas. If we say that Kant's ideal of autonomy is the high point of the Enlightenment project, we can say that Levinas is a quintessentially postmodern thinker. Heteronomy is the key to true humanism.</p>
            <p>It is the emphasis on transcendence that provides the segue from ethics to religion. It is in the ethical relation that God “comes to mind.” Here again, Levinas is in important respects a Kantian. Kant insists that “on its own behalf morality in no way needs religion,” but he adds that it “inevitably leads to religion.”<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>16</sup>
               </xref>Of course, the self-sufficiency of ethics does not for Levinas rest on pure practical reason, nor does it lead to religion as “the idea of a mighty moral lawgiver outside the human being, in whose will the final end (of the creation of the world) is what can and at the same [time] ought to be the final human end.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>17</sup>
               </xref>But it is clear that for Levinas ethics does not depend on religion in this sense and that it does lead to religion in his own sense of the term.</p>
            <p>And what is that sense? Levinas claims that his philosophical discourse can include the God of the Bible since “the God of the Bible signifies the beyond being, transcendence” (GP 130). But one looks in vain for the God of the Bible in the philosophical writings of Levinas, and this is no accident.</p>
            <p>The God of the Bible is a God of covenantal promises, as Abraham, David, and Jeremiah might testify. But such a God, the heart of the Abrahamic monotheisms, is a personal God, an agent and a speaker distinct from all human agents and speakers. As such God is the ground of obligation, but more than this as well. The promises that accompany the commands in the case of Abraham, for example, mean that God is an agent who can carry out divine purposes (a theme Levinas never raises) and a speaker who can reveal divine purposes and expectations to humans (a possibility Levinas overtly denies).</p>
            <p>This denial comes when Levinas glosses his own claim, “There can be no ‘knowledge’ of God separated from the relationship with men.” This could be a correlate of the claim that there is no authentic love of God apart from love of neighbor, which is anything but the equation of the two. But Levinas means something stronger: “The Other is the very locus of metaphysical truth, and is indispensable for my [cognitive] relation with God…. The Other … is the manifestation of the height in which God is revealed. It is our relations with men … that give to theological concepts the sole signification they admit of…. Without the signification they draw from ethics, theological concepts remain empty and formal frameworks…. Everything that cannot be reduced to an interhuman relation represents not the superior form but the forever primitive form of religion” (TI 78–79).</p>
            <p>This leaves no room for covenantal promises, for such promises cannot be read in the face of the widow, the orphan, and the stranger or heard in their voices. But God has been turned into a mute who can speak to us in no other way. God is “not an interlocutor.” Just think how surprised Abraham, or Moses, or Isaiah, or Amos would be to learn this (GP 141).<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>18</sup>
               </xref>We can only speak of God in the third person, “the<italic>he</italic>in the depth of the You…. He does not fill me up with goods, but compels me to goodness, which is better than goods received” (GP 141). Just think how surprised the psalmists would be to learn that they cannot address God as “you.” In their praise and their laments they address God both as you and as he. The God who is reduced to “the<italic>he</italic>in the depth of the You” appears to be nothing more than the depth dimension of human selves that is the ground of our obligation to them.</p>
            <p>The God of the Bible has disappeared fully from sight or hearing when we read, “We propose to call ‘religion’ the bond that is established between the same and the other without constituting a totality” (TI 40). For this bond has been articulated entirely in terms of the face-to-face relation, the intrahuman conversation in which the responsible self is born. So it is neither surprising nor inconsistent when Levinas transfers such traditional divine attributes as transcendence, height, glory, and revelation to other human beings in their moral significance for us.<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>19</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>There is a name for this reduction—the term is Levinas's own, cited above—of theology to anthropology. It is Feuerbachian atheism. Those consistent secularists who find Levinas to be far too religious and those theistic believers who think themselves to have found a powerful ally in him are both mistaken. The God of the Abrahamic monotheisms and thus the God of the Bible, whether Jewish or Christian, has been defined out of existence. As with Spinoza, the term is retained, but the meaning is dramatically altered.</p>
            <p>With Derrida as with Ricoeur, there are far too many relevant themes for the time and space available. So I will mention just two points on which he reinforces what Levinas has been up to. First, he takes the notion of transcendence seriously and presents it in terms of inverted intentional- ity. Surprisingly, given the thoroughness of the linguistic turn in Derrida, he follows Sartre rather than Levinas and defines inverted intentionality in terms of being seen rather than being addressed. I am seen by an other whom I cannot see (read: objectify), and this means that “my gaze … is no longer the measure of all things.”<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>20</sup>
               </xref>Derrida treats the experience itself with all seriousness. It is utterly central to his project of “religion without religion” (GD 49), even if in its original appearance it belongs to the Abrahamic monotheisms, religion with religion.</p>
            <p>Derrida defines “religion without religion” as religion without “institutional dogma” or “an article of faith” (GD 49) or, in other words, without synagogue, church, or mosque. But even more fundamentally, it is religion without God. Transcendence does not disappear, and it is even expressed as “<italic>Mysterium tremendum</italic>” (GD 53). But every other is wholly other (<italic>tout autre est tout autre</italic>), and we need not turn to God to find mysterious transcendence; we encounter it in “each man and woman” (GD 82–83). This could be an affirmation of the<italic>imago dei</italic>, the likeness of created human selves to their divine creator. But this is not Derrida's meaning. While the question of God in a deconstructive context is objectively undecidable, undecidability calls for decision, and Derrida has made his: “We should stop thinking about God as someone, over there, way up there, transcendent, and what is more … capable, more than any satellite orbiting in space, of seeing into the most secret of the most interior places. It is perhaps necessary … to think of God and of the name of God without such idolatrous stereotyping or representation” (GD 108).</p>
            <p>In other words, religion without religion signifies that whatever its historical debts to the Abrahamic monotheisms, it has parted company with theism. The transcendence of inverted intentionality takes place in the context of a reductive humanism in which the marks of divinity that religion with religion ascribes to God are conferred instead on “each man and woman.”</p>
            <p>Such a transfer is a matter of habit for Derrida. Thus, he writes, “Language has started without us, in us and before us. This is what theology calls God.”<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>21</sup>
               </xref>Or again, Derrida speaks of “the absolute singularity of the other, whose name here is God” (GD 66).<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>22</sup>
               </xref>Or once again, “God is the name of the possibility I have of keeping a secret that is visible from the interior but not from the exterior” (GD 108). When such human characteristics or capacities as language, singularity, and interiority are given as the meaning of “God,” we have, once again, Feuerbachian atheism.</p>
            <p>It's time to add Kierkegaard to the mix. Of course, he did not enter the scene between<italic>then</italic>and<italic>now</italic>, but his reception has changed during that transition.<italic>Then</italic>he was an incipient Heidegger who hadn't quite purged the specifically religious (ontic) elements in favor of the religiously neutral, categorial concepts (ontological) that can provide needed correction to theology.<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>23</sup>
               </xref>The primary text was<italic>Concluding Unscientific Postscript</italic>, and<italic>Works of Love</italic>was all but entirely off the radar screen.<italic>Now</italic>he is seen either as an incipient Derrida whose literary devices deconstruct and dissolve any positive message or as the essentially religious writer he claimed to be, whose writings have both the intention and the potential to be edifying or upbuilding. The most discussed work is<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>(including discussions by Levinas and Derrida),<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>24</sup>
               </xref>and there has been an explosion of scholarly interest in<italic>Works of Love</italic>.</p>
            <p>Like Levinas and Derrida, Kierkegaard gives us a phenomenology of inverted intentionality.<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>25</sup>
               </xref>While objects may be given to us through my gaze or our language games, subjects are given to us as we are seen and (especially) as we are addressed by them. Thus, in Genesis and in<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>, Abraham and God have a covenantal relation. It is grounded in a series of promises and commands that God issues to Abraham. This God is thus a personal God, an agent capable of keeping those promises, and a speaking God, capable of such speech acts as making promises and giving commands. Unlike Levinas's God, Abraham's might well be called his Constant Interlocutor. Accordingly, Abraham's faith (the central theme of<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>) consists not primarily in a doxastic attitude toward various propositions (belief that …) but in the combination of trust in God's promises and obedience to God's commands.<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>26</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Kierkegaard's Silentio focuses attention on the last of God's commands to Abraham, the command to sacrifice Isaac. But he also calls our attention to a couple of the promises that constitute the covenantal relation, the promise of a land and the promise that through his seed all people will be blessed.<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>27</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>We should never equate the analysis of the ethical stage or sphere of existence in<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>with Kierkegaard's ethics. The former is the very formal view that the laws and customs of one's people (Hegel's<italic>Sittlichkeit</italic>) are the highest norms for an individual's behavior. This is meta-ethics, not any particular ethics, and, in any case, is not a view that Kierkegaard holds. To find his ethics we must turn primarily to<italic>Works of Love</italic>, and there we are once again introduced to inverted intentionality. Romantic love and friendship are good things, but they are grounded in self-love—the other must be attractive to the same in some way. They are rightly celebrated by poets. But they belong to the realm Levinas calls enjoyment. The responsible self comes into being only in responses to the divine command: you shall love your neighbor as yourself. The neighbor need not be attractive to me, and, in fact, my enemy is also my neighbor whom I am to love. I, my world, and my agenda in the world are defined by a voice not my own (or our own).</p>
            <p>But unlike Levinas and Derrida, Kierkegaard does not try to improve upon divinely commanded love by finding its ground in the neighbor. He does not place the phenomenology of inverted intentionality in a metaphysics of Feuerbachian atheism but, rather, in the context of a biblical theism. The neighbor remains transcendent, an other that must not be reduced to the same by becoming merely a means to my ends precisely because there is a God who transcends both of us and cares about both of us. Why should I love the neighbor, who may be the widow, orphan, or stranger I would rather ignore or the enemy I would rather hate? Because “God has created him and Christ has redeemed him” and for that reason commands me to love even the unattractive or hateful neighbor as myself.<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>28</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Jean-Luc Marion is more interested in the phenomenology of religion than in ethics.<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>29</sup>
               </xref>But before turning to his positive contributions, it is worth noticing a loud protest that concerns both him and Levinas, among others. In 1991 Dominique Janicaud published<italic>The Theological Turn of French Phenomenology</italic>, bitterly accusing Levinas and a series of younger scholars, including Marion, of betraying phenomenology. By sneaking God into phenomenology they abandon the reduction and thereby compromise phenomenology's scientific rigor and neutrality. Speaking of Levinas, but implicitly of Marion and others,<xref rid="r030" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>30</sup>
               </xref>he writes, “The dice are loaded and choices made; faith rises majestically in the background. The reader … finds him- or herself in the position of a catechumen who has no other choice than to penetrate the holy words and lofty dogmas…. All is acquired and imposed from the outset, and this all is no little thing: nothing less than the God of the biblical tradition. Strict treason of the reduction.”<xref rid="r031" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>31</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>This involves the rather curious presupposition that the idea of a philosophy without presuppositions is itself without presuppositions. But Marion's response takes a different direction. As he sees it, “It is an essential of phenomenology that the<italic>a posteriori</italic>makes it possible and therefore that no forbidden<italic>a priori</italic>predetermines it…. ‘It is forbidden to forbid!’ … That which shows itself justifies itself by this fact alone.”<xref rid="r032" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>32</sup>
               </xref>One cannot forbid religious subject matter to phenomenology. But in what sense does the latter justify the former? Not as independently and objectively real. It is a matter of possibility, not actuality. Thus, for example,<disp-quote>
                  <p>the phenomenon of revelation remains a mere possibility. I am going to describe it without presupposing its actuality…. [I]f an actual revelation must, can, or could have been given in phenomenal apparition, it could have, can, or will be able to do so only by giving itself according to the type of the paradox par excellence—such as I will describe it. Phenomenology cannot decide if a revelation can or should ever give itself…. I am obliged<italic>here</italic>—in phenomenology, where possibility remains the norm and not actuality—only to describe it in its pure possibility and in the reduced immanence of givenness. I do not<italic>here</italic>have to judge its actual manifestation or ontic status, which remain the business proper to revealed theology.<xref rid="r033" ref-type="fn">
                        <sup>33</sup>
                     </xref>
                  </p>
               </disp-quote>Marion does speak at times as a theologian. But given this clear criterion, it is easy enough to distinguish his theology from his phenomenology and, indeed, easy enough to read his theology (or Levinas's) as if it were phenomenology.</p>
            <p>Two of Marion's contributions to the phenomenology of religion are of special interest to us here. The first is the distinction between an idol and an icon.<xref rid="r034" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>34</sup>
               </xref>We are talking about any physical representation of the divine. But the difference is not between the modes of representation but between the modes of intending the picture, statue, or a symbolic object such as a cross. If our gaze comes to rest on the representation as if the represented were fully presented to us in the representation, transcendence is lost. There is an identity of thought and being here in which our thought perfectly mirrors the object but at the same time the object becomes merely a mirror of our mind's content or capacity. This is an idol. If, on the other hand, my gaze “transpierces” both itself and its noematic object, recognizing the nonadequation of thought and being, the mind and its referent, we have an icon, a religious representation that is given as a reminder of the incomprehensibility of the sacred. The same analysis can be applied to concepts as well as to visibles. Hence Marion's interest in the apophatic traditions sometimes referred to as negative theology.</p>
            <p>At least of equal importance is Marion's notion of the saturated phenomenon:<xref rid="r035" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>35</sup>
               </xref>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>To the phenomenon that is most often characterized by a defect of intuition [ordinary objects of vision in which we intend more than we can see and Kant's rational ideas, for which no adequate experience can be given] … why would there not correspond the possibility of a phenomenon in which intuition would give<italic>more, indeed unmeasurably more</italic>, than intention ever would have intended or foreseen [e.g., Kant's aesthetic idea]? … [B]ut it is no longer a matter of the nonadequation of the (lacking) intuition that leaves a (given [metaphysical]) concept empty; it is a matter, conversely, of a failure of the (lacking) concept that leaves the (overabundantly given) intuition blind.<xref rid="r036" ref-type="fn">
                        <sup>36</sup>
                     </xref>
                  </p>
               </disp-quote>There is nothing particularly religious about saturated phenomena. There are four kinds that are quite mundane: the historical event, the idol (work of art, especially a painting), the flesh (our experience of our own body), and the icon (the face of the other in the Levinasian sense).<xref rid="r037" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>37</sup>
               </xref>So far as the phenomenology of religion is concerned, the claim is simply that if a revelation or epiphany were to occur in the sense assumed by the Abrahamic monotheisms, its phenomenality would have to be of this sort, and moreover, it would be the saturated phenomenon par excellence insofar as it would involve all four types.</p>
            <p>I said that the earlier contrast of idol and icon and the later fivefold analysis of the saturated phenomenon were of special interest in the present context. How so? Quite unexpectedly, we discover that both analyses invoke the concept of an inverted intentionality. In the experience of the icon (as distinct from the idol) we find “a nearly perfect inversion” of the intentionality that constitutes the idol as such: “If man, by his gaze, renders the idol possible, in reverent contemplation of the icon, on the contrary, the gaze of the invisible, in person, aims at man…. [T]he icon opens in a face that gazes at our gazes … offering its spectacle to be transgressed—not to be seen, but to be venerated…. [T]he intention here issues from infinity…. [H]ere our gaze becomes the optical mirror of that at which it looks only by finding itself more radically looked at.”<xref rid="r038" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>38</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>Similarly, by virtue of its complex structure, the phenomenon of revelation involves the “paradox that an invisible gaze visibly envisages me and loves me.”<xref rid="r039" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>39</sup>
               </xref>Since accounts of revelation in the Abrahamic monotheisms typically have God speaking to or through some prophet, we have here the double structure of being seen and being addressed.</p>
            <p>One could surely give other narratives from the journey from<italic>then</italic>to<italic>now</italic>in ethics and philosophy of religion. But the narrative I have offered points to two features of our<italic>now</italic>in relation to our phenomenological origins. First, there is the revolution—some might say heresy—that we can call the hermeneutical turn and all it implies, including the hermeneutics of suspicion. This is, it seems to me, the decisive turn from modernity to postmodernity. I think that it can be fairly said that we are still working out the implications of this break from Cartesian phenomenology, even where the language of hermeneutics and transcendental phenomenology is not used.</p>
            <p>Second, there is a second revolution, even more radical and directly pertinent to both ethics and religion. But not only there. The concept of inverted intentionality, an intentionality of “a wholly different type,” requires a fundamental rethinking of the phenomenological method and project. We are not as far along on this, I think, as we are on coming to terms with the first revolution. More systematic work needs to be done in thinking through the transcendence, passivity, and heteronomy implied in being seen and being addressed. Perhaps Marion has pointed in the right direction in his answer to the question: Who comes after the (Cartesian) self (transcendental ego)? The self is<italic>l'interloqu</italic>é (<italic>Angesprochene</italic>), the one addressed, called out, claimed.<xref rid="r040" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>40</sup>
               </xref>The self is<italic>l'adonné</italic>, the one gifted or given over. Our task is in large measure to think out the meaning of such names for the self and to come up with others equally illuminating. For ethics and religion always concern the question, Who am I?—in relation to that which transcends me.</p>
            <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
               <title>NOTES</title>
               <ref id="r001">
                  <label>1.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Given limitations of time and space, I shall focus on European philosophers rather than North American philosophers inspired by and in conversation with them.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r002">
                  <label>2.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>These works were, respectively, the inspiration for my own work in<italic>God, Guilt, and Death</italic>(1984, 1987) and<italic>Suspicion and Faith</italic>(1993, 1998).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r003">
                  <label>3.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Paul Sartre,<italic>Being and Nothingness</italic>, trans. Hazel Barnes (New York: Philosophical Library, 1956), 412 n. 14.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r004">
                  <label>4.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Totality and Infinity: An Essay on Exteriority</italic>, trans. Alphonso Lingis (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, 1969), 171, 199, 216, 262, 303; henceforth cited as TI. Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Entre Nous: On Thinking-of-the-Other</italic>, trans. Michael B. Smith and Barbara Harshav (New York: Columbia University Press, 1998), 168; henceforth cited as EN.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r005">
                  <label>5.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>“Dialogue with Emmanuel Levinas,” in<italic>Face to Face with Levinas</italic>, ed. Richard A. Cohen (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1986), 24, 38; EN, 131, 169, 186.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r006">
                  <label>6.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas, “Ethics as First Philosophy,” in<italic>The Levinas Reader</italic>, ed. Seán Hand (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1989), 82; EN, 130, 169, 171. The three are found together at EN 168–69.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r007">
                  <label>7.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Otherwise than Being: or, Beyond Essence</italic>, trans. Alphonso Lingis (Boston: Martinus Nijhoff, 1981), 161; EN, 104; Emmanuel Levinas, “Peace and Proximity,” in<italic>Alterity and Transcendence</italic>, trans. Michael B. Smith (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999), 143.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r008">
                  <label>8.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>The Nicene Creed, 325 A.D., affirms that Jesus is and was fully human but also fully divine. The Chalcedonian Creed, 451 A.D., reaffirms Nicaea and declares the human and divine natures of Jesus to be united “inconfusedly, unchangeably, indivisibly, inseparably.” The face and the voice of the other in Levinas embody a similar unity of the empirical and transempirical.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r009">
                  <label>9.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas, interview with Richard Kearney, in Richard Kearney,<italic>Debates in Continental Philosophy: Conversations with Contemporary Thinkers</italic>(New York: Fordham University Press, 2004), 83. Same as “Dialogue” in note 5 above.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r010">
                  <label>10.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas, “God and Philosophy,” in<italic>Basic Philosophical Writings</italic>, ed. Adriaan T. Peperzak, Simon Critchley, and Robert Bernasconi (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1996), 147; henceforth cited as GP. Levinas tells us that he has Marx especially in mind. There's an irony insofar as Marx is unaware of his vulnerability to charges of plagiarism in the absence of some footnotes to Isaiah, Amos, Hosea, and Jeremiah.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r011">
                  <label>11.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Of God Who Comes to Mind</italic>, trans. Bettina Bergo (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1998), xi–xiv, 87, 124–26; EN 123–24.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r012">
                  <label>12.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Levinas,<italic>Of God Who Comes to Mind</italic>, 87.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r013">
                  <label>13.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See his critique of Husserl in Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>The Theory of Intuition in Husserl's Phenomenology</italic>, trans. André Orianne (Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1973); and Emmanuel Levinas, “The Work of Edmund Husserl,” in<italic>Discovering Existence with Husserl</italic>, trans. Richard A. Cohen and Michael B. Smith (Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1998), 47–87.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r014">
                  <label>14.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See my analysis in “Inverted Intentionality: On Being Seen and Being Addressed,”<italic>Faith and Philosophy</italic>26, no. 3 (2009): 233–52.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r015">
                  <label>15.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Cf. GP 136–38.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r016">
                  <label>16.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Immanuel Kant,<italic>Religion Within the Boundaries of Mere Reason</italic>, trans. George di Giovanni, in<italic>Religion and Rational Theology</italic>, ed. Allen W. Wood and George di Giovanni (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1996), 57, 59.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r017">
                  <label>17.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Ibid., 59–60.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r018">
                  <label>18.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>For a literary analysis of the Abraham stories in Genesis in which God is in ever renewed conversation with Abraham, his Prime Interlocutor, we might say, see Paul Borgman,<italic>Genesis: The Story We Haven't Heard</italic>(Downers Grove, Ill.: InterVarsity Press, 2001), pt. 2. But it would suffice to read Genesis since the question concerns the God of the Bible.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r019">
                  <label>19.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>For a more detailed analysis of Levinas on God, see my<italic>Levinas and Kierkegaard in Dialogue</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2008), chaps. 3–4.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r020">
                  <label>20.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jacques Derrida,<italic>The Gift of Death</italic>, trans. David Wills (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1995), 27, cf. 2, 6, 25, 27–28, 31–33, 56, 91, 93; henceforth cited as GD. Unfortunately the pagination in the second edition, 2008, is different. For shame! Sometimes this theme emerges in Derrida's analysis of Patočka, and sometimes, on its own.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r021">
                  <label>21.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jacques Derrida, “How to Avoid Speaking: Denials,” in<italic>Derrida and Negative Theology</italic>, ed. Harold Coward and Toby Foshay (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1992), 99.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r022">
                  <label>22.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Derrida sees this definition of God as important for ethics and not just for religion without religion (GD 66–67).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r023">
                  <label>23.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>That it is the task of phenomenology to correct theology is a central theme of Martin Heidegger's own “Phenomenology and Theology,” in<italic>Pathmarks</italic>, ed. William McNeill (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1998), 39–62.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r024">
                  <label>24.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>On the relation of<italic>Postscript</italic>to<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>as late as 1991, see Edward F. Mooney,<italic>Knights of Faith and Resignation: Reading Kierkegaard's “Fear and Trembling”</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 1991), ix, 143 n. 1.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r025">
                  <label>25.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Jeffrey Hanson, ed.,<italic>Kierkegaard as Phenomenologist: An Experiment</italic>(Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 2010).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r026">
                  <label>26.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Of course, that trust and that obedience presuppose some “beliefs that …,” such as that there is a God, that God has spoken to him, that God has said thus and so, etc. But the biblical formula is not that Abraham “believed that …” but, rather, that Abraham believed God, that is, trusted and obeyed God.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r027">
                  <label>27.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Søren Kierkegaard,<italic>Fear and Trembling/Repetition</italic>, trans. Howard V. Hong and Edna H. Hong (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983), 17.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r028">
                  <label>28.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Søren Kierkegaard,<italic>Works of Love</italic>, trans. Howard V. Hong and Edna H. Hong (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1995), 69.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r029">
                  <label>29.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>
                     <italic>The Erotic Phenomenon</italic>is a phenomenology of love but not a direct contribution to normative ethics.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r030">
                  <label>30.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-François Courtine, Michel Henry, and Jean-Louis Chrétien.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r031">
                  <label>31.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Dominique Janicaud,<italic>The Theological Turn of French Phenomenology</italic>, trans. Bernard G. Prusak, in Dominique Janicaud, Jean-François Courtine, Jean-Louis Chrétien, Michel Henry, and Jean-Luc Marion,<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn”: The French Debate</italic>(New York: Fordham University Press, 2000), 27. Of course, it is far from clear that one can find the God of the Bible in Levinas's philosophical writings. See above.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r032">
                  <label>32.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Luc Marion, “Metaphysics and Phenomenology: A Summary for Theologians,” in<italic>The Postmodern God</italic>, ed. Graham Ward (Oxford: Blackwell, 1997), 289.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r033">
                  <label>33.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Luc Marion,<italic>Being Given: Toward a Phenomenology of Givenness</italic>, trans. Jeffrey L. Kosky (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2002), 235–36.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r034">
                  <label>34.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Luc Marion,<italic>God Without Being</italic>, trans. Thomas A. Carlson (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991), chap. 1.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r035">
                  <label>35.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Jean-Luc Marion, “The Saturated Phenomenon,” in Janicaud et al.,<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn”</italic>; Jean-Luc Marion,<italic>Being Given</italic>, bk. 4; and Jean-Luc Marion,<italic>In Excess: Studies of Saturated Phenomena</italic>, trans. Robyn Horner and Vincent Berraud (New York: Fordham University Press, 2002).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r036">
                  <label>36.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Marion, “Saturated Phenomenon,” 195–96.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r037">
                  <label>37.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>It is clear that Marion is using<italic>idol</italic>and<italic>icon</italic>quite differently here from their usage in the earlier contrast.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r038">
                  <label>38.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Marion,<italic>God Without Being</italic>, 19–22.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r039">
                  <label>39.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Marion, “Saturated Phenomenon,” 215. The notion of an inverted intentionality is a recurring theme throughout Marion's<italic>In Excess</italic>, though not necessarily by name (see 37, 44, 61, 99, and, in connection with the icon, 113–17).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r040">
                  <label>40.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Luc Marion, “L'Interloqué,” in<italic>Who Comes After the Subject?</italic>ed. Eduardo Cadava, Peter Connor, and Jean-Luc Nancy (New York: Routledge, 1991).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
            </ref-list>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <sec-meta>
            <contrib-group>
               <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <string-name>
                     <italic>John D. Caputo</italic>
                  </string-name>
                  <aff>Syracuse University and Villanova University</aff>
               </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
         </sec-meta>
         <title>Continental Philosophy of Religion: Then, Now, and Tomorrow</title>
         <p>Was the fiftieth anniversary meeting a celebration of a vital philosophical society—or was it a memorial service held by the elders at the passing of a beloved old friend? That is the question I pose in addressing the state of Continental philosophy and religion “then and now,” which cannot elude the question of their future.<xref rid="r041" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>Accordingly my essay has three parts—“then”: the theological sources of “Continental philosophy” and of the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP) in particular; “now”: the state of the question today, the “theological turn”; and “tomorrow”: a reaction demanding a return of realism and antireligion.<xref rid="r042" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <sec id="s02_1">
            <title>Origins: The Becoming Philosophical of the Theological</title>
            <p>SPEP in particular and Continental philosophy in the United States generally were first nourished in originally religious and theological soil. That the papers delivered in the first five years, from 1962 to 1967, show nothing of the sort is actually a part of my thesis.<xref rid="r043" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>3</sup>
               </xref>Contemporary Continental philosophy emerged under what John Wild called in 1955 “the breakdown of modern philosophy”:<xref rid="r044" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>4</sup>
               </xref>the discontent with the epistemologies of the seventeenth and eighteenth century, the critique of metaphysics in the wake of Kant, the critique of Hegel launched by the Kierkegaardian pseudonyms, the popularity of existentialism. None of this need necessarily have anything to do with theology, but it did, and that is because this discontent with modernity found an especially receptive audience among people who—like the founders of SPEP—were either theologically minded philosophers outright or philosophers who having been theologically minded had given it up and were looking for a successor form of thinking to their theological interests. The significant thing is not so much that they gave up theology, which they did in varying degrees, but that in looking for a successor form they turned to Continental philosophy. If they turned to Anglo-American sources, they embraced not the then regnant Anglo-American analytic and positivistic philosophies but, rather, classical American thinkers such as William James or Whitehead's process philosophy (theology). One reason for this is the “E” in SPEP, the question of philosophy as an “existential” matter, a matter of personal passion, a form of life. Let us briefly consider the Catholic, Protestant, and Jewish sources of SPEP.</p>
            <sec id="s02_1_1">
               <title>Catholic.</title>
               <p>Continental philosophy has been a central component in the philosophical curricula of most American Catholic colleges and universities ever since the Second Vatican Council, which was convened on October 11, 1962 (the first meeting of SPEP was held fifteen days later, October 26, 1962). A good half of the doctoral programs in the United States that offer programs specializing in Continental philosophy are to be found in Catholic institutions, and many prominent members of the movement have Catholic origins. Catholics, to borrow a phrase from Bruno Latour, have never been modern,<xref rid="r045" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>and that was especially the case for Catholic European immigrants to a predominantly Protestant Anglo-Saxon country. At the Catholic University of America, students were even asked to take an oath against “modernism,” which by no means should be understood as an oath to postmodernism. When the hegemony of neo-Thomism was finally broken, Catholics took up their Continental European heritage in a sustained way.<xref rid="r046" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>They readily turned to the philosophers of “concrete existence” and to the phenomenological movement that encouraged a return to the Lebenswelt. Continental philosophy was cut to fit the intellectual tradi- tion and growing historical consciousness of Catholics. Indeed, there is a kind of natural migration from Aristotle to phenomenology. Heidegger made his way into phenomenology from a Catholic German neo-Scholastic world and came to see in Aristotle the greatest phenomenologist of antiquity. John Wild made a similar migration from realism. Wild was being read by Catholics in the 1950s, and they moved with him from the realism of Aristotle and Aquinas to phenomenology, resulting in a form of phenomenology that is free from the transcendentalism that beset pure Husserlian versions of phenomenology.</p>
               <p>Of all the philosophers Catholics read, Heidegger enjoyed pride of place, aided by a wave of English translations and by the landmark study<italic>Heidegger: Through Phenomenology to Thought</italic>, by William Richardson, a Jesuit then at Fordham University.<xref rid="r047" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>7</sup>
                  </xref>When Catholic philosophers read<italic>Being and Time</italic>it sounded just like what they who were wary of modernity had been looking for. When Heidegger criticized Descartes's idea of a worldless subject and his reduction of the world to<italic>res extensa</italic>, when Heidegger said that the question of the existence of the world when it is raised by a being whose being is being-in-the-world makes no sense, when Heidegger said that as soon as Dasein comes to be it finds that it is already there, that made instant sense to Catholic realists.<xref rid="r048" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>8</sup>
                  </xref>They had been critical of modern Cartesian epistemology for decades,<xref rid="r049" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>9</sup>
                  </xref>and here was Heidegger putting that argument on the map of contemporary philosophy in an original and magisterial way. When the “later” Heidegger offered a critique of what he called “onto-theo-logic,” when he said that an atheism about the God of metaphysics, about the<italic>causa sui</italic>, was closer to the truly divine God, Catholics knew from firsthand experience what he was talking about.<xref rid="r050" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>10</sup>
                  </xref>They had enough of the neo-Scholastic manuals, and they wanted to “overcome” them.<xref rid="r051" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>11</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s02_1_2">
               <title>Protestantism.</title>
               <p>The ultimate setting of the creation of SPEP was Harvard in the 1950s. The founding father of SPEP is John Wild (1902–1972), who taught at Harvard from 1927 to 1961 and who had spent 1931–32 in Freiburg hearing the lectures of Heidegger and Husserl. Wild's study of Heidegger came to fruition for him only after he read Merleau-Ponty, which sent Wild back to the sources and led him to give courses on Heidegger at Harvard.<xref rid="r052" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>12</sup>
                  </xref>This occasioned his own shift from realism to phenomenology and his departure from Harvard to Northwestern, where he established one of the two major programs in Continental philosophy at the time outside the Catholic institutions, the other being the New School of Social Research, and then moved on to Yale. To Wild's presence at Harvard we should add the arrival of Paul Tillich in the United States, first at Union Theological Seminary (1933–55) and then at Harvard (1955–62; and finally at Chicago). Students at Harvard in the 1950s had the remarkable opportunity to study existentialism and phenomenology with Tillich and Wild.</p>
               <p>Calvin Schrag was one such student. He was Paul Tillich's teaching assistant at Harvard, and he wrote a dissertation on Heidegger and Kierkegaard, directed by Tillich and Wild (and he also notes meeting a young French exchange student at Harvard named Jacques Derrida). One of the most important effects of the theology of Paul Tillich was to help introduce Heidegger to a generation of American students. What Schrag says was true for a whole generation: “It should come as no surprise that it is difficult to write about Kierkegaard and Heidegger without having philosophical and religious topics and themes crisscross at rather crucial junctures. Thus in this very early work certain background interests that circumscribe the present project are already discernible.”<xref rid="r053" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>13</sup>
                  </xref>Schrag's journey is a prism of the journey of many if not most of the original generation of SPEP. Don Ihde tellingly recalls: “I got an M. Div from Andover Newton in 1959…. I took most of my theology with Paul Tillich…. Cal Schrag was his assistant then, too…. I learned of Heidegger via Tillich” (e-mail correspondence, October 5, 2011). Wild, Edie, and Schrag were three of the five figures on the first “Executive Committee” at the first meeting at Northwestern in October 1962. Of the two others, William Earle had taken a Ph.D. at the University of Chicago under Charles Hartshorne, the leading process theologian of the day, and had a mystical streak,<xref rid="r054" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>14</sup>
                  </xref>and George Schrader (1917–1998) came to Yale in 1939 as a student in the Divinity School, where he earned his B.Div. in 1942. In all five cases, a theological project turned philosophical.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s02_1_3">
               <title>Jewish.</title>
               <p>Aaron Gurwitsch and the group of Jewish phenomenologists and thinkers who had assembled in exile at the New School were not part of the first Executive Committee, but they had established the first beachhead of Continental philosophy in the United States, and their pure Husserlian brand of phenomenology was an important part of SPEP early on. The first debate to break out in the nascent society took place between pure Husserlian “phenomenologists” and the “existentialists.” Still, the New School philosophers showed very little interest in Jewish theology or religion. So even here, we must go back to John Wild, whose role in advancing the current interest in Levinas has been documented by Richard Sugarman, then a young Jewish student of Wild's at Yale and Florida in the 1960s, who was first introduced to the work of Levinas by Wild.<xref rid="r055" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>15</sup>
                  </xref>According to Sugarman, Wild wrote a commentary on<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>that “keenly anticipated” the changes Levinas would introduce in<italic>Otherwise than Being</italic>.<xref rid="r056" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>16</sup>
                  </xref>Edith Wyschogrod, who took her first course in philosophy under Wild at the Harvard Summer School, was the first theologically and religiously sensitive philosophical Jewish presence to gain prominence in SPEP.<xref rid="r057" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>17</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </sec>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s02_2">
            <title>The Theological Turn: The Becoming Theological of Philosophy</title>
            <p>The expression “theological turn,” coined by Janicaud, was intended as a complaint that philosophy was again becoming a handmaiden of a theological agenda. But it also described a genuine renewal of what had been traditionally called the “philosophy of religion,” resulting in a new subdiscipline, a specifically “Continental philosophy of religion,” offering an alternative to the reigning neo-Scholastic and analytic approaches, conceived in the spirit of Heidegger's critique of “onto-theo-logic” and his meditations on “non-objectifying thinking.”<xref rid="r058" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>18</sup>
               </xref>God is not an object for a subject, not the referent of a propositional assertion, not the subject matter of a demonstration, all staples of “modernity,” which is why the theological turn is sometimes called “postmodern theology.” Heidegger produced a paradigm shift of revolutionary proportions for the philosophy of religion, for theology, and for religion itself. While the young Heidegger was immersed in Augustine, Kierkegaard, and the letters of Saint Paul, the later Heidegger had in mind the Greek divinities, and by nonobjectifying thinking he meant poetic thinking, not biblical. That was the basis of the critique of Heidegger, first by his contemporary Levinas, thinking from the Jewish tradition, and in the next generation by Jean-Luc Marion, working from the Catholic tradition, each of whom proposed alternate ways of thinking God “otherwise than Being” or “without Being.” Levinas and Marion are the central figures in the theological turn (singled out for sharp criticism by Janicaud). Levinas has been the subject of countless sessions at SPEP for several decades, while Marion was introduced to the membership in a plenary address he gave at SPEP in 1993 (Chicago) and has since built up a very considerable American presence.<xref rid="r059" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>19</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>For Levinas, the liberation of God from Being was the definition of “ethics,” which Levinas himself called “metaphysics.” Levinas meant that ethics alone breaks the crust of Being, which he called the sphere of the “same.” The ethical other breaches what we comprehend and pre-have in advance and exposes us to the “wholly other,” by which he meant not God but the “face” of the neighbor or the stranger, which is the “trace” that God leaves behind in withdrawing from the world (Being). Levinas radicalizes the ethics of neighborly love and hospitality in the Jewish Scriptures, by means of which he thought “first philosophy” could be revitalized and ethics returned to center stage in Continental thinking, a project in which he broadly succeeded. Marion's trope, “without Being,” is structurally similar to Levinas's, but Marion really does mean God (the God of the mystical theology of the Christian neo-Platonists), whom he approaches in an ingenious series of three “reductions” in the Husserlian sense: first of transcendental subjectivity (Kant and Husserl), then of existential agency (Dasein), and finally of Being itself. The upshot of reduction is to release the givenness (<italic>Gegebenheit</italic>) of what he calls the “saturated phenomenon.” By this he means the phenomenon untethered from prior limiting conditions, which is free to be given in a flood of<italic>donation</italic>that overwhelms the conceptual resources of the one to whom it is given (the<italic>adonné</italic>). Reversing orthodox Husserlianism, the givenness of the saturated phenomenon exceeds the intentional act.</p>
            <p>In my own opinion the most interesting expression of the religious turn in Continental philosophy is found in Derrida because Derrida is by anyone's standards a secular thinker and even, by the standards of the local pastor or rabbi, an atheist. So it came as a shock to read about Derrida's “religion” in his famous “Circumfession” (1989), which is a deconstructive riff on Augustine's<italic>Confessions</italic>in which Derrida restages the scene of the<italic>Confessions</italic>. We come upon a scene in which the speaker (Augustine/Jackie), an emigrant from North Africa to the Big Apple (Rome/Paris), has his back to us and is praying to someone (<italic>te</italic>, God/<italic>tu</italic>), while his mother (Monica/Georgette) lies dying on the northern shore of the Mediterranean (Ostia/Nice). Derrida tells us that he has been praying all his life and that no one, not even his mother, has understood this, which has led to a misunderstanding of his work.<xref rid="r060" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>20</sup>
               </xref>But to whom is Derrida praying, and how could he be praying at all? Does he not “rightly pass for an atheist”?<xref rid="r061" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>21</sup>
               </xref>There is a more obscure sense of religion “without religion” in Derrida, and a prayer to a God not only unknown but nonexistent that nonetheless constitutes a genuine prayer. If, as Jean-Louis Chrétien says, himself one of the new religious phenomenologists,<italic>prayer</italic>is a “wounded word,” what word is more wounded than a word from one who does not know to whom he is praying (a lost letter, destination unknown), or if anyone is there to hear his prayers, or if he is praying at all, who has to pray to be able to pray at all, for something, he knows not what, something “coming,” the coming or incoming (<italic>invention</italic>) of something unforeseeable?<xref rid="r062" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>22</sup>
               </xref>Derrida's atheism is crucially important to his religion because it allows him to isolate the very structure of prayer, and hence of the religious posture, with or without what we in the great monotheisms call “God,” thereby putting into question the very binarity of theism and atheism. A whole body of work has sprung up in its wake, inside and outside SPEP, which takes its lead from the idea that deconstruction is structured like a religion (unless it is the opposite, that religion is structured like a deconstruction).<xref rid="r063" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>23</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>More recently a series of atheistic and materialist interpretations of Saint Paul have arisen, beginning with Alain Badiou's<italic>The Universalism of St. Paul</italic>, according to which Paul is an exemplar of the galvanized subjectivity that is required by a truth process. Paul's letters are a journal of the transformation of the subject under the impact of the event, which produces an apostolic mission to establish the universality of the truth. The universality of the truth event is achieved in a process of the subtraction of ethnic particularity, resulting in a reign of truth where there is neither Greek nor Jew, male nor female, master nor slave. Of course, the content of Paul's letters, the resurrection of Jesus, is not the truth but a fable, but it is in the form of the truth. Slavoj Žižek contributes to this debate by way of an unorthodox version of Hegel read through Lacan, the watchword of which is Lacan's saying that the therapy is over when the patient realizes that there is no Big Other. The final words of Jesus on the cross, “My God, why have you forsaken me?” bear witness to the final atheistic conversion of Jesus, when God himself ceases to believe in God, leaving behind the community of those who, having assumed responsibility for themselves, set out to produce a radical egalitarian socialist order.<xref rid="r064" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>24</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s02_3">
            <title>The Return of Realism and of Antireligion</title>
            <p>In his later writings Gianni Vattimo's “weak thought” became a “death of God” theology, one that is rooted in a reading of Heidegger and Nietzsche and as such is continuous with what we have been calling “postmodern” theology and Continental philosophy.<xref rid="r065" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>25</sup>
               </xref>But Badiou and Žižek represent a departure and a discontinuity, holding up the “postmodern” for scorn. They insist on the universality of truth and its clear separation from fiction and on the decisiveness of political action as opposed to “undecidability” and what they mock as an anemic “political correctness.” They advance “strong” metaphysical thinking, and they ridicule what they call a weak and flaccid postmodern play of signifiers. In their wake, a new generation of philosophers say that Continental philosophy has no future, at least not as we know it. They would regard the anniversary meeting as a memorial service, at which we were giving loving eulogies of the late lamented. Not only are the<italic>soixante-huitaires</italic>dead—the whole thing is dead.<italic>Requiescat in pace</italic>.</p>
            <p>Interestingly, we have reached a curious state of déjà vu. If SPEP was very much the work of John Wild, and if Wild followed a trajectory from realism to phenomenology, we are today seeing a movement in reverse, from phenomenology back to realism. Furthermore the later theological turn, almost predictable from the implicit theological beginnings of Continental philosophy, has occasioned a turn toward an antireligion, toward a new atheism, a new modernism, and a new materialism, reminiscent of the debates about scientific realism when Wilfrid Sellars presented his views on the manifest image and the scientific image in the early years of SPEP. The new movement has gathered around Quentin Meillassoux's<italic>After Finitude</italic>.<xref rid="r066" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>26</sup>
               </xref>Meillassoux, a student of Badiou's, makes two charges. First is “correlationism”: Continental philosophy from Kant to the present is inherently subjectivistic and antirealist and makes nonsense of modern science (the premise that provoked the Alan Sokal ruse).<xref rid="r067" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>27</sup>
               </xref>The villain of the piece is Kant's perversion of the Copernican Revolution, wherein Kant reinstated the very anthropocentrism destroyed by Copernicus. Second is “fideism”: when Kant said that he found it necessary to deny knowledge in order to make room for faith, he laid the ground for the theological turn. He invented the God of the gaps. He turned philosophy into a kind of apologetics that delimits the natural sciences and leaves the barn door wide open, through which theology makes an easy escape. Phenomenology, hermeneutics, and deconstruction are just so many versions of Kantian idealism under another name, constituting the dark damp soil in which the poisonous mushrooms of theology take root. If the theological turn is where Continental philosophy leads us, the young critics seem to say, that is the last straw, its reductio ad absurdum!</p>
            <p>I think that what Meillassoux calls “correlationism” is a red herring and, since this is his root complaint, the new realism is the fruit of a poisoned tree. Even in the case of Husserl—there are statements in Husserl that have left us all wondering—the best scholarship today has made it plain that Husserl is not serving up metaphysical idealism but, rather, a theory of what sorts of acts are necessary on the part of the subject in order that objects may appear to the subject.<xref rid="r068" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>28</sup>
               </xref>Objects do not drop from the sky—and that goes for scientific objects.<xref rid="r069" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>29</sup>
               </xref>But the history of phenomenology after Husserl, especially nervous about pure transcendental phenomenology, mounted a sustained insistence on the reality of our being-in-the-world, to adopt the formulation of a young sometime Catholic Aristotelian realist named Heidegger, to which Merleau-Ponty added later on that being-in-the-world is a radically incarnational phenomenon. Levinas made an argument for the radical alterity—read irreducible “reality”—of the other person. Interestingly enough the new realists will sometimes cite Levinas's “reversal” of intentionality and his plea for radical “exteriority” as a residual trace of a quickly evaporating realism among the phenomenologists.<xref rid="r070" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>30</sup>
               </xref>When faced with the charge that deconstruction has locked us all within the prison house of language, Derrida replied, a bit nonplussed, that everything he has to say concerns the “other” of language and hence represents a discourse on the real.<xref rid="r071" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>31</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>That correlationism is a red herring is made plain by turning to the most sensible voice in the new debate, Bruno Latour, who was a student of Michel Serres's and whose work in “science studies”—conducted under the motto of the title of his first major book,<italic>We Have Never Been Modern</italic>—has been to show that science does not drop out of the sky. One would be hard put to differentiate what Latour calls his “non-modernism” from what Continental philosophers (loosely called “postmodern”) are saying. Indeed Latour's work had led to the charge that even he does not “believe in reality,” an objection that only momentarily left him speechless but quickly led to a wonderful book entitled<italic>Pandora's Hope</italic>.<xref rid="r072" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>32</sup>
               </xref>There he argues that, far from being opposed to each other, our power of “construction”—read “constitution”—goes hand in hand with “reality.” The more construction—the more sophisticated the scientific community, the more complicated the experiment, the more technical the laboratory instruments, the more funding for research—the more reality science will attain. Unhappily, Latour dismisses phenomenology as a “philosophy of consciousness,” as if the entire history of phenomenology after Husserl never happened. Don Ihde, one of the SPEP's most distinguished thinkers, has called Latour to task on just this point.<xref rid="r073" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>33</sup>
               </xref>Latour's point applies no less to religion.<xref rid="r074" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>34</sup>
               </xref>Religious beliefs and practices are certainly constructed—in concrete cultures, languages, traditions, and historical worldviews. The people whose practices these are understand (just like the people who actually practice science) both that they have composed these prayers, constructed these places of worship, made these statues, and so on<italic>and</italic>that in them they access something real that they have not made.</p>
            <p>Nonetheless, while I think that “correlationism” is a phony rap, there is something to Meillassoux's critique of “fideism,” because there is a version of Continental theory that sees it as a way to limit science in order to create a gap that can only be filled with faith in God. The real meaning of fideism is found in the God of the gaps. In my view, Continental theory is more “realistic” than Meillassoux allows, and it is also capable of a more critical reading of religion than the Kantian version of postmodern theory allows, which I think is indeed a version of fideism.<xref rid="r075" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>35</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <p>To rush to my conclusion: while the charge of “correlation” made by the enfants terribles has led to wildly unreasonable criticisms of late Continental philosophy, it is far from unreasonable to complain that postmodern French philosophy, and SPEP along with it, has marginalized the natural sciences. We have shown some interest (via Heidegger) in “technology,” but we have avoided the confrontation with mathematics and the natural sciences that was a part of the early phenomenological movement. Up to now philosophers such as Michel Serres and Bruno Latour have been treated as minor voices, and that, I think, has to change. The future of Continental philosophy depends on it, not just the future of a Continental philosophy of religion.</p>
            <p>We at SPEP have never been modern and have made a good living off the critique of modernism and of its binary oppositions. But I think that the business as usual of Continental philosophy will have to be expanded to include a critique of the opposition of the human and the nonhuman, of<italic>physis</italic>and<italic>techne</italic>, and of “Continental philosophy” and “science.” For the truth is that we have been a party to the science wars. That is why I think that the work of Catherine Malabou is exactly the sort of work that SPEP and Continental philosophy generally will have to do in the future.<xref rid="r076" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>36</sup>
               </xref>We have yet to admit how deeply inscribed the human is in the nonhuman and the technical. We have yet to appreciate that being-in-the-world is not only historicized, gendered, and incarnate but also both a neural and a galactic event, of both microscopic and macroscopic proportions. Can it be of no interest to “philosophy,” can there be nothing to “wonder” about, that our bodies are literally made of stardust? We have yet to realize how deeply interwoven is the imagination of speculative physics with the wonder of the philosophers. If the best we can do is to protect our turf by saying that science does not think, the sciences will steal our thunder, that is, our wonder, right out from under us. Science does think, and science wonders, because wonder is the piety of thought. That is a matter to which SPEP, and Continental philosophers generally, whether they have taken a theological turn or are running in the opposite direction, should give more thought.<xref rid="r077" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>37</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
            <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
               <title>NOTES</title>
               <ref>
                  <mixed-citation>My thanks go to Calvin Schrag, Don Ihde, Robert Scharff, and Richard Sugarman for help about matters discussed in this paper of which they were witness.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r041">
                  <label>1.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>The proceedings of the last conference I ran before my retirement from Syracuse University, “The Future of Continental Philosophy of Religion,” are being edited for publication.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r042">
                  <label>2.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Dominique Janicaud, “The Theological Turn of French Phenomenology,” in<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn”: The French Debate</italic>, ed. Dominique Janicaud, Jean-François Courtine, Jean-Louis Chrétien, Michel Henry, Paul Ricoeur, and Jean-Luc Marion (New York: Fordham University Press, 2000), 3–103.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r043">
                  <label>3.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See James Edie, ed.,<italic>An Invitation to Phenomenology</italic>(Chicago: Quadrangle, 1965), based on the first two meetings; James Edie, ed.,<italic>Phenomenology in America</italic>(Chicago: Quadrangle, 1967), based on the third, fourth, and fifth meetings.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r044">
                  <label>4.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>John Wild,<italic>The Challenge of Existentialism</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1955), 9ff.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r045">
                  <label>5.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Bruno Latour,<italic>We Have Never Been Modern</italic>, trans. Catherine Porter (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1993).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r046">
                  <label>6.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>
                     <italic>Philosophy Today</italic>, one of the first and most popular American journals in the field, was founded and edited by Robert Lechner, a Catholic priest, out of DePaul University, where it is still housed today under the editorship of David Pellauer, with which SPEP had a long and fruitful relationship. James Collins (St. Louis University) wrote two widely read books—<italic>The Existentialists: A Critical Study</italic>(Chicago: H. Regnery, 1952) and<italic>The Mind of Kierkegaard</italic>(Chicago: H. Regnery, 1953). Wilfrid Desan (Georgetown University), a Belgian philosopher who had taken a Ph.D. at Harvard, wrote<italic>The Tragic Finale: An Essay on the Philosophy of Jean-Paul Sartre</italic>(New York: Harper, 1960) and<italic>The Marxism of Jean-Paul Sartre</italic>(Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1965). Courses on “atheistic existentialism and Christian existentialism” (Gabriel Marcel) were staples of the day. Thomas Langan (Toronto) wrote one of the first books in English on Merleau-Ponty,<italic>Merleau-Ponty's Critique of Reason</italic>(New Haven: Yale University Press, 1966).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r047">
                  <label>7.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>William J. Richardson,<italic>Heidegger: Through Phenomenology to Thought</italic>, preface by Martin Heidegger (The Hague: M. Nijhoff, 1974).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r048">
                  <label>8.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Martin Heidegger,<italic>Being and Time</italic>, trans. John Macquarrie and Edward Robinson (New York: Harper and Row, 1962), §§29, 41.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r049">
                  <label>9.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Both Gilson and Jean-Luc Marion started their careers and achieved international eminence as Descartes scholars.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r050">
                  <label>10.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Martin Heidegger,<italic>Identity and Difference</italic>, trans. Joan Stambaugh (New York: Harper and Row, 1969).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r051">
                  <label>11.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>James Edie, a central figure on the original Executive Committee, was an ex-Benedictine priest and did his dissertation at the Catholic University of Louvain on Etienne Gilson: Callistus James Edie,<italic>The Philosophy of Etienne Gilson</italic>(Louvain: Université Catholique de Louvain, 1958). Edie would also co-edit a volume with John Wild and William Earle entitled<italic>Christianity and Existentialism</italic>(Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1963). Joseph Kockelmans had been a seminarian in Rome, although he was never ordained. Reiner Schürmann's career in the United States began as a Dominican priest teaching at the Catholic University of America. For many years, the laypeople teaching philosophy in Catholic universities were former seminarians, priests, or members of religious orders.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r052">
                  <label>12.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>William McBride, “John Wild, Phenomenology in America, and the Origins of SPEP,”<italic>Continental Philosophy Review</italic>44, no. 3 (August 2011): 282. This special issue, “Remembering John Wild,” dedicated to the memory of Alan Paskow, is invaluable.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r053">
                  <label>13.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Calvin Schrag,<italic>God as Otherwise than Being</italic>(Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 2002), xi–xii.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r054">
                  <label>14.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See William Earle,<italic>Mystical Reason</italic>(Chicago: Regnery/Gateway, 1980), 106–7.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r055">
                  <label>15.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Richard Sugarman, “Wild and Levinas: Legacy and Promise,”<italic>Continental Philosophical Review</italic>44, no. 3 (August 2011): 307–16.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r056">
                  <label>16.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>
                     <italic>The Promise of Phenomenology: Posthumous Papers of John Wild</italic>, ed. Richard I. Sugarman and Roger Duncan (Lanham, Md.: Lexington Books, 2006).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r057">
                  <label>17.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Today, SPEP numbers among its satellite groups both a “Society for Continental Philosophy in a Jewish Context” and the “Society for Continental Philosophy and Theology.”</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r058">
                  <label>18.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Heidegger's communication to the participants in a conference held at Drew University in 1964 in Martin Heidegger,<italic>The Piety of Thinking</italic>, ed. J. G. Hart, trans. J. C. Maraldo (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1977), 22–31.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r059">
                  <label>19.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Luc Marion, “The Saturated Phenomenon,”<italic>Philosophy Today</italic>40, no. 1 (SPEP suppl.; Spring 1994): 103–24.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r060">
                  <label>20.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jacques Derrida, “Circumfession: Fifty-Nine Periods and Periphrases,” in Geoffrey Bennington and Jacques Derrida,<italic>Jacques Derrida</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1993), 154–55. See also John D. Caputo and Michael Scanlon, eds.,<italic>Augustine and Postmodernism: Confessions and Circumfession</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2005).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r061">
                  <label>21.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Derrida, “Circumfession,” 155.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r062">
                  <label>22.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jean-Louis Chrétien, “The Wounded Word: Phenomenology of Prayer,” in Janicaud et al.,<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn,”</italic>147–75.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r063">
                  <label>23.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Mark Taylor's<italic>Erring: An A/Theology</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1984) was the first major presentation of Derrida and theology to cause a stir at SPEP and elsewhere, but it was a “death of God” Derrida written before the quasi-Augustinian quasi-prayerful Derrida who became focal during the later so-called theological turn.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r064">
                  <label>24.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Alain Badiou,<italic>The Universalism of St. Paul</italic>(Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2003); Slavoj Žižek and John Milbank,<italic>The Monstrosity of Christ: Paradox or Dialectic</italic>? ed. Creston Davis (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2009); John D. Caputo and Linda Martín Alcoff, eds.,<italic>St. Paul Among the Philosophers</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r065">
                  <label>25.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Gianni Vattimo,<italic>Belief</italic>, trans. Luca D'Isanto and David Webb (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999); and Gianni Vattimo,<italic>After Christianity</italic>, trans. Luca D'Isanto (New York: Columbia University Press, 2002).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r066">
                  <label>26.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Quentin Meillassoux,<italic>After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity of Contingency</italic>, trans. Ray Brassier (London: Continuum, 2008), 28ff.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r067">
                  <label>27.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Alan Sokal and Jean Bricmont,<italic>Fashionable Nonsense</italic>(New York: Picador, St. Martin's Press, 1998).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r068">
                  <label>28.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See, in particular, Dan Zahavi,<italic>Husserl's Phenomenology</italic>(Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2003).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r069">
                  <label>29.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Robert Sokolowski, a Catholic priest and classical Thomistic philosopher, was also a distinguished Husserlian, defending the idea that “constitution” is an epistemological not a metaphysical principle.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r070">
                  <label>30.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Ray Brassier,<italic>Nihil Unbound</italic>(London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007), 230–34. Graham Harman studied at Pennsylvania State University with Alphonso Lingis, Levinas's first English translator, where he found the beginnings of what he calls “object oriented ontology.” His work stems from an idiosyncratic interpretation of Heidegger's analysis of tools in his dissertation at DePaul on Heidegger. See his emigration from the world of SPEP in Graham Harman,<italic>Towards Speculative Realism: Essays and Lectures</italic>(Winchester, U.K.: Zero Books, 2009), which includes papers rejected by SPEP and the Heidegger Conference, which he wears as badges of honor.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r071">
                  <label>31.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Jacques Derrida, “Hospitality, Justice, and Responsibility,” in<italic>Questioning Ethics: Contemporary Debates in Philosophy</italic>, ed. Richard Kearney and Mark Dooley (New York: Routledge, 1999), 77.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r072">
                  <label>32.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Bruno Latour,<italic>Pandora's Hope: Essays on the Reality of Science</italic>(Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1999).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r073">
                  <label>33.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Don Ihde, “ANT Meets Postphenomenology,”<italic>4/S</italic>(2008),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          xlink:href="http://www.4sonline.org">http://www.4sonline.org</uri>.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r074">
                  <label>34.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>See Bruno Latour,<italic>On the Modern Cult of the Factish Gods</italic>, trans. Catherine Porter and Heather MacLean (Durham: Duke University Press, 2010), 93–94, passim.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r075">
                  <label>35.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>I take on the Kantian version of postmodern theory in John D. Caputo, “On Not Settling for an Abridged Edition of Postmodernism: Radical Hermeneutics as Radical Theology,” in<italic>Religion with Religion</italic>, ed. Aaron Simmons (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, in press).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r076">
                  <label>36.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>Catherine Malabou,<italic>What Should We Do with Our Brain?</italic>trans. Sebastian Rand (New York: Fordham University Press, 2008).</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r077">
                  <label>37.</label>
                  <mixed-citation>It may be a sign of the times that at the concluding plenary at the anniversary meeting John Sallis gave a paper on “Black Holes!”</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
            </ref-list>
         </sec>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
