<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">intrevquares</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>International Review of Qualitative Research</journal-title>
            <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">irqr</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">19408447</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19408455</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">irqr.2008.1.1.103</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">irqr.2008.1.1.103</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Is Culture a Problem for Social Psychology?</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Yoshihisa Kashima</string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff>Department of Psychology, The University of Melbourne.</aff>
            <bio>
               <p>Yoshihisa Kashima's research is concerned with a social psychology of cultural dynamics, namely, the process of cultural formation, maintenance, and transformation by micro-level activities in situ. He has combined cultural comparative, experimental, and formal modelling methods in his research program to examine the dynamics involving culture and self, the formation, maintenance, and transformation of cultural stereotypes, and culture and language use. He has authored or co-authored papers that appeared in<italic>Psychological Review, Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</italic>,<italic>Personality and Social Psychology Review</italic>,<italic>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</italic>,<italic>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</italic>,<italic>Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</italic>and<italic>Asian Journal of Social Psychology</italic>among others. He has co-edited books on<italic>Social Psychology and Cultural Context</italic>,<italic>Self and Identity: Personal, Social, and Symbolic</italic>, and<italic>Stereotype Dynamics</italic>. He taught at the University of Queensland and La Trobe University in Australia before he came to the University of Melbourne where he is Professor of Psychology. He holds a Bachelor of Law from Tokyo University, a BA in Psychology from the University of California, Santa Cruz, and a PhD in Psychology from the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign. He is the current editor of<italic>Asian Journal of Social Psychology</italic>.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>1</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>irqr.2008.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>103</fpage>
         <lpage>115</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/irqr.2008.1.1.103"/>
         <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>Culture has been regarded as an anathema to psychology as an empiricist research tradition. Despite the explosive growth of research on culture and psychology over the last decade of the 20<sup>th</sup>century and its importance in Asian social psychology, the ontological and epistemological tension between psychology as a science and psychology as a cultural/historical discipline introduced in the writings of the thinkers of the Enlightenment and counter-Enlightenment still lingers on in the contemporary discourse of psychology. Clifford Geertz once ominously suggested that cultural psychology may have chewed more than it can. In this paper, the interpretive turn in social science as exemplified by writings of Charles Taylor and Paul Ricoeur is reviewed and discussed how it may impinge on the practice of Asian social psychology as an empirical science in methodological, epistemological, and ontological respects. It is argued here that the current practice of Asian social psychology is largely, though not entirely, free of the challenges mounted by these theorists, and that Asian social psychology has an advantage of not encumbered by this traditional tension due to a monist ontology that is prevalent in Asia.</p>
         </abstract>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="13"/>
         </counts>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
