<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">man</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100268</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Man</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>journal-series-title</meta-name>
               <meta-value>New Series</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00251496</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2804111</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Monkey as Metaphor? Transformations of a Polytropic Symbol in Japanese Culture</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Emiko</given-names>
                  <surname>Ohnuki-Tierney</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>1990</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>25</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>i330183</issue-id>
         <fpage>89</fpage>
         <lpage>107</lpage>
         <page-range>89-107</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1990 Royal Anthropological Institute</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804111"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Most symbols are polytropic as well as polysemic in that their multiple meanings in various contexts functions as different types ot trope. This article pursues the complex nature of polytropes through a formulation of synecdoche as an interstitial trope between metaphor and metonymy, and demonstrates how the two conceptual principles of analogy and contiguity, that define metaphor and metonymy respectively, are interdependent and interpenetrated, rather than of basically different natures as presented in the biaxial image of structural linguistics. The analogic thought expressed in methaphor involves movement and temporality, just as does the discursive thought of metonymy. The interpenetration of the two modes of thought is demostrated through an analysis of the process of objectification of what, throughout history, has been a dominant symbol of self in Japanese culture: the monkey. As a polysemic and polytropic symbol, the monkey takes on different meanings, and functions as different tropic types, sequentially or simultaneously, as actors use and/or interpret the symbol in varying historical and social contexts.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
