<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">histpolithou</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013883</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>History of Political Thought</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Imprint Academic</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0143781X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">20512988</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26219896</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>COMMUNITARIANISM AND DISTANCE: FREUD AND THE HOMELESSNESS OF THE MODERN SELF</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Eyal</given-names>
                  <surname>Chowers</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2002</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">23</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i26219891</issue-id>
         <fpage>634</fpage>
         <lpage>653</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>copyright: Imprint Academic, 2002</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26219896"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This essay argues that Freud's theory pictures modern selves as coping with a new existential and social predicament: a sense of homelessness within their own home. More specifically, Freud suggests that individuals feel estranged from parts of their own psyche (their super-egos) as well as feeling distant from their own culture and tradition (as they are represented by this psychic agency); in modernity, neither one's mind nor one's community can promise any longer a sense of ground. Because of this sense of perpetual and irrevocable displacement, Freud feared that modern selves might become semi-psychotic, selves lacking an inner social-normative voice. He calls on moderns, however, to overcome this bleak prospect and the related danger of political chaos by accepting the social norms imposed by their super-egos. But Freud champions only a conditional acceptance of tradition, one that involves ongoing scepticism, ambivalence and emotional distance. Freud's position could therefore be characterized as a unique type of communitarianism: it seeks a balance between admission of the constitutive force of tradition on the one hand, and the formation of an emotional detachment from its myths, practices and normative claims on the other.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d2152e114a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e123" publication-type="other">
Sigmund Freud, in Minutes of the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society, Volume II:
1908-10 (New York, 1967), p. 174 (my emphasis). The references to Freud's writings in
this article are to The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works ofSigmund
Freud, ed. J. Strachey and A. Freud (24 vols., London, 1953-74). Citations follow this order:
title of work, volume number, page number.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e142a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e149" publication-type="other">
See Agnes Heller, 'Where are We at Home?', Thesis Eleven, 41 (1995), p. 2. Heller
argues that in modernity space is no longer the privileged sphere in which selves create their
home, and that they prefer to make 'the absolute present' into the chief anchor of identity.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e162a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e169" publication-type="other">
See, for example, Herbert Marcuse, Eros and Civilization: A Philosophical Inquiry
into Freud (Boston, 1955); Norman O. Brown, Life Against Death: The Psychoanalytic
Meaning of History (Middletown, CT, 1959); and Jiirgen Habermas, Knowledge and
Human Interest (Boston, 1968), especially ch. 12.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e185a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e192" publication-type="other">
Martin Heidegger, Being and Time, trans. J. Macquarrie and E. Robinson (New
York, 1962), p. 233. For Heidegger, Dasein has a sudden sense of uncanniness, of not
being at home, when it experiences itself as being-in-the-world. Dasein attempts to
escape this state by losing itself in an environment it considers familiar and safe: the
world of everyday concerns, of the 'they'. On the notion of homelessness in Heidegger,
see Leslie Paul Thiele, Timely Meditations: Martin Heidegger and Postmodern Politics
(Princeton, NJ, 1995). On the similarity between Freud and Heidegger on this subject,
see David Farrell Krell, 'Das Unheimliche: Architectural Sections of Heidegger and
Freud', in Research in Phenomenology, XXII (1992), pp. 43-61.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e225a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e232" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 220. There is, of course, a vast literature on Freud' s
concept of the uncanny, most of which is not concerned with the self-civilization relation
that is explored in this essay. Julia Kristeva, for example, examines the uncanny in the
context of the self-other relation. 'The uncanny strangeness', she writes, 'allows for
many variations: They all repeat the difficulty I have in situating myself with respect to
the other.' See Julia Kristeva, Strangers to Ourselves, trans. Leon S. Roudiez (New York,
1991), p. 187. While Kristeva's interpretation underscores the place of the uncanny in
human intercourse, Samuel Weber finds the uncanny important in forming a correct
theory of knowledge, one that does not hold to the Cartesian illusion of an objectivizing,
insulated and reliable cognition. 'Whereas for Descartes the essential condition for
attaining certitude was the subject's withdrawal from a world that in its alterity could no
longer be relied on, it is precisely the discovery that such withdrawal is a fata morgana,
an unsustainable construct that informs the misrecognition, that constitutes the uncanny. '
See Samuel Weber, The Legend of Freud (Stanford, CA, 2000), p. 20. For a political
interpretation of the concept, see Derrida's brief but illuminating discussion of the
uncanny element in Marxism, in Jacques Derrida, Specters of Marx (New York, 1994),
pp. 172-5. For a general discussion of Freud's theory of memory, see Richard Terdiman,
Present Past: Modernity and the Memory Crisis (Ithaca, NY, 1993).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e293a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e300" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 225. This is a quotation from Grimm's German dic-
tionary (1877, 4, Part 2, p. 875).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e310a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e317" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Introductory Lectures on Psychoanalysis', XVI, p. 285.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e324a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e331" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'An Outline of Psychoanalysis', XXIII, p. 163. My interpretation of psy-
choanalysis highlights the formation of the self as an outcome of identifications via the
super-ego. Freud, however, also believed in Lamarckian theory, and argued that acquired
psychic characteristics of the race are transmitted organically, through the id. Since this
point is not relevant to the present discussion, I will not explore it below. See Freud, 'The
Ego and the Id', XIX, pp. 12-68.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e354a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e361" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'New Introductory Lectures', XXII, p. 74.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e368a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e375" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'New Introductory Lectures', XXII, p. 110. For the import of political meta-
phors in Freud's work, see J. Brunner, On the Political Rhetoric of Freud's Individual
Psychology', History of Political Thought, V (1984), pp. 315-32; and Paul Roazen,
Freud: Political and Social Thought (New York, 1986).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e392a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e399" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Civilization and its Discontents', XXI, p. 134.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e406a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e413" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Future of an Illusion', XXI, p. 11.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e420a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e427" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 241. Freud's textual interpretation of the uncanny
in Hoffmann's story is controversial. See, for example, Harold Bloom, Agon; Towards a
Theory of Revisionism (New York, 1982); and Nicholas Rand and Maria Torok, 'The
Sandman Looks at the Uncanny', in Speculation After Freud: Psychoanalysis, Philoso-
phy, and Culture, ed. S. Shamdasani (London, 1994), pp. 185-204. For Freud's under-
standing of the repetitions in Hoffmann's work, see Neil Hertz, The End of the Line:
Essays on Psychoanalysis and the Sublime (New York, 1985), pp. 97-121.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e453a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e460" publication-type="other">
E.T.A. Hoffmann, Tales ofE.T.A. Hoffmann, ed. L. Kent and E. Knight (Chicago,
1972), p. 95.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e470a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e477" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 98. For the role of the Oedipal complex in identity-formation, see Hans W.
Loewald, 'The Waning of the Oedipus Complex', in H.W. Loewald, Papers on Psycho-
analysis (New Haven, 1980), pp. 384-404.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e490a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e497" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 223. At this stage, Freud did not yet use the con-
cept 'super-ego'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e508a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e515" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 235.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e522a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e529" publication-type="other">
J. Laplanche and J.B. Pontalis, The Language of Psychoanalysis, trans. D. Nicholson-
Smith (New York, 1973), p. 349.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e539a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e546" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 354 (my emphasis). This interpretation of projection is partly based on the
Schreber case study.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e556a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e563" publication-type="other">
Otto Rank, The Double, trans. H. Tucker (Chapel Hill, 1971), p. 82.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e570a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e577" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Uncanny', XVII, p. 235.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e584a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e591" publication-type="other">
In 'The Uncanny', Freud does not distinguish between psychotic pathologies and
narcissistic ones, seeming to regard them as one category. As Olsen and Koppe explain,
Freud 'found that most of the traits [of psychoses], that is, self-centeredness, lack of
libidinous object cathexis, the loss of the sense of reality, and domination of primary pro-
cesses, were related to their narcissistic mode'. They add that 'what in particular distin-
guishes the neuroses from the psychoses is their reliance on the defense mechanisms of
projection and denial in contrast to repression'. See O. Olsen and S. Koppe, Freud's
Theory of Psychoanalysis, trans. J.C. Delay and C. Pedersen (New York, 1988),
pp. 244-5. However, Freud's classification of psychic illnesses changed with the intro-
duction of the super-ego. In 'Neurosis and Psychosis' (1923), Freud argues that 'Trans-
ference neuroses correspond to a conflict between the ego and the id; narcissistic neuro-
ses [such as melancholia], to a conflict between the ego and the super-ego; and psycho-
ses, to one between the ego and the external world' (XIX, p. 152). This distinction is
problematic, since Freud claims that part of the demands of the external world is repre-
sented by the super-ego. In any event, in my discussion below I will continue to refer to
projection as a psychotic defence with narcissistic motivations.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e646a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e653" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'An Outline of Psychoanalysis', XXIII, pp. 206, 207.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e660a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e667" publication-type="other">
Ibid., XXII, p. 206. On identification in psychoanalytic theory, see Jessica
Benjamin, Shadows of the Other: Intersubjectivity and Gender in Psychoanalysis (New
York, 1998).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e680a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e687" publication-type="other">
In the context of autonomy, it is important to note the affinities between Freud and
what is known as 'positive liberty' (the type of liberty Isaiah Berlin suggested both Rousseau
and Kant adhered to). Freud believes that the self s freedom involves self-mastery, the capac-
ity of the ego to occupy the mind as much as possible. From his perspective, freedom is not
simply given once external interferences and obstacles are removed; rather, it is gained by
learning to conquer the psychic forces that spring from both the id and the super-ego, forces
that if left unchecked inhibit our capacity to function in and cope with the world. Neverthe-
less, Freud did not translate his understanding of human freedom to the political realm, and
avoided the notion that self-mastery also involves similarity among selves. On this matter,
see J. Brunner, Freud: The Politics of Psychoanalysis (London, 1995), ch. 10.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e722a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e729" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'New Introductory Lectures', XXII, p. 67.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e736a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e743" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Civilization and its Discontents', XXI, pp. 135-6.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e750a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e757" publication-type="other">
The critique of these bourgeois values was developed by writers after Freud, particu-
larly by Marcuse. From the latter's perspective, Freud's concept of the super-ego is anachro-
nistic: in modernity no genuine individuation and autonomy are acquired by the institution of
the super-ego, since the father and other close figures are no longer significant in forming this
psychic agency. 'Under the rule of economic, political, and cultural monopolies', Marcuse
writes, 'the formation of the mature super-ego seems to skip the stage of individuation: the
generic atom becomes directly a social atom. The repressive organization of the instinct
seems to be collective, and the ego seems to be prematurely socialized by a whole system of
extra-familial agents and agencies' (p. 97). This understanding of the super-ego and of the
resultant 'surplus repression' leads Marcuse to demand radical reorganization of social and
economic institutions in a manner that differs from Freud' s cautiousness and adherence to the
bourgeois order. See Marcuse, Eros and Civilization.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e800a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e807" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Civilization and its Discontents', XXI, pp. 141, 142.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e814a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e821" publication-type="other">
Alexis de Tocqueville, Democracy in America, Vol. 2 (New York, 1951),
pp. 258-9.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e831a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e838" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Group Psychology', XVIII, p. 116.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e845a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e852" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Civilization and its Discontents', XXI, pp. 115,116. Freud was highly crit-
ical of Woodrow Wilson, whom he considered a naive leader who misread the mutual
hostility inherent in social life. On this point, see Brunner, Freud: The Politics of Psycho-
analysis, ch. 4. It is important to note that when fascism emerged in Europe, Freud's sug-
gestion that the leader is essential to the formation of groups was strongly criticized.
Erich Fromm, for example, saw in his age a disintegration of the super-ego or conscience
(p. 167), and suggested that it is precisely the lack of individuality that springs from this
disintegration that propels men and women to crave an all-powerful leader and external
source of authority (or the anonymous rein of public opinion, the norm and science in
democratic regimes). Fascism, according to this interpretation, springs from the inability
of modern men and women to cope with their freedom and individuality, and with their
corresponding aloneness (or homelessness) in the world. See Erich Fromm, Escape
From Freedom (New York, 1941), especially chs. 5 and 7.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e897a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e904" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Future of an Illusion', XXI, p. 41.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e911a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e918" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'Civilization and its Discontents', XXI, p. 136.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e926a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e933" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Future of an Illusion', XXI, p. 41.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e940a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e947" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 39 (my emphasis).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e954a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e961" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 15. In 'Civilization and its Discontents', Freud displays a more equivocal
judgment about the value of civilization. See XXI, pp. 144-5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e971a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e978" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'An Outline of Psychoanalysis', XXIII, p. 175.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e985a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e992" publication-type="other">
On Freud' s Jewish identity and motivations for writing 'Moses and Monotheism',
see Yosef Hayim Yerushalmi' s study Freud's Moses: Judaism Terminable and Intermi-
nable (New Haven, CT, 1991 ). For the general place of suspicion towards accepted truths
and myths in Freud's thought, see Paul Ricoeur, Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on
Interpretation (New Haven, CT, 1970).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1011a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1018" publication-type="other">
Alasdair Maclntyre, After Virtue (Notre Dame, 1984), p. 220. See also Charles
Taylor, Hegel and Modern Society (Cambridge, 1979), pp. 157-8. For a psychoanalytic
critique of Maclntyre, see Fred Alford, The Self in Social Theory (New Haven, CT,
1991), ch. 1. Alford shares Maclntyre's understanding of the self in terms of narrative
within a given, constitutive social context. He criticizes Maclntyre, however, for not
granting the self sufficient capacity to change and shape its circumstances in the face of
tradition and social expectations. Alford also discusses other communitarian theorists in
this chapter.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1048a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1055" publication-type="other">
On these affinities between Freud and communitarians, see Jeffrey Abramson, Libera-
tion and Its Limits: The Moral and Political Thought of Freud (Boston, 1984), ch. 8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1065a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1072" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Disillusionment of the War', XIV, p. 286.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1079a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1086" publication-type="other">
According to Philip Rieff, Freud affirms the distance of the individual from the com-
munity, and in this sense psychoanalysis agrees with liberalism. The Freudian individual is
aloof from politics and learns not to seek radical changes in society, avers Rieff. That individ-
ual adapts to society in a calculated way which suits his or her needs: 'a rationally alienated
person learns how to guard against social over-investments, and how to make them when
necessary' (Philip Rieff, Freud: The Mind of a Moralist (Garden City, NY, 1961), p. 278).
Freud, then, teaches that the individual's attachment to society should be dependent on a
rational, economic exercise—on the conscious distribution of instinctual energy. Moreover,
once psychoanalytic therapy becomes a way of life, it contributes to detachment from others
by enhancing self-absorption. 'While enjoining a person to be less severe with himself,
observes Rieff, 'Freudian analysis may also develop in the patient new qualities of self-
suspicion... The therapy manufactures a new sort of conscience, one which demands a more
accurate and yet more scrupulous self-centeredness' (ibid., pp. 106-7).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1131a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1138" publication-type="other">
John Rawls, A Theory of Justice (London, 1971 ), p. 560.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1145a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1152" publication-type="other">
Freud, 'The Future of an Illusion', XVII, p. 12.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2152e1159a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2152e1166" publication-type="other">
Zygmunt Bauman, Liquid Modernity (Cambridge, 2000), p. 178. Agnes Heller makes
a similar point in her 'Where are We at Home?', pp. 17-18.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
