<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">intrevquares</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>International Review of Qualitative Research</journal-title>
            <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">irqr</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">19408447</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19408455</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">irqr.2008.1.1.55</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">irqr.2008.1.1.55</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>(Post)Feminist Methodology</article-title>
            <subtitle>Getting Lost OR a Scientificity We Can Bear to Learn From</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Patti Lather</string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff>Ohio State University.</aff>
            <bio>
               <p>Patti Lather is a Professor in the School of Educational Policy and Leadership at Ohio State University where she teaches qualitative research and gender and education. She has held visiting positions at the University of British Columbia, Goteborg University, York University, the Danish Pedagogy Institute, the Humanities Research Institute, University of California-Irvine and a 1989 Fulbright to New Zealand. She is the author of<italic>Getting Smart: Research and Pedagogy With/in the Postmodern</italic>that received a 1991 Critics Choice Award,<italic>Troubling the Angels: Women Living with HIV/AIDS</italic>, co-authored with Chris Smithies, that received a 1998 CHOICE Award, and<italic>Getting Lost: Feminist Efforts Toward a Double(d) Science</italic>(2007).</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>1</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>irqr.2008.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>55</fpage>
         <lpage>64</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/irqr.2008.1.1.55"/>
         <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>This paper puts the nature of scientificity on the feminist agenda. Sedgwick's reparative reading, Spivak's dislocating negotiation, Wilson's analytics of breaching and Lather's getting lost are unpacked via exemplars from recent feminist re-inscriptions of empirical work in order to begin to grasp what is on the horizon in terms of new analytics and practices of inquiry.</p>
         </abstract>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="10"/>
         </counts>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
