<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">jreligionafrica</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100250</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Journal of Religion in Africa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill Academic Publishers</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00224200</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">27594413</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="pub-doi">10.1163/157006607X188911</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>On Leaving and Joining Africanness Through Religion: The 'Black Caribs' across Multiple Diasporic Horizons</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Paul Christopher</given-names>
                  <surname>Johnson</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2007</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>37</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i27594410</issue-id>
         <fpage>174</fpage>
         <lpage>211</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2007 Koninklijke Brill NV</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/27594413"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Garifuna religion is derived from a confluence of Amerindian, African and European antecedents. For the Garifuna in Central America, the spatial focus of authentic religious practice has for over two centuries been that of their former homeland and site of ethnogenesis, the island of St Vincent. It is from St Vincent that the ancestors return, through spirit possession, to join with their living descendants in ritual events. During the last generation, about a third of the population migrated to the US, especially to New York City. This departure created a new diasporic horizon, as the Central American villages left behind now acquired their own aura of ancestral fidelity and religious power. Yet New-York-based Garifuna are now giving attention to the African components of their story of origin, to a degree that has not occurred in homeland villages of Honduras. This essay considers the notion of 'leaving' and 'joining' the African diaspora by examining religious components of Garifuna social formation on St Vincent, the deportation to Central America, and contemporary processes of Africanization being initiated in New York.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>Garifuna</kwd>
            <kwd>Black Carib</kwd>
            <kwd>religion</kwd>
            <kwd>diaspora</kwd>
            <kwd>migration</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d9994e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e141" publication-type="other">
Alpers, Edward A. 2001. 'Defining the African Diaspora. Unpublished manuscript pre-
sented to the Center for Comparative Social Analysis Workshop, University of
California-Los Angeles.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e154a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e158" publication-type="other">
Anderson, Alexander. 1992. Alexander Anderson and the Carib War in St. Vincent
(ca. 1798)'. In Peter Hulme and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters
with Caribs from Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 217-230.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e171a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e175" publication-type="other">
Appadurai, Arjun. 1996. Modernity at large: Dimensions of Globalization. Minneapolis:
University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e185a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e189" publication-type="other">
Axel, Brian Keith. 2004. 'The Context of Diaspora'. Cultural Anthropology 19.1, 26-60.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e197a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e201" publication-type="other">
Bard, Samuel L (Ephraim George Squier). 1855. Waikna: Adventures on the Mosquito Shore.
New York: Harper &amp;amp; Brothers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e211a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e215" publication-type="other">
Barth, Fredrik. 1969. 'Introduction'. In Fredrik Barth (ed.), Ethnic Groups and Boundaries:
The Social Organization of Culture Difference. Oslo: Scandinavian University Press,
9-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e228a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e232" publication-type="other">
Baumann, Martin. 2000. 'Diaspora: Genealogies of Semantics and Transcultural Com-
parison. Numen 47, 313-337.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e242a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e246" publication-type="other">
Beaumont, Monsieur de. 1992 [1705]. 'Letter of M. de Beaumont on the Caraïbes and
Father Le Breton's Mediation in Grenada, 3 September 1705'. In Peter Hulme and
Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from Columbus to the
Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 174-177.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e262a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e266" publication-type="other">
Behrend, Heike. 2002. 'I am Like a Movie Star in My Street': Photographic Self-Creation
in Postcolonial Kenya. In Richard Werbner (ed.), Postcolonial Subjectivities in Africa,
London and New York: Zed Books, 44-63.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e279a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e283" publication-type="other">
Benjamin, Walter. 1968. Illuminations: Essays and Reflections. New York: Schocken Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e291a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e295" publication-type="other">
Berking, Helmuth. 2003. '"Ethnicity is Everywhere": On Globalization and the Transfor-
mation of Cultural Identity'. Current Sociology 51.3/4, 248-264.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e305a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e309" publication-type="other">
Bianchi, Cynthia Chamberlain. 1988. 'Gubida Illness and Religious Ritual Among the
Garifuna of Santa Fe, Honduras: An Ethnopsychiatric Analysis'. Ph.D. thesis, Ohio
State University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e322a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e326" publication-type="other">
Braithwaite, John. 1992 [1726]. 'Report on the Proceedings at St. Vincent by Cpt. Braith-
waite. In Peter Hulme and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with
Caribs from Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 177-179.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e339a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e343" publication-type="other">
Breton, Raymond. 1992 [1647]. 'Of the Origin, Mores, Religion, and Other Customs of
the Caraïbes Commonly Called Savages, Ancient Inhabitants of Guadeloupe'. In
Peter Hulme and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from
Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 108-116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e359a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e363" publication-type="other">
Butler, Kim D. 2001. 'Defining Diaspora, Refining a Discourse'. Diaspora 10.2, 189-219.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e370a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e374" publication-type="other">
Butler, Judith. 1997. The Psychic Life of Power: Theories in Subjection. Stanford, CA: Stan-
ford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e385a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e389" publication-type="other">
Cassirer, Ernst. 1955. The Philosophy of Symbolic Forms, Volume Two: Mythical Thought.
New Haven and London: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e399a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e403" publication-type="other">
Clifford, James. 1994. 'Diasporas'. Cultural Anthropology 9, 302-338.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e410a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e414" publication-type="other">
Coelho, Ruy. 1955. 'The Black Carib of Honduras: A Study in Acculturation'. Ph.D. thesis,
Northwestern University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e424a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e428" publication-type="other">
Coelho, Ruy Galváo de Andrade. 1995. Los negros caribes de Honduras, 2nd edition. Tegu-
cigalpa, Honduras: Editorial Guaymuras.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e438a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e442" publication-type="other">
Cohen, Robin. 1997. Global Diasporas. Seattle: University of Washington Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e449a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e453" publication-type="other">
Coke, Thomas. 1790. An Address to the Subscribers for their Support of the Missions Carried
on by Voluntary Contributions to the Benefit of the Negroes in the British Islands, in the
West Indies. London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e467a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e471" publication-type="other">
Comaroff, John, and Jean Comaroff. 1992. Ethnography and the Historical Imagination.
Boulder: Westview Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e481a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e485" publication-type="other">
Conzemius, Eduard. 1928. 'Ethnographical Notes on the Black Carib (Garif)'. American
Anthropologist30..2, 183-205.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e495a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e499" publication-type="other">
Crawford, Michael H. 1984. 'Problems and Hypotheses: An Introduction. In Michael
H. Crawford (ed.), Black Caribs: A Case Study in Bio cultural Adaptation. New York:
Plenum Press, 1-9.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e512a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e516" publication-type="other">
Curtin, Philip D. 1969. The Atlantic Slave Trade: A Census. Madison: University of Wis-
consin Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e526a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e530" publication-type="other">
Davidson, George, of St. Vincent. 1787. The Case of the Caribbs in St. Vincents. London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e537a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e541" publication-type="other">
Davidson, William V. 1984a. 'The Garifuna in Central America: Ethnohistorical and Geo-
graphical Foundations'. In Michael H. Crawford (ed.), Black Caribs: A Case Study in
Bio cultural Adaptation. New York: Plenum Press, 13-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e555a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e559" publication-type="other">
—. 1984b. 'El Padre Subirana y las tierras concedidas a los indios hondurenos en el
siglo XIX'. América Indígena 44.3, 447-459.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e569a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e573" publication-type="other">
De Jonnès, Alexandre Moreau. 1920. Adventures in Wars of the Republic and Consulate.
Translated by A.J. Abdy. London: John Murray.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e583a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e587" publication-type="other">
De la Borde, Sieur. 1704. 'Avec un Voyage qui contient une relation exacte de l'origine,
moeurs, coutumes, religion, guerres &amp;amp; voyages des Caraibes, sauvages des isles Antilles
de l'Amerique, faite par le Sieur de La Borde, tirée du cabinet de Monsr. Blondel'. In
Louis Hennepin, Voyage ou Nouvelle decouverte d'un très-grand pays, dans l'Amerique,
entre le Nouveau Mexique et la Mer Glaciale, par le R.P. louis Hennepin, avec toutes les
particularitez de cepaïs, &amp;amp; de celui connu sous le nom de la louisiane. Amsterdam: Chez
A. Braakman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e617" publication-type="other">
du Tertre, Jean Baptiste. 1992 [1667]. Jean Baptiste du Tertre and the Noble Savages. In
Peter Hulme and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from
Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 128-138.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e630a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e634" publication-type="other">
Edwards, Bryan. 1818-9. The History, Civil and Commercial, of the British West Indies,
vol. IV London, G. and W.B. Whittaker.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e644a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e648" publication-type="other">
—. 1799. The History, Civil and Commercial, of the British Colonies in the West Indies.
London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e659a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e663" publication-type="other">
Eliade, Mircea. 1964. Shamanism: Archaic Techniques of Ecstasy. London: Routledge and
Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e673a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e677" publication-type="other">
England, Sarah. 1999. 'Negotiating Race and Place in the Garifuna Diaspora: Identity
Formation and Transnational Grassroots Politics in New York City and Honduras'.
Identities 6.,1, 5-53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e690a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e694" publication-type="other">
—. 2006. Afro Central Americans in New York City: Garifuna Tales of Transnational
Movements in Racialized Space. Gainesville: University Press of Florida.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e704a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e708" publication-type="other">
Foner, Nancy (ed.). 2001. Islands in the City: West Indian Migration to New York. Berkeley:
University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e718a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e722" publication-type="other">
Frazier, E. Franklin. 1974 [1964]. The Negro Church in America. New York: Schocken
Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e732a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e736" publication-type="other">
Froebel, Julius. 1859. Seven Years Travel in Central America, Northern Mexico, and the Far
West of the United States. London: Richard Bentley.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e747a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e751" publication-type="other">
Gadamer, Hans-George. 1975. Truth and Method. New York: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e758a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e762" publication-type="other">
Genovese, Eugene D. 1972. Roll, Jordan, Roll: The World Slaves Made. New York: Pantheon
Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e772a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e776" publication-type="other">
Gibbs, Archibald Robertson. 1883. British Honduras: An Historical and Descriptive Account
of the Colony from its Settlement, 1670. London: Sampson Low, Marston, Searle, &amp;amp;
Rivington.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e789a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e793" publication-type="other">
Gilroy, Paul. 1993. The Black Atlantic: Modernity and Double Consciousness. Cambridge,
MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e803a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e807" publication-type="other">
Gonzalez, Nancie L. 1988. Sojourners of the Caribbean: Ethnogenesis and Ethno history of the
Garifuna. Urbana and Chicago: University of Illinois Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e817a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e821" publication-type="other">
—. 1984. 'Garifuna (Black Carib) Social Organization'. In Michael H. Crawford (ed.),
Black Caribs: A Case Study in Bio cultural Adaptation. New York: Plenum Press, 51-66.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e832a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e836" publication-type="other">
Gonzalez, Nancie L. Solien. 1969. Black Carib Household Structure: A Study of Migration
and Modernization. Seattle and London: University of Washington Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e846a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e850" publication-type="other">
Gordon, Edmund T. 1998. Disparate Diasporas: Identity Politics in an Afro-Nicaraguan
Community. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e860a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e864" publication-type="other">
Gordon, Edmund T., and Mark Anderson. 1999. 'The African Diaspora: Toward an Eth-
nography of Diasporic Identification'. Journal of American Folklore 112.445, 282-
296.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e877a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e881" publication-type="other">
Gross, Jane. 2006. 'In Throes of a Diaspora, Two Families Bind'. New York Times, 6 September.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e888a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e892" publication-type="other">
Gullick, C.J.M.R. 1984. 'The Changing Vincentian Carib Population'. In Michael H.
Crawford (ed.), Black Caribs: A Case Study in Bio cultural Adaptation. New York: Ple-
num Press, 37-50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e905a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e909" publication-type="other">
Helms, Mary W. 1981. 'Black Carib Domestic Organization in Historical Perspective:
Traditional Origins of Contemporary Patterns'. Ethnology 20.1, 77-86.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e920a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e924" publication-type="other">
Herskovits, Melville. 1958. The Myth of the Negro Past. Boston: Beacon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e931a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e935" publication-type="other">
Hulme, Peter. 2000. 'Travel, Ethnography, Transculturation: St. Vincent in the 1790s'.
Unpublished manuscript. Presented at the University of Miami. 29-30 September.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e945a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e949" publication-type="other">
Hulme, Peter, and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.). 1992. Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs
from Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e959a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e963" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Paul Christopher. 2006. 'Joining the African Diaspora: Dynamics of Migration
and Urban Religion'. In R. Marie Griffith and Barbara D. Savage (eds.), Women and
Religions of the African Diaspora. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 37-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e976a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e980" publication-type="other">
—. 2007. Diaspora Conversions: Black Carib Religion and the Recovery of Africa. Berke-
ley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e990a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e994" publication-type="other">
Keenagh, Peter. 1938. Mosquito Coast: An Account of a Journey through the Jungles of Hon-
duras. Boston &amp;amp; New York: Houghton Mifflin Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1005a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1009" publication-type="other">
Kerns, Virginia. 1997. Women and the Ancestors: Black Carib Kinship and Ritual, 2nd edi-
tion. Urbana and Chicago: University of Illinois Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1019a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1023" publication-type="other">
Klein, Herbert S. 1999. The Atlantic Slave Trade. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1030a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1034" publication-type="other">
Klimt, Andrea, and Stephen Lubkemann. 2002. Argument across the Portuguese-speaking
World: A Discursive Approach to Diaspora. Diaspora 11.2, 145-162.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1044a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1048" publication-type="other">
Kolapo, Femi J. 2004. 'The Igbo and their Neighbours during the Era of the Atlantic Slave-
Trade'. Slavery and Abolition 25.1, 114-133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1058a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1062" publication-type="other">
Labat, Jean Baptiste. 1992 [1722]. 'A Sojourn on Dominica'. In Peter Hulme and Neil L.
Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from Columbus to the Present
Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 155-168.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1075a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1079" publication-type="other">
La Borde, Sieur de. 1992 [1674]. An Account from the Jesuit Missions'. In Peter Hulme
and Neil L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from Columbus to
the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 139-154.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1093a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1097" publication-type="other">
Leblond, Jean-Baptiste. 2000 [1813]. Voyage aux Antilles: D'île en île, de la Martinique à
Trinidad. Paris: Editions Karthala.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1107a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1111" publication-type="other">
Lefebvre, Henri. 1991 [1974]. The Production of Space. Translated by Donald Nicholson-
Smith. Oxford: Basil Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1121a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1125" publication-type="other">
Lovejoy, Paul E. 1997. 'The African Diaspora: Revisionist Interpretations of Ethnicity,
Culture and Religion under Slavery'. Studies in the World History of Slavery, Abolition
and Emancipation 2, 1-23.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1138a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1142" publication-type="other">
Malkki, Lisa H. 1997. 'National Geographic: The Rooting of Peoples and the Territorial-
ization of National Identity among Scholars and Refugees'. In Akhil Gupta and James
Ferguson (eds.), Culture, Power, Place: Explorations in Critical Anthropology. Durham,
NC, and London: Duke University Press, 52-74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1158a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1162" publication-type="other">
Matory, J. Lorand. 2005. Black Atlantic Religion: Tradition, Transnationalism, and Matriar-
chy in the Afro-Brazilian Candomblé. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1172a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1176" publication-type="other">
McAlister, Elizabeth. 1998. 'The Madonna of 115th Street Revisited: Vodou and Haitian
Catholicism in the Age of Transnationalism'. In R. Stephen Warner and Judith
G. Wittner (eds.), Gatherings in Diaspora: Religious Communities and the New Immi-
gration. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 123-160.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1193a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1197" publication-type="other">
—. Rara! Vodou, Power, and Performance in Haiti and its Diaspora. Berkeley: University
of California Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1207a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1211" publication-type="other">
Meléndez, Armando Crisanto. 1997. Adija sisira gererun aguburigu garinagu: El enojo de las
sonajas; palabras del ancestor. Tegucigalpa, Honduras: Graficentro Editores.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1225" publication-type="other">
—. 2002. El enojo de las sonajas: Palabras del ancestor, 2nd edition. Tegucigalpa, Hon-
duras: Editorial Cultura.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1235a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1239" publication-type="other">
Merkin, Daphne. 2006. 'What's so Hot about 50? Sex and the Female Boomer is Not
Booming'. New York Times Magazine. 12 February, 17-18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1249a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1253" publication-type="other">
Morris, Valentine. 1787. A Narrative of the Official Conduct of Valentine Morris, Esq. late
Captain General, Governor in Chief, of the Island of St. Vincent and its Dependencies.
London: J. Walter, Logographic Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1266a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1270" publication-type="other">
Ong, Aihwa. 1999. Flexible Citizenship: The Cultural logics of Transnationality. Durham,
NC, and London: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1281a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1285" publication-type="other">
Palmer, Colin A. 1998. 'Defining and Studying the Modern African Diaspora. Perspectives
36.1, 22-25.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1295a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1299" publication-type="other">
Posas, Mario. 1993. Breve Historia de la Ciudad de La Ceiba. Tegucigalpa, Honduras: Alin
Editora, S.A.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1309a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1313" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 2004. Memory, History, Forgetting. Translated by Kathleen Blarney and David
Pellauer. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1327" publication-type="other">
Roberts, Orlando W. 1827. Narrative of Voyages and Excursions on the East Coast and in the
Interior of Central America. Edinburgh: Constable &amp;amp; Co.; and London: Hurst, Chance &amp;amp;
Co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1340a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1344" publication-type="other">
Rochefort, Charles César de. 1992 [1658]. 'Relative Values'. In Peter Hulme and Neil
L. Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from Columbus to the Pres-
ent Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 118-127.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1357a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1363" publication-type="other">
Rumbaut, Rubén G. and Alejandro Portes. 2001. 'Ethnogenesis: Coming of Age in Immi-
grant America'. In Rubén G. Rumbaut and Alejandro Portes (eds.), Ethnicities:
Children of Immigrants in America. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California
Press, 1-21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1380a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1384" publication-type="other">
Safran, William. 1991. 'Diasporas in Modern Societies: Myths of Homeland and Return'.
Diaspora 1.1,83-99.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1394a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1398" publication-type="other">
Shaw, Rosalind. 2002. Memories of the Slave Trade: Ritual and the Historical Imagination in
Sierra Leone. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1408a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1412" publication-type="other">
Sheffer, Gabriel. 2003. Diaspora Politics: At Home Abroad. Cambridge: Cambridge Univer-
sity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1422a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1426" publication-type="other">
Shepperson, George. 1966. 'The African Abroad or the African Diaspora'. African Forum:
A Quarterly Journal of Contemporary Affairs 2, 76-93; reprinted in TO. Ranger (ed.),
1968, Emerging Themes of African History. London: Heinmann, 152-176.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1439a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1443" publication-type="other">
Smith, Jeffrey S., and Benjamin N. White. 'Detached from their Homeland: The Latter-
Day Saints of Chihuahua, Mexico'. Journal of Cultural Geography Spring/Summer
2004 21.2,57-76.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1456a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1460" publication-type="other">
Stephens, John Lloyd. 1949 [1841]. Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas, &amp;amp;
Yucatan, Volume One. Edited by Richard L. Predmore. New Brunswick: Rutgers Uni-
versity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1474a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1478" publication-type="other">
Swett, Charles. 1868. A Trip to British Honduras, and to San Pedro, Republic of Honduras.
New Orleans: Price current print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1488a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1492" publication-type="other">
Taylor, Douglas. 1951. The Black Carib of British Honduras. New York: Wenner-Gren
Foundation for Anthropological Research.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1502a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1506" publication-type="other">
—. 1949. 'The Interpretation of Some Documentary Evidence on Carib Culture'.
Southwestern Journal of Anthropology 5, 379-392.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1516a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1520" publication-type="other">
Telles, Edward E. 2004. Race in Another America: The Significance of Skin Color in Brazil.
Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1530a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1534" publication-type="other">
Thornton, John. 1998. Africa and Africans in the Making of the Atlantic World, 1400-1800,
2nd ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1544a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1548" publication-type="other">
Tölölyan, Katchig. 1996. 'Rethinking Diaspora(s): Stateless Power in the Transnational
Moment'. Diaspora 5.2, 3-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1559a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1563" publication-type="other">
Tweed, Thomas A. 1997. Our Lady of the Exile: Diaspora Religion at a Cuban Catholic
Shrine in Miami. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1573a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1577" publication-type="other">
Uring, Nathaniel. 1749. A History of the Voyages and Travels ofCapt. Nathaniel Uring, with
a New Draught of the Bay of Honduras. London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1587a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1591" publication-type="other">
Van Hear, Nicholas. 1998. New Diasporas: The Mass Exodus, Dispersal and Regrouping of
Migrant Communities. Seattle: University of Washington Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1601a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1605" publication-type="other">
Vertovec, Steven. 2000. The Hindu Diaspora: Comparative Patterns. London and New York:
Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1615a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1619" publication-type="other">
Waters, Mary C. 1999. Black Identities: West Indian Immigrant Dreams and American Real-
ities. New York and Cambridge, MA: Russell Sage Foundation and Harvard Univer-
sity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1632a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1636" publication-type="other">
Werbner, Pnina. 2000. 'Introduction: The Materiality of Diaspora—Between Aesthetic
and "Real" Polities'. Diaspora 9.1, 5-20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1647a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1651" publication-type="other">
Young, Thomas. 1847. Narrative of a Residence on the Mosquito Shore. London: Smith,
Elder and Co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1661a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1665" publication-type="other">
Young, Sir William. 1764. Some Observations; Which May Contribute to Afford a Just Idea of
the Nature, Importance, and Settlement, of our New West-India Colonies. London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1675a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1679" publication-type="other">
—. 1971 [1795]. An Account of the Black Charaibs in the Island of St Vincents, with the
Charaib Treaty of 1773, and Other Original Documents. Abingdon: Frank Cass &amp;amp; Co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1689a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1693" publication-type="other">
—. 1992 [1795]. An Account of the Black Charaibs in the Island of St. Vincent'. In
Peter Hulme and Neil L. Whitehead. (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from
Columbus to the Present Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 191-209.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1706a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1710" publication-type="other">
—. 1992. 'William Young's Tour of the Islands'. In Peter Hulme and Neil L.
Whitehead (eds.), Wild Majesty: Encounters with Caribs from Columbus to the Present
Day. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 211-215.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="d9994e1732a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1739" publication-type="other">
Sarah England (2006: 13)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1746a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1753" publication-type="other">
Gilroy 1993: 23,
205-208</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1762" publication-type="other">
Cohen 1997</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1769a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1776" publication-type="other">
Palmer (1998)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1783a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1790" publication-type="other">
Hennepin's 1704</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1798a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1805" publication-type="other">
Hulme and Whitehead 1992: 194</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1812a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1819" publication-type="other">
West Indies (1787: 18).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1826a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1833" publication-type="other">
John Lloyd Stephens,
Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas, and Yucatan, vol. 1 (New York: Harper and
Brothers, 1841), in Kerns 1997: 34.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1845" publication-type="other">
Gonzalez (1988: 97)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1852a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1859" publication-type="other">
Gonzalez 1988: 21</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1866a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1873" publication-type="other">
Alexander Anderson's 1798</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1880a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1887" publication-type="other">
'Black Power' symbol (1995: 165).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1895a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1902" publication-type="other">
Curtin 1969: 188</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1909a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1916" publication-type="other">
Hodgson 1757</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1922" publication-type="other">
Bard (1965 [1855]: 338, 357</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1928" publication-type="other">
Thornton 1998: 284</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1935a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1942" publication-type="other">
Davidson 1984b: 449-451</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1949a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1956" publication-type="other">
Catholic (1968: 78).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1962" publication-type="other">
Gibbs (1883: 151)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1969a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1976" publication-type="other">
Solien Gonzalez 1969: 34</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1982" publication-type="other">
Posas 1993: 16</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9994e1989a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d9994e1996" publication-type="other">
Edward Alpers (2001: 4)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
