<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="book-review">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">jameracadreli</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100053</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of the American Academy of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>American Academy of Religion</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00027189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">14774585</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">1463047</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Bibliographical Survey</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Toward a Generic Analysis of a Classic of the Social Gospel: An Essay-Review of Walter Rauschenbusch</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Charles R.</given-names>
                  <surname>Strain</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>1978</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>i263714</issue-id>
         <fpage>525</fpage>
         <lpage>543</lpage>
         <page-range>525-543</page-range>
         <product>
            <source>Christianity and the Social Crisis</source>
            <string-name>
               <given-names>Walter</given-names>
               <surname>Rauschenbusch</surname>
            </string-name>
         </product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1979 American Academy of Religion</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1463047"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Walter Rauschenbusch's Christianity and the Social Crisis, viewed by many as the masterpiece of the social gospel movement, has been confined to the dusty shelves of the library. Can we catch no glimpse of what astounded its massive reading public, no glimmer of Rauschenbusch's own sense of the work as a "dangerous book" written in fear and trembling? This article suggests that a generic analysis of Christianity and the Social Crisis might lead to surprising disclosures. Any generic analysis involves the discussion of a group of texts. Consequently this study proceeds via a comparison of the structure of Christianity and the Social Crisis with those of other works of a similar type which were produced between 1890 and 1915. The genre is isolated by utilizing the techniques of Tzvetan Todorov. Certain negative traits are specified which separate the genre from its neighbors. The positive leitmotif of a dual crisis-a crisis affecting society as a whole and the ramifications of that crisis within the Christian churches-is specified as the decisive trait of the genre. To deal with this leitmotif a specific structure was generated by the works under consideration. They provided-to pirate the words of Clifford Geertz in his landmark essay on modern ideologies-"maps of problematic reality" and "matrices for the creation of collective conscience." In designing their maps of problematic reality our authors worked along two separate but related vectors. The first of these vectors was constituted by a historical analysis of the origins of the present crisis, while the second consisted of a systemic analysis of the present social order. Each of these elements of the genre is examined in turn. The mapping of problematic reality by means of a historical and a structural analysis was geared towards provoking as well as defining the crisis. Crisis, once defined, demanded decision. Nevertheless the "permanent basis for action" which Rauschenbusch and others sought could not be grounded upon ideological conviction alone. It required both concrete guidelines for praxis and the creation of an institutional matrix to mobilize the moral forces of the society, to form public opinion. These works then as ideological matrices for the creation of collective conscience were also designed to precipitate the transformation of the Church into an agent of human emancipation. The art of the genre was also an act. But in an age noted for "writing-as-action" the exemplars of the genre laid a complexly interwoven, carefully stressed foundation for Christian involvement in social change. Rauschenbusch's Christianity and the Social Crisis appears at the end of this analysis as the unsurpassed formulation of this distinctive genre.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
