<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/654823</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR1388</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Critique and Promise in Paul Tillich’s Political Theology: Engaging Giorgio Agamben on Sovereignty and Possibility<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Walter</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">St. Olaf College</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>October 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>90</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>651999</issue-id>
         <fpage>453</fpage>
         <lpage>474</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2010 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/654823"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>This essay is a revised form of a paper presented to the Tillich: Issues in Theology, Religion, and Culture Group for the annual meeting of the American Academy of Religion, Chicago, November 2008. I owe thanks to Peder Jothen, Gary Simpson, and the anonymous reviewers. Their comments greatly improved this essay. All errors that remain are my own.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
      <notes notes-type="epigraph">
         <disp-quote>
            <p>
               <italic>Nec deus intersit, nisi dignus uindice nodus inciderit</italic>. (Horace,<italic>Ars Poetica</italic>, 191–92)</p>
         </disp-quote>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Theologians who seek a firm pact (<italic>ewiger Vertrag</italic>) between themselves and another domain have much at stake in the well‐being of that nontheological partner, especially when it seems that the other sphere has significant difficulties of its own.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>Giorgio Agamben has called attention to problems with the definition of the nature of the political itself. It seems, following his analysis, that the political sphere is unstable and indeterminate in its very constitution. In short, the problem is that the very idea of sovereignty can turn everything into the political. There would in this sense be nothing apolitical, nothing transcending the political sphere in any sense in order to critique or modify it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>This problem of sovereignty leads to the ontological significance of what Michel Foucault called biopolitics, a state of affairs where the very nature of life is inescapably political.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>Perhaps, worse, the indeterminate character of the political under Agamben enervates any prospect for critique by its evacuation of possibility. For to critique is to rely on the possibility that reality might be otherwise than it is.</p>
      <p>Agamben leaves us with more than just his diagnosis. He translates the problem of sovereignty into the relationship between the political and ontology. Paul Tillich’s political theology can engage the unsettled aporia of the political and nonpolitical by use of his conceptions of critique and promise. This requires a reassessment of Tillich’s writing on immanent and transcendent critique and making use of some possibilities available in his writings that he did not see to their end: the critical potential and political significance of the prophetic as promise.</p>
      <p>Such an engagement with Agamben will strengthen Tillich’s conception of prophetic critique and further his contributions to political theology. Reconsideration of Tillich is needed since his conception of the prophetic cannot stand on his own terms. Still further, taking up Tillich will allow theologians to continue a theological correlation project in new ways that do not replicate older patterns and divisions of correlation, especially after the emergence of postsecular thinking. To fail to take up any of these initiatives would reinscribe Blaise Pascal’s cleft between the God of philosophers and of the biblical patriarchs in the domain of politics, an opposition Tillich rejected.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Political theology—by virtue of its dual citizenship—situates itself in both the world of political discourse and theological tradition. This joint residency is very important since it demands that radical critique and the power of gift embrace alongside the kiss of justice and peace. Theology draws its life from the gift of God; the health of the political depends upon critical reflection. Put together, political theology demands a critical involvement, a measure, a publicity that theology has long labored to engage. But the stakes for such a union are higher: one might suggest that the gift is the dire opposite of the critical since the gift demands acceptance; its offering requests that it be taken up or refused while critique seeks to weigh, judge, and obtain distance. Immanuel Kant wrote on behalf of many when he wrote that the gift or the given smacks of the dogmatic and oppressive but having recourse to publicly examinable principles is the gold with which the critical path is paved.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>Because of this challenge of combining the gift and the critical, political theology must heed its practical callings at many ports yet always must return to drop anchor in the harbor of fundamental ontology. Tillich directly contributes to this question since he articulated theological criticism, which he called the prophetic, as a peculiar gift to immanent criticism. When reconsidered in the light of promise and gift, the relationship to prophetic and immanent criticism can offer a modest form of correlation between the political and theology.</p>
      <p>In order to develop this union of the critique and the gift at the site of the political, I will first examine the aporia of sovereignty and the political that Agamben has examined. Next, I will revisit Tillich’s writing on critique and gift and show how that writing can serve more purposes by developing the prophetic in the category of promise. Discovering promise and its peculiar being will lead to his own proposed fundamental ontology and the significance of Tillich’s argument in addressing the aporia of sovereignty.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>John P. Clayton gives an essential account of correlating theology by elaborating two conditions that distinguish it from other approaches to theology in modernity: autonomy and reciprocity. See John P. Clayton,<italic>The Concept of Correlation: Paul Tillich and the Possibility of a Mediating Theology</italic>(Berlin: de Gruyter, 1980), 34–42. The phrase “ewiger Vertrag” comes from Friedrich Schleiermacher’s<italic>Zweites Sendschreiben an Lücke</italic>(1829), in<italic>Kritische Gesamtausgabe</italic>, ed. Hans‐Joachim Birkner, Hermann Fischer, Ulrich Barth, and Konrad Cramer (Berlin: de Gruyter, 1980–), 1, pt. 10:350.30–351.12. See Clayton,<italic>The Concept of Correlation</italic>, 39 n. 15, for discussion of the meaning of this phrase for correlational or mediating theology.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Nikolas Kompridas, without any reference to Agamben, points out in his review of the state of contemporary critical theory the need to provide possibility that elaborates a chance to think and be otherwise than the way things are. See Nikolas Kompridas,<italic>Critique and Disclosure: Critical Theory between Past and Future</italic>(Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2006), 21–23. As Kompridas further points out, the deflation or weakening of criticism by the constriction of possibility or the absence of utopia has been noted in various ways and to diverse ends throughout the history of critical theory from Walter Benjamin to Jürgen Habermas and Axel Honneth.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Foucault first defined biopolitics in these terms: “modern humanity is an animal whose politics calls his existence as a living being into question”; Michel Foucault,<italic>Histoire de la sexualité: La volonté de savoir</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1976), 188.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>“The correlation of ontology and biblical religion is an infinite task. There is no special ontology which we have to accept … to ask the ontological question is a necessary task. Against Pascal I say: The God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob and the God of the philosophers is the same God”; Paul Tillich,<italic>Biblical Religion and the Search for Ultimate Reality</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1955), 85.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>“When I abstract the content of all knowledge, it is either historical or rational. Historical knowledge is<italic>cognito ex datis</italic>, but the rational is rather<italic>cognitio ex principiis</italic>.” Immanuel Kant,<italic>Kritik der reinen Vernunft</italic>(1787) B 864;<italic>AkA</italic>3, 540. He made the connection to the dogmatic at B 764;<italic>AkA</italic>3, 482. I use these by extension to the categories of criticism and gift exchange.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>The Aporia of Sovereignty and the Political Animal</title>
         <p>Giorgio Agamben’s wide‐ranging essay,<italic>Homo Sacer: Sovereign Power and Bare Life</italic>, presents the aporias of political power as rooted in the very nature of the political itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>Agamben begins his study by noting Aristotle’s classical distinction between life (<italic>bios</italic>) and animal life (<italic>zoe</italic>) and the foundation of his inquires on the political animal (<italic>politikon zoen</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>The creation of the political involves the expulsion of bare life from its sphere by the sovereign. This power constitutes itself by its ability to exclude and, strangely, to include the excluded. Agamben aims to understand “why Western politics first constitutes itself through an exclusion (which is simultaneously an inclusion) of bare life.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>Power, in this sense, cannot have any boundaries and so can extend limitlessly and even absorb the outlying territory into its interior.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>
         </p>
         <p>To illustrate the extension of the political through sovereign power, Agamben invokes Herman Melville’s<italic>Bartleby, The Scrivener</italic>, but we might find another figure in the character of the Magistrate from J. M. Coetzee’s<italic>Waiting for the Barbarians</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>This nameless Magistrate displays the inscription of imperial power in his body as the result of the power of the Empire that he serves. The Empire intrudes on his border village when it decides it is at war with the barbarians surrounding it. This Magistrate, long out of the reach of the centers of power on the edge of the anonymous Empire, criticizes the futile efforts of the Empire to combat the barbarians surrounding them and identifies their status as convenient fictions for the Empire’s sovereignty. When the soldiers of the Empire attempt to destroy these barbarians, all they can round up are some fisherfolk. Yet, when the Magistrate undercuts the Empire’s efforts, he is himself arrested, tortured, and imprisoned.</p>
         <p>The Magistrate’s history invokes Agamben’s analysis of power and the constitution of the political as necessarily including what it has rejected, shaping each of its citizens as excluded in potential. As Agamben notes in his introduction, we may make a more modest claim about his argument by looking at what analysis has led us to wonder not just about the “possible articulations of the good life,” as he puts it, but why this definition of the political includes and excludes life itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>This construction of the political in principle can combat and therefore exclude life itself, not just this or that modality of life. Nothing may escape the sovereign since the sovereign may make all into nothing. Or, to put it more strictly, the sovereign already countenances everything within his or her domain as nothing in potentiality, to place sovereign power in the schematic of being and nonbeing, a key to Agamben’s analysis and its resolution in Tillich’s essay.</p>
         <p>As the Magistrate in<italic>Waiting for the Barbarians</italic>discovers, the Empire he serves needs its barbarians in order to exist, no matter how fantastic and phantasmal they really are. As he observes in his small frontier town, wave after wave of military expeditions are unable to engage or defeat any barbarians. But that does not stop the Empire’s use of them to constitute their power, their nation, and their way of ordering human life. Coetzee’s Empire needs them within its bounds just as much as it seeks to expel them without. Lacking flesh‐and‐bone barbarians, it will transform its own servants into them. The Magistrate, calling the Empire’s actions folly, is made into a barbarian.</p>
         <p>For Agamben, this amounts to the chief aporia of sovereignty: though it concerns political life, it turns or can turn any of its own, those who live within the bounds, into bare life, into the outsider. There is no life that is not political and no politics that does not concern life. This situation is biopolitics if not “thanatopolitics.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Giorgio Agamben,<italic>“Homo Sacer”: Sovereign Power and Bare Life</italic>, trans. Daniel Heller‐Roazen (Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 1995).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Aristotle,<italic>Politics</italic>, 1253a1–18.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Agamben,<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>, 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>It seems that one way of addressing Agamben’s concerns would follow from stating that Aristotle does not define the political in essence but distinguishes it on the basis of its appearance, eschewing any attempt to get at the being of the political. Readers of Aristotle are divided on this matter. See the following examinations of Aristotle’s definition of politics: John M. Cooper, “Political Animals and Civic Friendship,” in<italic>Aristotle’s “Politics”: Critical Essays</italic>, ed. Richard Kraut and Steven Skultety (Lanham, MD: Rowan &amp; Littlefield, 2005), 65–90; Richard Bodéüs, “L’Animal politique et l’animal économique,” in<italic>Aristotelica: Mélanges offerts a Marcel De Corte</italic>(Liège: Presses Universitaires, 1985), 65–81; Wolfgang Kullmann, “Man as Political Animal in Aristotle,” in<italic>A Companion to Aristotle’s “Politics,”</italic>ed. David Keyt and Fred D. Miller Jr. (Oxford: Blackwell, 1991), 94–117.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>J. M. Coetzee,<italic>Waiting for the Barbarians</italic>(New York: Penguin Books, 1980).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Agamben,<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>, 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Ibid., 142.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Sovereignty and Potentiality</title>
         <p>Agamben’s complex and provocative thesis merits attention.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>The all‐consuming character of political power challenges political thinkers, as Carl Schmitt did, to seek out notions of power that can escape this problem. But, unlike Schmitt, Agamben translates the problem of power into reflection on being and metaphysics, a correlation that makes it easier to see the theological significance of a political sphere that is radically unstable.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>Even if sovereign power is constituted by the transfer of an inalienable right to the executive, Agamben holds that exceptional powers always threaten polities of every kind, including Western democracies.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>Despite the practical issues this may raise, a sovereign power that retains all potency reserves being for itself and does not permit any way to think otherwise. Agamben argues that Western practices of power find their ontological correlates in the relationship of possibility to actuality. Any way of remedying this aporia must proceed by careful analysis of being to make sense of sovereignty and the political.</p>
         <p>In general, Western thought privileges actuality over possibility in its conception of being. In order to avoid leaving this as an empty and general observation, it is important to note that what is granted actuality by this privilege depends upon the elaborations of what such priority indicates, of course, but the priority of actuality seems to leave possibility as a derivative concept, a shadow or dream of what might be. The significance of Agamben’s examination of the political and sovereignty rests on this privilege granted to actuality over possibility.</p>
         <p>Discussing this potency begins properly with Schmitt’s<italic>Political Theology</italic>. The state of exception in Schmitt’s thought requires a translation or grounding in ontology since he claims that the sovereign decides when the state of exception is in effect.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Because the decision of the sovereign enacts the state of exception, the exceptional always lurks in potentiality. To put Schmitt’s statement in the terms of law, the extraconstitutional exists within the ordinary constituted order. This problem may be further stated as how to anticipate that which exceeds all expectations. No one can plan for the state of exception. As exceptional, it necessarily exceeds the ordinary order of law, constitution, and actuality. Schmitt thought legislative or constitutional efforts to define the exceptional in advance were futile.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>Since the sovereign must have this power to confront the exceptional situation, according to Schmitt, the exception is always within the ordinary constitution of things since the sovereign is ceded “exceptional powers” that can address the unanticipated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>Schmitt argued that this issue of exceptionality affects all polities, no matter their form. Because the sovereign can decide the exceptional, anything may be turned into a state of exception, in Schmitt’s view, even if the sovereign only possesses legitimacy through a democratic regime. Thus, the natural outcome of the possibility of a state of exception is that life is capable of being undone; every citizen is potentially an outcast and bandit, losing one’s ordinary status as a citizen.</p>
         <p>The sort of existence one accords the exceptional or state of exception depends entirely upon the sort of being potency possesses, if one may say that which may be has any existence at all. Agamben makes two points regarding the role of the possible in the political sphere. First, if political life earns its definition by a negative relation and a life ordered by a positive relation to the good, it is constituted by the relation to the exceptional, that which exceeds politics and is therefore included in it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>This means, second, that the potency we possess always threatens to undermine any actual life we have. Agamben defines sovereign power succinctly: the sovereign, by virtue of his or her power, can always undercut life itself.</p>
         <p>The constitution of the ordinary by the excluded, the human by the quasi‐human wolf‐man and the political by the state of exception, demands a new concept of possibility in order to think the political afresh and prevent its downfall into a spiral of pure exceptionality. Agamben states the need clearly: “only if it is possible to think the relation between potentiality and actuality differently—and even to think beyond this relation— … a political theory freed from the aporias of sovereignty remains unthinkable.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>Agamben calls for a potency that is freed from any relation to actuality and so freed from any ban. Just as the outcast or bandit is forever marked, by his or her exclusion, by the ban, being calls for a new conception in order to free it from its cancellation or annihilation. Tillich’s writing on prophetic critique can untie this knot by showing and developing the potency of promise and rethinking that relation. Taking up this promise will issue in alternate practices that engage sovereignty without succumbing to its difficulties.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Agamben does not eschew consideration of political philosophy in the sense that Foucault did, owing to his use of Carl Schmitt’s<italic>Politische Theologie</italic>. Agamben refers to Foucault,<italic>La volonté de savoir</italic>, and his refusal to take up theories of sovereignty in his analysis of power. Foucault seems to have taken more account of these theories in his College de France lectures. See, for instance, Michel Foucault,<italic>Naissance de la biopolitique</italic>(Paris: Editions du Seuil, 2004).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>This is his attempt to find a truly practical thinking that sees<italic>phronesis</italic>as first philosophy. See Giorgio Agamben, “Poesis and Praxis,” in<italic>Man without Content</italic>, trans. Georgia Albert (Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 1999), 68–93.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Giorgo Agamben,<italic>State of Exception</italic>, trans. Kevin Attell (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2005), 1–31.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>“Soverän ist, wer über den Ausnahmezustand entscheidet,” in Carl Schmitt,<italic>Politische Theologie: Vier Kapitel zur Lehre von der Soveränität</italic>, 8th ed. (Berlin: Duncker &amp; Humblot, 2004), 13; “Sovereign is he [<italic>sic</italic>] who decides the exception,” in Carl Schmitt,<italic>Political Theology</italic>, trans. George Schwab (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1985), 5.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>For a discussion of the complex situation surrounding Schmitt’s formulation of the exceptional in the Weimer era, see John P. McCormick,<italic>Carl Schmitt’s Critique of Liberalism: Against Politics as Technology</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), 121–56; George Schwab,<italic>The Challenge of the Exception: An Introduction to the Political Ideas of Carl Schmitt between 1921 and 1936</italic>(Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1989).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>The exception cannot “be circumscribed factually and made to conform to a pre‐formed law”; Schmitt,<italic>Politische Theologie</italic>, 18, and<italic>Political Theology</italic>, 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>It is not bare life or unspeaking life, since Aristotle defines political life through speech and organized work (<italic>ergon</italic>) and not reason. See Aristotle,<italic>Historia animalium</italic>, 488a; there Aristotle groups animals together according to the society they obtain through their activity and not their capacity for reason. Notably, humans and bees are both political animals since they both have a work common to their species.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>Agamben,<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>, 44.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Potentiality and Gift</title>
         <p>The path to address this aporia of the possible in sovereignty begins with Agamben’s invocation of the figure of the gift in his ontological grounding of sovereign power. Since sovereignty is a power that decides what is exceptional and what is not, it is a power that relates the actual and potential to each other, according some actual and others potential being. In order to elaborate the being of sovereignty, Agamben refers to Aristotle’s discussion of potentiality and actuality in<italic>De anima</italic>on the faculties of sensation. In this dense passage Aristotle writes that potentiality is, in fact, saved in actuality as a gift of itself to itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>Agamben renders the word<italic>epidosis</italic>as “giving.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>This dissents from the majority of English translations of this word as “develop” or “alter.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>In his discussion, Aristotle means that by doing something that one has the power or faculty to do does not alter oneself (for instance, as a tree alters itself as it grows) but gives oneself to oneself. Since Agamben’s construal of potency implies that potency and actuality are neither parts of a whole nor subordinate to each other but that potency gives actuality to itself, we find that the actual has no priority to the possible in the power exercised by the sovereign. That which is actual does not represent something that is more real in this scheme than that which is merely possible. Rather, potentiality rules over actuality since it always retains the possibility of giving this or that being at all. This may seem metaphysically exotic since we ordinarily take that which is actual to possess more being than that which is a mere possibility. Actual food tastes better than a potential meal. But this counterintuitive claim made by Agamben about the priority of the possible in sovereignty is part of the dangers that attend it.</p>
         <p>Further analysis of both his statement of potency and his conception of the gift is needed since Agamben’s choice to render<italic>epidosis</italic>as “to give” can imply a kind of agency on the part of the growing tree. Discovering that gifts seem to have agency of their own, of course, is one of the great revolutions brought about by the anthropological study of gift economies. With those initial discoveries, made by Branislaw Malinowski and Marcel Mauss in different works, many important questions have emerged about the character and force of gifts and gift economies. We can take up one of these lines of inquiry in order to focus on the ones that matter for our engagement with Agamben. We have the question whether gifts always and everywhere demand reciprocity or whether it is possible to give a gift that lacks any obligation. Likewise, we could wonder whether the demand to return a gift is pernicious and an act of domination or whether such obligations can be peaceful and purged of all agonism. Beyond the challenges of reciprocity, we can also wonder if there can ever be a gift free of obligation and what such a pure gift might be. All these questions have significance for considering human community, the character of God’s offering to the world, and the like. We take up the gift here not to address all of these issues but to consider the character of the gift involved in Agamben’s analysis of sovereignty and the gift that Tillich’s prophetic criticism offers immanent criticism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This line of inquiry bears greatly upon our question since it seems that the sovereign’s ability to give to another is barred by the sovereign’s retention of the ability to decide the exception. Does potential, when it gives, divest itself of what it has when it gives actuality to itself? Does the white‐on‐white of pure potency ever bear the marks of other color? Perhaps, the giving of actuality by potency is a kind of surplus that does not diminish what being potency has. This sort of gift does not give in the sense of an ordinary gift, a thing alienable from a donor to recipient. Though potency gives actuality to itself, in Agamben’s formulation, what makes sovereignty aporetic is that it always retains itself as potentiality. The sovereign gives to itself and to no other since any gift of actuality that it gives never gives itself away. Barbarians and aliens are included in the political because they are no real outsider, no exception, because the sovereign neither gives to another nor does it receive. Agamben’s aporia approaches the impossibility of a gift, the impossibility of anything ever being given away at all.</p>
         <p>Though actuality appears to be the result of potentiality’s gift, it is not all of what potency is. The gift of actuality to itself exhausts neither the possible nor sovereign. In practical terms, the inalienability of the gift means that the sovereign, even when operating within the limits of a constitution or other political order, always retains the possibility to decide for an exceptional situation and so may suspend the ordinary constitution again. Yet, when the sovereign decides that his or her polity has encountered an exceptional state, it gives without loss, without appearance so as not to violate the conditions for possibility and impossibility of all giving. For potentiality to appear in its entirety as potentiality would amount to its full actualization and so lose its ability to not be. If the gift were to appear at all and so be recognized as a gift, it would appear within a larger field of constraints and subject to critique or demand.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>As the exchange of the gift of being from itself to itself, potentiality or sovereign power demands a return of the being it gives so far as it appears.</p>
         <p>This seemingly reflexive construction of possibility as a gift of itself to itself shows the blind alley facing Agamben and the need to undo this knot or to find ways of engaging it. One of the particular difficulties the problem of sovereignty engenders is that since sovereign power always retains possibility to itself, it evacuates the air of possibility from all corners of space. Lacking any of the resources of the possible, critics cannot propose alternatives to the sovereign. For instance, the idea of natural right and its inalienable character itself can buckle under the state of the exception. Right, which would seem indelible, is an actuality that grounds the political and could never be evacuated. But for Schmitt and Agamben, sovereignty can swipe to one side right with its ability to engage the possible beyond every actuality. Immanent criticism depends upon the discovery of possibility, and when critics lack this ability to think otherwise than the actual, to imagine an alternative to what is, their powers wither. Restoring the critical and the political requires a reconsideration of possibility, sovereignty, and the relationship of critique to gift. To that end we now turn at last to Tillich’s work.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Aristotle,<italic>De anima</italic>, trans. Hugh Lawson‐Tancred (New York: Penguin, 1986), 417b.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Agamben translates the entire passage in this way: “patire non è un termine semplice, ma, in un senso, è una certa distruzione attraverso il principio contrario, in un altro è piuttosto la conservazione (<italic>sōteriā</italic>, la salvazione) di ciò che è in Potenza da parte di ciò che è simile ad esso … Poiché colui che possiede la scienza (in Potenza) diventa contemplante in atto, e questo o non è un’alterazione—poiché si ha qui dono a stesso e all’atto (<italic>epidosis eis eautó</italic>)—ovvero è un’alterazione di altra specie”; Giorgio Agamben,<italic>Homo Sacer: Il potero sovrano e la nuda vita</italic>[in Italian] (Torino: Giulio Einaudi, 1995), 53.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>As done, e.g., in Lawson‐Tancred's translation of Aristotle,<italic>De anima</italic>, 170–71.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Literature that takes up the gift in its philosophical, theological, or anthropological modes abounds. For the phenomenological context, see Jacques Derrida,<italic>Donner le temps: 1, Le fausse monnaie</italic>(Paris: Galileé, 1991), 71–77. Translated into English by Peggy Kamuf as Jacques Derrida,<italic>Given Time: 1, Counterfeit Money</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992), 50–52; Jacques Derrida, “On the Gift: A Discussion between Jacques Derrida and Jean‐Luc Marion, Moderated by Richard Kearney,” in<italic>God, The Gift, and Postmodernism</italic>, ed. John D. Caputo and Michael J. Scanlon (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1999), 58–59. Philosophical and anthropological appropriation of the gift has had a wide history. On this see Karen Sykes,<italic>Arguing with Anthropology: An Introduction to Critical Theories of the Gift</italic>(New York: Routledge, 2005). Many theologians have taken up similar questions as the philosophers and anthropologists in conjunction with God’s grace, human community, the practices of forgiveness and hospitality, and many other matters. For at least one brief overview, see Sarah Coakley, “Why Gift? Gift, Gender and Trinitarian Relations in Milbank and Tanner,”<italic>Scottish Journal of Theology</italic>61 (2008): 224–35.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>“If one recognizes a gift as gift, if the gift appears as such, this simple recognition suffices to annul the gift”; Derrida,<italic>Donner le temps</italic>, 26, and<italic>Given Time</italic>, 14.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Critique and Gift</title>
         <p>Tillich’s political writing frequently unites critique and gift.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>The main resource for our reconstruction is his 1929 essay,<italic>Protestantism as Critical and Creative Principle</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>In this writing Tillich provided an important impulse to examining the aporia between the political and the nonpolitical, and he introduced a different manner of thinking.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>He upheld the two demands of any theology of correlation: there should be reciprocity between the political and theology that does not violate the integrity of each domain. I will show how the lines of thought in this essay on critique and gift alter this correlation project in a way that upholds these essential demands even if it seems to weaken the autonomy of the two domains of the theological and the political. After detailing the lines of Tillich’s essay that we will take up, I will offer a reconstruction of the prophetic as promise. This will issue into a need to develop practices of promise that are otherwise than sovereign.</p>
         <p>In the course of this essay Tillich proposes two kinds of critique: the rational and the prophetic. He had already developed and foregrounded the importance of the prophetic for political theology and continued to do so long after this essay was written. Here, rational criticism is wholly immanent and depends upon the transformation of reason as developed throughout history. Rational criticism does not aspire to an eternal and unchanging set of norms but relies instead upon its immanent and contingent judgments.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>Prophetic critique, on the other hand, is unconditioned.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>It relies on no norm or immanent measure whatsoever; instead, it offers an absolute affirmation and negation to the finite. Since Tillich had worried that the prophetic power of religious socialism and the early dialectical theology would remain abstract and silent before the world, it became decisive for him to articulate the interrelationship of these two kinds of critique in order to uphold the political significance of prophetic critique. He wrote that prophetic criticism is concrete only in a rational form and that it gives depth and boundaries through its limitless source, unbounded grace.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>The prophetic is the site of the gift. We can note a convergence of aims here between Tillich’s aim to bring together the immanent and transcendent productively with Paul Ricoeur’s similar discussion of the economies of equivalence and superabundance in various places.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>Considering the prophetic through the phenomenon of gift exchange will offer us a chance to further articulate the relationship of the prophetic to the immanent through the phenomenon of promise.</p>
         <p>There is, then, for Tillich, no prophetic critique that is not an immanent critique. To claim that there is some finite criticism or norm that we might employ simply as the unconditioned judgment of God would entertain Tillich’s charge of idolatry and demonization.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>The depth of any criticism may be given to it by transcendent and prophetic critique.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Because the prophetic appears within the immanent and never apart from those forms, it is needful to discern when an immanent critique has this depth. If prophetic criticism always has the form of an immanent critique, we need to be able to identify when such an immanent critique bears prophetic depth or when it is merely immanent. Tillich offered few criteria to discern where and when such a depth may be. It would seem that detecting a prophetic critique would easily fail since it does not permit an ordinary canon of judgment or sensibility. It seems there could be no school one could attend to develop this skill. In the essay, like much of his writing, Tillich relied on his concepts of<italic>kairos</italic>and other intuitionist criteria. These criteria succumb to difficulties since they are not readily public in the sense of being readily available or given to the consent of many. So, as some interpreters of Tillich have rightly pointed out, this intuitionism needs discursive or procedural supplementation to develop Tillich’s thought further.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>This reconstruction of<italic>kairos</italic>does not mean abandoning it but revisiting it. His preferred manner of discerning the presence of the prophetic is nondiscursive and immediate, ways that do not aid the development of political theology and its attempt to make itself public.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Though we must expand Tillich’s use of<italic>kairos</italic>, it remains important to uphold his worry that thought or practice might objectify the prophetic and abrogate its giftlike character. I suggest that the promise, as a particular form of gift exchange, can suffice. Failing to uphold the demands of the prophetic will reduce it into specific immanent or natural realities, evacuating any of the power of potential and any ability to engage Agamben’s aporia. Any extension of Tillich’s thought should tend to this dimension of his work since the form of grace, the unconditioned, is the power that drives prophetic criticism.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Tillich’s writings on social and political community and, in particular, his work on socialism are extensive and range from the occasional to the fundamental. It would take us away from the aim of this argument to take up other writings of Tillich’s. The following works, among others, provide important directions in these other areas of Tillich’s writings that have political significance: John R. Stumme,<italic>Socialism in Theological Perspective: A Study of Paul Tillich, 1918–1933</italic>(Missoula, MT: Scholar’s Press, 1978); Ronald H. Stone,<italic>Paul Tillich’s Radical Social Thought</italic>(Atlanta: John Knox Press, 1980); Mark Lewis Taylor, “Tillich’s Ethics: Between Politics and Ontology,” in<italic>The Cambridge Companion to Paul Tillich</italic>, ed. Russel Re Manning (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009), 189–206.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Paul Tillich, “Der Protestantismus als kritisches und gestaltendes Prinzip” (1929), in<italic>Theological Writings</italic>, ed. Gert Hummel, Main Works/Hauptwerke (Berlin: de Gruyter, 1992), 6:127–50 (hereafter cited as MW/HW 6). Translated into English by James L. Adams and Victor Nuovo as “Protestantism as a Critical and Creative Principle,” in<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, ed. James L. Adams (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1971), 10–39. All translations are my own unless otherwise noted. I cite the English translation for reference.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Tillich sought to take up the challenge of constructing a theology that mediated between theology itself and human culture, broadly construed. In this essay (Paul Tillich, “Uber die Idee einer Theologie der Kultur,” in<italic>Writings in Philosophy of Culture</italic>, ed. Michael Palmer, Main Works/Hauptwerke [Berlin: de Gruyter, 1990], 2:69–88), Tillich outlined much of his subsequent task, no matter its lapidary formulations and his shifting use of these concepts, especially as demonstrated by John Powell Clayton (<italic>The Concept of Correlation</italic>, 191–221). Here one may read his proposal for thinking of the relationship between religion and culture as<italic>Gestalt</italic>and<italic>Gehalt</italic>. These two metaphors have either together or singly been the axle and motor of correlation in theology; less so has his writing on critique and prophetic theology. Pursuing these underdeveloped metaphors can aid the reconstruction of a theology of correlation in its various domains, as I have outlined here, at least for political theology.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>“This first form of criticism has a measure and can use it to sort out a Yes and No. That is a rational undertaking even when the measure is not obtained by reason.” Tillich, MW/HW 6:128, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>“The second form of criticism has no measure; for that, which lies beyond all form, cannot turn into a measure and useful form. This criticism therefore does not separate out a Yes from a No. Rather, it binds together an absolute Yes and an absolute No.” Tillich, MW/HW 6:128, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>“The prophetic becomes concrete in rational criticism. Rational criticism obtains its depth and boundary in prophetic criticism”; Tillich, MW/HW 6:131, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>See Paul Ricoeur, “Love and Justice,” in<italic>Radical Pluralism and Truth: David Tracy and the Hermeneutics of Religion</italic>, ed. Werner G. Jeanrond and Jennifer L. Kike (New York: Crossroad, 1991), 187–202. Ricoeur also developed this distinction in Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Course of Recognition</italic>, trans. David Pellauer (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2005), 220–63.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>The critique of finite forms by the form of grace, even those forms in which grace appears, is a necessary “anti‐demonic struggle”; Tillich, MW/HW 6:141, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 29.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>Tillich alternatively characterized this gift of depth as “gravity,” 131; “strength,” 132; “weight,” 134 (<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 15, 16, 18).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Dennis McCann, “Tillich’s Religious Socialism: ‘Creative Synthesis’ or Personal Statement?” in<italic>The Thought of Paul Tillich</italic>, ed. J. L. Adams, W. Pauck, and R. Shinn (San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1984), 81–101; Gary M. Simpson,<italic>Critical Social Theory: Prophetic Reason, Civil Society, and Christian Imagination</italic>(Minneapolis: Fortress, 2002), 33–52. Both McCann and Simpson argue that a more discursive approach to Tillich’s prophetic criticism can address his deficits; they both take up Jürgen Habermas’s proposal for a communicative rationality and discourse ethics.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>As Simpson indicates, Tillich criticizes the role of the heroic or the hero in this essay for being too intuitionistic and therefore not really useful for developing a theology. Taking exception to Tillich’s use of<italic>kairos</italic>or intuitionism, therefore, is still to stay on the grounds of Tillich’s own thought, not to introduce a perspective alien to him. See Simpson,<italic>Critical Social Theory</italic>, 50–52.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Promise as Gift</title>
         <p>For our purposes it is sufficient to indicate that promise is the sign under which the path of criticism, gift, and sovereignty may converge. This advance can be gotten by considering promising in its relationship to gift exchange and the kinds of gift economies considered by Marcel Mauss and his philosophical and anthropological heirs. This connection can bring to the fore a line of thought in Tillich’s reflection on the prophetic as a way to address the aporia of sovereignty that Agamben indicates.</p>
         <p>By considering the phenomenon of promise as a kind of gift, we can see that a promise has features of the pure gift advocated by Jacques Derrida as well as the ordinary gift of Marcel Mauss that can engage the economy of give‐and‐take, the circular exchange of gifts. We do not need to take up whether it can solve other problems facing the various forms of gift as they are used in theology and philosophy. To take up promise as gift means that the phenomenon of promise features altruistic or unilateral moments as well as the ability to effectively interact in the economy of equivalence or reciprocity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>This is an important challenge that Tillich stated early on. He held that the prophetic is other than the immanent. But if it cannot interact with immanent rationality and positively function in that economy, the prophetic will leave the immanent world of politics untouched. For all its radical difference, the prophetic would have no practical significance.</p>
         <p>The divine promise, which demands interaction and development with narrative, time, and its possibility, not only can behave in a way that satisfies the problems of the gift (how can a pure gift be given?) but also enable a sort of possibility, and so sovereignty, that is communicable and dispossessive. To take this up we need to revisit the questions facing the gift we already considered with Agamben. Because it is this sort of gift, promise shares in the unconditioned gift championed by Derrida as well as in the gift that demands reciprocity and competitive giving as articulated by Mauss. The disagreements surrounding the obligation or purity largely concern its ontological significance as well as the sort of force it possesses to press obligation or debt on its recipients, both matters that promise can address.</p>
         <p>Tillich construed the gift and form of prophetic criticism as nonobjective yet present. Grace as a gift cannot be fixed yet must address its recipients if it might give depth to immanent criticism. To avoid fixing the prophetic in a finite form and to prevent prophetic criticism from assuming a plastic and immovable shape in history, Tillich leaned toward intuitionism and the oracular as a way of construing grace as a nonobjective gift. To him, it seemed that the formlessness and nonobjectivity of the prophetic preserves the transcendent from being reduced to the immanent without remainder. This claim has some resemblance to Derrida’s articulation of the pure gift that has no presence. Yet the promise is a gift that anticipates the future and is eschatological in its scope. Indeed, this motion preserves the aleatoric and transcendent character of the prophetic, but such a nonobjectivity could be as apolitical as Tillich thought dialectical theology was by its insistence that God is always other than the world. Tillich wrote that such nonobjectivity and otherness lent itself an abstract character and had no truck with the life of the world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>These goals of Tillich’s must be upheld so that the prophetic can interact with the immanent political sphere. The pure gift needs to interact with the reciprocated gift. Putting together the features of the prophetic, we will see that the gift it offers to immanent criticism is a gift as promise. To proceed, we need to consider the phenomenon of promise.</p>
         <p>A promise is a gift. Yet, it is a gift that warps the ordinary economy of giving. In this, any thinker who develops promise as a gift must attend to those who are interested in interrupting the ordinary gift economies that the anthropologists since Marcel Mauss have considered. Those gifts of equivalence, as Ricoeur called them, are economies that demand gifts to be returned. Because a promise consists of a given pledge and its ultimate fulfillment, it can be considered a doubled and extended gift. We can then generally state that a promise is a doubled gift. The donor promises, offering a token, down payment, or one’s word as the pledge of the promised gift. He or she next fulfills that promise by giving the promised gift. These two gifts are actually a single, doubled gift since they are related to one another by the act of promising and its initial symbolic delivery. Further, the promise is an extended gift since the promissory token and its final gift are separated in time; as Mauss indicated that gifts take and make time, a promise requires time.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>The delay that obtains between the doubled token and gift extends the promise throughout time.</p>
         <p>More important, how a promise is exchanged differentiates it from other forms of the gift along with its doubling and extension. Where the ordinary gift consists of the exchange that leaves the recipient in the debt of the donor, the promise dispossesses itself and inverts the order of debt. The proper worry about gifts is that they inflict debt on their recipients. Mauss indicated that gifts must be returned. Divine gifts in this mode would carry with them a servitude that cannot be escaped. What creature of finite resources can repay a divine gift? A promise reverses this order of debt since the donor has not given anything yet, just a token or word. The donor, not the recipient, assumes the obligation to give in this exchange. This reversal of obligation dispossesses the donor by a radical act of assuming debt rather than issuing it, an act that will allow this reformulation of Tillich’s prophetic critique to address the problem of potency and sovereignty. While the potency Agamben described gives actuality to itself, it indebts or obligates actuality to potency; this means that the existence that actuality possesses always can be returned to pure potential or nothingness. The sovereign may always undo his or her subjects, taking away their actuality or existence.</p>
         <p>Derrida took up another way to think of the gift without these obligations. Comparing his pure gift with the promise, several matters emerge. Because the pledged token is not the fulfillment of the promise itself, it resembles this pure gift. Derrida took as an example of the impossibility of a pure gift a counterfeit coin circulated in Charles Baudelaire’s “Counterfeit Money.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>One dimension of Baudelaire’s brief poem is the ambiguity that attends one character’s gift to a beggar: does he give a real coin and only say it was counterfeit to preserve his dignity in front of his friend, so he might “give in secret” as Jesus demanded?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>The two friends encounter the beggar, offer some money to him, and then the friend of the narrator speculates what might happen with the counterfeit coin. A question hangs over the poem: did the man really offer a counterfeit coin? We must distinguish this coin from the promissory token since a promissory token does not forever defer or resist closure, unlike the putative counterfeit coin that is never tested to see if it is real or not. The promise as an actual gift is ambiguous so long as the pledge remains unfulfilled. No amount of scrutiny of the promised token can disclose whether the promise proves true or not. But the expectation of the recipient need not turn into endless dissemination and deferral. Rather, the token bears a relationship to the future and so the donor, by giving her word, in fact hands over sovereignty, hands over honor, transfers her name to the recipient. This sort of gift is “given back” to the donor when the recipient trusts her. The donor receives honor from the one promised in this trust. The countergift of trust is truly free and uncoerced, since the token is not the gift promised but is its double. The one receiving the pledge of promise never has the promise in actual view but only a word, a pledge, or a mere token. This gift has force so far as the one receiving trusts the one making the promise. In the case of a biblical example, the promises made to Abraham are given to him in tokens, words, and ritual, but they are not themselves the gift promised; this is the case even if we generalize the various scenes of promise.</p>
         <p>This doubled character of a promise satisfies Tillich’s description of prophetic critique. It cannot be fixed yet must appear present.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>If the prophetic were to appear forever cemented in finitude, it would fail to be prophetic, and it would cease to be the transcendent. Likewise, Tillich claims that any “form of grace,” any immanent appearance of prophetic critique, will always anticipate a future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>It will always rightly hold open the hope of a future, a utopia perhaps, or the fulfilled reign of God.</p>
         <p>The sort of possibility and actuality that accompanies this notion of promise Tillich describes in his essay as a giving that is communicable and therefore dispossessive of its own sovereignty. While Agamben’s analysis of potentiality issues in a being that forever retains its own power while giving itself to itself in actuality, being promised communicates itself to another, to the one outside of itself and so offers itself in a differential (the token) so as to fulfill itself to another. Thus, we can see that another kind of possibility is needed to reconstruct the political. The promise addresses, refers, and performs; this is the case even if the promise is in some sense creative of the one that the promisor addresses, as is the case of giving new names to Abram and Sarai. Contrast this with a pure gift that never arrives, never is present to consciousness. The pure gift may interrupt, but it does not create in the way that a gift as promise does. It, as Tillich pointed out, may criticize and negate without ever saying “Yes” or issuing in new forms, actions that all preserve the purity of the gift from any exchange. The pure gift only dwells in the negative, shattering ordinary attempts to fulfill the demands of reciprocity by offering in return a gift of equivalence. Promise issues itself into the field of exchange.</p>
         <p>We may now put the phenomenon of the promise together with the problems of sovereignty in order to address the difficulties about exceptionality and the political raised by Agamben. Promise goes beyond his construal of gift and potency by giving actuality not to itself but to another. It is not a gift that is only given within identity or one that retains the sovereign potential but is instead promised to another being.</p>
         <p>This concept of potentiality in being promised does not rest on a self‐contained or self‐giving gift. If we inscribe the promise in place of the ordinary gift in Agamben’s translation of<italic>epidosis</italic>, we find that the stranger still intrudes on the constituted and ordinary political situation but not in the aporetic way Agamben has demonstrated. Rather, the promise is a gift that addresses another, taking the stranger as neighbor, to serve and dispossesses itself to the neighbor. The agonistic gift is competitive and challenges the other; the pure gift shocks, interrupts, or haunts the other. Derrida’s construction of the stranger, as well as the way the stranger demands an absolute hospitality in the manner of the pure gift, both retain a chasm or equivocity between self and stranger, between home and exile.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>Being promised can address this fundamental chasm, as an analogical approach might, by its dispossession and address.</p>
         <p>Far from resisting transparency and critique, Tillich’s prophetic critique in our modification is one that is debatable, contestable, and weak, a key showing how our proposal is discursive and public. Indeed, this view of promise and critique, if carried out in the political sphere that Agamben considers, would amount to the sovereign handing him or herself over to be judged and accounted for by the barbarian. Put into ontological terms, this being promised communicates itself to the other, not merely to itself, and so risks—steps outside of—itself. In the terms of gift exchange, anyone promising hands over her or his name, his identity, to another. So, the ability of the sovereign to make good on the promise is in question until it is fulfilled. The sovereign awaits the Yes or No of the outsider, the one promised who can credit the sovereign that she or he is indeed worthy of trust. A promise is otherwise than sovereign because it communicates its possibility to another and so makes itself transparent to the other, and, thus, the one promising may be said to dispossess him‐ or herself. To take an important example, Cain may have received the ban from God, but God’s mark of protection holds God in Cain’s debt if Cain trusts God. No sovereign can expel like that, so God’s promising occurs otherwise than sovereign. But it is neither beyond sovereignty nor is it utterly nonsovereign, because the final gift is only available to the one promised by virtue of his or her according truth to the one promising, receiving the promissory token in trust. That first token is still not yet the gift promised. Sovereignty is neither utterly transcended nor is it abandoned altogether. Thus, our development of Tillich’s assertion does not attempt to solve the aporia of sovereignty but rather to offer a way to engage it through practices of promise.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur importantly contends that the logic of equivalence and the logic of superabundance, the reciprocated and the pure gift, are not ultimately opposed. He articulates this in “Love and Justice” and<italic>The Course of Recognition</italic>. Contrast this with John Milbank who, while he rightly wishes to purify the agonism of Mauss’s gift without abandoning exchange or reciprocity, objects to any moment of gift exchange that has a unilateral moment. See John Milbank, “Can the Gift Be Given? Prolegomena to a Future Trinitarian Metaphysic,”<italic>Modern Theology</italic>11 (1995): 139–61.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>“Abstract prophetic critique is effectively conservative”; Tillich, MW/HW 6:130, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 14.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Marcel Mauss,<italic>Essai sur le Don</italic>(1923–24), in<italic>Sociologie et anthropologie</italic>, ed. Georges Gurvitch (Paris: Presses Universitaires de France, 1950), 198–99, and<italic>The Gift: The Reason for Form and Exchange in Archaic Societies</italic>, trans. W. D. Halls (New York: Norton, 1990), 36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>The chancy and indeterminate character of the counterfeit coin that the character in Charles Baudelaire’s eponymous short story gives as alms to a beggar resembles the chancy and indeterminate character of a promise. Both are perhaps “real,” both can be passed off as genuine or as false. This character rests on the “perhaps.” See Derrida,<italic>Donner le temps</italic>, 189ff., and<italic>Given Time</italic>, 149ff.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Derrida did not explore the relationship between giving in secret per se to Baudelaire’s poems in<italic>Donner le temps</italic>except to note that the counterfeit money can never reveal itself to be counterfeit. See Derrida,<italic>Donner le temps</italic>, 95, and<italic>Given Time</italic>, 124.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>“Grace is presence but not object”; Tillich, MW/HW 6:138, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 24. We should not take this as “presence” in the phenomenological sense. Rather, we should consider Tillich to be arguing that grace, though not present as an object among objects, yet has force or agency within the immanent.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>“The relationship between the appearance and non‐objectivity of the form of grace can be defined as ‘anticipation’”; Tillich, MH/HW 6:139, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>See Jacques Derrida and Anne Dufourmantelle,<italic>Of Hospitality</italic>, trans. Rachel Bowlby (Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2000).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc6">
         <title>Otherwise than Sovereign</title>
         <p>In engaging the aporias Agamben articulates, a theologian laboring to consider the political and the theological together should pay heed to Horace’s playwriting advice: do not bring a god into the narrative unless the plot’s problem merits the god’s entrance. The theologian must avoid the temptation to absorb the sphere of the political into the theological and to first consider how forces and agents immanent to the political can attend to the problems facing it. This should not avoid the important insights of Schmitt and others that find that modern political philosophy often has drawn its breath from secularized theological and ecclesiological concepts. Nevertheless, it would do considerable violence to political thought to demand that it depend in its entirety upon prophetic criticism and the form‐without‐form of divine judgment. Instead, we must look for the way that prophetic judgment and its concept of promise has immanent effect and the way that promise itself mediates between the divine gift and the immanent reciprocal gift. This way will articulate a relationship between the theological and the political that continues in the correlational tradition. Once again, it is promise and its being that will permit these connections; we will rely on the interaction and interruption of the promise.</p>
         <p>We can now indicate how this revised form of prophetic criticism as gift can open itself to public reason, afford a free exchange between the political and theological, and sustain the political. Each of these achievements depends upon the nature of the promise as a kind of gift between the pure and agonistic forms of the gift.</p>
         <p>Because the promise extends and depends upon trust, it opens a space fertile for free exchange and responsibility purged of agonism. This free and noncompetitive reciprocity depends upon the doubling of the promise into its initial token and final gift. The first token might be symbolically related to the final gift, as the deed and keys are to the house, but they are simply not the final gift. This difference is decisive for addressing the character of competition and the threat of violent giving, the offer one cannot refuse, since the token is nothing, a trace, perhaps, a little something that requires trust in order for it to have any significance. Because the promise is doubled into a token, it does not have reality without trust. The promisor may indeed go on to deliver the final gift without anyone according him or her truth, but there is no debt created here since the significance of this token depends upon the trust of the one receiving it. It has no force without it and so does not replicate the way the appearance of one bearing gifts carries with it the threat of acceptance or rejection.</p>
         <p>But even when the token is received in trust, there is no debt created since the final gift has not yet arrived. One might feel obligation in anticipation of the gift, but such obligation differs from that in which a gift would actually have been received rather than a gift one might receive. Because of the translation of obligation into the future, it opens up a space for exchange without debt. One can take this token in trust and then offer gratitude in return to God without debt, without obligation in freedom. Derrida constructed the pure gift in order to preserve it from exchange and reciprocity. He did not thereby think that the gift so purified would not affect the world of exchange, forever hovering aloft. Rather, his preferred way of describing the gift is as an interruption, a trace, or cinders that would in some oblique or indirect way haunt or challenge the ordinary economy. By contrast, because the giving of the promise indebts God to the one promised in some sense, this token and final gift enters into the already existing exchange of gifts in human culture or the political sphere. Derrida’s gift, in some of its formulations, could silence immanent political criticism. Tillich feared that aphasia in the political was the consequence of dialectical theology when it refused to allow God to interact with the world for fear of tainting God’s wholly otherness. This refusal would prevent the token offered in promise, as well as the one promised, from entering into the give‐and‐take of life with the token in hand or the trust of the word, even though it can radically challenge by its interruption of gift economy.</p>
         <p>This kind of free exchange shows why promise does not accept the given without a critical reserve; it does not merely endorse political realities as it finds them. It does not introduce new immanent criteria for judging the political; rather, it, as Tillich indicated, opens possibility. The prophetic can provide an engine for addressing the construction of sovereignty as Schmitt has outlined it, as it seems to threaten human life; it can do so by endorsing political practices that are in fact otherwise than sovereign and that involve the establishment of free reciprocity and a field of exchange among equals without domination or debt. This seems to be the task that Tillich ascribes to the congregation: “The congregation should not take itself as a higher sociological form than other forms of community life, rather as a particular expression of the transcendental meaning of sociological forms … such a church that the social forms should elaborate their transcendental content‐meaning.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>The church, Tillich asserts, should be the place for this deliberation and anticipation. In short, he proposes the church as the site of promise.</p>
         <p>All this could work in an adaptation of Tillich’s writing without addressing his intuitionism until we now take up the way to discern and think of the promise in specific gifts and promises. Because the promissory token is itself not a gift in the rudimentary sense but only the initial sign of what the donor promises, its being as possibility additionally enables discourse and debate about the promise. The doubled character of the promise or prophetic can also enable us to think about prophetic criticism as itself debatable. Its status as knowledge is not final and is revisable since the token is but a trace of the final promised gift. It invites trust but does not demand it. This means that any sign already is partaking of the ordinary economy of exchange of gifts.</p>
         <p>The decisive question remains: what is promised? What offered gift can we take as the token‐as‐promise among the wealth of signs and givens that wash through the world? Owing to his view of prophetic criticism, Tillich claimed that yesterday’s prophetic act may be in need of revision and criticism today. This means that few or no signs may be taken as offered tokens. However, it would not be the case, he thinks, that Protestantism simply would carry out a sort of semiotic iconoclasm, wringing its hands, worried that every sign in the world is always a failing. Interestingly, at the end of his essay he turns to the congregation, and there we may find some ways to construe the prophetic as sign of the cross. Tillich does not develop what he calls the protestant form of grace, a chastened form that would dissent in his view from the objectification of what he calls Catholicism. Of course, this is a severely limited judgment on Tillich’s part, since there are many vibrant accounts of the Eucharist—Catholic and Protestant—together with their practical and political significance that are deeply marked by the same engagements and imperatives that Tillich raised.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>These senses of Eucharist still would benefit from reflection on promise, and its local form in the congregation makes better sense when it is framed by the Eucharist as site of promise, gift, exchange, and free reciprocity. Eucharist, briefly, invokes the character of promise as the offering of Jesus’s testament as well as a mutual action that is both communion as exchange between God and creation as well as in and amid creation. It would not take much to think through the Eucharist as the liturgical action and embodiment of promise, to reconsider it and its practice toward being otherwise than sovereign, as I have written here. Suffice it to note that the Eucharist is a meal of betrayal, as the<italic>Verba</italic>always announce: “On the night in which he was betrayed.”</p>
         <p>More, of course, remains to be said about the character of the prophetic and promissory in this scene, the tableau of a table host giving to those who desert him in the moments before his betrayal and eventual execution. Much remains to be developed in conversation with Tillich’s work to continue the work of political reasoning in and with the prophetic, searching for other ways and rationale to take the form or locus of divine promise and the character of the interaction between God’s gift as participation in the divine being, the breath of the Spirit that gives life and the promise that renews all things—all important subjects to which Tillich and others contribute. Nevertheless, the concept of possibility and promised being that we have found can develop and expand a concept of the political that does not include what it excludes, indeed, does not embrace only the abandoned. By finding the sign of the promise, we have discovered that being otherwise than sovereign does not move beyond ordinary sovereignty. It does not seek to dispel the realm of political autonomy with an ecclesial life beyond the realm of nonecclesial humanity. Yet, it recognizes the embrace of the marginal and barbarian that ordinary sovereignty includes by excluding. Finally, owing to the indeterminate character of a promissory note, the pledge, it does not trump, overwhelm, or absorb the world. It rather opens and transforms it from within with its unlooked‐for gift of possibility.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Tillich, MH/HW 6:146, and<italic>Political Expectation</italic>, 36. Gary Simpson identified this emphasis in Simpson,<italic>Critical Social Theory</italic>, 46–49.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>For instance, Hans Urs von Balthasar’s provocative account of the Eucharist: Hans Urs von Balthasar,<italic>Theodramatik</italic>(Einselden: Johannes, 1980), 3:363–78. Von Balthasar’s use of dramatic conceptuality seems to satisfy these demands by offering the Eucharist as a phenomenon that is surprising and free yet deeply imbedded within the economy of creation as a drama. Also of significance would be Bernd Wannenwetsch,<italic>Political Worship: Ethics for Christian Citizens</italic>, trans. Margaret Kohl (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
