<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jamermusisoci</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of the American Musicological Society</journal-title>
            <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">jams</abbrev-journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00030139</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15473848</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jams.2012.65.1.179</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/jams.2012.65.1.179</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Articles</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>
               <italic>Telos</italic>and Temporality: Phenomenology and the Experience of Time in Lewin's Study of Perception</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Maryam A. Moshaver</string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <p>MARYAM MOSHAVER is Associate Professor of Music Theory at the University of Alberta. The focus of her work is on the history of music theory and its intersections with aesthetic, scientific, and philosophical discourses. Her work is published in<italic>Music Theory Spectrum</italic>and the<italic>Dutch Journal of Music Theory</italic>.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <author-notes>
            <fn>
               <p>I would like to thank the anonymous readers for the<bold>Journal</bold>for their generous and insightful comments. Given David Lewin's idiosyncratic system of musical nomenclature, I have preserved his spelling for both chords and perception taxonomies in my own prose so as to present linguistic consistency across this article.</p>
            </fn>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>65</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>jams.2012.65.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>179</fpage>
         <lpage>214</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2012 by the American Musicological Society. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/jams.2012.65.1.179"/>
         <abstract>
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>In his 1986 essay on the intersections between music theory, phenomenology, and perception, David Lewin develops a heuristic model through which to come to terms with the constitution of multiple and heterogeneous perceptions of musical events. One of his principal vehicles for demonstrating this phenomenological turn is the well-known analysis of Schubert's “Morgengruß.” The present article considers the ramifications of Lewin's methodology, particularly with respect to the experience of time that emerges from Lewin's mobilization of the heuristic perception model, by approaching it from the perspective of Husserl's<italic>Phenomenology of Internal Time Consciousness</italic>. This perspective reveals a superposition of temporalities as well as a superposition of languages as the underlying factors through which Lewin's analysis is produced.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>David Lewin</kwd>
            <kwd>Edmund Husserl</kwd>
            <kwd>phenomenology</kwd>
            <kwd>perception</kwd>
            <kwd>music theory</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="36"/>
         </counts>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
