<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JR</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/659287</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR91125</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="aff27" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Sohn</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff27">Chicago, Illinois.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2011</year>
            <string-date>January 2011</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>91</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>656725</issue-id>
         <fpage>122</fpage>
         <lpage>124</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Thistleton</surname>,<given-names>Anthony C.</given-names>
            </string-name> 
            <source>Hermeneutics: An Introduction</source>. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2009. xiv+409 pp. $30.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2011 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/659287"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The purpose and aim of Anthony Thistleton's<italic>Hermeneutics: An Introduction</italic>is to serve as a textbook on the subject, and thus it is written for both the student and for a general readership. Despite some shortcomings, which I will address in some detail below, the work fulfills its essential task insofar as it introduces the reader to the formative thinkers of the hermeneutical tradition, traces significant developments, and isolates key themes that have shaped the history of hermeneutics. Appended to each chapter is a list of further recommended reading, which also provides helpful references for the reader to pursue thinkers, topics, or historical periods of interest more deeply.</p>
      <p>The first two chapters of the book are introductory in nature. In the first chapter, Thistleton sets out to justify the enterprise of hermeneutics by delineating its aim and scope and by distinguishing it from the enterprise of philosophy in general. In the second chapter, he contextualizes and integrates contemporary hermeneutics, through the most recent insights and developments, within biblical studies and literary theory. He concludes this chapter by arguing that a proper understanding of hermeneutics requires a multi- and interdisciplinary approach; such an approach is the impetus for chapter 3, which employs the parables of Jesus as a case study in how a multi-perspectival approach casts different shades and light on a given text. With this more general understanding of hermeneutics in hand, it is to the history and development of hermeneutics that he next turns. In the remaining fourteen chapters, he outlines that history beginning with classical Jewish and ancient Greek thought, tracing it through developments in early, medieval, and modern Christianity and following it on up to contemporary continental philosophy. He concludes this narrative arc by looking at some current approaches to hermeneutics, notably liberation and postcolonialist, feminist and womanist, and postmodernist. Clearly, the scope of the work is vast and the breadth of Thistleton's knowledge is encyclopedic, for it not only spans the history of hermeneutics as such but also engages interdisciplinary approaches in contemporary hermeneutics.</p>
      <p>Throughout the work, his approach is one that focuses on the key thinkers in the history of Western thought so as to illuminate the continuities and changes within the understanding of hermeneutics. Friedrich Schleiermacher, for instance, is named as the first turning point for inaugurating the modern subjective turn in hermeneutics by shifting its task from “rules of interpretation” to the “art of understanding.” He names Hans-Georg Gadamer as the second turning point for retrieving and rehabilitating notions of community, authority, history, and tradition for a more robust and rounded theory of hermeneutics. In addition to Schleiermacher and Gadamer, Thistleton accordingly devotes substantial sections and even separate chapters to other key thinkers in modern hermeneutics such as Wilhelm Dilthey, Rudolf Bultmann, and Paul Ricoeur. Thistleton is at his best in this work when he gives the sustained attention and acute analyses that these seminal thinkers in modern and contemporary hermeneutics deserve.</p>
      <p>Due to the encyclopedic character of the work and the extensive range it covers, however, certain significant thinkers are often treated too quickly, whereas other, more marginal thinkers are treated too closely. This is particularly the case in his treatment of hermeneutics in the “pre-modern” period. For example, in chapter 6, entitled “From the Third Century to the Thirteenth Centuries,” he covers no fewer than twenty-four thinkers. At times, one feels flooded and inundated with a litany of references and historical facts, and it is easy to get confused as to the overall trajectory and purpose of the chapter and how it contributes to the formation and development of hermeneutics. The work would have been better served if it was more balanced and had devoted the same kind of sustained attention and precision to important “pre-modern” thinkers that it devoted to many key figures in modern and contemporary hermeneutics. In the same vein, in the rush to cover the history of hermeneutics, chapters are often oddly divided. For instance, the reader may be surprised to find the thought of Karl Barth lumped in together with structuralism and poststructuralism in a chapter loosely titled, “Some Mid-Twentieth Century Approaches.” It remains unclear as to why such disparate figures and strands of thought are gathered together into a single chapter, and it thus lacks the tightness and coherence of argument that it otherwise could have. If certain sections may glide over thinkers too quickly and other sections pay attention too closely, there are, despite the encyclopedic range of this book, certain gaps altogether in the history of hermeneutics that Thistleton offers. Thistleton himself concedes in his conclusion, for example, that there is insufficient attention paid particularly to Catholic biblical scholarship, which clearly indicates a way of introducing hermeneutics from a distinctly Protestant perspective. Any work that seeks to introduce a subject matter necessarily makes editorial decisions on what gets included and excluded, and such is the case with this work on hermeneutics.</p>
      <p>These criticisms and oversights notwithstanding, there are many redeeming aspects to the book. Insofar as hermeneutics and exegesis are essential for any understanding of religious texts and traditions, Thistleton's work is a good way to be introduced to a complex history, the thorny debates, and the diverse approaches that have come to constitute its history and development. And the copious references that are made throughout and at the end of each chapter will enable readers to probe more deeply into a thinker, subject, or historical period of interest to them.</p>
   </body>
</article>
