<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">revcidafeint</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000726</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Revista CIDOB d'Afers Internacionals</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>CIDOB</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">11336595</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41300916</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Una Europa de complejidad: Otra manera de narrarlo / Europe of complexity: Another way of telling</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
                  <surname>Robins</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                  <surname>Savransky</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>9</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>95</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40058779</issue-id>
         <fpage>59</fpage>
         <lpage>74</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© CIDOB</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41300916"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Este artículo explora cuestiones relacionadas con la nueva diversidad y complejidad de la cultura europea, y procura hacerlo con referencia a debates contemporáneos en torno al cosmopolitismo. Un argumento central es que las ciencias sociales "dominantes" permanecen inadecuadas, en tanto que tratan estas cuestiones de forma abstracta y de manera superficial -sin tocar a nadie. El artículo propone una aproximación más concreta y sustantiva a la agenda cosmopolita -incluso poética-, ofreciendo sugerencias en términos de discursos alternativos relevantes -aquellos que han sido marginados a través de la elaboración histórica de lo que ha devenido la versión hegemónica de la cultura y tradición europeas. Se presenta una exploración de términos como "asombro" y "metamorfosis" (aparentemente obsoletos y quizás excéntricos), así como de la importancia comunicativa del pensamiento metafórico. Se argumenta que, al abordar el dilema cultural europeo contemporáneo, la finalidad es desarrollar un evocativo, y por lo tanto significativo y comunicativo, discurso en torno ai cosmopolitismo -en efecto, otra manera de narrarlo. This article explores issues relating to the new diversity and complexity within European culture, and seeks to do so with reference to contemporary debates on cosmopolitanism. A central argument is that the "mainstream" social science remains inadequate, in that it deals with the issues in an abstract and formulaic way -touching no-one. The article argues for a more concrete and substantive (and even poetic) approach to the cosmopolitan agenda, putting forward suggestions as to relevant alternative discourses -discourses that have been marginalised in and through the historical elaboration of what has become the hegemonic version of European culture and tradition. There is an exploration of such (seemingly obsolete, and maybe eccentric) terms as "wonder" and "metamorphosis", and of the communicative significance of metaphorical thinking. The point in addressing the contemporary European cultural dilemma, it is argued, is to develop an evocative, and thereby more effectively meaningful and communicative discourse of cosmopolitanism -another way of telling.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>spa</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d14060e126a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d14060e133" publication-type="other">
Thilo Sarrazin (2010)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Referencias bibliográficas</title>
         <ref id="d14060e149a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e153" publication-type="other">
ADONIS. An Introduction to Arab Poetics. Londres: Saqi, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e160a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e164" publication-type="other">
ARENDT, Hannah. The Life of the Mind. Volumen 1 : Thinking. San Diego: Harcourt, 1981 .</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e171a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e175" publication-type="other">
BAYART, Jean-Frangois. The Illusion of Cultural Identity. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e182a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e186" publication-type="other">
BERGER, John. Bento's Sketchbook. Londres: Verso, 201 1 .</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e198" publication-type="other">
BONNEFOY, Yves. Genève 1993. Paris: L'Herne, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e209" publication-type="other">
BURKE, Kenneth. Permanence and Change: An Anatomy of Purpose. Berkeley: University of California
Press, 3rd edition, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e219a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e223" publication-type="other">
BYNUM, Caroline Walker. Metamorphosis and Identity. Nueva York: Zone Books, 2001 .</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e230a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e234" publication-type="other">
CANETTI, Elias. The Secret Heart of the Clock. Londres: Andre Deutsch, 1991 .</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e241a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e245" publication-type="other">
CAVELL, Marcia. "Metaphor, dreamworkand irrationality". En: Lepore, E. (ed.) Truth and Interpretation:
Perspectives on the Philosophy of Donald Davidson. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1986. P. 495-507.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e255a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e259" publication-type="other">
CSAKY, Moritz. "La pluralite: pour contribuer a une théorie de I'histoire autrichienne". Austriaca. No.
33 (1991). P. 27-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e274" publication-type="other">
DAVIDSON, Donald. "What metaphors mean". En: Sacks, S. (ed.) On Metaphor. Chicago: University
of Chicago Press, 1979. P. 29-45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e284a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e288" publication-type="other">
DEU'NTY, Gerard y RUMFORD, Chris. Rethinking Europe: Social Theory and the Implications ofEuro-
peanization. Londres: Routledge, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e298a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e302" publication-type="other">
FEJTÖ, Frangois. Requiem pour un empire défunt: histoire de la destruction de lAutriche-Hongrie.
París: Lieu Commun, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e312a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e316" publication-type="other">
KADELBACH, Stefan (ed.) Europa als Kulturelle Idee. Baden-Baden: Nomos, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e327" publication-type="other">
PONTALIS, J-B. Windows. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e334a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e338" publication-type="other">
RICOEUR, Paul. The Rule of Metaphor. Londres: Routledge, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e346a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e350" publication-type="other">
ROBINS, Kevin. The Challenge of Transcultural Diversities. Strasbourg: Council of Europe, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e357a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e361" publication-type="other">
SARRAZIN, Thilo. Deutschland schafft sich ab. Munich: DVA, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e368a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e372" publication-type="other">
SAXON HOUSE, Arlene W. Fear of Diversity: The Birth of Political Science in Ancient Greek Thought.
Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e382a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e386" publication-type="other">
SCOTT, James C. Seeing Like a State. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e393a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e397" publication-type="other">
STEINER, George. Real Presences. Londres: Faberand Faber, 1989</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e404a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e408" publication-type="other">
TOMLINSON, Charles. Metamorphoses. Manchester: Carcanet, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14060e416a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d14060e420" publication-type="other">
ZIMMER, Jorg. "Evozierendes Denken: Ein Beitrag zur philosophischen Poetik". Zeitschrift furAsthetik
und Allgemeine Kunstwissenschaft. Vol. 47. No. 2 (2002). P 167</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
