<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">revirelirese</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100345</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Review of Religious Research</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0034673X</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">43185883</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reading the Bible in America: The Moral and Political Attitude Effect</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Aaron B.</given-names>
                  <surname>Franzen</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>9</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>55</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40124598</issue-id>
         <fpage>393</fpage>
         <lpage>411</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Springer 2013</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/43185883"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The Bible is an important text in American history, but research analyzing the social consequences of reading the Bible is very limited. Research focusing on religious practices or religiosity with Bible reading as part of a scale shows a tendency towards conservatism and traditionalism, as do more literalist views of the Bible. In the present study, biblical literalism is treated as a powerful context guiding one's reading. The focus here is a quantitative view of Bible reading, deploying two 'conservative' and two 'liberal' moral/political scales and two competing views for how Bible reading may function. Results indicate that Bible reading is positively related to both of the liberal scales as well as the conservative scales for non-literalists, but not for those with literalist Bible views. The findings begin to show the importance of independent Bible reading, how it may function differently for literalists and non-literalists, and highlights the degree to which literalism and Bible reading are different constructs.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d1870e171a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e175" publication-type="other">
Ammerman, Nancy T. 1987. Bible believers: Fundamentalists in the modern world. New Brunswick:
Rutgers University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e185a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e189" publication-type="other">
Argue, Amy, David R. Johnson, and Lynn K. White. 1999. Age and religiosity: Evidence from a three-
wave panel analysis. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 38(3): 423-435.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e199a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e203" publication-type="other">
Armstrong, Paul B. 1990. Conflicting readings: Variety and validity in interpretation. Chapel Hill:
University of North Carolina Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e213a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e217" publication-type="other">
Bader, Christopher, F. Carson Mencken, and Paul Froese. 2007. American piety 2005: Content and
methods of the Baylor Religion Survey. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 46(4): 447-463.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e228a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e232" publication-type="other">
Baylor University. 2007. They Baylor Religion Survey, Wave II. Waco: Baylor Institute for Studies of
Religion.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e242a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e246" publication-type="other">
Bielo, James S. 2009. Words upon the word: An ethnography of evangelical group Bible study. New
York: New York University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e260" publication-type="other">
Boone, Kathleen C. 1989. The Bible tells them so: The discourse of Protestant fundamentalism. Albany:
State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e274" publication-type="other">
Carpenter, Thomas P., and Margaret A. Marshall. 2009. An examination of religious priming and intrinsic
religious motivation in the moral hypocrisy paradigm. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion
48(2): 386-393.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e287a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e291" publication-type="other">
Coleman, Simon. 2006. When silence isn't golden: Charasmatic speech and the limits of literalism. In The
limits of meaning: Case studies in the anthropology of Christianity, ed. Matthew Eric Engelke and
Matt Tomlinson, 39-62. New York: Berghahn Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e304a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e308" publication-type="other">
Collins, Randall. 2010. The micro-sociology of religion: Religious practices, collective and individual.
State College: Association of Religion Data Archives Guiding Papers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e319a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e323" publication-type="other">
Crapanzano, Vincent. 2000. Serving the word: Literalism in America from the pulpit to the bench. New
York: New Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e333a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e337" publication-type="other">
Davis, Nancy J., and Robert Robinson. 1996a. Are the rumors of war exaggerated? Religious orthodoxy
and moral progressivism in America. American Journal of Sociology 102(3): 756-787.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e347a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e351" publication-type="other">
Davis, Nancy J., and Robert Robinson. 1996b. Religious orthodoxy in American society: The myth of a
monolithic camp. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 35(3): 229-245.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e361a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e365" publication-type="other">
Dostal, Robert J. 2002. The Cambridge companion to Gadamer. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e372a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e376" publication-type="other">
Dougherty, Kevin D, Byron R Johnson, and Edward C Polson. 2007. Recovering the lost: Remeasuring
U.S. religious affiliation. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 46(4): 483-4-99.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e386a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e390" publication-type="other">
Fish, Stanley E. 1976. Interpreting the 'Variorum'. Critical Inquiry 2(3): 465-485.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e398a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e402" publication-type="other">
Froese, Paul, and Christopher Bader. 2010. America's four gods: What we say about god and what that
says about us. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e412a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e416" publication-type="other">
Froese, Paul, and F. Carson Mencken. 2009. A U.S. holy war? The effects of religion on Iraq war policy
attitudes. Social Science Quarterly 90(1): 103-116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e426a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e430" publication-type="other">
Gadamer, Hans-Georg. 1995. Truth and method. New York: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e437a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e441" publication-type="other">
Hadaway, C.Kirk, and Penny Long Marler. 1993. All in the family: Religious mobility in America.
Review of Religious Research 35(2): 97-116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e451a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e455" publication-type="other">
Hall, Charles F. 1997. The Christian left: Who are they and how are they different from the Christian
right? Review of Religious Research 39(1): 27-45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e465a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e469" publication-type="other">
Hoge, Dean R., and Fenggang Yang. 1994. Determinants of religious giving in American denominations:
Data from two nationwide surveys. Review of Religious Research 36(2): 123-148.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e480a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e484" publication-type="other">
Hout, Michael, and Claude S. Fischer. 2002. Why more Americans have no religious preference: Politics
and generations. American Sociological Review 67(2): 165-190.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e494a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e498" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Byron. 2007. The case for empirical assessment of biblical literacy in America. In The Bible and
the University, ed. David Lyle Jeffrey, Craig Bartholomew, and C. Stephen Evans, 240-252. Grand
Rapids: Zondervan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e511a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e515" publication-type="other">
Keane, Webb. 2007. Christian moderns: Freedom and fetish in the mission encounter. Berkeley:
University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e525a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e529" publication-type="other">
Kellstedt, Lyman A., and Corwin E. Smidt. 1993. Doctrinal beliefs and political behavior: Views of the
Bible. In Rediscovering the religious factor in American politics, ed. David C. Leege and Lyman A.
Kellstedt, 177-198. Armonk: ME Sharpe.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e542a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e546" publication-type="other">
Leege, David C. 1988. Catholics and the civic order: Parish participation, politics, and civic participation.
The Review of Politics 50(4): 704-736.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e556a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e560" publication-type="other">
Levin, Jeffrey S. 1993. Age differences in mystical experience. The Gerontologist 33(4): 507-513.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e568a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e572" publication-type="other">
Long, Elizabeth. 1993. Textural interpretation as collective action. In The ethnography of reading, ed.
Jonathan Boyarin, 180-211. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e582a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e586" publication-type="other">
Malley, Brian. 2004. How the Bible works: An anthropological study of evangelical biblicism. Walnut
Creek: AltaMira Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e596a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e600" publication-type="other">
Marsden, George M. 1980. Fundamentalism and American culture: The shaping of twentieth century
evangelicalism, 1870-1925. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e610a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e614" publication-type="other">
Noll, Mark A. 2001. American evangelical Christianity: An introduction. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e621a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e625" publication-type="other">
Putnam, Robert D., David E. Campbell, and Shaylyn Romney Garrett. 2010. American grace: How
religion divides and unites us. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e635a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e639" publication-type="other">
Reimer, Samuel H. 1995. A look at cultural effects on religiosity: A comparison between the United
States and Canada. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 34(4): 445-457.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e650a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e654" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1976. Interpretation theory: Discourse and the surplus of meaning. Fort Worth: Texas
Christian University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e664a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e668" publication-type="other">
Robinson, Carin. 2006. From every tribe and nation? Blacks and the christian right. Social Science
Quarterly 87(3): 591-601.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e678a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e682" publication-type="other">
Ronald, Emily K. 2012. More than 'Alone with the Bible': Reconceptualizing religious reading.
Sociology of Religion 73(3): 323-324.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e692a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e696" publication-type="other">
Rowatt, Wade C., Jordan LaBouff, Megan Johnson, Paul Froese, and Jo-Ann Tsang. 2009. Associations
among religiousness, social attitudes, and prejudice in a national random sample of American adults.
Psychology of Religion and Spirituality 1(1): 14-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e709a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e713" publication-type="other">
Shahabi, Leila, et al. 2002. Correlates of self-perceptions of spirituality in American adults. Annals of
Behavioral Medicine 24(1): 59-68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e723a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e727" publication-type="other">
Smith, Christian, Michael Emerson, Sally K. Gallagher, Paul Kennedy, and David Sikkink. 1998.
American evangelicalism: Embattled and thriving. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e738a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e742" publication-type="other">
Stark, Rodney, and Jared Maier. 2008. Faith and happiness. Review of Religious Research 50(1):
120-125.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e752a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e756" publication-type="other">
Starks, Brian, and Robert Robinson. 2009. Two approaches to religion and politics: Moral cosmology and
subcultural identity. Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion 48(4): 650-669.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e766a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e770" publication-type="other">
Village, Andrew. 2005. Assessing belief about the bible: A study among Anglican laity. Review of
Religious Research 46(3): 243-254.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e780a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e784" publication-type="other">
Village, Andrew. 2006. Biblical interpretative horizons and ordinary readers: An empirical study.
Research in the Social Scientific Study of Religion 17: 157-176.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e794a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e798" publication-type="other">
Wellman, James K. 2008. Evangelical versus liberal. New York: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1870e805a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1870e809" publication-type="other">
Young, Robert L. 1992. Religious orientation, race and support for the death penalty. Journal for the
Scientific Study of Religion 31(1): 76-87.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
