<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="doi">10.5749</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">culturalcritique</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Cultural Critique</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Minnesota</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08824371</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15345203</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">culturalcritique.86.2014.0001</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5749/culturalcritique.86.2014.0001</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>FRACTURED LIFE AND THE AMBIGUITY OF HISTORICAL TIME: BIOPOLITICS IN AGAMBEN AND ARENDT</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Anthony Curtis Adler</string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <p>
                  <bold>Anthony Curtis Adler</bold>is associate professor of German and comparative literature at Yonsei University in South Korea.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2014</year>
                <string-date>Winter 2014</string-date>
            </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">86</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">culturalcritique.86.issue-2014</issue-id>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>30</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2014 Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/culturalcritique.86.2014.0001"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Examining Agamben's reception of Hannah Arendt, and especially<italic>The Human Condition</italic>, in his theorization of biopolitics, this essay argues that<italic>Homo Sacer I</italic>, by identifying Arendt with a quasi-Straussian “political philosophy,” fails to acknowledge the complexity of her conception of history. Far from simply affirming the normative force of classical political categories, Arendt regards these as emerging from a living power of distinction that thinking, by showing the historical process that brings about the effacement of these distinctions, seeks to bring into view. Nevertheless, Arendt's conception of history is not without contradiction: while arguing that metaphysics went astray by subordinating praxis to poiesis, her very account of history suggests that this subordination is inevitable, since only a “poetic,” indeed violent, act of making a distinction can distinguish praxis from poiesis. Precisely this problem lies at the center of Agamben's early engagement with Arendt in<italic>The Man without Content</italic>.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">In a 2004 interview, Agamben remarked, “I see my work as closer to no one more than to Foucault” (de la Durantaye, 209). And in an interview with Abu Bakr Rieger, he states, “There is no great theoretical difference between my work and Foucault's; it is merely a question of the length of the historical shadow” (<fpage>246</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The transliterated spellings<italic>zoē</italic>(used by Agamben, with an accent mark over the eta in the Italian edition) and<italic>zōē</italic>(used by Arendt) are dialectical variations of the same Greek word and do not correspond to any semantic difference. In citing both authors, I have retained the form that appears in the text cited. Elsewhere I have decided, following Arendt, to use<italic>zōē</italic>, since this is the first spelling given in Liddell-Scott's Greek-English lexicon.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">While Arendt's theorization of totalitarianism and the concentration camps is also important for the project of<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>especially the third part of the first volume, Agamben distinguishes this from her contribution to a biopolitical perspective per se.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See also<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Arendt</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1958</year>,<fpage>313n76</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Here, of course, we detect the influence of Benjamin's “Critique of Violence.” Cf. Agamben 1998,<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For a critique of Arendt's concept of society, see Pitkin, Benhabib, and Bernstein.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1998</year>,<fpage>38</fpage>. For a succinct, largely affirmative analysis of the biopolitical moment in Arendt, see Duarte.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The relationship between<italic>zōē</italic>, “bare life” (in Italian,<italic>vita nuda</italic>)—in essence a translation of Benjamin's<italic>blosses Leben</italic>—and Arendt's “biological life” is complex. The differences between them are sometimes exaggerated and misunderstood. In the introduction to<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>I, they are used more or less synonymously, but as the argument progresses, a more differentiated sense of “bare life” emerges: thus in the third of the three “provisional conclusions” that introduce the final “threshold,” “bare life” is understood as the “originary political element” that is produced through the “fundamental activity of sovereign power,” and as the “threshold of articulation between nature and culture,<italic>zoē</italic>and<italic>bios</italic>” (Agamben 1998, 181). In this sense, Arne De Boever is also right to speak of it as a “third term” introduced alongside<italic>zōē</italic>and<italic>bios</italic>. Yet the difference is really one of perspective rather than referential value: bare life, as the “threshold” of articulation between<italic>zōē</italic>and<italic>bios</italic>, is the point at which the distinction collapses into in-distinction and hence can be grasped in its genesis as distinction. But, for the Greeks,<italic>zōē</italic>is essentially<italic>indistinct life</italic>and<italic>bios</italic>distinct, qualified forms of life. Bare life is not something fundamentally different from<italic>zōē</italic>but is<italic>zōē</italic>conceived in its structural relation—unthinkable to the Greeks—to<italic>bios</italic>and to the political.<italic>Zōē</italic>, one might say, is in-distinction thought from the perspective of distinction (of<italic>eternal ideas or forms</italic>); bare life is in-distinction thought from the perspective of in-distinction.<italic>Biological life</italic>, in a similar fashion, corresponds to<italic>zōē</italic>but also takes on the sense of<italic>bare life</italic>, emerging as the perspective from which<italic>life</italic>becomes thinkable as a unitary process that produces<italic>bios</italic>out of itself. Biological life becomes the way of thinking all forms of life in their emergence.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1998</year>,<fpage>27</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Against the dominant tendency to see an affinity between Arendt's project and the political philosophy of Leo Strauss, Miguel Abensour (2006) maintains that Arendt resists both the scientification of politics and the turn to political philosophy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">As Paul Ricoeur explains, she seeks to establish norms through which to “<italic>judge</italic>the eclipse of politics as the supreme expression of free action and to<italic>condemn</italic>all the attempts to dissolve politics into human engineering” (<fpage>50</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See Edkins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">In<source>
                  <italic>The Man without Content</italic>
               </source>, Agamben explores the meaning and etymology of the Greek<italic>epochē</italic>, understanding it in terms of the double sense of holding back and presenting/offering, and then suggests translating it as “rhythm” (100). This relates to the<italic>katechon</italic>of Paul's second epistle to the Thessalonians: “something that slows and delays the advent of the Messiah” (Agamben 1999a, 114). Of interest in this context is Agamben's discussion of the “Catechontic” dimension of both Carl Schmitt and Erik Peterson (<year>2011a</year>,<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arendt was certainly aware, as Agamben also notes, that the Latin<italic>vita</italic>actually comprises both<italic>bios</italic>and<italic>zōē</italic>. Given this, it is perhaps all the more significant that she reserves the English “life” (or German<italic>Leben</italic>) to signify the concept of life in the most encompassing sense.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arendt identifies<italic>Lebensphilosophie</italic>principally with Nietzsche and Bergson, but she also suggests their proximity to Marx. Indeed, she speaks of “life and labor philosophers” in the same breath (cf. Arendt 1958, 172), and then, in an important footnote, actually refers to all three together as “[t]he greatest representatives of modern life philosophy” (<fpage>313n76</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Agamben begins<italic>Homo Sacer</italic>I with an account of this fracture (<fpage>1</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">It is significant, in this regard, that, as Agamben observes,<italic>zōē</italic>can accept comparative adjectival qualifications, such as<italic>zōē aristē kai aidios</italic>(“a more noble and eternal life”)—it can have<italic>different</italic>qualities predicated or attributed to it—and yet one does not say<italic>zōē politikē</italic>but<italic>bios politikos</italic>. This suggests not only, as Agamben observes, that “simple, natural life” is excluded from the polis but that<italic>zōē</italic>cannot be qualified in such a way as to establish different, substantively distinct regions of life.<italic>Zōē</italic>likewise does not allow pluralization (<year>1998</year>,<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>2</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For Agamben, as Adam Thurschwell notes, “politics is nothing but philosophy”: the constitutive structures of politics and metaphysics are one and the same (<fpage>173</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>Vatter (2006) suggests that Arendt's crucial invocation of “natality” in<italic>The Human Condition</italic>must be situated within biopolitics</source>. It is indeed quite curious, as Vatter notes, that readers of Arendt have paid so little attention to the link between the affirmative characterization of natality, which plays a fundamental role in the structure of action, and the critique of merely “biological life.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For a brief but provocative discussion of the significance of “surplus” for biopolitical theory, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Vatter</string-name>
               </person-group>(<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Many commentators have observed Arendt's delight in making distinctions (Benhabib, 123–24). Yet Arendt's “art of making distinctions,”<source>I would argue, does not so much involve, as for Benhabib, “phenomenological essentialism”—the “belief, particularly prominent in<italic>The Human Condition</italic>
               </source>, that each type of human activity has a proper ‘place’ in which it can be carried out”—but performance: an enactment of the power of biological life to generate distinctions from out of its in-distinction through self-transcendence.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>There is no mention in<italic>The Human Condition</italic>of Dilthey, who appears in Heidegger's<italic>Being and Time</italic>as the principal representative of<italic>Lebensphilosophie</italic>(1979, 46–47)</source>. For Heidegger, the problem with<italic>Lebensphilosophie</italic>is not so much the privilege it grants to life as its failure to interrogate the being of life. For Heidegger, indeed, philosophy stands in so close a relation to life that the term<italic>Lebensphilosophie</italic>is a pleonasm—as redundant as the “botany of plants.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Martin Jay, in his account of Hannah Arendt's dependence on existentialism, is right to stress the “decisionist” and ultimately Nietzschean tendencies in Arendt.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>This, of course, recalls<italic>Being and Time</italic>
               </source>, where death is understood as the “eigenste, unbezügliche, unüberholbare Möglichkeit” (Heidegger<year>1979</year>,<fpage>250</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>We recall Heidegger's characterization of Nietzsche's thought as a “reversed Platonism”</source>(<year>1961</year>, 1:<fpage>188</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <source>We may find an explicit model in Nietzsche: in the<italic>Birth of Tragedy</italic>
               </source>, his account of the tragic death of tragedy makes it possible to think its Wagnerian rebirth.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I would thus contest de la Durantaye's claim that Arendt's influence on Agamben only began to figure prominently in his writings in the early 1990s (<fpage>207</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The first essay in<italic>Nudities</italic>, published in Italian in 2009, could be seen as an attempt to again join together these two historical narratives and establish their inner unity (Agamben<year>2011b</year>,<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arendt conceives of genius, in contrast, as the attempt of<italic>homo faber</italic>to achieve the equivalent of action and speech. The ascent of labor itself brings an end to the age of genius (<year>1958</year>,<fpage>210</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">In the 1988–89 essay prefacing the new edition of<italic>Infancy and History</italic>, Agamben seeks to establish continuity between his earlier work and the emerging project of his mature philosophy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ernesto Laclau calls attention to the utopian aspect of Agamben's thought, arguing that this precludes the possibility of meaningful political interventions (22). Negri suggests, against Agamben's alleged utopianism, the need for a practical yet transformative and revolutionary engagement with the system of production as it exists (<fpage>124</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Abensour, Miguel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2006</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Hannah Arendt contre la philosophie politique?</italic>
               </source>:<publisher-name>Sens &amp; Tonka</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1991</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Language and Death: The Place of Negativity</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Karen E. Pinkus</string-name>,<string-name>Michael Hardt</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1982.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1993</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Coming Community</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Michael Hardt</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1990.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1995</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Idea of Prose</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Michael Sullivan</string-name>and<string-name>Sam Whitsitt</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>SUNY Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1985.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1998</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Homo Sacer: Sovereign Power and Bare Life</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Daniel Heller-Roazen</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1995.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1999a</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The End of the Poem: Studies in Poetics</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Daniel Heller-Roazen</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1996.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1999b</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Man without Content</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Georgia Albert</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1994.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2007</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Infancy and History: On the Destruction of Experience</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Liz Heron</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1978.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2011a</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Kingdom and the Glory: For a Theological Genealogy of Economy and Government</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Lorenzo Chiesa</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 2007.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2011b</year>.<italic>Nudities</italic>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>David Kishik</string-name>and<string-name>Stefan Pedatella</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 2009.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Arendt, Hannah</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1958</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Human Condition</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Arendt, Hannah</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1982</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Lectures on Kant's Political Philosophy</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Ronald Beiner</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Benhabib, Seyla</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1996</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Reluctant Modernism of Hannah Arendt</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bernstein, Richard J.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1986</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Philosophical Profiles: Essays in a Pragmatic Mode</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>De Boever, Arne</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2011</year>.<article-title>“Bare Life.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>The Agamben Dictionary</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Alex Murray</string-name>and<string-name>Jessica Whyte</string-name>
               </person-group>,<fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>de la Durantaye, Leland</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2009</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Giorgio Agamben: A Critical Introduction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Duarte, André.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>.<article-title>“Biopolitics and the Dissemination of Violence: The Arendtian Critique of the Present.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Hannah Arendt: Critical Assessments of Leading Political Philosophers</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Garrath Williams</string-name>
               </person-group>,<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 2004.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Edkins, Jenny</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2007</year>.<article-title>“Whatever Politics.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Giorgio Agamben: Sovereignty and Life</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Matthew Calarco</string-name>and<string-name>Steven DeCaroli</string-name>
               </person-group>,<fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Heidegger, Martin</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1961</year>.<italic>Nietzsche</italic>.<volume>2 vols</volume>.:<publisher-name>Neske</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Heidegger, Martin</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1979</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Sein und Zeit</italic>
               </source>. 15th ed.:<publisher-name>Max Niemeyer Verlag</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1927.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Jay, Martin</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1986</year>.<article-title>“The Political Existentialism of Hannah Arendt.”</article-title>In<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Jay</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Permanent Exiles: Essays on the Intellectual Migration from Germany to America</italic>
               </source>,<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Laclau, Ernesto</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2007</year>.<article-title>“Bare Life of Social Indeterminacy.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Giorgio Agamben: Sovereignty and Life</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Matthew Calarco</string-name>and<string-name>Steven DeCaroli</string-name>
               </person-group>,<fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Negri, Antonio</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2007</year>.<article-title>“Giorgio Agamben: The Discreet Taste of the Dialectic.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Giorgio Agamben: Sovereignty and Life</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Matthew Calarco</string-name>and<string-name>Steven DeCaroli</string-name>
               </person-group>,<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Nietzsche, Friedrich</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1999</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Kritische Studienausgabe in 15 Bänden</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Giorgio Colli</string-name>and<string-name>Mazzino Montinari</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Pitkin, Hanna Fenichel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1998</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Attack of the Blob: Hannah Arendt's Concept of the Social</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2006</year>.<article-title>“Action, Story, and History: On Re-Reading<italic>The Human Condition</italic>.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Hannah Arendt: Critical Assessments of Leading Political Philosophers</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Garrath Williams</string-name>
               </person-group>,<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>. (Orig. pub. 1983.)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Thurschwell, Adam</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2005</year>.<article-title>“Cutting the Branches for Akiba: Agamben's Critique of Derrida.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Politics, Metaphysics, and Death: Essays on Giorgio Agamben's “Homo Sacer,”</italic>
               </source>ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Andrew Norris</string-name>
               </person-group>,<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Vatter, Miguel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2006</year>.<article-title>“Natality and Biopolitics in Hannah Arendt.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Revista de Ciencia Política</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>26</volume>,<issue>no. 2</issue>:<fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Vatter, Miguel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>2009</year>.<article-title>“Biopolitics: From Surplus Value to Surplus Life.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Theory and Event</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>12</volume>,<issue>no. 2</issue>.<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                         ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/theory_and_event/">http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/theory_and_event/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Villa, Dana R.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1996</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Arendt and Heidegger: The Fate of the Political</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
