<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">mosajintestudlit</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013819</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Mosaic: An Interdisciplinary Critical Journal</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Manitoba</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00271276</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">19255683</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">90011634</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>“Don’t You See I’m Burning?”</article-title>
            <subtitle>Comparing Thought to Fire in Freud, Michelangelo, and Wittgenstein</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>WEST</surname>
                  <given-names>WILLIAM N.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <bio>
                  <p>WILLIAM N. WEST teaches English at Northwestern University. He is the author of Theatres and Encyclopedias in Early Modern Europe (Cambridge UP, 2003) and most recently of articles on early modern anatomy and poetry, and architectural meaning. He is currently writing a book called Understanding and Confusion in the Elizabethan Theaters.</p>
               </bio>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>March 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">39</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e90011626</issue-id>
         <fpage>99</fpage>
         <lpage>114</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/90011634"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This essay compares passages from Freud’s<italic>Interpretation of Dreams</italic>, Michelangelo’s sonnets, and Wittgenstein’s<italic>Zettel</italic>that include the image of a burning speaker, and suggests how to make sense of such uncanny repetitions between authors and texts. Comparative interpretation is justified less by theoretical understandings of psychoanalysis than by psychoanalytic practices.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bowie, Malcolm. Psychoanalysis and the Future of Theory. Oxford: Blackwell, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Buonarroti, Michelangelo. The Poetry of Michelangelo. Ed. and trans. James M. Saslow. New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Caruth, Cathy. Unclaimed Experience: Trauma, Narrative, and History. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins UP, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cavell, Stanley. The Claim of Reason: Wittgenstein, Skepticism, Morality, and Tragedy. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Felman, Shoshana. “To Open the Question.” Yale French Studies 55–56 (1977): 5–10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “Analysis Terminable and Interminable.” 1937. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 23. London: Hogarth Press, 1964. 216–53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “Constructions in Analysis.” 1937. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 23. London: Hogarth Press, 1964. 255–69.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. Delusions and Dreams in Jensen’s Gradiva. 1907. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 9. London: Hogarth Press, 1959. 3–95.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “Fausse Reconaissance (‘Déjà Raconté’) in Psycho-Analytic Treatment.” 1914. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 13. London: Hogarth Press, 1955. 201–07.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “Fragment of an Analysis of a Case of Hysteria.” 1905 [1901]. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 7. London: Hogarth Press, 1953. 1–122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “From the History of an Infantile Neurosis.” 1918 [1914]. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 17. London: Hogarth Press, 1955. 1–122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “The Future of an Illusion.” 1927. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 21. London: Hogarth Press, 1961. 5–56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. The Interpretation of Dreams. 1900. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vols. 4 and 5. London: Hogarth Press, 1953.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “Leonardo da Vinci and a Memory of his Childhood.” 1910. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 11. London: Hogarth Press, 1957. 63–137.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. Moses and Monotheism. 1937. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 23. London: Hogarth Press, 1964. 7–137.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. “The Moses of Michelangelo.” 1914. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 13. London: Hogarth Press, 1955. 211-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. Totem and Taboo. 1913. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 13. London: Hogarth Press, 1955. 1-161.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. Die Traumdeutung. 1900. Gesammelte Werke, chronologisch geordnet. Vol 2/3. London: Imago Press, 1942.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freud, Sigmund. Studies in Hysteria. 1895. The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works. Gen. ed. James Strachey. Vol. 2. London: Hogarth Press, 1955.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gallop, Jane. Reading Lacan. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kristeva, Julie. “The True-Real.” 1979. The Kristeva Reader. Ed. Toril Moi. Trans. Seàn Hand. New York: Columbia UP, 1986. 214–37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lacan, Jacques. The Four Fundamental Concepts of Psycho-Analysis. 1973. Trans. Alan Sheridan. New York: W. W. Norton, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lacan, Jacques. “The Freudian Thing, or the Meaning of the Return to Freud in Psychoanalysis.” 1956. Écrits: A Selection. Trans. Bruce Fink. New York: W. W. Norton, 2002. 107–37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lacan, Jacques. “The Function and Field of Speech in Psychoanalysis.” 1953. Écrits: A Selection. Trans. Bruce Fink. New York: W. W. Norton, 2002. 3–106.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Miller, David Lee. Dreams of the Burning Child: Sacrificial Sons and the Father’s Witness. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, Paul. Freud and Philosophy: An Essay in Interpretation. Trans. Denis Savage. New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wittgenstein, Ludwig. Zettel. Eds. G.E.M. Anscombe and G.H. von Wright. Trans. G.E.M. Anscombe. Berkeley: U of California P, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
