<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">jr</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/668266</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR258013</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af13" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Joel</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Harter</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af13">Chicago, Illinois.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>October 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>92</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>665386</issue-id>
         <fpage>573</fpage>
         <lpage>575</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Walton</surname>,<given-names>Heather,</given-names>
               <suffix>ed</suffix>
            </string-name>.<source>Literature and Theology: New Interdisciplinary Spaces</source>. Burlington, VT: Ashgate, 2011. xi+219 pp. $99.95 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/668266"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Genuine interdisciplinary inquiry is demanding, often destabilizing work, and the overall ethos of<italic>Literature and Theology</italic>challenges the “multidisciplinary tourism” that so often passes for interdisciplinary scholarship (35). It is therefore welcome to read Heather Walton’s introductory statement that literature must not be “assimilated by theology,” for literature is “as likely to confound our understandings of faith as to confirm them” (1). Andrew Hass’s appropriation of Paul Ricoeur’s “tensional” theory of metaphor is apt. The ever-ambiguous field of literature and theology is most productive of new insight when the two disciplines are held in tension.</p>
      <p>This tensional approach enables new possibilities for the field. As David Jasper recognizes, literature is no longer (to quote John Wesley) the “handmaid of piety” (5). Accordingly, the field is not limited to art and literature that are explicitly theological or religious, nor is it limited to literature and theology within the Christian traditions. Literature can now both instruct and deconstruct theology. For Jasper, theology is no longer tenable without literature. Invoking Emmanuel Lévinas as well as Ricoeur, Hass helps us to understand why: theology needs the apophatic power of metaphor to redescribe reality and to confront the other that cannot be reduced to any single discipline. Alana Vincent reminds us that this is not easy, nor is this work ever done, but this is what makes the work so valuable. Interdisciplinary inquiry confronts us with insurmountable uncertainties and ambiguities, but these challenges are constructive opportunities to reflect upon the limits of our knowledge, our boundaries, and our disciplines.</p>
      <p>This approach, however, is not altogether new. We must be careful not to presume—as Jasper does—“the impossibility of any systematic theology in a time of the unsystematic and aphoristic” (5). Fragment and system are not mutually exclusive. Aphorism acknowledges the apophatic, and a complex Neoplatonic system informs the negative theology that resonates with many of the essays in this volume. Here, it is encouraging that Jasper, Hass, and Kelly Van Andel all invoke Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Van Andel is correct that Coleridge’s theories of symbol and imagination, as well as his practice as a poet, challenge what often passes for literature and theology by celebrating “open ambiguity rather than closed certitude” (212). Coleridge fails to complete his system—his impossible quest for unity—but he nonetheless articulates (through symbol) a systematic method. To understand this, we must recognize the relation of Coleridge’s symbol to traditional allegory and negative theology via a more careful reading of<italic>The Statesman’s Manual</italic>(London, 1816) that considers (contra Van Andel’s overreliance on Thomas McFarland) the hermeneutic and biblical context of the symbol/allegory distinction in Coleridge’s lay sermon. This is a minor but important adjustment that reinforces the larger claim that the tensional practice of literature and theology can revitalize old truths, for “the renewal of traditions is often accomplished through discomforting processes of radical critique” (2).</p>
      <p>What does this tensional approach look like in practice? A few noteworthy examples illustrate the scope of this collection. In her own essay, Walton destabilizes the conventional hetero-normative ordering of the disciplines. With Julia Kristeva and Luce Irigaray, Walton seeks to reclaim the metaphysical power of the feminine (and the literary) through a genuine “honouring of difference” that stresses “alterity rather than complimentarity” via tension without hierarchy (43). She demonstrates this through brief but insightful readings of Toni Morrison’s<italic>Beloved</italic>(New York, 1987), Ian McEwan’s<italic>Atonement</italic>(New York, 2002), and J. M. Coetzee’s<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>(New York, 2003). Fiona Darroch examines the politics of representation in postcolonial Caribbean literature—specifically, the various ways the literature reimagines the sacred and thereby challenges Western conceptions of the religious and the sacred that persist within comparative religious studies. Finally, John O’Connor exposes the tendency of recent theological aesthetics (following Hans Urs von Balthasar) to ignore or oversimplify aesthetics since the Enlightenment. Theology thereby assimilates aesthetics and fails to take seriously the ambiguities present in actual aesthetic experience—namely, the tensions between our experience and our understanding of beauty as revelatory, including “the possible untrustworthiness of the imagination” (123).</p>
      <p>Symbol is a useful construct for literature, theology, and their intersection. Mark Godin, however, cautions against “owned symbols” that appropriate (or colonize) the other (154). Through a discussion of the contemporary literature of Michael Ondaatje and Gabriel Josipovici that draws on Ricoeur and Graham Ward, Godin argues for the importance of touch and vulnerability within the symbolic world. We must not reduce symbol to the universal or ideal. We experience symbols with our minds<italic>and</italic>bodies, opening ourselves to the other, and confronting together via shared fragments our mutual fragility, our depth and this-ness that cannot be categorized.</p>
      <p>Overall, the essays in this volume admirably correct theology’s tendency to exploit other disciplines for its own purposes. However, there is also the danger that literary-cultural-anthropological approaches will displace theology. A tensional conjunction of literature and theology could prove especially useful for comparative theology. However, with the exception of Darroch’s essay, there is no serious engagement in this volume with non-Christian theology—and, even here, the result is more comparative anthropology than comparative theology. In a similar but more explicit fashion, Mattias Martinson calls for a post-Christian interdisciplinarity that severs theology’s historical ties to Christian practice. Theology thus becomes another cultural science—“a displaced cultural language of the secular” (78)—but can one still call this theology?</p>
      <p>The cultural and social sciences are welcome to examine and critique theology and Christian practice, and theology can profitably learn from these studies, but the studies themselves are not theology. To be theology, even in an interdisciplinary sense, the work must become constructive and speak to the<italic>religious</italic>thought and practice of specific communities or faith traditions. In any given community, theology can become a displaced language in need of renewal, but theology can also uncover the displaced or implicit religion within the seemingly secular. To do this well, theology must remain in critical tension with the cultural sciences, including literature. The result may well be deconstructive, but such radical critique is necessary for any living tradition.</p>
   </body>
</article>
