<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmodernhistory</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Modern History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222801</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375358</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3555585</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/425442</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JMH760304</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Review Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Exile and His Kingdom: The Reception of Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean</italic>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>John A.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Marino</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of California, San Diego</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>September 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>76</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>jmh.2004.76.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>622</fpage>
         <lpage>652</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>©2004 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/425442"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>It is very unusual that an early modern European historian has the opportunity to engage in oral history. I would like to thank Bernard Bailyn, Lydia Cochrane, George Huppert, Richard Kagan, Julius Kirshner, William H. McNeill, and Orest Ranum for their response to questions in either correspondence or conversation. An earlier version of this essay was presented at the UCLA Center for Seventeenth‐ &amp; Eighteenth‐Century Studies and the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library seminar, “Braudel Revisited. The Mediterranean World, 1600–1800” (October 26, 2002), in commemoration of the one‐hundredth anniversary of Braudel’s birth. Fellow panelists Peter Burke and Jacques Revel offered helpful comments. My thanks to Maurice Aymard for valuable offprints and bibliography, and to Michael Bernstein, Terry Burke, Luce Giard, Jules Kirshner, Danny Vickers, and especially Bill McNeill for their generous comments, corrections, and suggestions.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The reception of Fernand Braudel’s<italic>La Méditerranée et le monde méditerranéen à l’époque de Philippe II</italic>would appear to be simple and straightforward in the English‐speaking world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>It has been very well documented, with so much written about the book and its author—by Braudel himself, Mme. Paule Braudel (his wife, research assistant, and collaborator from 1933), Braudel’s colleagues, students, followers, admirers, biographers, and journalists—that one may wonder if anything new could possibly be said.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>Pierre Daix’s 1995 biography, for example, counts the great success of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>in its diffusion: 2,500 copies of the 1949 edition printed, 50,000 of the 1966 second edition and an initial run of 20,000 of that edition in paperback, with translations of the first edition into Italian and Spanish (in Mexico) in 1953 and of the second edition into English in 1972–73, Spanish, Hungarian, and Polish in 1976, Portuguese in 1983, Italian in 1986, Serbo‐Croatian in 1987, Greek in 1991, German, Dutch, and Japanese in 1992, and Chinese in 1996.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>In America, John Elliott welcomed the translation of volume 1 in 1973: “It will doubtless stand as one of the crowning achievements of twentieth‐century historical craftsmanship.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>In England, Helmut Koenigsberger’s 1974 review went further: “It is recognized as a masterpiece, a classic you can compare with the great classics of history writing, from Thucydides to Gibbon and from Macaulay to Burckhardt.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>In 1975, Richard Mowery Anderson revised J. H. Plumb’s initial mixed review in the<italic>New York Times Book Review</italic>(1972) with rave acceptance of “the most significant historical work of our time” as “a revolution in historical thought, the only one commensurate with our century and its global necessities.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>Samuel Kinser declared in a 1981<italic>AHR</italic>graced with a cover photo of Braudel, “If the Nobel Prize were given to historians, it would almost certainly have been awarded to Fernand Braudel.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>By 1992, Peter Burke confidently agreed that it was “a book with a good chance to be regarded as the most important historical work of the century.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>
      </p>
      <p>When, then, should we date the conquest of America by Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean</italic>? Or, as Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt put it, when did America discover the<italic>Annales</italic>?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>No one would dispute the date of the American reception of Braudel to be the five‐year period from the 1972 English translation of volume 1 and the famous December 1972<italic>Journal of Modern History</italic>issue on Braudel to the Inaugural Conference held on May 13–15, 1977, of Immanuel Wallerstein’s Fernand Braudel Center for the Study of Economics, Historical Systems, and Civilizations at the State University of New York at Binghamton.</p>
      <p>In those five short years, “History with a French Accent,” as the<italic>JMH</italic>editor William H. McNeill titled his introductory “fanfare on behalf of this majestic monument of twentieth‐century historiography,” exploded onto the English and American book market in excellent and inexpensive English translation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>The<italic>JMH,</italic>as the official journal of the Modern European History Section of the American Historical Association, stamped the hot‐off‐the‐presses first volume of the Harper &amp; Row English translation of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>(and volume 2 soon to follow in 1973) with its imprimatur.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>Two<italic>Annales</italic>essay collections and a review article on<italic>Annaliste</italic>historiography also appeared in 1972,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>four more translations in 1973,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>two books, a review article and a panel at the AHA annual meeting in 1974,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>and in 1975 the first of seven volumes of collected essays on selected topics from the<italic>Annales.</italic>
         <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>In 1976 Traian Stoianovich’s paean to the<italic>Annales</italic>
         <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>appeared, along with Braudel’s lectures at Johns Hopkins (published in 1977).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>A translation of Le Roy Ladurie’s inaugural lecture to the Collège de France<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>and Braudel’s apotheosis at the inaugural conference of Wallerstein’s Center<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>ended the five‐year period in spring 1977.</p>
      <p>The number of citations and publications of Braudel and the<italic>Annalistes</italic>has continued to grow exponentially from that mid‐1970s moment. An online search of JSTOR’s 242 English‐language journals for all citations mentioning “Braudel” for the years 1927 (when Braudel published his first two French book reviews) through 2000 yields 2,851 items that confirm my periodization.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>Only two Braudel references are recorded in English citations in the 1930s and ten items in the 1940s. But he receives much more notice in the 1950s, with 130 citations—not unexpectedly, given the publication of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>in 1949; and there is double that number in the 1960s, with 285 citations—a total of 525 citations before the December 1972<italic>JMH</italic>issue, which alone includes seven items by the JSTOR method of counting. In the five‐year period from December 1972 through June 1977, JSTOR records 274 citations, about one‐half the number of citations that had come in the previous forty‐five years. And for the twenty‐three years from July 1977 through December 2000, an additional 2,052 citations have appeared in English, for an average of almost ninety citations per year, more than three times the number of annual citations in the 1960s.</p>
      <p>Having confidently answered the easy question of dating the reception, one discovers that three more difficult and interesting questions emerge. First, why was Braudel received so favorably in 1972 but not earlier, after the 1949 first edition of<italic>La Méditerranée?</italic>Second, what do and what should readers take away from the book? After reading 1,082 pages—not counting bibliography or indexes, just text and notes—in the 1966 French second edition, or 1,244 pages in the 1972–73 English translation, what do readers—students, specialists, and general readers—remember? And, third, why should we still remember either Braudel the man (1902–85), especially given the<italic>Annaliste</italic>historiographical tradition’s disdain for biography,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>or his book, now, more than a third of a century after the revised second edition, more than a half century after its original 1949 publication, and almost two‐thirds of a century after its “main outline … was determined if not entirely written by 1939”?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>
      </p>
      <p>In a word, the problem I want to address is memory. That Braudel wrote the first draft from memory as a prisoner of war highlights the theme, but I am especially interested in the relationship between memory and the passage of time—that is, how memory is subject to forgetfulness, manipulation, erosion through honest mistakes that we might call “tricks” of memory, nostalgic distortion, emendation to even scores or inflate résumés, propagandistic monumentalization by keepers of the flame, the information explosion, and the Renaissance commonplace that fame yields to time.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>Pierre Nora has brilliantly examined the problem of memory’s mediation of past and present as “<italic>les lieux de mémoire.</italic>” His specification of the relationship between memory and time locates memory in an untranslatable place, site, or realm and explores memory as “a response to the acceleration of history, to rapid social change, and to the problems of identity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>
      </p>
      <p>There is nothing canonical in my three‐question organization—why the reception happened when it did, what readers remember from the book, why remember the author and his book—but the answers should help us to understand better Braudel’s object of study and how he understood space and time in his holy trinities of plains, plateaus, mountains and<italic>longue durée, conjoncture, événements.</italic>
         <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>I have linked space and time in Braudel’s material world to their appearance between memory and history, because such “realms,” or, in Renaissance terms, “theaters” of memory bring us to the central problem of Braudel’s “possibilism”—that is, individual choice and freedom, what contemporaries considered to be the Renaissance predicament of<italic>fortuna</italic>(determinism) versus<italic>virtù</italic>(human action). This relationship between structure and event is the point of departure for both praise and blame of Braudel, for he “is either praised for his love of the concrete or condemned for his obsession with non‐incremental details.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>
      </p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Fernand Braudel,<italic>La Méditerranée et le monde méditerranéen á l’époque de Philippe II,</italic>1st ed. (Paris, 1949), 2d ed., 2 vols. (Paris, 1966);<italic>The Mediterranean and the Mediterranean World in the Age of Philip II,</italic>trans. Siân Reynolds, 2 vols. (London and New York, 1972–73). See Sam Kinser, “Braudel en Amérique,”<italic>Magazine Littéraire</italic>212 (November 1984): 38–39.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>The bibliography on Braudel and his works has continued to grow since his death in 1985; see, e.g., Maurice Aymard et al.,<italic>Lire Braudel</italic>(Paris, 1988); Bianca Arcangeli and Giovanni Muto, eds.,<italic>Fernand Braudel: Il mestiere di uno storico</italic>(Naples, 1988); Giuliana Gemelli,<italic>Fernand Braudel e l’Europa universale</italic>(Venice, 1990); Paule Braudel, “Les origins intellectuelles de Fernand Braudel: Un témoignage,”<italic>Annales ESC</italic>47, no. 1 (1992): 237–44; Carlos A. Aguirre Rojas et al.,<italic>Primeras jornadas Braudelianas</italic>(San Juan Mixcoac, Mexico, 1993), and<italic>Segundas jornadas Braudelianas: Historia y ciencias sociales</italic>(San Juan Mixcoac, Mexico, 1995); Pierre Daix,<italic>Braudel</italic>(Paris, 1995); William H. McNeill, “Fernand Braudel, Historian,”<italic>Journal of Modern History</italic>73 (March 2001): 133–46; and John A. Marino, ed.,<italic>Early Modern History and the Social Sciences: Testing the Limits of Braudel’s “Mediterranean,”</italic>Sixteenth Century Studies and Essays (Kirksville, Mo., 2002).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Daix, p. 379, n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>J. H. Elliott, “Mediterranean Mysteries,”<italic>New York Review of Books</italic>(May 3, 1973), p. 25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>H. G. Koenigsberger, “Fernand Braudel and the Mediterranean,”<italic>The Listener</italic>(January 3, 1974), p. 10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Richard Mowery Anderson, review of Braudel in<italic>New York Times Book Review</italic>(May 19, 1975), pp. 1 and 45, revises that of J. H. Plumb,<italic>New York Times Book Review</italic>(December 31, 1972), pp. 8, 14, upon the translation of vol. 1. Plumb praises Braudel for his “erudition,” up to a point: “As an intellectual and scholarly tour de force it is almost unequaled; each paragraph is not only erudite, but more often than not pierced with novel insights.… Erudition always dazzles, and Braudel is formidably erudite, but it is not enough; erudition can easily befog, mislead and distort.” Plumb’s strong words zero in on the question of details, the choice of topics of inquiry, and narrative: “Studies of the undergrowth of history, even of those seismic forces which undoubtedly push society in new directions can only be of true historical value so long as they relate and help to explain the narrative of history, and<italic>pace</italic>Braudel, history without events is no history at all—and by events I do not mean the pitter‐patter of everyday life—but the wars, the catastrophes, the conflicts of institutions and religions, class struggles and ideologies, political decisions at the center, and also the inventions, the ideas, the books that have molded human history. These things have made us what we are and what we may be.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Samuel Kinser, “<italic>Annaliste</italic>Paradigm? The Geohistorical Structuralism of Fernand Braudel,”<italic>American Historical Review</italic>86 (February 1981): 63, begins his essay with this statement. Kinser’s important essay is not one of fawning praise, however, but rather critically analyzes Braudel’s methodology of “structural history” and concludes that Braudel offers “an inspiring suggestiveness” more than a model (pp. 104–5): “Braudel’s prose persuades, entices, commands the reader’s assent with its easy roll, its repetitious lilt, its polysemic richness. The coruscating movement from subject to subject launches the reader toward the past with marvelous élan. Braudel’s historical account is like the Mediterranean: a basin full of shifting, sun‐lit water, scintillating with varied and variable insights, ever moving swiftly on. But what then? It is the surface of the text that fascinates, not its depths.<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>itself has been, and remains, rather more of an ‘event’ than a ‘structure.’”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Peter Burke,<italic>History and Social Theory</italic>(Ithaca, N.Y., 1992), p. 16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt, eds.,<italic>Histories: French Constructions of the Past,</italic>trans. Arthur Goldhammer et al. (New York, 1995), p. 349. Alternatively, one might ask, when did America discover structuralism? For the development of structuralism within France and its dominance in French history, see François Dosse,<italic>History of Structuralism,</italic>trans. Deborah Glassman, 2 vols. (Minneapolis, 1997), 1:316–48, with three chapters emphasizing 1966 as the “annum mirabile.” At the same time that the French structuralist wave inundated the United States, it had already crested and was on the ebb in France itself.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>The Mediterranean</italic>cost $17.50 for each 1972–73 cloth volume, and $6.95 for each 1975 paperback volume. In 2002, the paperback cost $34.95 per volume. Today’s higher production costs have greatly reduced the book translation market.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Journal of Modern History,</italic>vol. 44 (December 1972), includes William H. McNeill, “History with a French Accent,” p. 447; Fernand Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” pp. 448–67; H. R. Trevor‐Roper, “Fernand Braudel, the<italic>Annales,</italic>and the Mediterranean,” pp. 468–79; and J. H. Hexter, “Fernand Braudel and the<italic>Monde Braudellien,</italic>” pp. 480–539. Jack Hexter’s wickedly witty parody dubbed it a “classic” (p. 480): “For it stretches credulity to the breaking point to believe that an English commercial publishing house would undertake the translation and issue of a 1,200‐page history book, unless it were a classic.” Hugh Trevor‐Roper, the distinguished Regius Professor at Oxford, began his less memorable article with an inimitable Oxbridge accolade to the French historical profession (p. 468), “No group of scholars has had a greater impact, or a more fertilizing effect, on the study of history in this century than the French historians of ‘the<italic>Annales</italic>school.’” (Is this manure metaphor a double entendre that Trevor‐Roper may have meant to be read as nurturing, getting knee deep into material life, and we might say politely, heaping it on?) And Trevor‐Roper hinted at the problem (p. 472): “His was at once recognized as a historical classic, although, as with many classics, it is difficult to define its peculiar quality.” And, of course, Braudel himself, then seventy years old, after much<italic>JMH</italic>prompting, under the threat of an interview by a graduate student from the University of Chicago (Peter Berger), and only with his wife’s insistence, reluctantly wrote his extraordinarily revealing “Personal Testimony” filled with memories about himself and his book. William H. McNeill (telephone interview, September 17, 2002) credits Mme. Paule Braudel with convincing Braudel to write the memoir himself. Mme. Braudel (“Un témoignage,” p. 28) points to “McNeill’s obstinance” in obtaining it.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Peter Burke,<italic>Economy and Society in Early Modern Europe: Essays from “Annales,”</italic>trans. Keith Folca (London, 1972); Marc Ferro, ed.,<italic>Social Historians in Contemporary France: Essays from “Annales”</italic>(New York, 1972); and Maurice Aymard, “The<italic>Annales</italic>and French Historiography (1929–72),”<italic>Journal of European Economic History</italic>1 (1972): 491–511.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>vol. 2; Fernand Braudel,<italic>Capitalism and Material Life 1400–1800,</italic>trans. Miriam Kochan (New York, 1973); Lucien Febvre,<italic>A New Kind of History,</italic>trans. Keith Folca (London, 1973); and Pierre Goubert,<italic>The Ancien Régime,</italic>trans. Steve Cox (New York, 1973).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie,<italic>The Peasants of Languedoc,</italic>trans. John Day (Urbana, Ill., 1974), and Immanuel Wallerstein,<italic>The Modern World‐System</italic>(New York, 1974), introduced his mentor Braudel and the<italic>Annales</italic>to a wider audience in the social sciences, in a pathbreaking attempt to overturn the Weberian idealist paradigm in sociology with an<italic>Annaliste</italic>‐inspired historical materialist one. Isser Woloch, “French Economic and Social History,”<italic>Journal of Interdisciplinary History</italic>5 (Winter 1974): 435–57; and a panel at the AHA annual meeting in Chicago on December 29, 1974, was dedicated to “The Mediterranean in Economic History: Braudel’s Synthesis Twenty‐Five Years Later,” as described in Traian Stoianovich,<italic>The French Historical Method: The “Annales” Paradigm</italic>(Ithaca, N.Y., 1976), p. 140, n. 12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>The Johns Hopkins University Press series of seven books, Selections from the<italic>Annales, économies, sociétés, civilisations,</italic>was edited by Robert Forster and Orest Ranum with translations by Elborg Forster and Patricia M. Ranum, 1975–82:<italic>Biology of Man in History</italic>(1975);<italic>Family and Society</italic>(1976);<italic>Rural Society in France</italic>(1977);<italic>Deviants and the Abandoned in French Society</italic>(1978);<italic>Food and Drink in History</italic>(1979);<italic>Medicine and Society in France</italic>(1980); and<italic>Ritual, Religion, and the Sacred</italic>(1982).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>Stoianovich,<italic>The French Historical Method.</italic>
               </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Fernand Braudel,<italic>Afterthoughts on Material Civilization and Capitalism,</italic>trans. Patricia M. Ranum (Baltimore, 1977).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>Le Roy Ladurie’s 1973 lecture, “L’histoire immobile,” appeared as “Motionless History,”<italic>Social Science History</italic>1 (Winter 1977): 115–36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>The proceedings, published the following year in the center’s new journal<italic>Review</italic>1, nos. 3–4 (1978), that was modeled on the<italic>Annales,</italic>includes seven articles on the<italic>Annales</italic>reception, impact, or influence. See Jacques Revel on “The<italic>Annales:</italic>Continuities and Discontinuities” in France, pp. 9–18; Maurice Aymard on Mediterranean countries, pp. 53–64; Halil Inalcik on Ottoman studies, pp. 69–96; Krysztof Pomian on Eastern Europe, pp. 101–18; Alfred Dubuc on Quebec, pp. 123–45; Peter Burke on British social history, pp. 147–56; and Richard Mowery Andrews’s summary of the already significant effect of<italic>Annaliste</italic>historiography in American studies in “Historical Writings about the United States,” pp. 165–80. Greatly expanded versions in Jacques Revel, “Introduction” (Revel and Hunt, eds., pp. 1–63), and Peter Burke,<italic>The French Historical Revolution: The “Annales” School, 1929–89</italic>(Oxford, 1989), provide learned and authoritative overviews of the French historiographical tradition.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>Online JSTOR search for “Braudel” in full text in all journals where publication is from 1923 to 2002, conducted 9/25/02. Citations include everything from front and back matter, tables of contents, book notices, and passing reference in an article or book review.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Gemelli,<italic>Fernand Braudel e l’Europa universale</italic>(n. 2 above), pp. 9–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (Eng. trans.), preface, p. 15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>For a systematic study of Renaissance “practices related to memory,” see Lina Bolzoni,<italic>The Gallery of Memory: Literary and Iconographic Models in the Age of the Printing Press,</italic>trans. Jeremy Parzen (Toronto, 2001).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Revel and Hunt, eds. (pp. 631–32), in their introduction to the project directed and edited by Nora; see Pierre Nora,<italic>Realms of Memory,</italic>trans. Arthur Goldhammer, 3 vols. (New York, 1996–98), and Nora’s introduction, “Between Memory and History,”<italic>Representations</italic>26 (Spring 1989): 7–25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>Following Braudel, many critics and reviewers, such as Hexter and Gemelli, have organized their essays into three parts. Two of Braudel’s most important influences relied on tripartite distinctions. Paul Vidal de la Blache,<italic>Principes de géograhie humaine</italic>(Paris, 1922), is divided into three parts: “Human Distribution on Earth,” “Forms of Civilization,” and “Circulation”—all themes central to<italic>La Méditerranée;</italic>and even more tellingly, Henri Berr, in an encyclopedia entry coauthored with Lucien Febvre, “History,”<italic>Encyclopaedia of the Social Sciences</italic>(New York, 1932), 7:357–68, and again in the single‐authored<italic>En marge de l’histoire</italic>(Paris, 1934), 1:12–13, divides historical causality into three modes—contingency (pure data), necessity (institutional), and logic (rational, human initiative). For Berr’s influence on Braudel and the<italic>Annales,</italic>see Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” pp. 454–61.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Hans Kellner, “Disorderly Conduct: Braudel’s Mediterranean Satire,”<italic>History and Theory</italic>18 (May 1979): 205.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <label>I.</label>
         <title>The U.S. Reception</title>
         <p>To return to 1972, then, neither the English publication of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>nor the proclamations of the<italic>JMH</italic>’s editor and two distinguished English‐language authorities on either side of the Atlantic made Braudel’s book a classic. It already had arrived. When Hexter, in his 1972<italic>JMH</italic>article, mined early reviews of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>to examine “some of its flaws” and later quoted critical “fragments from appraisals,” he did so not because “the appraisals themselves were unfavorable. Quite to the contrary, most of them were sympathetic, some enthusiastic.” Rather, Hexter wanted to point out that, despite the reviewers’ “overall judgment,” they displayed “similar misgivings” about Braudel’s success in achieving his goal of integrating multilayers of time, especially the short‐term events in Part III.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>But did early reviewers share more than “misgivings”?</p>
         <p>The three most influential American journals in the field—<italic>The American Historical Review, The Journal of Economic History,</italic>and<italic>The Journal of Modern History</italic>—all published favorable reviews in 1950.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>Garrett Mattingly of Columbia set the tone in his January<italic>AHR</italic>review. Despite criticisms and caveats about Part III, he concluded: “But this review should not close on a note of disparagement. Whatever its faults, this is a brilliant, exciting, and profoundly stimulating book, a creditable labor of scholarship and historical imagination. Every student of sixteenth century history ought to read it; every lover of the art of history should welcome it.” Melvin M. Knight of Berkeley, a French colonial historian,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>reviewed<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>in the<italic>JEH</italic>in a neutral fashion by thoroughly describing the book’s contents and emphasizing its revisionist theses and evidence in five pages, “The Geohistory of Fernand Braudel,” but he withheld judgment except for praising its coverage of Mediterranean history as “admirable.” Richard A. Newhall from Williams College, an expert on the Crusades and late medieval England and Normandy, wrote a one‐page<italic>JMH</italic>review that emphasized Braudel’s impressive efforts, details, and suggestiveness but found that the author posed more questions than he answered and opined that “probably Braudel would disclaim any intent to do more than provide information leading toward a possible synthesis by some future historian.” For his part, Braudel, no doubt, would have made no such disclaimer; he surely believed he had presented that very synthesis.</p>
         <p>The most often cited example of American historians’ early resistance, naiveté, or misunderstanding with respect to Braudel’s work is Bernard Bailyn’s “Braudel’s Geohistory—a Reconsideration” in the Summer 1951<italic>Journal of Economic History,</italic>which, readers will recall, had just reviewed<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>six months before in its November issue.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>Bailyn (b. 1922) was then a twenty‐nine‐year‐old graduate student at Harvard, a war veteran, and was writing in a confident, mature voice after a year of study in Paris. He was hardly naive; in fact, he was deeply influenced by the<italic>Annales.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>Asked about his review, Bailyn emphasizes that “there was no twenty year gap before recognizing Braudel and the<italic>Annales.</italic>”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>Rather, the<italic>Annales</italic>were fully assimilated, but Braudel was simply not writing good history.</p>
         <p>Bailyn’s diction and derision in his 1951 review are devastating. He found Braudel’s tripartite temporal schematization “an exhausting treadmill … Braudel has mistaken a poetic response to the past for an historical problem … there was no central problem Braudel wished to examine.” He repeated his assessment that “what is painfully lacking from this huge, rambling book is the integration of its parts that could result from the posing of proper historical questions … [and that] Braudel could overcome the naturally resulting incoherence only by classifying, separating, compartmentalizing.” Bailyn chastises Braudel for not knowing “the most elementary teaching of the sociologists about social change … that no important element moves in isolation.” He argued that the book was “uncritically heralded” by “[Lucien] Febvre’s passionate encomium” in the 1950<italic>Revue historique</italic>because of the felt need for new principles of synthesis due to the “avalanche of specialized monographs as well as the historical studies of the social scientists.” Bailyn concluded with a categorical rejection of “Braudel’s book [as] a revolution in historical method” and echoed the December<italic>JMH</italic>judgment of Newhall, who had been an important influence on Bailyn in college, that Braudel’s work was “rather a summary in three parts of a large body of knowledge.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>
         </p>
         <p>What some may think was the rhetoric of a young Turk trying to make his mark, or simply a critique growing out of U.S. historiography’s long antitheoretical tradition, I believe can instead be explained in three complementary ways. First, Bailyn was not alone in finding fault with the lack of integration in Braudel’s tripartite structure. In a 1957<italic>JMH</italic>article, “French Scholarship in Modern European History: New Developments since 1945,” Edward R. Tannenbaum characterized the debate as one between conventional and innovative history: “[Braudel’s<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>] has stimulated an international controversy between conventional historians and those who want history to include the techniques of other disciplines in an all‐embracing synthesis.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>Hans Kellner, writing in<italic>History and Theory</italic>(1979), summarized the early criticism of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>as posing the question, “Was the work an enormous heap of diverse materials or a truly revolutionary step in historical methodology?”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Second, Bailyn, who went on to an extraordinary career in U.S. colonial history,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>was expressing his own early views on ideas and methods in history, which belong to a long pragmatic tradition in American historiography that he still affirms today: “I was never interested in the application of theories or models of any kind to history, and have never referred to any such writings in anything I’ve written.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>Bailyn expressed views similar to those in his 1951 review of Braudel twenty‐five years later in a<italic>JEH</italic>(1977) book review of Stoianovich.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>With a wider audience before the “bully pulpit” he occupied in his 1981 AHA Presidential Address, he again took aim at Braudel to make his point: “Braudel’s<italic>Méditerranée</italic>has been justly celebrated for its wealth of information, much of it esoteric, and its revealing, at times brilliant, descriptions of the way people lived; but it should be known too for its ahistorical structure, which drains the life out of history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>In 1994 Bailyn’s position on French historical scholarship remained much the same: “Braudel, of course, was a great historian, but the structure of his famous book on the Mediterranean is metahistorical; it’s directed not at history but at certain notions about the nature of history, which is quite different.… It’s a different way of thinking about history … as historians [the French] live in a somewhat different world.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>Bailyn remembers his original Braudel review and his further engagement with French<italic>Annaliste</italic>history in a matter‐of‐fact way, as part of his constant vision of history: “There is nothing dramatic in any of this. I was studying French medieval history and reading the French historical journals, came on Braudel, and wrote what I thought. Subsequently I’ve followed up somewhat on the problems I saw in his kind of history. My current work on Atlantic history is explicitly the opposite of Braudel’s Mediterranean history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Third, Bailyn represented a new approach to economic history, that of entrepreneurial history.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>Economic history in America was itself a relatively new discipline that was greatly stimulated by the World Wars, the postwar recovery, and subsequent problems from the Great Depression to the Cold War.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>Edwin F. Gay, himself an economic historian, who was founding dean of the Harvard Business School in 1907 and cofounder of the National Bureau of Economic Research in 1920, promoted the establishment of two institutions in 1940, the Economic History Association and the Committee for Research in Economic History (CREH), which spawned entrepreneurial history as a research agenda.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>The Rockefeller Foundation provided funding to establish the offshoot Entrepreneurial History Research Center at Harvard in the academic year 1948–49.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>The entrepreneurial ideology of the Center emphasized the creative individual as risk taker and prime mover in making choices for economic change and growth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The curious problem about Bailyn’s review is why the<italic>JEH</italic>published this second rather long review so soon after Melvin Knight’s very professional review the previous November. Since reviews are usually commissioned, not unsolicited, who or what was behind this piece?</p>
         <p>We should look, I believe, to the silent partners in Bailyn’s review, the<italic>JEH</italic>coeditors: the great Venetian economic historian Frederic C. Lane (1900–84)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>at Johns Hopkins, and the distinguished U.S. economic historian Thomas C. Cochran (1902–99),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>then at the University of Pennsylvania—both promoters of the entrepreneurial history philosophy. The editors of the<italic>JEH</italic>had announced a new policy in the winter 1951 issue, the number immediately following the Knight review: The journal was being expanded from a biannual to a quarterly, and it would include a new section dedicated to “Review Articles and Discussion.” The<italic>JEH</italic>would not necessarily exclude a book “merely because it has once been reviewed here. Accordingly we are making this flexible arrangement for appraisal and reappraisal of important contributions to economic history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>Perhaps the editors were not pleased with the Knight review and sought another scholar with good French and entrepreneurial history sympathies to intervene in the discussion on the reception of Braudel’s work. Bailyn, for his part, initially recalled that “I came on Febvre’s ecstatic review of Braudel [in<italic>Revue historique</italic>(April–June 1950)]. So I read the book, and was rather shocked at its non‐historical nature and the other things that I wrote in the short piece. I wrote the piece and sent it in. The issues I found in the book went to the main concerns I had about historical thought, and writing seemed to be worth the trouble.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>Possibly Bailyn may have also been aware of Braudel’s work through his mentor Newhall’s December 1950<italic>JMH</italic>review, which might have prompted him to write an expanded review on his own per the new<italic>JEH</italic>policy. Regrettably, Bailyn does not remember the details of the submission of his revew.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>Solicited or not, Bailyn’s review was published by the<italic>JEH</italic>editors, as it expressed their entrepreneurial history agenda.</p>
         <p>Although Lane knew Braudel’s<italic>Méditerranée</italic>well enough in September 1950 to refer to its description of the inland sea’s economic realities as “brilliantly pictured,” as the Europeanist coeditor of the<italic>JEH</italic>he planned the journal’s expansion with Cochran and would have been well aware of Bailyn’s pending June 1951 negative review before he left the coeditorship that year.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>Lane and Braudel had not met in the Venetian archives when Braudel and Mme. Braudel worked there during their Brazilian winter vacations in 1935 and 1936; in fact, they only met for the first time in Paris, when Lane, as assistant director of the Division of Social Sciences of the Rockefeller Foundation, was based there for two years—from June 1951 (the very time that Bailyn’s<italic>JEH</italic>review appeared) until summer 1953.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>In Paris, Lane provided important funding for the Ecole, worked with Clemens Heller to develop “area studies” in the Cold War reconstruction of European academic institutions and intellectual life, and played an important role in introducing American‐style social sciences, especially a modern kind of economics that emphasized theory, statistics, and history and was intended to supersede the traditional business law discipline of the French university.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This<italic>JEH</italic>“conspiracy” theory thickens with the addition of Earl J. Hamilton (1899–1989), who was president of the Economic History Association (the<italic>JEH</italic>’s parent organization) in 1951–52 and was long connected with the Harvard CREH.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>In addition to having his invisible hand on the<italic>JEH</italic>editorial board, Hamilton was a professor of economic history at the University of Chicago and editor (1948–54) of Chicago’s prestigious<italic>Journal of Political Economy.</italic>Hamilton, who is mentioned frequently in the Braudel biographical materials, is remembered fondly as a great friend from the Spanish archives in Simancas starting in the summer of 1928.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>One would have expected a review of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>in Hamilton’s journal. The only mention is an October 1949 citation in “Books Received”; there is no review.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>This omission is even more curious since Braudel’s coauthored book with Ruggiero Romano on Livorno shipping was reviewed in Hamilton’s journal in June 1952.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">58</xref>Was Hamilton being polite to save his old friend the embarrassment of a bad review or snubbing him for a book Hamilton’s entrepreneurial history orientation did not approve?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">59</xref>With only sixteen citations of Braudel in the<italic>Journal of Political Economy</italic>(and two of those were in book notices, two in tables of contents, and two as part of paid advertisements for other publications), one could safely say that France’s leading economic historian of the postwar era, whose main interest in that discipline was in the power of markets, was not only a persona non grata but even a persona incognita to the market‐mantra driven Chicago School of Economics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">60</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In sum, economic, diplomatic, and Renaissance historians—all from Braudel’s closest subdisciplines—rejected<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>on disciplinary and intellectual grounds and delayed Braudel’s U.S. reception. First among the detractors were the leaders of economic history at Chicago, Hopkins, Columbia, and Harvard, who opposed Braudel’s French‐style economic history.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">61</xref>Braudel’s own generation of economic historians among the Americans—Hamilton (b. 1899), Lane (b. 1900), and Cochran (b. 1902)—were the ones who blackballed his book and promoted Bailyn’s early negative reception of it. Similarly, the diplomatic historian Garrett Mattingly (1900–1962), whose<italic>AHR</italic>review had praised Braudel’s “originality and boldness,” still expressed strong reservations about<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>’s repetitiveness, its selective use of evidence, and its many banal generalizations. Mattingly was “compelled to admit that the third section … [on] war and diplomacy … is disappointing … not merely because the account seems relatively perfunctory, and written without much enthusiasm, but chiefly because” it did not connect with what went before. Mattingly later would tell Columbia graduate students in Renaissance history of his strong opposition to Braudel.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">62</xref>And, incredibly, the U.S. Renaissance studies establishment let Braudel’s book pass in silence. Although his 1949 volume did not seem to garner much attention in U.S. scholarly journals early on, in autumn 1950 the New York bookseller Gregory Lounz took out a half‐page advertisement in<italic>Renaissance News</italic>announcing the availability of<italic>La Méditerranée.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">63</xref>Neither that journal (1948–66) nor its successor,<italic>Renaissance Quarterly</italic>(1967–98), however, reviewed either of the French editions or the English translation of Braudel’s book.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">64</xref>Finally, intellectual historians in the Harvard historiographical tradition generally mirrored the rejection of Braudel. H. Stuart Hughes, for example, denigrated Braudel’s book since it “marked a further step away from clarity of thought and presentation … was sprawling and invertebrate … lack[ing] a discernible focus.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">65</xref>
         </p>
         <p>What happened to<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>among English and American readers in the next twenty years from 1951 to 1972 to make it a “classic” that was no longer disapproved? Lawrence Stone (1919–99) described the postwar English mood of “boundless optimism … [on the part of] us young men who returned from war in 1945”: “We were dedicated converts to the<italic>Annales</italic>school of history based in Paris, and we were certain that the most intractable problems of history would soon fall to the assaults of quantitative social and economic investigation.… We waited breathlessly for each new issue of<italic>Annales</italic>or the<italic>Economic History Review,</italic>every one of which seemed to contain an article which opened up great new vistas of historical exploration and interpretation.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">66</xref>Demand from a number of English publishers in the early 1960s led Braudel to attempt what some of his friends and colleagues considered sacrilegious, if not impossible—to revise the already‐classic 1949 first edition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">67</xref>Likewise, a new American generation—for example, William McNeill (b. 1917), Robert Forster (b. 1926), and Orest Ranum (b. 1933), with the Harvard cohort of Bailyn (b. 1922) and Hughes (b. 1916) serving as the exceptions proving the rule—heard Braudel’s literary evocation of a vast geographic world, the synthetic claims of global history, and the use of social scientific methodologies as ushering in a new kind of history.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">68</xref>Braudel’s April 1968 seminar in Chicago and his spring 1976 lectures at Hopkins solidified his newfound audience in American academia.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">69</xref>Trevor‐Roper (b. 1914) identified such delayed acceptance as in the nature of a classic: “A classic, by definition, breaks through the accepted standards of its time, by which it must at first be judged. It may take a generation before it is absorbed and can be examined critically.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">70</xref>What exactly did this younger generation of English and U.S. historians—not necessarily economic, diplomatic, nor intellectual history specialists—find in Braudel?</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Hexter (n. 11 above), pp. 513, 531–32.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Garrett Mattingly,<italic>American History Review</italic>55 (January 1950): 349–51; Melvin M. Knight, “The Geohistory of Fernand Braudel,”<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>10 (November 1950): 212–16; and Richard A. Newhall,<italic>Journal of Modern History</italic>22 (December 1950): 365.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Knight, the lone American scholar to cite the young Braudel in the 1930s, listed Braudel among the fifteen named authors in a book review of J. Alazard et al.,<italic>Histoire et historiens de l’Algerie,</italic>in<italic>American Historical Review</italic>38 (October 1932): 110–11, and later in a footnote citing the Alazard book in “French Colonial Policy—the Decline of ‘Association,’”<italic>Journal of Modern History</italic>5 (June 1933): 214, n. 14. But Knight makes no reference to Braudel or his article in the collection “Les Espagnols en Algérie” in either text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, “Braudel’s Geohistory—a Reconsideration,”<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>11 (Summer 1951): 277–82.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>For biographical information on Bernard Bailyn, see the International Seminar on the History of the Atlantic World (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~atlantic/bailyn.html"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~atlantic/bailyn.html</ext-link>) and Jack Rakove, “Bernard Bailyn: An Appreciation,”<italic>Humanities</italic>19 (March/April 1998): 8–13, available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.neh.fed.us/news/humanities/1998-03/rakove.html"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.neh.fed.us/news/humanities/1998‐03/rakove.html</ext-link>). Bernard Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 11, 2002: “I was very much involved in medieval French history as a graduate student in 1951 as a consequence of studying with Prof. Charles Taylor, a wonderful medievalist whose courses in medieval French institutional and intellectual history I found fascinating. I was then reading all the relevant French historians (Bloch above all, but also Febvre, Fawtier, Tilly [the geographer], de Lagarde, Lousse, Luchaire, Focillon, Renouard, Pirenne, etc.). I still have some of their books and the French historical journals that came to hand, esp.<italic>Annales</italic>(whatever it was called then) and for some reason that curious Marxist existentialist journal<italic>Esprit</italic>(I must have been the only American subscriber to<italic>Esprit</italic>).” On<italic>Esprit,</italic>a leftist, Catholic journal founded in 1932, see<italic>Esprit: Une revue dans l’histoire 1932–2002</italic>(Paris, 2002), pp. 27–33. Between 1945 and 1954,<italic>Esprit</italic>rejected the Christian democratic political program in France, and its postwar, pro‐Marxist writers engaged Marxism in probing theoretical and practical debate on the pressing political and social questions of the day.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 11, 2002, continues, “Soon after [the Braudel review in 1951], I developed an active interest in Goubert and the other French demographic historians whose writings have had a significant influence on what I have worked on. I was aware too of the sociologists (my father‐in‐law Paul Lazarsfeld and his colleagues at Columbia and here [at Harvard] kept me up on some of what they were doing).” Lazarsfeld (b. 1901, Vienna) taught at the Sorbonne and the Ecole’s Sixth Section in 1962–63; he contributed an essay to the two‐volume Mélanges en l’honneur de Fernand Braudel, “Toward a History of Empirical Sociology,” in<italic>Méthodologie de l’histoire et des sciences humaines</italic>(Toulouse, 1972), pp. 289–301. See also Paul F. Lazarsfeld, “An Episode in the History of Social Research: A Memoir,” in<italic>The Intellectual Migration: Europe and America 1930–1960,</italic>ed. Donald Fleming and Bernard Bailyn (Cambridge, Mass., 1969), pp. 270–337. Even Americans without Bailyn’s French language skills would have found French scholarship readily available in English before the 1970s: Marc Bloch’s<italic>Strange Defeat</italic>in 1940,<italic>The Historian’s Craft</italic>in 1955,<italic>Feudal Society</italic>in 1961,<italic>French Rural History</italic>in 1966, and collected essays in 1967, and Lucien Febvre’s<italic>A Geographical Introduction to History</italic>in 1925 and<italic>Martin Luther</italic>in 1929. For the younger generation of social scientists associated with Braudel at the Sixth Section of the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, English translations of Claude Lévi‐Strauss’s<italic>Tristes Tropiques</italic>appeared in 1961 and<italic>Structural Anthropology</italic>in 1963. In fact, Clyde Kluckholm had Talcott Parsons offer Lévi‐Strauss a tenured professorship at Harvard in 1953, but Lévi‐Strauss (who had been a fellow professor with Braudel in Brazil in the mid‐1930s and later taught in New York at the New School during the war) declined, remembering later, “I had no desire to start life as an exile again,” cited in Marcel Hénaff,<italic>Claude Lévi‐Strauss and the Making of Structural Anthropology,</italic>trans. Mary Baker (Minneapolis, 1998), p. 254.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Bailyn, “Braudel’s Geohistory,” and Newhall,<italic>JMH</italic>review. On Bailyn and Newhall, A. Roger Ekirch, “Sometimes an Art, Never a Science, Always a Craft: A Conversation with Bernard Bailyn,”<italic>William and Mary Quarterly</italic>51 (October 1994): 627, quotes Bailyn on his influences at Williams College for two and a half years beginning in 1940 and cut short by the war: “I drifted toward the opposite influence within the faculty, whose main figure for me was Richard Newhall. … He was a rather cynical, hard‐bitten, tough‐minded empiricist and, in a very different way, also an attractive intellectual.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>Edward R. Tannenbaum, “French Scholarship in Modern European History: New Developments since 1945,”<italic>Journal of Modern History</italic>29 (September 1957): 247.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Kellner (n. 26 above), p. 200.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Bailyn’s 1953 thesis would become his first book,<italic>New England Merchants in the Seventeenth Century</italic>(Cambridge, Mass., 1955). Rakove, “Bernard Bailyn” (n. 31 above), explains that Bailyn made his first big mark in American history a decade later, “but his arrival as a major force in American history and letters had to await the publication of the first edited volume of<italic>Pamphlets of the American Revolution</italic>in 1965. Its lengthy introduction, originally titled ‘The Transforming Radicalism of the American Revolution,’ was reprinted two years later as<italic>The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution.</italic>Not since Charles Beard published his<italic>Economic Interpretation of the Constitution</italic>in 1913 has a single book so radically transformed the writing of American history.” For more on Bailyn, see Bernard Bailyn,<italic>On the Teaching and Writing of History: Responses to a Series of Questions,</italic>ed. Edward Connery Lathem (Hanover, N.H., 1994), and Ekirch.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 11, 2002, continues, “But Weber’s quite historical ideas about religion and economic life interested me, and the<italic>New England Merchants</italic>was undertaken as the perfect test of those ideas; I ended up endorsing emphatically R. H. Tawney’s quite un‐Weberian views and switching the theme to class structure, or the lack thereof.” See Bailyn’s more detailed comments in Ekirch, pp. 630–31. Peter Novick,<italic>That Noble Dream: The “Objectivity Question” and the American Historical Profession</italic>(Cambridge, 1988), pp. 373, 398, and 579, cites Bailyn extensively on how professional historians choose research topics and the place of philosophy in history.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, review article of Traian Stoianovich,<italic>French Historical Method,</italic>in<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>37 (December 1977): 1028: “This is a paradoxical, puzzling book—as paradoxical and puzzling as its subject matter. Like the<italic>Annales</italic>school itself, it combines intelligence with word‐intoxicated vaporizing, hard research with abstract schematizing, creative imagination with self‐indulgence; and it consequently manages to be both elevating and depressing, informative and obscure.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, “The Challenge of Modern Historiography,”<italic>American Historical Review</italic>87 (February 1982): 5, continues: “For the essence and drama of history lie precisely in the active and continuous relationship between the underlying conditions that set the boundaries of human existence and the everyday problems with which people consciously struggle. The goal of history is not to separate out events of these different dimensions at a particular point in time but to show their continuous interaction in an evolving story. The drama of people struggling with the conditions that confine them through the cycles of limited life spans is the heart of all living history, and the development of that drama itself, not a metahistorical scheme of classifying events, must provide the framework for any effective interpretation of history.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Bailyn’s recognition that the French produced history in a different intellectual milieu and with a different question in mind is cited in Ekirch, pp. 643–44.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 11, 2002.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Ibid: “I and the others I was working with in graduate school and after were well aware of what the French, including Braudel, were doing, and some (like Landes and Sawyer at the Entrepreneurial History group here) were doing their main work on French topics.” Harvard University Press published Bailyn’s 1955<italic>New England Merchants</italic>in its Studies in Entrepreneurial History series. For an example of the ideas of Sawyer and Landes in those years, see S. A. Sass,<italic>Entrepreneurial Historians and History: Leadership and Rationality in American Economic Historiography 1940–1960</italic>(New York, 1986), pp. 180–83, and their early articles (John E. Sawyer, “Strains in the Social Structure of Modern France,” and David S. Landes, “French Business and the Businessman: A Social and Cultural Analysis,” in<italic>Modern France: Problems of the Third and Fourth Republics,</italic>ed. Edward Mead Earle (Princeton, N.J., 1951; New York, 1964), pp. 293–312, 334–53), which apply social and cultural factors to economic history analysis regarding redevelopment of postwar France.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Michael A. Bernstein,<italic>A Perilous Progress: Economists and Public Purpose in Twentieth‐Century America</italic>(Princeton, N.J., 2001), pp. 84, 94, 100, and 120, discusses how theory and practice were linked, especially in the professional training of economists. Sass (pp. 1–28) traces the development of economic history in the United States, with emphasis on its early “fragmented and poorly defined” character.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Bernstein (pp. 42–45, 66) on Gay as a key figure in joining academic economics with government policy and foundation funding. Sass (pp. 29–90) traces Gay’s career and his idea of entrepreneurial research as modified by Arthur H. Cole, chair of the CREH, in his 1946 EHA presidential address, “An Approach to the Study of Entrepreneurship: A Tribute to Edwin F. Gay,”<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>6, suppl. (1946): 1–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Sass, pp. 53–153. The Rockefeller Foundation had provided $250,000 to the CREH in winter 1940–41 for four and a half years funding (p. 58) and decided to fund the Harvard Entrepreneurial History Research Center on May 21, 1948 (pp. 88–89), despite lukewarm support from Harvard itself. Rockefeller funding sustained the Center until early 1958, with specific projects also supported by other granting agencies such as the Carnegie Corporation (p. 91). See also Novick (p. 310) on foundation funding for area studies as part of their Cold War initiatives.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Sass (pp. 107–54) and the Center’s newsletter/journal,<italic>Explorations in Entrepreneurial History,</italic>vol. 1 (1949).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>For short biographies of Lane, see the University of Venice website: “Frederic C. Lane: Profilo biografico,”<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://helios.unive.it/~riccdst/sdv/storico/lane/profilolane.htm"
                            xlink:type="simple">http:/helios.unive.it/~riccdst/sdv/storico/lane/profilolane.htm</ext-link>; Reinhold Müeller, “Frederic C. Lane: Un profilo, con bibliografia aggiornata,”<italic>Ateneo veneto</italic>22 (1984): 169–275; and the foreword by Braudel, “Biographical Note,” and “Bibliography of Frederic C. Lane, 1924–66,” in<italic>Venice and History: The Collected Papers of Frederic C. Lane</italic>(Baltimore, 1966), pp. v–xiii, xv–xviii, 543–49. Lane began graduate work at Harvard in 1925 and completed his Ph.D. in 1930 under the direction of Roland P. Usher. He was a member of the informal East Coast Institute of Entrepreneurial History that preceded the Harvard Research Center in 1947–48, as noted in “The Origin of the Harvard Research Center,”<italic>Explorations in Entrepreneurial History</italic>1 (January 1949): 2; much later he published one article with the Entrepreneurial History group, “Investment and Usury in Medieval Venice,”<italic>Explorations in Entrepreneurial History,</italic>2d ser., 2 (1964): 3–15. Two earlier articles demonstrate Lane’s links to entrepreneurial history: “Force and Enterprise in the Creation of Oceanic Commerce,” in “The Tasks of Economic History,” Supplement to the<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>10 (1950): 19–31 (reprinted in<italic>Venice and History,</italic>pp. 399–411), was a paper delivered at the Tenth Annual Economic History Association meeting, September 15–16, 1950, and examined the relationship between government and business enterprise in the sixteenth century; and “Some Heirs of Gustav von Schmoller,” in<italic>Architects and Craftsmen in History, Festschrift für Abbott Payson Usher</italic>(Tübingen, 1956), pp. 9–39 (reprinted in<italic>Venice and History,</italic>pp. 462–95), reviews the contributions to economic history of the German forefathers of U.S. economic history (especially at Harvard)—Schmoller, Werner Sombart, Arthur Spiethoff, Joseph A. Schumpeter, and Walter Eucken. Among his many honors, Lane was coeditor of the<italic>JEH</italic>1943–51, president of the Economic History Association in 1958, AHA president in 1964, and International Economic History Association president in 1965.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Sass (pp. 75–79, 174–80) describes Cochran’s close connection with the Harvard Entrepreneurial History Research Center. Cochran received his Ph.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1930, taught at NYU for more than twenty‐five years, was coeditor of the<italic>JEH</italic>1946–55, received a year’s resident fellowship in the first year of the Harvard Center in 1948–49 while attempts to hire him permanently at Harvard failed, returned to Penn in 1950, and capped his career as AHA president in 1972.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>11 (Winter 1951): 1–2 is signed by the editors, Cochran and Lane, who explained the new policy. In the fall issue, the<italic>JEH</italic>would publish the papers of the annual meeting of the Economic History Association. “In the winter, spring, and summer numbers, comment and reporting on the current literature of economic history and allied fields will fill about half of each issue, or perhaps a little more than half, as it has in past issues of<italic>The Journal.</italic>This half of<italic>The Journal</italic>will now contain two parts: ‘Review Articles and Discussions’ and ‘Reviews of Books.’ Under the first of these general headings will be published the more extended reviews devoted to recent works of importance, but we include ‘Discussions’ in the title of this section because we plan to present here critical analyses that focus on a theme rather than on a book. In a review, the reviewer is under obligation to give a judgment on the whole of the publication under consideration. We believe there should be opportunity also to discuss a theme or thesis without assuming obligation to give a balanced judgment on the whole book within which it has been presented.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 11, 2002. For Febvre’s review, “Un livre qui grandit:<italic>La Méditerranée et le monde méditerranéen á l’époque de Philippe II,</italic>”<italic>Revue historique</italic>203 (April–June 1950): 216–24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Bernard Bailyn, personal correspondence, October 12, 2002, writes in response to the specific question whether his<italic>JEH</italic>submission was a solicited or an unsolicited review, “I don’t remember in any detail the circumstances of submitting the review. It’s possible I knew about the new policy of the<italic>JEH,</italic>but I don’t recall anything about that specifically.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Lane, “Force and Enterprise in the Creation of Oceanic Commerce,” p. 23: “Spices were again moving through the Red Sea in as large a volume as ever—an aspect of that continued commercial predominance of the Mediterranean in sixteenth‐century Europe which has been brilliantly pictured in Fernand Braudel’s recent volume.” (N.B. the<italic>Venice and History</italic>reprint, p. 403, deletes the word “recent” from the original text.)</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>“Frederic C. Lane: Profilo biografico” (n. 47 above) gives Lane’s dates and mission in Paris. Before beginning his graduate studies at Harvard and developing his career in Venetian history, Lane studied in Bordeaux (1923–24) and Vienna (fall 1924). His first two articles were published in French in the<italic>Revue historique de Bordeaux</italic>(1924–26); see<italic>Venice and History,</italic>pp. xv–xvi, 549. Braudel was honored to write the 1966 foreword to<italic>Venice and History,</italic>pp. v–xiii, in which he expresses his gratitude for Lane’s friendship, scholarship, and intelligence.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Gemelli, pp. 301–23 (n. 2 above); Daix, pp. 292–94 (n. 2 above), reports that Lane provided Braudel with a $5,000 Rockefeller grant toward Venetian studies for the Centre de recherches historiques and that the Braudels visited Columbia, Harvard, Chicago, Berkeley, and Princeton in 1955 on an “area studies” fact‐finding junket. Heller (1917–2002), an Austrian immigrant who moved with his family to the United States in 1938 and a Harvard graduate, was one of the founders of the 1947 Salzburg Seminar dedicated to the intellectual reconstruction of Europe and the study of American civilization. Founder of the “Marshall Plan of the Mind,” Heller came to Paris in 1949; and, with his plans for reviving social science and knowledge of American institutions, he became one of Braudel’s closest collaborators in postwar French intellectual and institution‐building projects. See also Dosse,<italic>History of Structuralism</italic>(n. 9 above), 1:166–72, “The French School of Economics Takes a Structural Path.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>Sass (n. 42 above), pp. 58–59; Hamilton was one of the nine members of the original CREH.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” pp. 451–52; Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage” (p. 240), reports that Hamilton was jealous that he couldn’t find a similar camera to make microfilm anywhere; and Daix (pp. 76–78) reports on Hamilton’s aggressive playfulness in postwar debates among the researchers. Jacques Revel, personal communication, October 26, 2002, reports that upon Braudel’s election to the Académie française in 1984, Hamilton made an unusually large contribution toward the<italic>épée d’académicien</italic>for the new member.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Journal of Political Economy</italic>57 (October 1949): 460.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>Robert L. Reynolds, book review of<italic>Navires et merchandises a l’entrée du port de Livourne (1547–1611), Journal of Political Economy</italic>60 (June 1952): 265. At the same time, Hamilton himself had written warmly to Braudel to visit the United States in January 1952; see Gemelli (n. 2 above), p. 160, n. 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>Personal interview with Earl J. Hamilton in the Department of Economics, University of Chicago, January 1978. I met Hamilton, then almost eighty, to ask about some specific kinds of illegal, extraeconomic documentation that I had found in Simancas the previous summer. Hamilton preferred to reminisce about his own archival forays and couldn’t help himself in expressing his very strong dislike for the Braudels and their standoffishness during research in foreign archives. His was an active, passionate animus, whether of jealousy, old or new causes I could not say. My colleague David Ringrose reports a similar conversation with Hamilton that corroborates Hamilton’s strong dislike for Braudel. Hamilton’s private correspondence in the Duke Library might yield some concrete explanation. The Hamilton collection is described in Special Collections Library, Duke University (where Hamilton taught 1927–44),<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://scriptorium.lib.duke.edu/economists/hamilton"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://scriptorium.lib.duke.edu/economists/hamilton</ext-link>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>JSTOR search for “Braudel” in the<italic>Journal of Political Economy</italic>through the year 2000. In England, the<italic>Economic History Review</italic>similarly excluded Braudel. One reference is made to Braudel in Paul Leuilliot, “Recent French Writings in the Social and Economic History of Modern France,”<italic>Economic History Review,</italic>2d ser., 1 (1949): 63, which identifies F. Braudel as “an expert on Mediterranean history and author of an outstanding thesis (to be published by Armand Colin) on the Mediterranean under Philip II” and gives the titles of three recent articles. A JSTOR search for “Braudel” in the<italic>EHR</italic>finds 168 citations through 1997; but there is no review of either<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>’s 1949 or 1966 editions.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>David S. Landes, “The Statistical Study of French Crises,”<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>10: (November 1950): 195–211, rebuts both the theoretical foundation and empirical reality of the problems and methods of price history as presented by Ernest Labrousse and his student M. A. Chabert. On Landes and France, see also Gemelli (n. 2 above), pp. 256–57, and Robert Forster, “Achievements of the<italic>Annales</italic>School,”<italic>Journal of Economic History</italic>38 (March 1978): 66–69, which surveys contributions to the<italic>Annales</italic>discipline by discipline and explains why its method and conclusions about economic history lost out in the international economic history community and were abandoned in favor of sociology and anthropology in France itself.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>Mattingly (n. 28 above), pp. 350–51. Julius Kirshner, email correspondence, September 12, 2002: “For sure, I can say that G. Mattingly’s opposition to Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean</italic>(which, as a graduate student at Columbia, I had heard from GM’s own lips) had a lot to do with its late reception in the USA.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Renaissance News</italic>3 (Autumn 1950): back cover, p. 60.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>A JSTOR search of<italic>RN</italic>and<italic>RQ</italic>through 1998 finds thirty‐nine references to Braudel in advertisements, book notices, conferences, citations in articles, and reviews of other books, but no review of any of his books.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>H. Stuart Hughes,<italic>The Obstructed Path: French Social Thought in the Years of Desperation 1930–1960</italic>(New York, 1968), pp. 58–59, cites his Harvard colleague Bailyn’s review. Hughes presents his passing judgment on Braudel in a chapter on Marc Bloch and Lucien Febvre, “The Historians and the Social Order,” as part of his critical outsider’s view on the often celebratory tone that the French historical profession has of its historiographical tradition, especially in his praise for Bloch and disapproval of Febvre (p. 55).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>Lawrence Stone, “A Life of Learning,”<italic>ACLS Newsletter</italic>36 (Winter–Spring 1985): 12, captures his ironic tone: “In Britain, the post‐war period was a time of boundless optimism and confidence.… To us young men who returned from the war in 1945, the whole world seemed to be our oyster, and all problems of scholarship—to say nothing of those of suffering humanity—were thought to be soluble.… In history, some of us had much the same hubristic confidence in a wholly new approach. We were dedicated converts to the<italic>Annales</italic>school of history based in Paris, and we were certain that the most intractable problems of history would soon fall to the assaults of quantitative social and economic investigation. The political narrative mode of our elders—‘L’histoire historisante’ as it was derogatively called—was beneath our contempt. In time, we believed, such hitherto unsolved problems as the causes of the English or the French Revolutions, or the origins of capitalism and the rise of the bourgeoisie, would be solved by our new tools and new approaches. Bliss it was to be alive and a radical social historian in 1945. We waited breathlessly for each new issue of<italic>Annales</italic>or the<italic>Economic History Review,</italic>every one of which seemed to contain an article which opened up great new vistas of historical exploration and interpretation.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>1:13–14, preface to the English edition, states that the prospect of an English translation prompted the second revised French edition in 1964. Braudel’s memory is unfortunately untrustworthy here, however, for the preface to the second edition is dated June 19, 1963, and its conclusion dated two years later, June 26, 1965. The clear plan for revision articulated in the second edition preface suggests that Braudel had been thinking about the revised edition for some time in 1963 or before. The English publisher Routledge had a contract for the translation, but I have not been able to discover who or how many other of these “several English‐language publishers” there were.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn69">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>McNeill, telephone interview, September 17, 2002, and Gemelli (n. 2 above), p. 208, n. 63, remembers quite vividly being invited to New York by Hugh Van Dusen of Harper &amp; Row after McNeill’s 1964 National Book Award for<italic>The Rise of the West.</italic>Van Dusen asked McNeill if he had read any good books lately that he would recommend, and McNeill mentioned Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean,</italic>which he remembers reading circa 1959–60 and finding its powerful evocation of the sea’s<italic>longue durée</italic>congruent with his own experiences in the Mediterranean during the war and in postwar Greece. McNeill remembers Van Dusen’s face going blank, as if he had never heard of Braudel and his book before. While McNeill cannot claim with certainty that he alone was responsible for introducing Braudel to Van Dusen, Braudel was soon on the Harper &amp; Row drawing board—but this was after the second edition preface was written and revisions under way. George Huppert from the University of Illinois at Chicago was instrumental during Braudel’s 1968 Chicago visit in helping Braudel find a translator for<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>(telephone conversation, September 21, 2002; George Huppert, “The<italic>Annales</italic>Experiment,” in<italic>Companion to Historiography,</italic>ed. Michael Bentley [London and New York, 1997], p. 874; and Gemelli, pp. 208–9). Braudel received a draft of the Routledge translation while in Chicago and consulted Huppert for his advice. Huppert found the Routledge translation untenable, called Van Dusen at Harper &amp; Row, who flew to Chicago and signed Braudel to a new contract. Huppert himself contracted to find an English translator, but he was unsuccessful after some half‐dozen attempts, and it was Mme. Braudel who found Siân Reynolds, whose sample translation was warmly approved by Huppert. Harper &amp; Row also contracted Orest and Patricia Ranum to proofread the translation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
               <label>69</label>
               <p>McNeill (telephone interview, September 17, 2002), as chairman of the University of Chicago History Department, brought Braudel to Hyde Park for the spring quarter. Earl J. Hamilton had retired the year before and had moved to SUNY Binghamton (1966–69); but Eric Cochrane (1928–85), with his wife, Lydia, was one of the younger generation who had known the Braudels in Florence from the Datini Institute in Prato. Six months before McNeill’s official invitation, Cochrane had written Braudel to sound him out about the Chicago visit that was to be cut short by the May 1968 events in Paris (Gemelli, pp. 207–8, cites Cochrane’s letter of invitation of December 11, 1966, and McNeill’s of April 5, 1967). Braudel had no fixed text for the seminar. Rather he brought massive amounts of microfilm with him that he and Mme. Braudel would read during the week in their characteristic manner (alternating reading aloud while the other took notes), and he would then present the week’s microfilm reading to the faculty seminar in terms of questions for their thoughts and suggestions. Ranum (telephone interview, September 7, 2002), as department chair of the Johns Hopkins History Department, invited Braudel to lecture on his “Capitalism and Material Life” project in spring 1976. The Braudels stayed for a week in the Ranums’ home as their guests, where Braudel met Philippe Ariès for the first time; but Frederic Lane had long since retired and was living in Maine. Braudel delivered three polished, elegant lectures. Richard Kagan (personal correspondence, September 10, 2002), remembers that, in his characteristic interrogative style, Braudel would question his audience afterward for their thoughts, even in the packed auditorium. Ranum and his Hopkins colleague, Forster, were also responsible for initiating the Hopkins seven‐volume essay collection from the<italic>Annales</italic>that began in 1975. Forster’s 1978<italic>JEH</italic>article, “Achievements of the<italic>Annales</italic>School” (n. 61 above), is among the most incisive and critical reviews of the contributions and limitations of the<italic>Annales.</italic>On Braudel, Forster (n. 61 above) writes (p. 63), “If the Annales has a paradigm, it is his<italic>Mediterranean</italic>” in its three conceptions of time.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
               <label>70</label>
               <p>Trevor‐Roper (n. 11 above), p. 472.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <label>II.</label>
         <title>Readers’ Responses</title>
         <p>First‐time readers of Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean,</italic>in fact, are invariably dazzled or daunted by his dizzying array of detail. Two British encomia reproduced for publicity on the jacket of the Harper &amp; Row edition are exemplary.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">71</xref>Arnold Toynbee commends Braudel’s all‐encompassing vision: “His research, reflection, and judgment are magisterial and illuminating … on all points that he takes up—and there are no gaps in his survey; it is admirably many‐sided and comprehensive.” Trevor‐Roper praises the encyclopedic coverage: “We are amazed by Braudel’s range of illustration, his eye for detail, his power to select, animate, generalize. He seems to know every crease in these mountains, every island in that sea, every climatic freak, every human response to the problems which they pose.”</p>
         <p>Mme. Braudel writes, as “a witness to the intellectual origins of Fernand Braudel,” that in 1939 “what he had in his head was a fantastic phantasmagoria of colors, of landscapes, of men, of great events and small anecdotes, a composite of what he recombined and resuscitated from life.” Readers have to see beyond the trees to the forest, just as Braudel the author had to rely on his prodigious memory to create an ensemble of the distant sea from his prison camp in Lübeck “from a thousand facts and a thousand details often very far removed from one another in time and space.” Mme. Braudel describes Braudel’s “intellectual adventure” as “a slow accumulation little by little not of ideas, and less even of a system of ideas, but of images by the millions, the fabulous spectacles of history, mixing yesterday and today. In all of it, not a concern for logic.” She identifies Braudel’s key organizing principle as “a spectacle—it is a spectacle that he says took off, not a previous idea”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">72</xref>and she quotes his<italic>JMH</italic>autobiographical essay: “And my vision of history took on its definitive form without my being entirely aware of it, partly as a direct intellectual response to a spectacle—the Mediterranean—which no traditional historical account seemed to me capable of encompassing, and partly as a direct existential response to the tragic times I was passing through.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">73</xref>Turning that “spectacle” into a “vision of history” is a first, shorthand answer to our question of what readers remember.</p>
         <p>Second, readers of Braudel’s<italic>Mediterranean,</italic>no matter how much of the book they actually have read, continue to be struck by the energy, engagement, and dedication of a fervent lover and committed convert. “I have passionately loved the Mediterranean, no doubt because I am a northerner like so many others in whose footsteps I have followed.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">74</xref>This famous opening sentence in the preface to the first edition, dated May 1946, one year after VE Day and Braudel’s release from a German prisoner‐of‐war camp, resonates in Braudel’s remarks during a 1981 interview thirty‐five years later on his initial excitement at seeing the Mediterranean for the first time in October 1923 at the age of twenty‐one:<disp-quote>
               <p>It was for me such a surprise! I did not know the sea, I saw the Mediterranean, avowing that it is a present of the gods! Imagine someone like me who went down the Rhone Valley for the first time, who stopped at Marseille, who embarked on a boat and learned with pleasure that he had sea legs—it was just like that—and abruptly saw the arrival of Algiers on the horizon.… Algiers was the most beautiful city in France, after Paris, and a city itself very different, with, I would say, the beauty of its streets, the extraordinary beauty of its women.… It was hot, there was wine, fish, everything that one wants. For me, I began to live.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">75</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>North Africa freed Braudel, like so many earlier enchanted and enthralled romantic travelers, from his provincial complaisance. One can almost hear him chanting Goethe’s 1787 credo on finding one’s true self in the liberating southern sun: “I hardly recognize myself. I feel like a completely different person. Yesterday I thought: ‘Either you used to be mad, or you are now.’”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">76</xref>Or we see him “venturing out [into the desert] on a camel”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">77</xref>like Gide’s<italic>immoraliste</italic>Michel, the fictional professor at the Collège de France, discovering a new culture and self in 1902, the year of Braudel’s birth, at the Roman amphitheatre in El Djem. Such enthusiasm, excitement, and experience Braudel wishes to share with his readers; and the 1949 preface continues with the hope that the pages of his book would shine forth with “a little bit of this [personal] joy and a great deal of its [Mediterranean] light.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">78</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Memory and reciprocity between author and reader, in the way a good teacher connects with students, is also part of Braudel’s earliest writing of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>; this is a third approach to the question of readers’ responses. In the preface to the first edition Braudel invites the reader to participate in the book’s image‐ and memory‐making: “The reader who approaches this book in the spirit I would wish will do well to bring with him his own memories, his own vision of the Mediterranean to add colour to the text and to help me conjure up this vast presence, as I have done my best to do.” And in this same spirit of memory and reciprocity, Braudel in turn returns to his own student days to remember the “unwavering conviction” imparted by his teachers: “if I have retained nothing else from the geographers who taught me at the Sorbonne,” it was that the “sea itself, the one we see and love, is the greatest document of its past existence.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">79</xref>Thus it is not by chance that Braudel’s 1969 manuscript on the Mediterranean in prehistory and antiquity (“la très longue durée”), not published until 1998, is called<italic>Memory and the Mediterranean,</italic>and its opening paragraph, with the heading “Seeing the Sea,” eloquently explains how memory reconstitutes reality for Braudel: “This is a sea that patiently recreates for us scenes from the past, breathing new life into them, locating them under a sky and in a landscape that we can see with our own eyes, a landscape and sky like those of long ago. A moment’s concentration or daydreaming, and that past comes back to life.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">80</xref>The Braudelian metaphor is resuscitation and re‐creation. There is not the slightest hint of spiritualist resurrection; Braudel invokes instead the dynamism of waves. “Mediterranean civilization spreads far beyond its shores in great waves that are balanced by continual returns. What leaves the sea comes back and then departs once more.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">81</xref>And even though these waves can turn into metaphors of precision instruments—“waves of past time which ought ideally to accumulate like the divisions in the mechanism of a watch, the seconds, minutes, hours, and days”; or, again, the waves of long to short‐term time through the three parts of his book itself, which are likened to “an hourglass, eternally reversible”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">82</xref>—Braudel is only a scientist in that he describes more than he explains. Better, he presents himself as the artist painting images, the novelist telling a story, or the playwright staging a scene.</p>
         <p>Mme. Braudel, again our best witness, confirms that the Braudelian itinerary never followed the path “of a logician or a philosopher. Perhaps that of an artist?” She even recalls a telling conversation in which Braudel laughingly agreed that his “method” (“c’est un peu ce que je fais”) was a little like that of “Matisse redesign[ing] every day the same portrait of the same model … and each day regularly throw[ing] his design away in the wastebasket, until the moment that he finally had found the line that pleased him.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">83</xref>Earlier in her testimony she emphasized a similar point. Braudel carried in his head all his experiences—sights, smells, tastes—without the need “to explain them to himself logically or methodically.” Rather, he was like a poet who enjoyed the moment; “but this poet was also, contradictorily, a professor” who had the uncanny facility of “perfect clarity” and “the memory of an elephant.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">84</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Braudel’s connection with his readers through spectacle, passion, and memory gives life to the numbing facts of his book. Although not of a philosophical or theoretical bent, Braudel began the 1967 introduction to the first volume of<italic>Ci</italic>
            <italic>vi</italic>
            <italic>lisation matérielle et capitalisme</italic>with a bow to theory: “A general history always requires an overall model, good or bad, against which events can be interpreted. ‘No theory, no history,’ said Werner Sombart.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">85</xref>Braudel’s underlying “theory” or original organizational schema in<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>grew out of necessity and distance—the accumulation of masses of material over more than a decade and the enforced separation from his notes and documentary base while a POW. It was a theory grounded in<italic>géographie humaine,</italic>the primary discipline supporting French historical instruction from elementary school, and forged in war.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">86</xref>It was more a practice than a theory; it was about war and remembrance, the incantation of memory, as he emphasized in his 1950 inaugural lecture to the Collège de France.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88">87</xref>The revised 1966 edition, however, was reconstituted out of a critical rereading and rethinking; for Braudel’s method—the method of the original<italic>Annales</italic>of Marc Bloch and Lucien Febvre—was the critical<italic>compte rendu,</italic>incorporating combats and debates, judgment and analysis in reviewing books and articles. In the 1969 preface to his<italic>On History,</italic>Braudel explained his method of revising his own work: “Since I am not a man of polemic, being concerned only with my own path, my own particular path, and since polemic and dialogue are a double and unavoidable necessity, here I am holding dialogues and engaging in polemic with myself, in a natural process of detachment from texts for which I obviously remain responsible. It was this sentiment which led me recently to rewrite<italic>The Mediterranean.</italic>”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89">88</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Braudel’s 1966 revised<italic>Mediterranean</italic>was a different book. It changed its perspective from a focus on geography to a greater emphasis on economics, political science, a revised conception of civilization, and demography.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90">89</xref>The second edition jettisoned outdated controversies and outmoded arguments, added new problematics and archival references, and synthesized the enormous body of new monographic work on socioeconomic history amassed in the previous fifteen years, often inspired by his first edition.</p>
         <p>Reconstructing Braudel’s intellectual itinerary and mapping its congruence with twentieth‐century French social thought follows John Elliott’s 1973 observation that “in a sense, the history of Braudel’s great book is the history of twentieth‐century historiography itself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91">90</xref>The revised second edition was the fruit of postwar optimism and of the “time of certainties” most associated with the success of Braudel’s first edition and his stewardship of the<italic>Annales</italic>and of the Ecole’s Sixth Section during the 1950s and 1960s. Even more fascinating, however, is the afterlife of Braudel’s 1966 edition of<italic>The Mediterranean</italic>in the last third of the twentieth century, long after the text itself was set forever in typescript and translations. The problem of the disjunction between structure and event, the question of human freedom and individual action, the proof claims of language and quantification, the subordination of politics—all came under intense scrutiny and critical revision within France by subsequent generations of<italic>Annales</italic>historians. Thus, the criticism of Braudel’s<italic>Méditerranée</italic>within his own tradition itself spawned new historiographical formulations and projects.</p>
         <p>Beginning in the early 1960s, and punctuated by Foucault’s 1966<italic>Les mots et les choses</italic>(<italic>The Order of Things</italic>) and his 1969<italic>L’archéologie du savoir</italic>(<italic>The Archaeology of Knowledge and the Discourse on Language</italic>), poststructuralist critiques of truth claims and the imperialism of global history, a rethinking of the certainty of words and concepts in an “archeology (that is, a deconstruction) of the social sciences” struck at the heart of long‐standing<italic>Annaliste</italic>principles.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92">91</xref>Whether studying social control, discipline, power, or sexuality, old assumptions were dissected and new agendas initiated. The 1976<italic>Il formaggio e i vermi</italic>(<italic>The Cheese and the Worms</italic>) by Carlo Ginzburg and the 1979 launching of<italic>microstoria</italic>by Ginzburg, Carlo Poni, and Edoardo Grendi—practiced in France by Le Roy Ladurie in his 1975<italic>Montaillou</italic>and 1979<italic>Carnival in Romans</italic>—fostered a new kind of ethnographic history of everyday life that focused on the individual.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93">92</xref>“The revival of narrative,” whether from Lawrence Stone’s famous 1979<italic>Past and Present</italic>article or Paul Ricoeur’s 1983–85<italic>Time and Narrative,</italic>was to restore the story to history and to return to the event, as Pierre Nora had called for in his 1974 essay in<italic>Faire de l’histoire.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94">93</xref>Pierre Bourdieu’s 1979<italic>La distinction</italic>pushed for a reconciliation between events and structure.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95">94</xref>By emphasizing that systems of oppositions are not stable structures but are constantly in the process of becoming, being made and remade, Bourdieu’s project to understand how social reality is constructed gets us closer to incorporating practice and perception with objective categories and suggests a way of bridging the gap between the endless details of one thing after another and causal explanation. This list of key<italic>Annaliste</italic>ideas and methods derived from the<italic>Méditerranée</italic>’s problematic could include sharp criticism like that of François Dosse; the constructive response of Jacques Revel on the<italic>Annales</italic>paradigms, the social sciences, and the construction of the social; Pierre Nora’s crystallization of the concepts of “the explosion of history” and “les lieux de mémoire”; and Bernard Lepetit’s response to the “critical turning point” of the late 1980s in the epistemology, research practices, and exchange among the social sciences with his 1995 collection of essays on “forms of experience” as “another social history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96">95</xref>We might apply Braudel’s own metaphor of the sea to his book—that it was like a pebble dropped in the water, creating concentric rings of wider and wider ripples, both material and intangible.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97">96</xref>That is why what follows—a discussion of the author‐historian’s life and influences—matters.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn72">
               <label>71</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 1, back cover.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn73">
               <label>72</label>
               <p>Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage,” pp. 242–43.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn74">
               <label>73</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” pp. 453–54. See also Braudel’s inaugural lecture to the Collège de France (December 1, 1950) in Braudel, “The Situation of History in 1950,” in<italic>On History,</italic>trans. Sarah Matthews (Chicago, 1980), p. 10, “Just like life itself, history seems to us to be a fleeting spectacle, always in movement, made up of a web of problems meshed inextricably together, and able to assume a hundred different and contradictory aspects in turn. How should one tackle such a complex, living entity and break it up so as to be able to lay hold of it, or at least of some part of it?” Braudel’s answer, of course, is “global” or “total history,” the three levels of time and their contingent realm of inquiry—the long term of geography, the conjuncture of structures, and the short term of events.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn75">
               <label>74</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>La Méditerranée,</italic>1st ed. (1949), p. ix: “J’ai passionnément aimé la Méditerranée, sans doute parce que venu du Nord, comme tant d’autres, après tant d’autres.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn76">
               <label>75</label>
               <p>Daix (n. 2 above), p. 50.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn77">
               <label>76</label>
               <p>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe,<italic>Italian Journey,</italic>trans. Robert R. Heitner (New York, 1989), pp. 169–70, diary entry Caserta, March 16, 1787.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn78">
               <label>77</label>
               <p>Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage,” p. 239.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn79">
               <label>78</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>La Méditerranée,</italic>1st ed. (1949), p. ix: “En revanche, j’espère qu’un peu de cette joie et beaucoup de sa lumière éclaireront les pages de ce livre.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn80">
               <label>79</label>
               <p>Ibid.: “Le lecteur qui voudra aborder ce livre comme je le souhaite, fera donc bien d’apporter ses propres souvenirs, ses vision précises de la mer Intérieure et, à son tour, d’en colorer mon texte, de m’aider de façon active à recréer cette vaste presence, ce à quoi je me suis efforcé autant que je l’ai pu.… Je pense que la mer, telle qu’on peut l’aimer et la voir, reste le plus grand document qui soit sur sa vie passée. Si je n’ai retenu que cette idée de l’enseignement des géographes qui furent mes maîtres à la Sorbonne, je l’ai retenue avec une obstination qui donne sa couleur et son sens à mon enterprise.” Geography continues to play a fundamental role in French historical education from elementary school through university scholarship.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn81">
               <label>80</label>
               <p>Fernand Braudel,<italic>Memory and the Mediterranean,</italic>ed. Roselyne de Ayala and Paule Braudel, trans. Siân Reynolds (New York, 2001), pp. xxv, 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn82">
               <label>81</label>
               <p>See Kellner (n. 26 above), p. 212, who quotes Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 1:170.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn83">
               <label>82</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 2:893, 903.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn84">
               <label>83</label>
               <p>Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage,” p. 244: “Comme je critiquais un jour ce gaspillage de temps et de force, il m’a réprondu en riant qu’il ne pouvait fair autrement. ‘Mais, a‐t‐il dit, c’est toi qui m’as parlé, chaque jour le même portrait du même modèle. Tu m’as dit que chaque jour il jetait régulièrement son dessin à la corbeille, jusqu’au moment où il avait trouvé enfin la ligne qui lui plaisait. Eh bien, après tout, c’est un peu ce que je fais!’” Braudel as painter, however, had a special relationship between the “object” and the “background,” as he states in Braudel, “The Situation of History in 1950” (n. 73 above), p. 9, “The problem of history is not to be found in the relationship between painter and painting, nor even, though some have thought such a suggestion excessively daring, in the relationship between the painting and the landscape. The problem is right in the landscape, in the heart of life itself.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn85">
               <label>84</label>
               <p>Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage,” p. 242.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn86">
               <label>85</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>Capitalism and Material Life,</italic>p. xi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>On Braudel and geography, see John A. Marino, “On the Shores of Bohemia: Recovering Geography,” in<italic>Early Modern History and the Social Sciences</italic>(n. 2 above), pp. 3–32.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn88">
               <label>87</label>
               <p>Braudel, “The Situation of History in 1950” (n. 73 above), p. 6: “History today finds itself faced with formidable but challenging responsibilities.… Now, over the past forty years those experiences have been particularly harsh for all of us; they have thrown us violently back into our deepest selves, and thence into a consideration of the whole destiny of mankind—that is to say, into the crucial problems of history. It is a time to lament our state, to agonize, to ponder, a time in which we must of necessity call everything into question. Besides, why should the fragile art of writing history escape from the general crisis of our age? We are quitting a world of which we have not always had the time to understand or appreciate the benefits, the errors, the certainties, and the dreams—the world, shall we say, of the early twentieth century? We are leaving it, or rather, it is slipping inexorably away from us.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn89">
               <label>88</label>
               <p>Ibid., p. vii.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn90">
               <label>89</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 1:12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn91">
               <label>90</label>
               <p>Elliott (n. 4 above), p. 25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn92">
               <label>91</label>
               <p>Lucien Febvre’s concept of “mental tools” (<italic>outlillage mental</italic>) is one of the core ideas that articulated the<italic>Annaliste</italic>tradition. For Foucault’s critique, see Revel, “The<italic>Annales:</italic>Continuities and Discontinuities” (n. 19 above), p. 17. Revel argues “that among Foucault’s tenacious, ravaging works,<italic>The Order of Things</italic>(<italic>Les mots et les choses</italic>) occupies a symbolic position.” See also Michel Foucault, “The Archaeology of Knowledge: Introduction” (1969), in Revel and Hunt, eds. (n. 9 above), pp. 202–16; Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 411–24; Stoianovich (n. 14 above), pp. 206–11; and Dosse (n. 9 above), 1:330–42.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn93">
               <label>92</label>
               <p>The possibility of microhistory is already contained within Braudel’s global vision; see<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 2:1243: “That is not to say that this brilliant surface is of no value to the historian, nor that historical reconstruction cannot perfectly well take this micro‐history as its starting‐point.… Benedetto Croce has argued, not without reason, that any single event—let us say the assassination of Henry IV in 1610, or to take an example outside our period the arrival in power in 1883 of the Jules Ferry government—contains in embryo the entire history of mankind.” See Edward Muir, “Introduction: Observing Trifles,” and Carlo Ginzburg and Carlo Poni, “The Name and the Game: Unequal Exchange and the Historiographic Marketplace,” in<italic>Micro</italic>
                  <italic>history and the Lost Peoples of Europe,</italic>ed. Edward Muir and Guido Ruggiero, trans. Eren Branch (Baltimore, 1991), pp. vii–xxviii, 1–10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn94">
               <label>93</label>
               <p>Lawrence Stone, “The Revival of Narrative: Reflections on a New Old History,”<italic>Past and Present</italic>85 (1979): 3–24; Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Time and Narrative,</italic>trans. Kathleen McLaughlin and David Pellauer, 3 vols. (Chicago, 1984); and Pierre Nora, “Le retour de l’evénement,” in<italic>Faire de l’histoire,</italic>ed. Jacques Le Goff and Pierre Nora, vol. 1,<italic>Nouveaux problèmes</italic>(Paris, 1974), pp. 217–27.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn95">
               <label>94</label>
               <p>Pierre Bourdieu, “Social Space and Symbolic Power,” in<italic>In Other Words: Essays towards a Reflexive Sociology,</italic>trans. Matthew Adamson (Cambridge, 1990), p. 124: “between two apparently incompatible points of view, two apparently irreconcilable perspectives: objectivism and subjectivism, or … physicalism and psychologism.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn96">
               <label>95</label>
               <p>François Dosse, “History in Pieces” (1987); Jacques Revel, “The Paradigms of the<italic>Annales</italic>” (1979), and “Microanalysis and the Construction of the Social” (1996); Pierre Nora, “The Library of Histories” (1971) and “Between Memory and History:<italic>Les Lieux de Mémoire</italic>” (1984); and the editors of<italic>Annales,</italic>“History and Social Science: A Critical Turning Point” (1988) and “Let’s Try the Experiment” (1989), in Revel and Hunt, eds., pp. 469–70, 471–75, 492–502, 467–68, 631–43, and 479–91. Bernard Lepetit, ed.,<italic>Les formes de l’expérience: Un autre histoire sociale</italic>(Paris, 1995), presents essays by twelve authors; see esp. his introduction, “Histoire des pratiques, pratique de l’histoire” (pp. 9–22), which focuses on interdisciplinary practices in language, logic, norms, conventions, categories, time, and the social itself in light of the ideological uncertainty and paradigm instability of “the critical turning point” at the end of the 1980s.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn97">
               <label>96</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 1:170; “The circulation of man and of goods, both material and intangible, formed concentric rings round the Mediterranean.”</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <label>III.</label>
         <title>The Man and His Book</title>
         <p>The long gestation period of the book—Braudel’s life to 1949 and beyond—forces remembrance of the man and his book. On the intellectual plane, as we have seen, Braudel’s<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>is a history of the Mediterranean and Philip II’s Spanish empire as well as a primary document illustrating the trajectory of twentieth‐century French historical studies and social thought both before and after its publication and revision.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98">97</xref>On a biographical level, it was the sum of his personal experiences and studies, as Braudel’s preface to the first edition in 1949 recalls: “I have joyfully dedicated long years of study to it—much more than all my youth.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99">98</xref>Already in his forty‐seventh year at the time of the book’s publication, Braudel had had an eventful life; but it should be remembered that at mid‐century he had not yet made his mark nor won an established academic position in France, as, for example, his colleague Ernest Labrousse (1895–1988) or his American peers Hamilton and Lane had done long before.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100">99</xref>Braudel himself knew what his friends thought about his never‐ending book: “among my friends and colleagues it was reported that I would never finish this very ambitious work.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101">100</xref>In 1976 he himself would correct the common false impression of the positive reception in 1947 of his thesis and the<italic>Annales</italic>movement in general—“without drum and trumpet and with a thousand nice‐sounding words in my ear,” he was rejected for an appointment at the Sorbonne and received condescending criticism at his thesis defense. “One of the judges suavely said to me, ‘You are a geographer: let me be the historian.’”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102">101</xref>Braudel saw himself as a perpetual outsider, an exile, not unlike the self‐image of the<italic>Annales</italic>itself, memorialized at the Binghamton inaugural conference, as a historical tradition of resistance.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103">102</xref>Yet, in the administrative sphere, in his post‐1950 career as director of the<italic>Annales,</italic>the Ecole, and the Maison, Braudel’s keen intelligence, force of personality, power with words, and moral authority from his war experiences made him a formidable presence in French intellectual and academic culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104">103</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Mme. Braudel summarizes “the very slow, independent, and solitary maturation” of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>in terms of, on the one hand, “the isolation of prison,” and, on the other hand, “the isolation of university practices.” Braudel’s was “a very chaotic life, chopped into many bits and pieces of which each had been a sort of adventure and particular experience.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105">104</xref>She specifies Braudel’s successive experiences in rural France, North Africa, Brazil, and German prisoner‐of‐war camps. These four sites in Braudel’s biography and his autobiographical recollections about them are well documented.</p>
         <p>Braudel was a self‐proclaimed, patriotic northerner, born in 1902 in the tiny Lorraine village of about two hundred inhabitants, Luméville‐en‐Ornois (Meuse). He spent his early years there until the age of seven with his paternal grandmother, Emilie Cornot, whom he calls in his dedication in<italic>The Identity of France</italic>“lumière de mon enfance.” Thereafter, until the age of twenty‐one, he returned for summers and holidays from his parents and school in Paris, where his father was a secondary school teacher. Paris may have been where the young Braudel lived and went to school for fourteen years, where in later life he remembered his school chum Jean Gabin (1904–76), the great actor; but Luméville was his home, where he learned the nitty‐gritty of preindustrial material life, the names of plants and the rhythm of planting, became acquainted with the village artisans and the arts of village life. Upon completion of university at the Sorbonne in 1923, his ambition was to teach<italic>lycée</italic>locally in his region and to become its historian. Mme. Braudel remembers how “a historian of the Meuse was amused to find all the allusions to the village of Luméville” in<italic>La Méditerranée,</italic>as if it were a local history writ on a larger scale.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106">105</xref>McNeill goes so far as to say that “Luméville undoubtedly provided the inspiration for the<italic>longue durée</italic>… [and] provoked Braudel’s most successful innovation in the writing of history: his insistence on the basic importance of geographically variegated everyday custom and almost unconscious routines, which, he claimed, set limits to all deliberate effort, whether in matters economic, political, or military.” And McNeill believes that Braudel found an audience in the “French reading public” much because his work evoked that “vanishing world.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107">106</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This idyllic youth between city and country was followed by academic exile and exclusion—eight academic years (1923–32) teaching<italic>lycée</italic>in Algeria, three years (1935–37) at the newly founded University of São Paulo in Brazil, and five years (1940–45) as a German prisoner of war at Mainz and Lübeck. As different as these experiences may appear, they all reinforced his self‐image of the exile, even when Braudel had ascended to the triple crown of priest, king, and prophet at the<italic>Annales,</italic>the Ecole, and the Maison.</p>
         <p>In 1923, when Braudel was appointed a<italic>lycée</italic>teacher of history in Algeria, he spent the first year working in Constantine; thereafter he taught in Algiers until 1932 (save for eighteen months of military service in the Rhineland, April 1925–October 1926).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108">107</xref>He returned home to Luméville in the summer of 1924 only to receive news of his beloved paternal grandmother Cornot’s death. In Algeria, he seems to have enjoyed life as a bachelor bon vivant, given to discovering and enjoying North Africa and its colonial charms. “I thus had the opportunity to give myself over to the pleasures of living in a magnificent city with great joie de vivre, and to visit intensively all the countries of North Africa, into the Sahara, which fascinated me.… Some day perhaps a<italic>pied noir</italic>settler will write a book like<italic>Gone with the Wind</italic>about those lost years. At any rate, I did not personally feel any twinges of conscience. The bad conscience would be there twenty years later.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109">108</xref>What do we make of such extraordinary candor? Is the jarring reference to Scarlet O’Hara lingering romanticism, the French civilizing mission, or longing for lost innocence?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn110">109</xref>Braudel’s memories bear the curiosity of discovery, the seriousness of study, the naiveté of a twenty‐year‐old in the 1920s, and the sentimental nostalgia of the French colonial<italic>pied noir.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn111">110</xref>
         </p>
         <p>A psychological turning point in Braudel’s life came at age twenty‐five with his father’s death on January 27, 1927.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn112">111</xref>That summer Braudel returned to Paris to help sort out family affairs. He began his first serious archival research at the Archives Nationales and the Bibliotheque Nationale and changed the title of his<italic>thèse</italic>to “Philippe II et la politique espagnole en Méditerranée de 1559 à 1574” (i.e., from Cateau‐Cambrésis to the Turkish reconquest of Tunis). That fall his mother came to Algiers to keep house for him, which prompted him to undertake a first marriage with the daughter of the vice‐principal of his school on October 27, 1927, which ended in divorce five years later. Archival work in Simancas began in the following summers, 1928 through 1933.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn113">112</xref>His 1928 first article, “The Spaniards and North Africa,” was derived from his revised<italic>thèse</italic>topic, and it eventually made its way into Part III of<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>in a discussion of the North African defense network. Neither this section nor a topic such as the battle of Alcázarquivir (August 4, 1578) constitute anything other than “potted” history derived from 1930s scholarship—nothing, in fact, to suggest his intimate contact with North African society and culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn114">113</xref>If the view of “the Mediterranean as seen from the opposite shore, upside down” revolutionized his vision, his geographic orientation tuned out any unique or original perspective in this section of what became Part III. In 1930 Braudel served as an assistant secretary at the Congress of Historical Sciences held in Algiers amid the celebrations of Algeria’s one‐hundredth anniversary as a French colony, and he appears to have been less on the outside than his memory or self‐image would like to admit. More than the place, it was what he did there, his role as a secondary school teacher, that shaped the young Braudel.</p>
         <p>In July 1932 Braudel became engaged to one of his former<italic>lycée</italic>students, Paule Pradel, from a<italic>pied noir</italic>settler family, then departed Algeria for a new<italic>lycée</italic>assignment at Neuilly outside Paris, returning to France via Tunis and Italy, which he visited then for the first time. In September 1933, the thirty‐one‐year‐old Braudel returned to Algeria to marry the nineteen‐year‐old Paule Pradel in her hometown of Tiaret, between Oran and Algiers in the Algerian interior. The Braudels began to work together in Mediterranean archives in 1935 during their Brazilian winter vacations, and the “delight in discovering the marvelous registers of Ragusa at Dubrovnik” in 1936 was highlighted in Braudel’s memory. “For the first time, I saw the Mediterranean of the sixteenth century.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn115">114</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Just as North Africa provided a defining perspective that turned his thinking upside down, teaching in Brazil and captivity in German prisoner‐of‐war camps also gave Braudel important reflective distance. Brazil provided a different kind of colonial perspective to look across the ocean at the Mediterranean as through a distant mirror. For Braudel, Brazil’s stark class divisions resembled an earlier stage of European economic development and a way to look back in time at the origins of modern capitalism in the Mediterranean. “Brazil is the same civilization [as ours], but not at the same age. It is true that Brazil allowed me to arrive at a certain conception of history that I would not have had if I had remained round about the Mediterranean.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn116">115</xref>Prison camp, in contrast, brought enforced solitude to contemplate the whole, away from the jumble of details in Braudel’s notes. Prison was a “long time of testing … a good school. It teaches patience, tolerance.” The Mediterranean “distracted me in the true etymological meaning of the word,” and Braudel wrote his book. “Only my memory permitted this tour de force. Had it not been for my imprisonment, I would surely have written quite a different book.… Far removed from our persons and our daily misery, history was being made, shifting slowly, as slowly as the ancient life of the Mediterranean, whose perdurability and majestic immobility has so often moved me. So it was that I consciously set forth in search of a historical language—the most profound I could grasp or invent—in order to present unchanging (or at least very slowly changing) conditions which stubbornly assert themselves over and over again.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn117">116</xref>Braudel’s memory juxtaposed the repetition of the routines of daily life amid a sea of imperceptible change with the retelling of the same events during the reign of Philip II from different frames of reference in the three parts of his book, so that the temporal linkage between structure‐conjuncture‐event would become clear. Thus, the spatial separation between his life experiences in North Africa, Brazil, and the German camps would meld into a mnemonic device to understand and to teach how, in the lands around the ever‐changing and never‐changing sea, time and space, history and geography together shaped one coherent past, present, and future.</p>
         <p>Teaching, above all, launched Braudel on his intellectual itinerary. It was first in North Africa where he encountered the “joy” and “spectacle” of life outside his circumscribed world of farm and family, school and books. In colonial Algeria, he began his adult life and his life’s work as a teacher trying to make sense out of the historical spectacle and its spectacular stories in order to formulate lessons for his students. The Socratic teacher never forgot his point of departure in North Africa.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn118">117</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn98">
               <label>97</label>
               <p>Horden and Purcell, and Marino, are two recent examples.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn99">
               <label>98</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>La Méditerranée,</italic>1st ed. (1949), p. ix: “Je lui aurai consacré avec joie de longues années d’études—pour moi bien plus que toute ma jeunesse.” On the length of time in composition, the English edition of 1972 quotes Nigel Dennis, “It took twenty years to write this remarkable book, and one cannot pay it a higher compliment than to say that twenty years could be well spent reading it” (vol. 1, back cover), and Geoffrey Parker, “No serious student of history can afford to be without a copy. It may have taken twenty‐six years to write, but which historian would not willingly sacrifice half his working life in order to create a masterpiece which will stand forever?” (vol. 2, back cover).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn100">
               <label>99</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Foreword,” in Stoianovich (n. 14 above), pp. 15–16, and Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 343–44. Ernest Labrousse,<italic>Equisse du mouvement des prix et des revenues en France au XVIIIe siècle</italic>(Paris, 1932), and his<italic>thèse, La crise de l’économie française à la fin de l’Ancien Régime et au début de la Révolution</italic>(1944), resulted in his 1945 election to the chair of economic history at the Sorbonne formerly held by Marc Bloch; Earl J. Hamilton,<italic>American Treasure and the Price Revolution in Spain, 1501–1650</italic>(Cambridge, Mass., 1934), was first appointed to Duke in 1927; Frederic C. Lane,<italic>Venetian Ships and Shipbuilders of the Renaissance</italic>(Baltimore, 1934), was first appointed to Johns Hopkins in 1928.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn101">
               <label>100</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” p. 452.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn102">
               <label>101</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Foreword,” in Stoianovich (n. 14 above), pp. 14–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn103">
               <label>102</label>
               <p>Ibid., pp. 14–16, Braudel emphasizes his exclusion from the elite, degree‐granting French universities and from directing graduate student theses, and he calls the Sixième Section of the Ecole “the miracle, for its creation hung by a thread in 1947.” Despite his 1949 appointment to the Collège de France, his 1949–54 tenure as chair of the history section of the national examination (<italic>aggrégation</italic>), or his positions in the Sixth Section of the Ecole or in the Maison, Braudel saw himself and his group as “heretics until almost 1968,” when “the troubles of May and June 1968 changed everything.” He compares his own marginalization outside the prestigious degree‐granting universities offering graduate student instruction in France with the exclusion by the Collège de France of Marc Bloch and Henri Berr. See also Immanuel Wallerstein, “<italic>Annales</italic>as Resistance,”<italic>Review</italic>1, nos. 3–4 (1978): 5–7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn104">
               <label>103</label>
               <p>Among the many testimonials upon Braudel’s death, Jacques Le Goff remembered him as “a ferocious partisan of the independence of spirit and of constructive disobedience,” and Georges Duby recalled, “I once wrote that he was the patron.… He had something of the prince in him,” as cited in Daix (n. 2 above), p. 539.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn105">
               <label>104</label>
               <p>Paule Braudel, “Un témoignage,” pp. 238–39.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn106">
               <label>105</label>
               <p>Ibid., p. 239.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn107">
               <label>106</label>
               <p>McNeill, “Fernand Braudel, Historian” (n. 2 above), p. 135.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn108">
               <label>107</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” p. 449, records his university and postuniversity malaise: “a student of history … graduat[ing] without difficulty, but also without much real enjoyment. I had the feeling I was frittering away my life, having chosen the easy way out.” Before he was to find his “vocation as a historian,” he “taught a superficial history of events, … becoming what one may call a good teacher,” liking and being liked in turn by his students.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn109">
               <label>108</label>
               <p>Ibid., pp. 450–51: “I believe that this spectacle, the Mediterranean as seen from the opposite shore, upside down, had considerable impact on my vision of history. But the change in my viewpoint was slow. At any rate, at that point in my life I did not understand the social, political, and colonial drama which was, nevertheless, right before my eyes. It is true that it was not until after 1929 that the North African countryside grew darker, and then, suddenly, the night had fallen. I have my excuses. First of all, the need to live when one is twenty, paying attention to oneself alone—a good and a bad counsellor; the difficulty of learning Arabic (I tried seriously and did not succeed); my particular anxiety about Germany which I had just seen at close hand, a country which I loved but which, as a man of eastern France, I distrusted. And above all it must be said, in 1923, in 1926, and in the years which followed, French Algeria did not appear as a monster to my eyes.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn110">
               <label>109</label>
               <p>In the parallel English colonial tradition, we might think of a Lawrence Durrell character from the “Alexandria Quartet” (1957–60) or one of the sophisticated European archeologists in Anthony Minghella’s film<italic>The English Patient</italic>(1996), dining, drinking, and dancing to jazz at the country club. Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed., 2:1239, 1242–43, adds references to Durrell and other novelists—Carlo Levi alone is cited in the first edition (pp. 1091–92)—to emphasize “those local, permanent, unchanging and much repeated features which are the ‘constants’ of Mediterranean history.” Braudel even quotes Durrell, “Under the formal pageant of events which we have dignified by our interest, the land changes very little, and the structure of the basic self of man hardly at all.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn111">
               <label>110</label>
               <p>For a short, still useful introduction, see Charles‐Robert Ageron,<italic>Modern Algeria: A History from 1830 to the Present,</italic>trans. Michael Brett (London, 1991), pp. 82 and 86 on population statistics. In 1926, the European population was 18 percent of the native Muslim population, that is, 833,000 Europeans, which included 657,000 French and naturalized French and 176,000 foreigners, while the Muslim population stood at 5,150,000. In 1931, 76 percent of the European population was urban—673,000 out of 881,600.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn112">
               <label>111</label>
               <p>Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 73–74 and elsewhere, provides suggestive indications for a psychoanalytic approach regarding Braudel’s deep attachment to his paternal grandmother, ambivalent love/fear of his father, and estrangement from his mother.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn113">
               <label>112</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” p. 452, tells us that during these years, “I lived in the archives without hurrying—not even hurrying to choose my subject—that my decision ripened of its own accord. And so I chose the Mediterranean.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn114">
               <label>113</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 2:854, 1178.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn115">
               <label>114</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testimony,” p. 453, incorrectly dates Dubrovnik to 1934, an event corrected in Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 125–28, during their second archival trip. On Paule Braudel as archival collaborator during their first winter archival foray in 1935, Daix, p. 116.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn116">
               <label>115</label>
               <p>Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 137–38, quotes Braudel’s memories of 1937, his last year in Brazil: “Le Brésil, c’est la mème civilisation, mais pas au mème âge. C’est vraiment le Brésil qui m’a permis d’arriver à une certaine conception de l’histoire que je n’aurais pas eue si j’étais resté autour de la Méditerranée.” Daix, pp. 109–23, provides a chapter on Brazil with the opening quotation, “C’est au Brésil que je suis devenu intelligent” (p. 109); he compares Braudel’s understanding of French colonial society in Algeria as placed on top of an indigenous society, whereas “the Brazilian social hierarchy [presented itself] less a local than an international economic” phenomenon (p. 111). See also the interview by François Ewald and Jean‐Jacques Brohier, “Un vie pour l’histoire,”<italic>Magazine littéraire</italic>212 (November 1984): 18: “Au Brésil, j’ai d’couvert ce que je ne connaissais pas, et avec une certaine violence: quelque chose qui ressemble à une haute société privilégiée d’autrefois, quelque chose, au bas de la société, qui ressemble au début de la vie industrielle française, etc. En tout cas, c’est au Brésil que je suis devenu ce que je suis aujourd’hui.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn117">
               <label>116</label>
               <p>Braudel, “Personal Testament,” pp. 453–54. See also Daix (n. 2 above), pp. 163–200.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn118">
               <label>117</label>
               <p>Lydia Cochrane first told me this story in 1992/93, and reconfirmed it May 31, 2003 (personal communication). She remembers that in the Braudels’ desire to reciprocate the endless round of dinners offered them in April 1968 during their first month in Hyde Park, she accompanied Mme. Braudel around all of Chicago searching for a couscous pan that Mme. Braudel might use for a return dinner to repay the hospitality they had received. The Braudels’ North African dinner was scheduled for Saturday May 4, and this led Braudel to downplay the increasingly urgent telephone calls and news of May 1, 1968 coming from Paris. “What I remember with greatest pleasure,” Lydia Cochrane writes (personal correspondence, November 6, 2003), “is trying to sympathize with M. Braudel in his supposed anxiety and getting the answer. ‘J’en ai vu d’autres,’ with an Olympian shrug of the shoulders.” Finally convinced of the gravity of May 1968, the Braudels decided that as soon as their Hyde Park couscous dinner was completed, they would fly back to Paris and forgo the rest of the spring quarter.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <label>IV.</label>
         <title>Conclusion: Eating Couscous with a Fork?</title>
         <p>Albert Camus, who should have been that Algerian‐colonial writer, if not strictly a<italic>pied noir,</italic>that Braudel curiously invoked in his 1972<italic>JMH</italic>reverie of an Algerian<italic>Gone with the Wind,</italic>was born in Oran in 1913 and began<italic>lycée</italic>in 1923, the same year Braudel arrived to teach<italic>lycée</italic>in Constantine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn119">118</xref>He attended the University of Algiers between 1932 and 1936, beginning his studies there just as Braudel was leaving Algeria for Paris and then Brazil. Camus published his great novel,<italic>The Plague,</italic>in 1947, the year of Braudel’s<italic>thèse;</italic>and Camus himself spent 1949, the year of<italic>La Méditerranée</italic>’s publication, in Brazil. These superficial correspondences have no causal relationship; rather, their juxtaposition evokes the mental world of denial and disjunction between France and Algeria that France maintained as the colonial power, the combatant in two world wars, the humiliated defeated dependent of Nazi Germany, and the postwar recovering power. In<italic>The Plague,</italic>“Camus’s insistence on placing individual moral responsibility at the heart of all public choices”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn120">119</xref>presents a vision of history that appears to be diametrically opposed to that of Braudel’s “possibilism.”</p>
         <p>Similarly, the haunting image of the schoolteacher Daru, who is<italic>l’hôte</italic>—the simultaneous “guest/host”—in Camus’s Algerian short story in his 1957 collection<italic>L’exil et le royaume,</italic>contrasts sharply with what Braudel remembered as the innocence of colonial Algeria thirty years before.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn121">120</xref>After freeing the Arab prisoner to allow him to choose his own destiny, Daru returns alone to his classroom. One can see the colonial classroom, the maps and chalkboard tools of the teacher, the Algerian landscape of sky and plateau and “the invisible lands stretching all the way to the sea” focusing our gaze on what it really means to be alone and an exile. The last paragraph of Camus’s story is as biting for us today as it was for France in 1957, the year that Camus received the Nobel Prize in Literature<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn122">121</xref>and that the French scored their Pyrrhic victory crushing terrorism in the “Battle of Algiers.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn123">122</xref>“A little later, standing before the window of the classroom, the schoolmaster was watching the clear light bathing the whole surface of the plateau, but he hardly saw it. Behind him on the blackboard, among the winding French rivers, sprawled the clumsily chalked‐up words he had just read: ‘You handed over our brother. You will pay for this.’ Daru looked at the sky, the plateau, and, beyond, the invisible lands stretching all the way to the sea. In this last landscape he had loved so much, he was alone.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn124">123</xref>Have the lessons of the schoolmaster in geography and politics been learned? Whose landscape and whose politics was or is it?</p>
         <p>The actions of Camus’s schoolteacher were not circumscribed or constrained by geography: they were the political decisions made from an assent or acquiescence to “dogma, compliance, and cowardice.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn125">124</xref>Because Braudel, always the schoolteacher, so emphasized his brief against biographical history, critics have often claimed that the delineation of limits and constraints in<italic>The Mediterranean</italic>devalues politics and events and leaves the book devoid of individual freedom.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn126">125</xref>Such misrepresentations distort the history that Braudel really presented: “The dangers of a social history are clear to us all, and in particular the danger of forgetting, in contemplation of the deep currents in the lives of men, each separate man grappling with his own life and his own destiny; the danger of forgetting, perhaps even of denying, the inimitable essence of each individual.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn127">126</xref>For Braudel, the lessons of World War II demanded remembering both the forces acting upon each individual and individual acts freely chosen.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn128">127</xref>Braudel’s<italic>Méditerranée</italic>was a call to arms: “The catastrophes and revolutions, dramas and surprises” of his time revealed “the social reality, the fundamental reality of man … in an entirely new light,” which in turn required a new history, a problem‐oriented and global, total history.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn129">128</xref>It was a new history slow to be understood, little to be appreciated, and rarely to be practiced in the Anglo‐American world remembering a different past and fighting different battles in the 1950s and 1960s. On the question of individual freedom, however, Braudel’s history of the sixteenth‐century Mediterranean is very similar to the work of its most brilliant contemporary political analyst, Machiavelli. We might recall the wily Florentine exile’s astute judgment when we reread the last words of Braudel’s penultimate paragraph in the second edition: “I would conclude with the paradox that the true man of action is he who can measure most nearly the constraints upon him, who chooses to remain within them and even to take advantage of the weight of the inevitable, exerting his own pressure in the same direction. All efforts against the prevailing tide of history—which is not always obvious—are doomed to failure.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn130">129</xref>Braudel, the self‐proclaimed exile, would chronicle a plethora of facts no longer merely to entertain his students with “a superficial history of events” but in order to remember the contingency of choice and to teach how to discern the times. Thus, the Renaissance predicament of<italic>fortuna</italic>and<italic>virtù</italic>—what an individual can do in the face of what he cannot control—was also the twentieth‐century “paradox” studied and taught by Braudel: how to act within the parameters of the possible to fulfill both one’s own and mankind’s destiny.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn119">
               <label>118</label>
               <p>Camus, the younger of two children, whose father, a day laborer, was killed during World War I and whose mother, a Spaniard, was illiterate and deaf, grew up in extreme poverty and attended<italic>lycée</italic>through a scholarship. On Braudel’s memories of Algeria, see above n. 108.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn120">
               <label>119</label>
               <p>Tony Judt, “On ‘The Plague,’”<italic>New York Review of Books</italic>(November 29, 2001), p. 6, from his introduction to the new Penguin Books translation by Robin Buss (2001).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn121">
               <label>120</label>
               <p>Albert Camus, “L’hôte,” in<italic>L’exil et le royaume</italic>(Paris, 1957). The plot explores the formal and personal divisions between two cultures as the French schoolteacher Daru (who lives deep in the desert interior) is brought an Arab prisoner (guilty of murder) and is ordered to deliver him to prison for execution.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn122">
               <label>121</label>
               <p>Camus outlined his idea of his art and the role of the writer that is resonant with the title of his short story collection,<italic>Exile and the Kingdom,</italic>in his 1957 Nobel Prize acceptance speech, available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.nobel.se/literature/laureates/1957/camus-acceptance.html"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.nobel.se/literature/laureates/1957/camus‐acceptance.html</ext-link>): “[My art] is a means of stirring the greatest number of people by offering them a privileged picture of common joys and sufferings. It obliges the artist not to keep himself apart; it subjects him to the most humble and the most universal truth.… By definition he cannot put himself today in the service of those who make history; he is at the service of those who suffer it. Otherwise, he will be alone and deprived of his art. Not all the armies of tyranny with their millions of men will free him from his isolation, even and particularly if he falls into step with them. But the silence of an unknown prisoner, abandoned to humiliations at the other end of the world, is enough to draw the writer out of his exile, at least whenever, in the midst of the privileges of freedom, he manages not to forget that silence, and to transmit it in order to make it resound by means of his art.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn123">
               <label>122</label>
               <p>Ageron (n. 110 above), p. 115: “The ‘Battle of Algiers,’ lasting from January to September 1957, ended in the destruction of the terrorist organization in the capital [as a result of governor‐general Robert Lacoste giving ‘the paratroopers the task of destroying the terrorist commandos in the city “by any means”’], but psychologically it proved a pyrrhic victory” since it radicalized the Muslim population of Algeria and alienated public opinion in France. See also Benjamin Stora,<italic>Algeria, 1830–2000: A Short History,</italic>trans. Jane Marie Todd (Ithaca, N.Y., 2001), “The Cruel War (1957),” pp. 49–56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn124">
               <label>123</label>
               <p>Albert Camus, “The Guest,” in<italic>Exile and the Kingdom,</italic>trans. Justin O’Brien (New York, 1967), p. 109.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn125">
               <label>124</label>
               <p>Judt, p. 9, in<italic>The Plague:</italic>“It was not ‘fascism’ that Camus was aiming at—an easy target, after all, especially in 1947—but dogma, compliance, and cowardice in all their intersecting public forms.” Camus aimed at a more universal problem, the problem of evil, and the moral dilemmas that evil presents to individuals.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn126">
               <label>125</label>
               <p>Braudel addressed the critics directly in<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 2:1243–44: “The question is frequently put to me, both by historians and philosophers, if we view history from such a distance, what becomes of man, his role in history, his freedom of action?” A classic example is embodied in Braudel’s portrait of Philip II himself. “What degree of freedom was possessed by Philip II, or by Don Juan of Austria as he rode at anchor among his ships, allies, and troops? Each of these so‐called freedoms seems to me to resemble a tiny island, almost a prison.” See the conclusion of Part III, 2:1236 that recounts the death of Philip II on September 13, 1598, based on three secondary sources of the 1920s, not from contemporary accounts of Philip’s “good death.” Braudel’s last poignant paragraph suggests that Philip did not know what he was doing: “[Philip] was not a man of vision: he saw his task as an unending succession of small details. Every one of his annotations is a small precise point, whether an order, a remark, or the correction of a spelling mistake or geographical error. Never do we find general notions or grand strategies under his pen.” The king’s “grand strategy,” however, is exactly what Geoffrey Parker set out to demonstrate in<italic>The Grand Strategy of Philip II</italic>(New Haven, Conn., 1998). Braudel may be correct that Philip, as a prince, was not a student of geography. But what Philip did study, architecture, emphasized design. No discipline was more useful to understanding “general notions or grand strategies.” Thus, Braudel’s Part III, as traditional as it is often said to be, appears to get the story and the king wrong because Braudel’s steering assumption, not Philip II, was in control: “Good reasons for us to reflect once more on the distance separating biographical history from the history of structures, and even more from the history of geographical areas” (2:1237). For a similar critique, see also M. J. Rodríguez‐Salgado, “Dust and Ashes: The History of Politics and War,” in<italic>Early Modern History and the Social Sciences</italic>(n. 2 above), pp. 145–67, esp. 164–65, which argues for greater focus on Philip II and his empire as in her<italic>The Changing Face of Empire: Charles V, Philip II and Habsburg Authority, 1551–1559</italic>(Cambridge, 1988). Already in McNeill’s 1972<italic>JMH</italic>introductory note, he hinted at the problem: “M. Braudel, who in writing of himself and his intellectual forerunners offers a remarkable example of both the strengths and weaknesses of the<italic>Annales</italic>school—perspicacious, penetrating, and detached, even in analyzing himself; yet, though in principle disdainful of mere occurrences, unable to explain his own history except in terms of personal encounters, friendships, conversations, yes and rivalries!”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn127">
               <label>126</label>
               <p>Braudel, “The Situation of History in 1950” (n. 73 above), p. 20, continues, “For to challenge the enormous role that has sometimes been assigned to certain outstanding men in the genesis of history is by no means to deny the stature of the individual as individual and the fascination that there is for one man in poring over the fate of another.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn128">
               <label>127</label>
               <p>Hexter (n. 11 above), pp. 509–10, argues that Braudel’s experiences in German prison camps created his vision of the importance of the<italic>longue durée</italic>over the short term as “a necessary act of faith, the narrow path to salvation” and survival. His point is reinforced by Daix (n. 2 above), p. 452.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn129">
               <label>128</label>
               <p>Braudel, “The Situation of History in 1950” (n. 73 above), pp. 6–8. See also Hexter (n. 11 above), pp. 510–12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn130">
               <label>129</label>
               <p>Braudel,<italic>The Mediterranean,</italic>2d ed. (1972), 2:1243–44. Among many references to Machiavelli, see, e.g., Machiavelli,<italic>The Prince,</italic>chap. xxv, beginning of last paragraph: “I conclude, then, that so long as Fortune varies and men stand still, they will prosper while they suit the times, and fail when they do not.”</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
