<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4625899</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519771</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR870402</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Two Apologetic Moments in Śaṅkara’s Concept of Brahman<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Nicholson</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Coe College</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2007</year>
            <string-date>October 2007</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>87</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>509555</issue-id>
         <fpage>528</fpage>
         <lpage>555</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2007 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/519771"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>Many thanks to Andrew Nicholson and Reid Locklin for their helpful critical comments on an earlier draft of this article.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Constructive theological works invariably contain refutations of opposing views. The positive formulation of religious belief is typically bound up with some form of polemics. And yet, what might appear obvious to the outside observer is rarely acknowledged by the religious insider, namely, that the content of religious belief is substantively influenced by the refutation of rival teachings. In traditional theological self‐understanding, apologetics is only a secondary theological enterprise; at most, rival teachings influence the formulation, but never the substantive content, of a self‐contained system of religious belief. Some contemporary theologians, however, have abandoned the dubious presumption that their tradition’s core beliefs are self‐generated, that they occupy a kind of magic circle insulated from outside influence. Appealing to Mikhail Bakhtin’s concept of “double‐voiced” discourse, Christian theologian Kathryn Tanner writes: “A kind of apologetics or polemics with other cultures is internal, then, to the very construction of Christian sense. … Theological statements themselves amount to a transformative and reevaluative commentary on the wider culture insofar as they are double‐voiced: theological statements mouth the claims of other cultures while giving them a new spin.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Tanner’s statement is a response to a problematic that is specific to Christian theology in the modern West, namely, the relation of theological claims to secular knowledge, or, to use a more theological idiom, the relation between “Christ and culture.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>The understanding of theological statements as double voiced transcends this particular problematic, however. As I hope to show in this article, the concept of double‐voiced discourse can shed considerable light on at least one theological tradition outside of Christianity, namely, the tradition of non‐Dualist or Advaita Vedānta.</p>
      <p>Śaṅkara’s<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>(early eighth century CE),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>the foundational text of the Advaita tradition, is an outstanding example of multivoiced theological discourse. Like most of Śaṅkara’s other major works, the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>belongs to the genre of commentary—actually, it is a metacommentary. The set of gnomic utterances known as the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>(fifth century CE)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>—the immediate object of Śaṅkara's commentary—itself constitutes a commentary on the disparate collection of texts composing the Upaniṣadic corpus (the earliest of which date from roughly the seventh to eighth centuries BCE).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>On each of these commentarial levels the intention of the commentary “spins” and refracts, but does not efface, that of the text upon which it comments.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>The perspective of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, which, as we shall see, differs in certain respects from Śaṅkara’s own, is still visible just beneath the refracting surface of the latter’s commentary.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>But the multivocality of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>is actually far richer and more complex than this tripartite schema of text, commentary, and metacommentary suggests. Both the commentary, the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, and the metacommentary, Śaṅkara’s<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>, incorporate discourses in addition to the respective texts upon which they explicitly comment.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>Included among the “voices” appropriated and spun are those of rival schools. Indeed, this apologetic dimension of the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>is as pronounced as the commentarial. Even a cursory glance at the text shows that refutations of opposing views compose a large portion of the work.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>
      </p>
      <p>In this article I hope to show that an appreciation of the commentarial and apologetic dimensions of Śaṅkara’s<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>is essential to a proper understanding of the Advaita concept of brahman. Here I follow the lead of Francis Clooney, who warns against the temptation to reduce the teaching of Advaita to an easily accessible set of conclusions or propositions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>A set of propositions cannot be abstracted from the exegetical practices and apologetic strategies from which they emerge without suffering a loss of meaning. Advaita doctrine is properly understood only when it is seen as the outcome of a careful negotiation of meaning with authoritative texts and competing interpretations of those texts. In keeping with Clooney’s insistence on the “intratextual” nature of Advaita doctrine, I would like to suggest that we view the concept of brahman, particularly with reference to its transcendental character, as generated out of the tension among the multiple voices that constitute the Advaita “Text.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>Here I find it helpful to relate the development of the Advaitic concept of brahman as recorded in the stratified text of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>to the metaphorical process by which the transcendent concept of God is constructed through the “qualification” (Ian Ramsey) of a basic conceptual model.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>The concept of brahman is gradually built up from the successive qualifications the founding teachers of Vedānta impart to the conceptual models they inherit from the brahmanical tradition. These qualifications, moreover, typically are apologetically motivated. The reception of traditional teachings occurs in a polemical context in which the meaning of those teachings is inflected by contemporary apologetic concerns. In the pages that follow, I shall identify two such apologetic “moments” in the development of the concept of brahman as it is found in the text of Śaṅkara’s<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>.</p>
      <p>In the first moment, the early Vedāntic tradition qualifies the Upaniṣadic understanding of the highest principle as the material cause of the world. The foundational text for this basic understanding is the celebrated sixth chapter of the Chāndogya Upaniṣad. There the sage Uddalāka Āruṇi likens the supreme gnoseological principle to the clay from which all clay artifacts can be known. Appealing to other Upaniṣadic texts that speak of brahman as the intelligent agent of creation, Vedānta “qualifies” this basic model by insisting that the supreme principle, brahman, is at the same time the world’s intelligent efficient cause (<italic>nimitta‐kāraṇa</italic>). Apologetic considerations played a central role in calling attention to the “agency” texts qualifying the model of brahman as<italic>causa materialis</italic>. To be specific, a crucial factor in this emphasis on the conscious and intelligent nature of brahman was a concern with refuting the influential interpretation of the Sāṃkhya school, which postulated insentient matter, or<italic>pra</italic>
         <italic>dhāna</italic>, as the world cause. This understanding of brahman as the world’s material and efficient cause was most probably the achievement of the pre‐Śaṅkara tradition of realist Vedānta.</p>
      <p>In a second apologetic moment, Śaṅkara’s Advaita school, perhaps borrowing from some version of the Buddhist Two Truths doctrine, introduced a hitherto unknown distinction between the conditioned and unconditioned forms of brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>This distinction further qualified the basic conception of brahman as the world’s material cause. While the first qualification had the effect of removing brahman from the range of empirical cognition (it being impossible for the human mind to wrap itself around the idea of material and efficient causation inhering in a single principle), the second qualified the cosmological conception of brahman to the point of rendering metaphorical the idea of brahman/God as creator. For the concept of qualityless (<italic>nirguṇa</italic>) brahman implies a denial of the independent existence of the very world that the personal, creator brahman—now relegated to a lower, conditioned manifestation of the former—was supposed to bring into being. As was the case with the first, this qualification was motivated by apologetic considerations. The concept of unconditioned,<italic>nirguṇa</italic>brahman was part of a discourse intended to undermine the legitimacy of ritual and meditative activity as salvific means. It reflects a polemic between Śaṅkara, representing the ideal of “pure” renunciation, and other Vedāntists who believed that a combination of renunciation and ritual activity was the most effective means of salvation.</p>
      <p>Given the paucity of sources, both textual and extratextual, for the history of early Vedānta, to say nothing of that of early Sāṃkhya, the proposed reading of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>in terms of two defining apologetic moments can claim to be little more than a hypothesis. Nevertheless, it does carry some important interpretive benefits. As I hope to show in the second part of this essay, it sheds fresh critical light on the long‐standing and controversial question of whether Śaṅkara taught that the phenomenal world is unreal. Moreover, this reading of the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>as double voiced, in emphasizing the creative tension between the personal and impersonal aspects of brahman, suggests a more dynamic conception of brahman than the abstract and static Absolute typically associated with the Śaṅkara tradition.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Kathryn Tanner,<italic>Theories of Culture</italic>(Minneapolis: Fortress, 1997), 116.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>See Kathryn Tanner, “The Difference Theological Anthropology Makes,”<italic>Theology Today</italic>50, no. 4 (January 1994): 568–69, on the commentarial nature of theology vis‐à‐vis the natural and human sciences.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>See Hajime Nakamura,<italic>A History of Early</italic>Vedānta<italic>Philosophy</italic>, trans. Trevor Leggett et al. (Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1983), pt. 1:65–89, for determination of Śaṅkara’s dates. Nakamura places the period of Śaṅkara’s creative activity in the first half of the eighth century.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Nakamura dates the final redaction of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>between 400 and 450 CE. The composition of the sutras would have taken place much earlier. See ibid., 436.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>See Patrick Olivelle, trans.,<italic>Upaniṣads</italic>(Oxford, 1996), xxxvi–xxxvii. The dates given for the Upaniṣads are extremely rough; as Olivelle observes, “Any dating of these documents that attempts a precision closer than a few centuries is as stable as a house of cards” (xxxvi).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>See Mikhail Bakhtin,<italic>Problems of Dostoevsky’s Poetics</italic>, trans. Caryl Emerson (Minneapolis, 1984), 189: “But the author may also make use of someone else’s discourse for his own purposes, by inserting a new semantic intention into a discourse which already has, and which retains, an intention of its own.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>My use of the metaphor of visibility and surface comes from Tanner,<italic>Theories of Culture</italic>, 116.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>The<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, for example, cites the teachings of Bādarāyaṇa as the authority for its own (Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 406). Occasional divergences between the views of Bādarāyaṇa and the author of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>(ibid., 519, 423)—most notably, on the relation between rites and knowledge—reveal (at least) two distinct intentions, two voices, internal to the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>. In a similar way, Śaṅkara’s commentary most likely preserves the “voice” of an earlier, although unfortunately no longer extant, commentary. As we shall see below, Śaṅkara followed an earlier commentarial tradition on the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, notwithstanding the fact that this earlier commentary represented a distinct interpretive position.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Sometimes, although relatively rarely, the commentarial and the apologetic dimensions of a classical Indian text coincided. It was not unheard of in classical India for an author to make use of a text from a rival community for the dissemination of his own views. It appears that sometimes the decision to comment on a given text was determined less by the level of agreement between its teachings and the commentator’s own than by the recognition that that text had attained in the wider brahmanical community. See Klaus Rüping,<italic>Philologische Untersuchungen zu den Brahmasūtra‐Kommentaren des Śaṅkara und des Bhāskara</italic>[Philological investigations on the Brahma‐sūtra commentaries of Śaṅkara and Bhāskara] (Wiesbaden: Steiner, 1977), 67: “Dort kommt es recht oft vor, dass ein Autor einen gegnerischen Text, etwa den einer rivalisierenden religiösen Gruppe, benutzt und ihn für seine eigenen Zwecke umarbeitet” (There it often happens that an author makes use of an opponent's text, perhaps that of a rival religious group, and modifies it in accordance with his own purposes).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Francis X. Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedānta</italic>(Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1993), 28–29 and passim, and “The Principle of Upasaṃhāra and the Development of Vedānta as an Uttara Mīmāṃsā,” in<italic>Studies in Mīmāṃsā</italic>, ed. R. C. Dwivedi (Delhi: Motilal, 1994), 279–80 and passim. Clooney’s preference for a textual/exegetical, rather than strictly philosophical, approach to the study of Vedānta is informed by his extensive study of Mīmāṃsā.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>While respecting the tradition’s insistence that brahman is more than the object of what Foucault would call a “discursive formation,” Clooney argues that the knowledge of brahman is thoroughly “inscribed” in the Advaita “Text”; that is to say, such knowledge becomes available only in and through a sustained engagement with the foundational texts of the Advaita tradition. See Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedānta</italic>, 33: “Though Brahman is neither a fiction (as might be a character in a novel) nor a textual production (as might be a ritual vis‐à‐vis the texts which accompany it), Advaita’s truth about Brahman does not exist outside of texts, but only after them.” See also “Principle of Upasaṃhāra,” 284, 294 n. 12, where Clooney draws an intriguing parallel between the Vedānta concept of brahman and the Mīmāṃsā principle of<italic>artha</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>For the theory of models and qualifiers, see Ian T. Ramsey,<italic>Religious Language</italic>(London: Macmillan, 1957), esp. chap. 2. Theological qualification need not imply an attenuation of cognitive meaning as assumed by the positivist critics of theological language in the original “theology and falsification” debate. Rather, if the theory of models and qualifiers is understood in terms of a tension or interaction theory of metaphor, then the theological qualification described by Ramsey can be seen as a mechanism for the creation of meaning. For a critical, although appreciative, use of Ramsey’s theory, see Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Paul Ricoeur on Biblical Hermeneutics</italic>, Semeia 4 (Missoula, MT: Scholars Press, 1975), 119–24; see also David Tracy,<italic>Blessed Rage for Order</italic>(Chicago, 1996), 121–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>See Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 488: “Śaṅkara regarded Brahman with such active character as the Lord (<italic>īśvara</italic>), and distinguished it from Brahman in itself, but the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>itself did not distinguish between the two.”</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>The Rejection of Sāṃkhya and the Doctrine of Brahman as Intelligent Material Cause</title>
         <p>In this first section I shall argue that a refutation of Sāṃkhya played a central role in the early conceptualization of brahman in the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>. The two defining features of that conception were, first, that brahman was the chief purport of the Upaniṣads and, second, that it was a reality irreducible to the objects of ordinary cognition (<italic>pramāṇaviṣayaḥ</italic>). These two propositions establish the defining principle of Vedānta, namely, the independent validity of the Upaniṣadic texts. To the extent that their object was a transcendent reality, the Upaniṣads were subservient neither to the injunctive portion of the Veda nor to the worldly means of valid cognition (<italic>pramāṇa</italic>).</p>
         <p>Even a casual perusal of Śaṅkara’s<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>reveals that a remarkably large portion of this text is devoted to a refutation of Sāṃkhya teaching.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>Śaṅkara apparently feels the need to justify the disproportionate attention given to Sāṃkhya when he suggests that a refutation of other rival doctrines is included in the refutation of the Sāṃkhya doctrine of insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>as the world’s cause.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>The hint of an apologetic attitude here indicates that Śaṅkara, in refuting Sāṃkhya theories so extensively, is simply following the lead of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, as he himself, in fact, acknowledges.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Indeed, the refutation of Sāṃkhya may not have been a vital and pressing concern for Śaṅkara himself, and the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>’s extensive treatment of Sāṃkhya doctrines may have been little more than a holdover from the concerns of the author(s) of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>. Whatever may have been the extent of Śaṅkara’s direct concern with Sāṃkhya, it is clear that the critique of Sāṃkhya belongs to the earliest, formative stages of the Vedānta tradition. As Nakamura observes, “A great portion of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>is devoted to the criticism of Sāṃkhya, and it is possible to say that it was through this criticism that the Vedāntic school established itself as an independent philosophical tradition.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As mentioned above, the Sāṃkhya doctrine that preoccupied the author(s) of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>was the doctrine of insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>as the world cause. The<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>doctrine presented an immediate challenge to the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>’s project of establishing brahman as the universal purport of the Upaniṣads. That all the Upaniṣads speak of Brahman as the fundamental cosmic principle is by no means obvious. The<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>selected brahman from a series of possible candidates mentioned in various places within the Upaniṣadic corpus—<italic>prāṇa</italic>,<italic>puruṣa</italic>,<italic>akṣara</italic>, and so on.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>If brahman’s claim to be the absolute cosmic principle seems obvious to us today, this is due to the now virtually unrivalled influence of the Vedāntic interpretation. During the time of the composition and redaction of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, however—that is, during Vedānta’s formative period—it was the Sāṃkhya school that most likely held a privileged and influential position within the brahmanical tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>Thus, the author of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, almost immediately after proposing brahman as the universal import of the Upaniṣads and as the world cause, is obliged in I.1.5ff. to repudiate<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>’s claim to that title. That the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>’s concept of brahman was developed in the context of a rejection of the<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>concept suggests a more intimate connection between polemics and doctrine in the formative stages of Vedānta than is usually acknowledged. To be specific, Vedānta’s insistence on the conscious nature of brahman appears to have been inextricably bound up with the explicit rejection of insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>as the world cause. And it is this insistence that forms the basis of the great teaching of the Vedānta, namely, the identification (however conceived by the various traditions of Vedānta) of brahman, as cosmic principle, and<italic>ātman</italic>, as the principle of consciousness.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>
         </p>
         <p>While the paucity of information about early Sāṃkhya and Vedānta rules out any firm conclusions regarding their historical relationship, the two schools most likely emerged out of a common tradition of brahmanical religious thought. An indication of this common origin is the fact that, as Edgerton demonstrated long ago in a still‐valuable article, the two main distinguishing doctrines of Sāṃkhya, namely, the denial of God and the plurality of souls, only appear in that tradition quite late.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>The earliest sources for Sāṃkhya philosophy in the (late) Upaniṣadic and epic literature, most notably in the Mokṣadharma Parvan of the<italic>Mahābhārata</italic>, contain little, if anything, to rule out a Vedāntic interpretation. Thanks to this common heritage in what Edgerton calls “epic brahmanism,” Sāṃkhya and Vedānta share, despite their mutual antagonism, a number of fundamental presuppositions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>Both presuppose the concepts of karma and samsara, as well as the understanding of salvation as liberation (<italic>mokṣa</italic>) from samsarric existence. Both schools advocate a kind of knowledge, as opposed to ritual or cultic activity, as the means of liberation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>Moreover, both understood the nature of this knowledge to consist in a discrimination (<italic>viveka</italic>) between the soul (<italic>ātman</italic>for the one;<italic>puruṣa</italic>for the other) and body.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>Both affirmed, against schools like the Vaiśeṣika, the principle of<italic>satkāryatva</italic>, that is, the preexistence of the effect in its cause. Most important, both schools recognized the authority of the Upaniṣads.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>We can readily understand the early Vedāntists’ antagonism toward the Sāṃkhya doctrines in terms of the sociological principle that proximity constitutes a threat to the distinctive identity of a school or tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>It is noteworthy that later, when the respective identities of the two schools were safely established, Indian thinkers like Vijñānabhikṣu were able to reconcile and synthesize the teachings of these two schools with relative ease.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Although these two schools did not originally differ greatly with respect to doctrinal content, sharing as they did a common body of brahmanical religious teaching, they did differ in terms of their respective methods. This difference in method is clearly indicated by the respective senses of the terms<italic>sāṃ</italic>
            <italic>khya</italic>and<italic>vedānta</italic>before these terms came to designate philosophical schools. In its early usage in the epic literature,<italic>sāṃ</italic>
            <italic>khya</italic>probably did not refer to a particular philosophical system but referred more generically to the intellectual method of salvation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>Edgerton interprets this original sense of<italic>sāṃ</italic>
            <italic>khya</italic>as “(the method of salvation) based on reckoning or calculation.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>In a similar way, the term<italic>vedānta</italic>, before it came to designate a particular set of doctrines, referred to the interpretive‐exegetical study of the Upaniṣadic corpus.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>This early sense of<italic>vedānta</italic>still remains close to its literal reference to a body of texts situated “at the end of the Veda.” Thus, from its earliest beginnings, the Vedāntic school was defined by its fidelity to the Upaniṣadic texts.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>Significantly, early texts such as Kauṭilīya’s<italic>Arthaśāstra</italic>appear not to have recognized Vedānta and its closely allied sister school, the Pūrva‐mīmāṃsā, as schools of philosophy (<italic>ānvīkṣikī</italic>), viewing them instead—and not unjustly—as schools of Vedic exegesis.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>While acknowledging the risks involved in using Western categories in the interpretation of Indian culture, we might capture the difference between Sāṃkhya and Vedānta by characterizing the former as primarily a system of philosophy and the latter as one of theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>Of course this difference in the respective attitudes of these two schools toward “faith” and “reason” was a matter of emphasis. Vedānta, for its part, recognized the validity, albeit restricted and subordinate, of the use of reason (<italic>yukti</italic>) in deciding matters of interpretation and doctrine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>For its part, Sāṃkhya also acknowledged the authority of the Upaniṣads, although it had a more realistic appreciation than did Vedānta of the ambiguities and inconsistencies of this disparate body of texts. Accordingly, it affirmed the preeminence of reason in deciding between conflicts of interpretation. Gerald Larson nicely summarizes this difference between Vedānta, represented by Śaṅkara, and Sāṃkhya when he writes: “For Śaṅkara philosophy is the handmaiden of ‘theology.’ For Sāṃkhya ‘theology’ is the handmaiden of philosophy.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In his commentary on<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>I.1.5, Śaṇkara indicates quite clearly that this methodological difference between Vedānta and Sāṃkhya is fundamental. Whatever doctrinal differences these two schools have derive from this fundamental difference in approach. The defining characteristic of the Sāṃkhya candidate for world cause,<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>, is that it is the product of inference (<italic>anumāṇika</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>Conceived independently of Upaniṣadic study,<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>is subsequently read into the Upaniṣads as an interpretive hypothesis. Śaṅkara implies that the Sāṃkhyas’ appeal to scripture was little more than an afterthought, a vain attempt to imbue their doctrines with underserved legitimacy. In keeping with their view that the Upaniṣads were hopelessly ambiguous apart from rational reflection, the Sāṃkhyas conceded that, from a purely exegetical point of view, brahman and<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>have equally plausible claims to Upaniṣadic purport.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>What tips the balance in favor of<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>is its greater plausibility from a rational point of view.<italic>Pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>, by virtue of its composite nature that allows it to undergo transformation, is more plausibly understood as the world’s material cause than is the simple and unchangeable brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Śaṅkara refuses to be drawn into a debate with his Sāṃkhya opponent on the latter’s terms. Although he promises a refutation of the Sāṃkhya hypothesis later on in his commentary on II.1.4, here Śaṅkara all but concedes the greater plausibility of the Sāṃkhya position. Unwavering in his exegetical focus, however, Śaṅkara declares this consideration to be irrelevant. However plausible it might seem on the surface, the Sāṃkhya hypothesis is to be rejected for the simple reason that it is not supported in the Upaniṣads.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>
         </p>
         <p>What disqualifies<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>from consideration as the world’s cause are Upaniṣadic passages such as Chāndogya 6.2.3 and Aitareya 1.1.1–2 that speak of an act of visualization (<italic>īkṣā</italic>) preceding creation (<italic>īkṣāpūr</italic>
            <italic>vikām sṛṣṭim</italic>). Here Śaṅkara’s commentary closely follows the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>Although such passages are well attested in the major Upaniṣads, it would be naive to deny that an interest in refuting Sāṃkhya played a crucial role in lifting up these passages for special attention. After all, it is well known that even interpreters sincerely committed to following scriptural texts have many interpretive stratagems at their disposal in order to get around passages that interfere with their interpretive interests. Here exegetical considerations are inextricably bound up with apologetic ones.</p>
         <p>When combined with passages such as Chāndogya 6.1 that speak of brahman as the cosmological substrate, this affirmation of brahman as an intelligent, deliberative causal agent results in a concept of brahman utterly transcending human powers of intuitive comprehension. A transcendent conception of brahman is generated from the juxtaposition of two logically irreconcilable claims. We witness this emergence of transcendence out of contradiction in the topical section, or<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>, consisting of the five sutras of I.4.23–27. Here Śaṅkara affirms brahman as the world’s material (<italic>upādāna</italic>) as well as efficient (<italic>nimitta</italic>) cause. The problematic dealt with in this<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>presupposes the result of I.1.5ff., namely, that brahman, against the claims of the Sāṃkhyas, is a deliberative causal agent. The<italic>pūrvapakṣin</italic>appeals to this result in arguing that only efficient causality can be plausibly attributed to brahman (<italic>nimittakāraṇatvam eva brahmaṇaḥ</italic>). Causality preceded by deliberation is observed only with respect to efficient causes like potters and goldsmiths.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>Moreover, efficient causality exempts the changeless and pure brahman from the requirement that the (material) cause share the same defiled nature as its effect.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Against this argument the Vedānta<italic>siddhāntin</italic>affirms the material causality of brahman by reaffirming principles that, if taken on their own, readily lend themselves to a Sāṃkhya interpretation. He appeals to the principle of the nondifference (<italic>ananyatva</italic>,<italic>avyatirekatva</italic>) of cause and effect, presupposed in Uddālaka Āruṇī’s promise, in Chāndogya 6, to impart to Śvetaketu a knowledge of that by which all else is known (<italic>ekena vijñānena sarvam anyad avijñātam api vijñātaṃ bhavati</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>A little later, following up on sutra I.4.26’s mention of the principle of modification (<italic>ātmakṛteḥ pariṇāmāt</italic>), he argues that brahman causes himself to be transformed (<italic>pariṇamayām āsa‐ātmānam</italic>) as the innermost nature of the resultant modifications.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>Śaṅkara is fully aware that the affirmation of brahman’s material causality in a context presupposing his agency renders the nature of brahman’s causality incomprehensible. He concludes this section by declaring irrelevant the opponent’s argument that deliberative causality appears in the world only with respect to efficient causes. Empirical experience is not decisive here, for brahman is not an object of inference.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Such a transcendent conception of brahman, generated from the twin affirmation of brahman’s efficient and material causality, forms the basis of the authority of the Upaniṣadic corpus. Here Vedānta follows its Mīmāṃsā cousin in founding its authoritative texts on an “object” inaccessible to ordinary means of cognition. Since brahman, like the Mīmāṃsā principle of dharma, is inaccessible to the worldly<italic>pramāṇas</italic>, the Upaniṣadic texts that have brahman as their purport cannot be rendered superfluous, much less contradicted, by ordinary forms of knowledge and experience.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>Here Vedānta reveals its close kinship with Mīmāṃsā.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>As a transcendent reality inaccessible to the worldly<italic>pramāṇas</italic>, brahman ensures against a slide into redundancy that would deprive the Upaniṣads of their authority.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>At the same time, brahman, insofar as it is a present reality (albeit a transcendent one), prevents the subordination of the Upaniṣads to the injunctive portion of the Veda, as claimed by the Mīmāṃsā.</p>
         <p>Like a play of mirrors, the development of the Vedāntic concept of brahman in the context of a repudiation of Sāṃkhya cosmology has a circular quality to it. On the one hand, the assertion of Upaniṣadic authority against Sāṃkhya rationalism leads to the conceptualization of brahman as a transcendent object. On the other, this conception of brahman in turn justifies the independent validity of the Upaniṣadic corpus.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>See Gerald James Larson,<italic>Classical Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>(Santa Barbara, CA: Ross/Erikson, 1979), 209: “Śaṅkara in his<italic>Vedānta‐sūtra‐bhāṣya</italic>gives more detailed and precise attention to the criticism of Sāṃkhya than he does to any other system.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Ibid., 210; see J. L. Shastri, ed.,<italic>BrahmaSūtra‐Śaṅkarabhāṣyam</italic>(Delhi: Motilal, 1980; hereafter<italic>BSūBh</italic>), 343, lines 6–8 (I.4.28): “ataḥ pradhānamallanirbahaṇanyāyenātidiśati—etena pradhānakāraṇavādapratiṣedhanyāyakalāpena sarve ʿṇvādikāraṇavādā api pratiṣiddhatayā vyākhyātā veditavyāḥ. teṣām api pradhānavad aśabdatvācchabdavirodhitvācceti” (Hence he extends [his critique to other views] with the argument used to defeat the pradhāna doctrine, the [strongest] wrestler, as it were. By this lead argument against the doctrine of pradhāna as the world cause, all other doctrines, such as the [Vaiśeṣika] atomic theory of causation, are also to be understood as refuted). Unless otherwise indicated, all translations are my own. I have erred on the side of readability over literal accuracy.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>But see Larson,<italic>Classical Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>, 211, for a reference to other scholars, George Thibaut in particular, who call into question Śaṅkara’s claim that his refutation of Sāṃkhya simply follows that of Bādarāyaṇa.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 472, 301, 432; Mysore Hiriyanna makes the same point in “Bhartṛ‐prapañca: An Old Vedāntin,” in his<italic>Indian Philosophical Studies</italic>(Mysore: Kavyalaya, 1957), 94: “It would perhaps be not far from correct to say that one of the foremost aims—albeit a negative one—of<italic>Bādarāyaṇa</italic>in composing the Vedānta‐<italic>sūtras</italic>was to refute the view that the realistic and dualistic<italic>Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>was the teaching of the Upaniṣads.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 105, gives a useful list of the various principles that Vedānta will correlate to brahman; see also 429, on the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>’s selection of brahman as the absolute principle from a number of possible alternative candidates.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Ibid., 472; see also Larson,<italic>Classical Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>, 213.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>The<italic>ātman</italic>‐brahman equation is best regarded as the achievement of Vedāntic interpretation rather than as a straightforward translation of the Upaniṣadic formula,<italic>tat tvam asi</italic>. This is the conclusion one draws from Joel Brereton’s seminal article, “<italic>Tat Tvam Asi</italic>in Context,”<italic>Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</italic>136, no. 1 (1986): 98–109.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Franklin Edgerton, “The Meaning of Sānkhya and Yoga,”<italic>American Journal of Philology</italic>45, no. 1 (1924): 7–14 (against the assumption that early Sāṃkhya was atheistic), 22–29 (on the relative lateness of the doctrine of the plurality of souls). In his critical summary of past scholarship on Sāṃkhya, Gerald Larson has mostly good things to say about Edgerton. His criticism is that the latter, in advancing the thesis that Sāṃkhya was defined by its method and not by any specific content, tended to overstate his case; Larson faults him for overcompensating for the tendency in previous scholarship to read later doctrines into early texts. As far as I can tell, however, this criticism has mostly to do with emphasis, leaving Edgerton’s basic theses intact. See Larson,<italic>Classical Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>, 33–36, esp. 36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Edgerton, “Meaning of Sānkhya and Yoga,” 33ff. See Hiriyanna, “Bhartṛ‐prapañca,” 92–94, on the resemblances between the early Vedānta of Bhartṛ‐prapañca and Sāṃkhya.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Edgerton, “Meaning of Sānkhya and Yoga,” 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Ibid., 12, 16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 432, 473.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Śaṅkara himself acknowledges the threat posed by the similarity of the Sāṃkhya teaching to Vedānta, specifically, with respect to the principle of<italic>satkāryavāda</italic>. See Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 343, line 3 (I.4.28): “sa ca kāryakāraṇānanyatvābhyupagamāt pratyāsanno vedāntavādasya” (The [Sāṃkhya position] is close to that of the Vedānta, on account of its acknowledgment of the principle of the nondifference between cause and effect).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>See Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 334; see also Andrew J. Nicholson, “Doxography, Classificatory Schemes, and Contested Histories,” which forms chap. 4 of his (as of yet) unpublished dissertation, “Doctrine and Boundary Formation: The Philosophy of Vijñānabhikṣu in Indian Intellectual History” (PhD diss., University of Chicago, Department of South Asian Languages and Civilizations, 2005), 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Edgerton,<italic>Meaning of Sānkhya and Yoga</italic>, 36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Ibid., 36–37. In support of this thesis Edgerton (36) cites and translates<italic>Mahābhārata</italic>12.11934: “doṣāṇāṃ ca guṇānāṃ ca, pramāṇaṃ pravibhāgataḥ, kaṃcid artham abhipretya, sā saṃkhyeti upadhāryatām” (The weighing of strong and weak points severally, as one presses forward to some conclusion, this should be understood as<italic>saṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>, reasoning, calculation).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 108–16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>Ibid., 116.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Ibid., 320–21; see also 331–32, on the similar perception of Vedānta in early Nyāya and Vaiśeṣika literature. Significantly, Vedānta and Mīmāṃsā were originally not seen as separate (331).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Clooney, in particular, has argued for the characterization of Advaita as theology rather than philosophy; see<italic>Theology after Vedānta</italic>, 26ff. Of course, to describe Advaita as primarily theological is not to suggest that Advaita thinkers like Śaṅkara were not capable of rigorous philosophical argumentation. Moreover, this “philosophical” dimension comes to the fore when Advaitins turn to the refutation of rival views, where reasoning was granted a certain autonomy, as the works of Citsukha and Śrīharṣa (among others) attest.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>For two excellent studies of the relationship between reason and authority in Śaṅkara’s Vedānta, see Wilhelm Halbfass, “Human Reason and Vedic Revelation in Advaita Vedānta,” in his<italic>Tradition and Reflection</italic>(Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1991), 131–204; and John Taber, “Reason, Revelation, and Idealism in Śaṅkara’s Vedānta,”<italic>Journal of Indian Philosophy</italic>9 (1981): 283–307.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Larson,<italic>Classical Sāṃ</italic>
                  <italic>khya</italic>, 219.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 100, lines 3–4 (I.1.5): “sāṃkhyādāyas tu pariniṣṭhaṃ vastu pramāṇāntaragamyam eveti manyamānāḥ pradhānadīni kāraṇāntarāṇy‐anumānās” (The Sāṃkhyas and others, assuming that an established [<italic>pariniṣṭham</italic>=<italic>siddham</italic>] reality is accessible to means of cognition other [than scripture], infer other causal principles, such as<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Ibid., 101, lines 4–5: “yāni vedāntavākyāni sarvajñasya sarvaśakter brahmaṇo jagatkāraṇatvaṃ darśayantīty avocās tāni pradhānakāraṇapakṣe ʿpi yojayituṃ śakyante” (Those Upaniṣadic texts that you [Vedāntists] claimed reveal the omniscient and omnipotent brahman as the world cause can also be reconciled with the view that<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>is the world cause).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Ibid., 102, lines 8–9: “api ca pradhānasyānekātmakasya pariṇāmasambhavāt kāraṇatvopapattir mṛdādivat; nāsaṃhatasyaikātmakasya brahmaṇa ity” (Composite<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>, on account of its capacity to undergo modification, more closely resembles familiar material causes like clay and is therefore more plausibly conceived as the world cause than is the uniform and simple brahman).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Ibid., 108, lines 2–3: “yad apy uktaṃ pradhānasyānekātmakatvān mṛdādivat kāraṇatvopapattir nāsaṃhatasya brahmaṇa iti, tat pradhānasyāśabdatvenaiva pratyuktam” (What was said above—namely, that<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>, on account of its composite nature, is, like clay and other material causes, more plausibly regarded as the world cause than is the simple brahman—this is refuted by the simple fact that<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>is not mentioned in scripture).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Note that the proper identification of the world cause is rooted in the problem of reconciling two Chāndogya texts, namely, 6.1 and 6.2. This observation supports Nakamura’s thesis that the teaching of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>was originally based on the Chāndogya Upaniṣad and later extended and adapted to the other Upaniṣads; see Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 429–31.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 338, lines 5–6: “īkṣāpūrvakaṃ ca kartṛtvaṃ nimittakāraṇeṣv eva kulālādiṣu dṛśṭam” (Causality preceded by deliberation is known only with respect to efficient causes like potters and the like).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>See ibid., 338, lines 8–10: “kāryaṃ cedaṃ jagatsāvayavam acetanam aśuddhaṃ ca dṛśyate kāraṇenāpi tasya tādṛśenaiva bhavitavyaṃ, kāryakāraṇayoḥ sārūpyadarśanāt” (Moreover, as this world, the effect, manifests itself as insentient, impure, and composite, its cause must also be of the same nature. For cause and effect are understood to be of the same nature).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Ibid., 339, lines 7–8 (I.4.23): “taccopadānakāraṇavijñāne sarvavijñānaṃ saṃbhavatyupādānakāraṇāvyatirekāt kāryasya; nimittakāraṇāvyatirekastu kāryasya nāsti” (It is possible for one to know everything when the material cause is known. This is possible [only] because the effect is not separate from its material cause. But this nonseparation of cause and effect is not true with respect to the efficient cause).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Ibid., 341, lines 8–9: “pūrvasiddho ʿpi hi sannātmā viśeṣeṇa vikārātmanā pariṇamayām asātmānamiti” (Even though the self is an established and present reality, he still causes himself to be transformed into distinct modifications).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Ibid., 342, lines 7–8 (I.4.27): “yat punar idam uktam īkṣāpūrvakaṃ kartṛtvaṃ nimittakāraṇeṣveva kulālādiṣu loke dṛśṭaṃ nopādāneṣvityādi, tatpratyucyate: na lokavad iha bhavitavyam. na hy ayam anumānagamyo ʿrthaḥ” (What was argued above—namely, that causality preceded by reflection appears in the world only in the case of efficient causes, like potters, and not in that of material causes—this is refuted as follows: what is to be affirmed here need not be like anything appearing in the world. For the object here is not to be grasped through inference). On the orientation toward Upaniṣadic authority over reason in the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>itself, see also the discussion of<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>II.1.26–27 in Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 476.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 360, line 8 (II.1.6): “āgamamātrasamadhigamya eva tvayam artho dharmavat” (Rather, this object [namely, brahman], like the principle of dharma, is to be known only from the scriptures).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>On the close kinship between early Vedānta and the Mīmāṃsā school, see Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 409–13.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 360, lines 6–8 (II.1.6): “yat tu uktaṃ pariniṣpannatvād brahmaṇi pramāṇāntarāṇi saṃbhaveyur iti tadapi manorathamātram. rūpādyabhāvāddhi nāyamarthaḥ pratyakṣasya gocaraḥ. liṅgādyabhāvācca nānumānādīnām” (The above‐mentioned claim—namely, that brahman must be accessible to the<italic>pramāṇas</italic>since it is an actually existing reality—is nothing more than an illusion. For this object does not lie within the range of perception since it does not have form. Nor does it lie in the range of the various forms of inference since it is devoid of distinguishing marks). See also ibid., 63, line 4 (I.1.4): “na ca pariniṣṭhitavastusvarūpatve ʿpi pratyakṣādiviṣayatvaṃ brahmaṇaḥ” (Though it is brahman’s nature to be a thoroughly known reality, still, brahman is not an object of the worldly<italic>pramāṇas</italic>). More ambiguous, perhaps, is the question of the<italic>ātman</italic>’s accessibility to the worldly<italic>pramāṇas</italic>. Tilmann Vetter’s suggestion, in<italic>Studien zur Lehre und Entwicklung Śaṅkaras</italic>([Vienna, 1979], 118), of a division of labor between “reason” and revelation corresponding to<italic>ātman</italic>and brahman, respectively, “Śāstra (Schriftzitate und das mit ihnen begründete theologische System) macht das Absolute zugänglich, Yukti (rationale Überlegung) den Kern der Person” (Śāstra [scriptural citations and the theological system based on them] makes the Absolute accessible; Yukti [rational reflection] makes the core of the person accessible), suggests a greater willingness on Śaṅkara’s part to concede the empirical knowability of the<italic>ātman</italic>. Yet Śaṅkara does not seem to have much confidence in (independent) reason’s ability to know the self, either. This is suggested, above all, by his criticism of the Mīmāṃsā tenet regarding the accessibility of the self to perception and inference (Halbfass,<italic>Tradition and Reflection</italic>, 148); for a discussion and critique of Vetter’s view, see 142, 177–80.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Śaṅkara’s Twist on Realist Vedānta</title>
         <p>As I suggested above, the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>’s preoccupation with Sāṃkhya theories is not original with Śaṅkara but rather belongs to an earlier phase of the Vedānta tradition. Although Śaṅkara’s is the oldest extant commentary on the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, it largely preserves the perspective of an earlier tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>This is indicated by the surprising level of agreement between Śaṅkara’s<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>and that of Bhāskara, who otherwise shows extreme hostility toward the teachings of Śaṅkara.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>Ingalls explains this agreement with the hypothesis, reminiscent of the Q hypothesis in New Testament studies, that Śaṅkara and Bhāskara both relied upon an earlier, although no longer extant, commentary.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>More recent scholarship has since called into question the claim that Bhāskara relied on an earlier commentary besides Śaṅkara’s.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>Nevertheless, Ingalls’s core proposition that Śaṅkara relied on an earlier commentator in composing his Bhāṣya still stands. Bhāskara and Śaṅkara’s followers both refer to this earlier commentator simply as the “commentator” (<italic>vṛttikāra</italic>). Ingalls, following this tradition, dubs him the “Protocommentator.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Now in those passages where Śaṅkara departs from the earlier tradition—that is, the tradition represented by the Protocommentator and also, albeit indirectly, Bhāskara—a new adversary comes clearly into view. This is the view, associated with precisely the realist Bhedābheda perspective characteristic of that earlier tradition, that ritual action plays a positive role in the attainment of liberation. This conviction is expressed in the doctrine of the “coordination of knowledge and works,” or<italic>jñānakarmasamuccayavāda</italic>. In rejecting the<italic>jñānakarmasamuccaya</italic>doctrine, Śaṅkara is taking up one side in a controversy in the brahmanical tradition between the single‐staff and triple‐staff traditions of renunciation. Representing the single‐staff tradition, Śaṅkara defined renunciation—or, to be more precise, its highest and paradigmatic form—in terms of a complete withdrawal from ritual activity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>The triple‐staff tradition, by contrast, held that a renunciant retained his brahmanical status—and thus ensured the legitimacy of his renunciation—only through a continuing commitment, albeit one greatly reduced, to ritual activity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>Two ideas that will later attain the status of formal doctrine in Advaita are developed in the context of this polemic. These are the unreality of the phenomenal world apart from brahman, on the one hand, and the impersonal, qualityless (<italic>nirguṇa</italic>) conception of brahman, on the other.</p>
         <p>An important source for these doctrines is Śaṅkara’s commentary on<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>II.1.14. This text makes it clear that these two characteristically Advaita doctrines are firmly rooted in the practical disagreement about the role of rites in the attainment of salvation. The aspects of difference and nondifference that the Bhedābhedavādins attribute jointly to brahman neatly correspond, respectively, to the ritual‐practical and gnoseological components of the orthodox brahman’s quest for liberation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>The aspect of multiplicity in brahman grounds the world of multiplicity—characterized by the distinction among actor, action, and result—that is presupposed by human activity, both social and ritual. For Śaṅkara, the attribution of an aspect of multiplicity to brahman reflects a need to justify such action.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>He feels that such a need is not only unfounded but also counterproductive. For the affirmation of a real basis to worldly activity undermines the very notion of emancipatory knowledge and therewith liberation itself. The Bhedābheda view implies a failure to acknowledge some kind of false cognition as the basis of samsaric existence—in other words, a kind of cognition whose simple removal brings liberation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">58</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Śaṅkara’s interest in depriving ritual activity of an ontological basis obliges him to break from the traditional understanding of the concept of nonseparation (<italic>ananyatva</italic>) as it pertains to the relation between the world and brahman. In keeping with the realist orientation of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">59</xref>the concept of<italic>ananyatva</italic>affirmed in<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>II.1.14 was very likely originally modeled after the “identity in difference” relation between the universal and the particular.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">60</xref>Thus, brahman functions as a unifying principle with respect to the things of the world in the same way that the universal unifies and subsumes its particular instantiations. That early Vedāntins conceived brahman’s relation to the world along these lines is suggested by the doctrine of brahman as the “great universal” (<italic>mahasāmānyam</italic>) that was apparently held by some earlier teachers of Vedānta mentioned by Maṇḍanamiśra and Kumārila.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">61</xref>Inasmuch as the particular instantiations of a universal are real, this understanding of the<italic>ananyatva</italic>concept implies that the things of the phenomenal world have a measure of independent existence. Śaṅkara offers an interpretation of this concept that is radically different. According to Śaṅkara, the effect is nondifferent (<italic>ananya</italic>) from its cause in the sense that it cannot exist apart from its cause (<italic>kāryakāraṇayor ananyatvaṃ</italic>—<italic>kāraṇād vyatirekeṇābhāvaḥ kāryasya</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">62</xref>Although Śaṅkara avoids the use of the term<italic>vivarta</italic>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">63</xref>his interpretation of<italic>ananyatvam</italic>here is one of the principal sources for the later, illusionistic doctrine of<italic>vivartavāda</italic>, that is, the teaching that the phenomenal world is only an apparent manifestation (<italic>vivarta</italic>) of its underlying cause, brahman. According to the traditional view reflected in the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, by contrast, the phenomenal world represents a real transformation (<italic>pariṇāma</italic>) of brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">64</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Śaṅkara’s uncompromising insistence on the immutability of brahman and his explicit denial that brahman undergoes modification threaten to unravel the conception of brahman as world cause, the hard‐won achievement of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">65</xref>Śaṅkara himself acknowledges this concern in an objection posed by the<italic>pūrvapakṣin</italic>: thanks to their preoccupation with the idea of absolute unity, the proponents of the idea of a changeless brahman effectively deny the notions of the ruler and the ruled and, in so doing, contradict the proposition that God (<italic>īśvara</italic>) is the world’s cause.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">66</xref>This<italic>pūrvapakṣin</italic>may not feel that Śaṅkara’s bald assertion to the contrary holds up particularly well in the context of discussions of the ontologically nebulous<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>(name and form) as the source of the world and of Śaṅkara’s version of the Two Truths doctrine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">67</xref>It is not, however, my concern here to evaluate, from a strictly philosophical point of view, the success of Śaṅkara’s concept of<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>in reconciling Vedāntic cosmology with the unity and impassability of brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">68</xref>Rather, I would like to suggest that the combination of assertion and relativizing commentary that constitutes Śaṅkara’s response here characterizes Śaṅkara’s interpretation of II.1.14 as a kind of double‐voiced discourse. In other words, Śaṅkara’s commentary preserves the older, Upaniṣadic cosmology but gives it a new spin. As an instance of double‐voiced discourse, Śaṅkara’s commentary on II.1.14 introduces a new intention into the older cosmological discourse, using it to say something else.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">69</xref>Indeed, Śaṅkara admits as much when he declares cosmogonic myths to be means of expressing the fundamental unity of being, as opposed to being taken literally.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">70</xref>Śaṅkara uses traditional brahmanical creation discourse, appropriately spun in an Advaitic direction, to make a point about the conditional validity of ritual and social practices. Viewing Śaṅkara’s reworking of traditional Vedāntic cosmology in terms of Ian Ramsey’s theory of models and qualifiers, we could perhaps regard the perspective that would later come to be systematized as<italic>vivartavāda</italic>as a realistic brahmanical‐Upaniṣadic cosmology made odd.</p>
         <p>Regarding Śaṅkara’s Advaitic perspective as internally constituted by the realistic discourse that it spins makes unnecessary many of the speculative hypotheses proposed to account for the presence of realistic elements in Śaṅkara’s thought. I am thinking in particular of the attempts on the part of scholars such as Paul Hacker and Tilmann Vetter to correlate the realist and illusionist tendencies in Śaṅkara’s thought to different stages in his philosophical development.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">71</xref>Along the lines of John Taber’s hypothesis that such developmental theories are often proposed in default of an adequate philosophical understanding of Śaṅkara’s texts,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">72</xref>I suspect that such theories partly reflect a failure to acknowledge the double‐voiced character of Śaṅkara’s thought.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">73</xref>They effectively pull apart the dialectical unity of Śaṅkara’s double‐voiced, commentarial discourse by assigning the voices to different phases in his career. According to Hacker’s well‐known conversion theory, for example, the realist elements of Śaṅkara’s oeuvre stem from a pre‐Advaita phase of his career when he wrote as an adherent of Yoga.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">74</xref>Yet realist elements stubbornly persist in Śaṅkara’s postconversion, Advaita works. Hacker’s explanation of these as mere survivals from Śaṅkara’s yogic past, as lapses into old habits of thought,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">75</xref>might appear as a makeshift intended to rescue a dubious theory from the evidence. That these realist elements cannot be so easily dismissed is indicated by the fact that at least one other scholar, Srinivasa Rao, makes them the basis for a realist interpretation of Śaṅkara.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">76</xref>In what appears to be an attempt to rescue the great name of Śaṅkara from orientalist and Christian apologetic critiques of “Hindu” quietism and world negation, Rao argues—somewhat unconvincingly in my view—that Śaṅkara never taught that the world was unreal.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">77</xref>Such a view appears only later among Śaṅkara’s followers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">78</xref>Although the interpretations of Hacker and Rao differ radically with respect to Śaṅkara’s classic Advaita works such as the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>, the two interpretations are similar in that they both seek to separate and compartmentalize the realist and illusionist aspects of Śaṅkara’s thought. The line of demarcation that Hacker places at an alleged moment of conversion Rao shifts to the point where Śaṅkara’s teaching is (mis)appropriated by his followers. Both interpretations presuppose what might be called a monological understanding of Śaṅkara’s discourse, an assumption that is typical of much of the scholarship on Śaṅkara’s “philosophy.” An approach that fully appreciates the inherently commentarial and apologetic nature of Śaṅkara’s works, by contrast, has little difficulty acknowledging the intimate coexistence of the realist and illusionist aspects of his thought—what we might call, borrowing a phrase from Bakhtin, an “intra‐atomic counterpoint of voices.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">79</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Śaṅkara’s Advaitic “qualification” of the cosmological “model” of brahman in the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>implies a qualityless, nonrelational, and—to the extent that the notion of personality presupposes relationality—impersonal conception of brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">80</xref>Inasmuch as they are relational concepts, brahman’s divine attributes—his lordship (<italic>īśvaratva</italic>), omniscience (<italic>sarvajñatva</italic>), and omnipotence (<italic>sarvaśaktitva</italic>)—presuppose a phenomenal world that has no existence, no substance, apart from brahman. A wall stands between the forms of religious thought and practice presupposing these divine attributes and the unconditioned reality of the self.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">81</xref>Liberation results only from the realization of brahman devoid of all qualities.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">82</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Another important source for this impersonal, qualityless conception of brahman is Śaṅkara’s commentary on I.1.12–19, an<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>that concerns the relation of brahman to bliss (<italic>ānanda</italic>). The topic is explored exegetically, through a discussion of the doctrine of the five sheaths (<italic>kośa</italic>) in the Taittirīya Upaniṣad. Of specific interest is brahman’s relation to the fifth and final sheath of the self consisting of bliss (<italic>ānandamaya</italic>). The<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>is striking because in its final sutra (I.12.19) Śaṅkara dramatically reverses the conclusion developed in the previous seven (I.1.12–18). This previous conclusion, which most likely represents an earlier, pre‐Advaita line of Vedāntic interpretation, states that the bliss sheath was indeed the highest self and thus brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">83</xref>Correcting this conclusion in I.1.19, Śaṅkara argues that the highest brahman transcends even the innermost sheath consisting of bliss as its ground and cause.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">84</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>beautifully illustrates the double‐voiced character of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>in that it highlights, as Clooney puts it, “the permanent openness of the Text to rereading and the articulation of new positions.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">85</xref>It demonstrates how one discourse can be subjected to another that redirects its meaning to different purposes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">86</xref>Śaṅkara’s “reversal” here exemplifies the modern hermeneutical principle that no text, even the most authoritative, is exempt from a later appropriation that renders its meaning conditional. A careful reading of I.1.12–19, however, shows that Śaṅkara does not simply negate the previous<italic>siddhānta</italic>, now reduced to a mere<italic>uttarapakṣa</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88">87</xref>Rather, Śaṅkara’s reversal reflects a shift in concern that places reflection on the doctrine of the sheaths in the context of a different problematic. This shift in concern corresponds to the two apologetic moments we have been discussing in this essay, namely, from the rejection of Sāṃkhya cosmogony to that of the salvific efficacy of works. The transition is sufficiently abrupt to force a reversal of the<italic>Bhāṣya’s</italic>interpretive judgment on the Taittirīya text. In other words, the dramatic nature of Śaṅkara’s revision reflects the discontinuity between the problematics corresponding, respectively, to the<italic>uttarapakṣa</italic>and the<italic>siddhānta</italic>.</p>
         <p>This underlying shift from one problematic to another can be discerned in what Śaṅkara says in his prologue to this<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>. After noting the accomplishment of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>text up to this point—namely, establishing brahman, and not insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>, as the world cause—a<italic>pūrvapakṣin</italic>naively asks what there is left to talk about in the remaining text of the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89">88</xref>After introducing the distinction between conditioned and unconditioned brahman,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90">89</xref>Śaṅkara responds by stating what is at issue for him in the<italic>adhikaraṇa</italic>, namely, to determine whether salvific knowledge of the self (<italic>sadyomuktikāraṇam ātmajñānam</italic>) pertains to the former or the latter.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91">90</xref>Śaṅkara is being a bit coy here when he suggests that there is still doubt when the question is expressed in these terms. Implicitly, his distinction between the two forms of brahman has already decided the question: knowledge (<italic>jñāna</italic>) clearly pertains to the unconditioned brahman. As was the case with II.1.14, what is at stake here is the question of whether religious activity contributes to liberation. Perhaps implicitly conceding the Mīmāṃsā concept of meditative injunctions (<italic>upāsanavidhi</italic>) while rejecting the Mīmāṃsā use of this principle to subordinate the Upaniṣads to the ritual portion of the Veda,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92">91</xref>Śaṅkara assimilates meditative practices (<italic>upāsana</italic>) to ritual activity. He views the former, again along Mīmāṃsā lines, as “internalized quasi‐rituals.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93">92</xref>In doing so, he is able to subsume a critique of Yoga into his rejection of the<italic>jñānakarmasamuccaya</italic>doctrine, a doctrine which, as we have seen, he regards as a salvifically fatal concession to Mīmāṃsā ritualism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94">93</xref>Meditative practice, no less than ritual activity, presupposes the duality of means and ends, thus placing it outside the nondual sphere of emancipatory knowledge.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95">94</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The dichotomous nature of Śaṅkara’s distinction between<italic>jñāna</italic>and<italic>upāsana</italic>should make us immediately suspicious of apologetic interests driving his analysis. The assimilation of meditation to ritual activity allows Śaṅkara to group Yoga, Mīmāṃsā, and Bhedābheda Vedānta together on one side of an apologetic divide. On the other side stands Śaṅkara’s Advaita as the lone defender of pure Vedāntic knowledge. As if there were any doubt as to the relative ranking of these two paths, Śaṅkara correlates<italic>jñāna</italic>and<italic>upāsana</italic>with the higher and lower (<italic>para</italic>and<italic>apara</italic>) forms of brahman, respectively.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96">95</xref>Like most apologetically motivated schemas, this one suppresses important aspects of the views that it relegates to positions of inferiority. In particular, as Halbfass notes, Śaṅkara fails to acknowledge the fact that the teachers of Yoga, no less than Śaṅkara, recognized the need to transcend a preoccupation with results and an acquisitive attitude.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97">96</xref>More generally, his dichotomy shears off the cognitive connotations of<italic>upāsana</italic>, which the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>most probably regarded as continuous with<italic>jñāna</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98">97</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Given that the “results orientation” that Śaṅkara associates with meditation (and, a fortiori, ritual activity) forms the basis of his apologetically driven classification of religious practices, it is easy to see why he would be reluctant to follow the tradition in recognizing bliss as an essential attribute of brahman.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99">98</xref>Bliss implies a relation—and hence a dualism—between the experience and the experiencer, or, in Śaṅkara’s idiom, between the one who enjoys (<italic>bhoktṛ</italic>) and what is enjoyed (<italic>bhogya</italic>). Moreover, in suggesting that the realization of brahman culminates in an experience of bliss, the identification of the bliss sheath and the highest self implies a path to brahman motivated by desire. Ultimately, the identification of the bliss sheath and brahman is unacceptable to Śaṅkara because it blurs the distinction between, on the one hand, salvific<italic>jñāna</italic>and, on the other, meditative acts oriented toward desired experiences. Overturning the<italic>uttarapakṣa</italic>allows Śaṅkara to affirm brahman as the transcendent source of bliss, not as a mere experience of bliss.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100">99</xref>Thus, Śaṅkara’s apologetic interest in constructing the<italic>jñāna</italic>/<italic>upāsana</italic>dichotomy, by occasioning a repudiation of the identification of the blissful self and brahman, plays a role in lifting the latter out of the realm of human experience and motivation.</p>
         <p>The notion that brahman transcends the experience of bliss as its source might seem obvious to a Vedāntin. Why, then, would the pre‐Śaṅkara tradition interpret the Taittirīya text in a way that might occasion a serious misunderstanding of the nature of the religious path? And why would Śaṅkara preserve the arguments for this deficient interpretation in his<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>, giving them full rein before finally overturning their conclusion in a kind of commentarial appendix? As indicated above, the answer has to do with the different problematic underlying this earlier line of interpretation, namely, the Vedāntic repudiation of the Sāṃkhya concept of<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>. The influence of this preoccupation on the earlier reading of Taittirīya II is transparent in I.1.18. The mention of desire (<italic>kāma</italic>) in the Taittirīya text, “He desired (<italic>akāmayata</italic>), ‘Let me become many, let me be born,’” excludes the possibility of the bliss sheath being identified with insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101">100</xref>The citation of<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>I.1.5,<italic>īkṣiter nāśabdam</italic>, immediately after this argument makes it clear that for the early interpreters of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, I.1.12–19 stands in continuity with the rejection of<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>as the world cause in I.1.5. In the context of this concern with rejecting Sāṃkhya teaching, the identification of brahman with the bliss sheath makes perfect sense, for bliss is one of the manifestations of the sentience that the Upaniṣads affirm of the world cause.</p>
         <p>Most likely, then, Śaṅkara leaves the earlier reading of Taittirīya II intact in his<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>because he recognizes its effectiveness in refuting the Sāṃkhya teaching. Indeed, there is some danger that the refinements he brings to Vedānta weaken the case against Sāṃkhya if these are taken out of context. To be specific, his relegation of the relational attributes of brahman to the sphere of nescience undermines the implicitly personalistic conception of brahman that the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>had used to assert the sentience of the world cause over the Sāṃkhya principle of insentient<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102">101</xref>Śaṅkara voices this concern in a passage in II.1.14 that we looked at above. Here a<italic>pūrvapakṣin</italic>wonders whether a preoccupation with absolute unity, in undermining the concepts of the ruler and the ruled, contradicts the teaching of the Lord (<italic>īśvara</italic>) as the world cause.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103">102</xref>A concern with weakening the case against Sāṃkhya might therefore account for Śaṅkara’s curious retention of the personalistic term<italic>īśvara</italic>to refer even to the highest manifestation of brahman (<italic>paraṃ brahma</italic>,<italic>parātmā</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104">103</xref>As Hacker notes, Śaṅkara leaves it up to his later followers to formulate a distinction between<italic>para</italic>brahman and<italic>īśvara</italic>, the latter now regarded as a lower manifestation of the former.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105">104</xref>A certain skittishness about Advaita being perceived as a lapse into Sāṃkhya would also explain the peculiarity, again noted by Hacker, that Śaṅkara, unlike his later interpreters, studiously avoids language that would suggest<italic>avidyā</italic>is a material cause.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106">105</xref>Perhaps Śaṅkara is concerned that the conception of<italic>avidyā</italic>as<italic>causa materialis</italic>could be perceived as a return, under a different name, of the Sāṃkhya principle of<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>; admitting an insentient material cause would effectively allow Sāṃkhya to enter into Vedānta through the back door, as it were.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107">106</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Thus, the refinements Śaṅkara brings to Vedānta risk undoing the apologetic achievement of his predecessors in distinguishing Vedānta from Sāṃkhya. The arguments of the<italic>uttarapakṣa</italic>in I.1.12–18 therefore function to shield the concept of<italic>nirguṇa</italic>brahman from a possible confusion with an insentient world cause. They mark off a reflective space where Śaṅkara can explore the nuances of Vedāntic theology without worrying about maintaining the sharpest possible contrast with Sāṃkhya teachings. Thus, he concludes his prologue to I.1.12–19 with the assurance that the reflections to follow are undertaken in the context of a refutation of an insentient world cause. The ensuing discussion presupposes the results of the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>up to this point, namely, that the scriptural texts to be discussed have brahman, and not<italic>pra</italic>
            <italic>dhāna</italic>, as their purport.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108">107</xref>
         </p>
         <p>We can view Advaita’s proximity to Sāṃkhya from another angle. If we recall Edgerton’s thesis that a commitment to the path of pure knowledge and a concomitant renunciation of all activity were the defining characteristics of early Sāṃkhya, then we can perhaps regard Śaṅkara’s rejection of the<italic>jñānakarmasamuccaya</italic>doctrine as a return of sorts to the Sāṃkhya position. That Śaṅkara’s Advaita was perceived in this way is indicated by Bhāskara, whose commentary on the Gita contains several passages that associate Śaṅkara’s teaching regarding the total abandonment of ritual activities with the Sāṃkhya school.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109">108</xref>If, as suggested above, an uncompromising commitment to Vedic authority distinguished early Vedānta from the rationalistic Sāṃkhya school, then perhaps the<italic>jñānakarmasamuccaya</italic>doctrine, or an early version thereof, functioned as a key factor in differentiating the two schools. This situation would reflect an early phase when the two Mīmāṃsās existed in a reasonably harmonious and complementary relationship.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn110">109</xref>As the Advaita school distanced itself from the ritual orientation of the Mīmāṃsā, however, it moved—inadvertently!—closer to the older Sāṃkhya position.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn111">110</xref>That this was allowed to happen may be taken as an indication that Sāṃkhya’s influence was on the wane during the emergence of the Advaita school. As mentioned above, the anti‐Sāṃkhya sections of the<italic>Bhāṣya</italic>may have been simply holdovers from an earlier stage in the evolution of the Vedānta tradition. They would be similar in this respect to Śaṅkara’s refutation, in II.2.18–27, of Buddhist realism (Sarvāstitvavāda), which, as Ingalls notes, had been dead in India centuries prior to the time of Śaṅkara.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn112">111</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>See the seminal article of Daniel H. H. Ingalls, “Śamkara’s Arguments against the Buddhists,”<italic>Philosophy East and West</italic>3, no. 4 (January 1954): 291–92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Ibid., 293; see also Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 458–59; Surendranath Dasgupta,<italic>A History of Indian Philosophy</italic>(Cambridge, 1940), 3:1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Ingalls, “Śaṃkara’s Arguments,” 294.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>See Rüping,<italic>Studien zur Frühgeschichte</italic>, 65–68. Rüping overturns Ingalls’s reasoning that Bhāskara could not have possibly copied directly from Śaṅkara. For the latter’s view, see “Śaṃkara’s Arguments,” 293–94.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Ingalls, “Śaṃkara’s Arguments,” 293.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>See Patrick Olivelle,<italic>Renunciation in Hinduism</italic>, vol. 1,<italic>The Debate and the Advaita Argument</italic>(Vienna, 1986), 32 and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>Ibid., 34–35.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 375, lines 1–2: “tatraikatvāṃśena jñānān mokṣavyavahāraḥ setsyati. nānāṃśena tu karmakaṇḍāśrayau laukikavaidikavyavahārau setsyata iti” (The experience of liberation from knowledge will come to fruition by virtue of the aspect of unity in brahman. Conversely, the worldly and Vedic experiences based on the ritual portion of the Veda will come to fruition by virtue of the aspect of multiplicity in brahman).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Ibid., 375, lines 8–9: “tadāśraye samastaḥ svābhāviko vyavahāro bādhito bhavati yatprasiddhaye nānātvāṃśo ʿparo brahmaṇaḥ kalpeta” (In order to establish a principle upon which all conventional experience can be based—experience whose nature is to be sublated—a nonultimate aspect of multiplicity is imagined in brahman).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>Ibid., 376, lines 6–8: “na cāsmindarśane jñānānmokṣa ityupapadyate, samyagjñānāpanodyasya kasyacinmithyājñānasya saṃsārakāraṇatvenānabhyupagamāt. ubhayasatyatāyāṃ hi katham ekatvajñānena nānātvajñānam apanudyata ityucyate” (If one accepts the [Bhedābheda] viewpoint, then the idea of liberation from knowledge becomes implausible. For this viewpoint fails to recognize some kind of false knowledge as the cause of samsaric existence, that is, a kind of knowledge that could be dispelled by true knowledge. For if we suppose that both multiplicity and unity have a basis in reality, then how can a knowledge of multiplicity be dispelled by a knowledge of unity?).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 490.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>For this argument, see Mysore Hiriyanna, “What Is Ananyatvam?” in<italic>Festschrift Moriz Winternitz</italic>, ed. Otto Stein and Wilhelm Gampert (Leipzig: Harrassowitz, 1933), 223. See also Daniel H. H. Ingalls, “Bhāskara the Vedāntin,”<italic>Philosophy East and West</italic>17, nos. 1–4 (January–October 1967): 66, for an exposition of Bhāskara’s<italic>bhedābheda</italic>understanding of the<italic>ananyatva</italic>relation. Ingalls (66) translates a passage from Bhāskara’s commentary on<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>I.1.4. An especially relevant portion of that passage is as follows: “All things, so far as they belong to the class concepts existence, object of knowledge, substance, etc., are unitary; and as individuals, from their mutual differences, they are plural.” For the corresponding Sanskrit, see Pandit Vindhyesvarī Prasāda Dvivedin, ed.,<italic>Brahmasūtrabhāṣyam ŚriBhāskarācāryaviracitam</italic>, Chowkhamba Sanskrit Series (Varanasi, 1991), 17, lines 3–5: “na hyabhinnaṃ bhinnameva vā kvacit kenacid darśayituṃ śakyate. sattā‐jñeyatva‐dravyatvādi‐sāmānyātmanā sarvam abhinnaṃ, vyaktātmanā tu parasparavailakṣaṇyād bhinnam.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>See, e.g.,<italic>Ślokavarttika</italic>, Pratyakṣavāda, 114 (in<italic>The Mīmāṃsa‐Śloka‐Vārttika of Kumārila Bhatta</italic>, Chowkhamba Sanskrit Series no. 11, ed. Rama Sastri Tailanga [Benares, 1898–99]), where Kumārila mentions the view held by some that the “great universal” (<italic>mahāsāmānya</italic>) is the object of perception (“mahāsāmānyam anyais tu dravyam sad iti cocyate”). In his<italic>Brahmasiddhi</italic>(37, lines 21–22; see<italic>Brahmasiddhi by Ācārya Maṇḍanamiśra</italic>, ed. S. Kuppuswami Sastri [Madras, 1937]), Maṇḍana similarly refers to “others well versed in the knowledge of brahman” who teach that brahman has the form (<italic>rūpa</italic>) of the universal (“ato ʿnyair brahmavidyābhiyuktaiḥ sāmānyasrūpaṃ brahma nirūpitam”). The vague references here possibly point to teachers associated with the school of Bhartṛhāri.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 373, line 2: “tasmātkāraṇātparamārthato ʿnanyatvaṃ vyatirekeṇābhāvaḥ kāryasyāvagamyate” (Therefore “nondifference” is to be understood to mean that, ultimately, the effect does not exist separately from its cause). See also Hiriyanna, “What Is Ananyatvam?” 221.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>Richard De Smet suggests that Śaṅkara avoided the term<italic>vivarta</italic>because of its association with the Śabdādvaita conception of<italic>bhedābhedavada</italic>. See his “Radhakrishnan’s Interpretation of Śaṅkara,” in<italic>Radhakrishnan: Centenary Volume</italic>, ed. G. Parthasarathi and D. P. Chattopadhyaya (Delhi: Oxford University Press, 1989), 56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>On the realist orientation of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, and its support of the modification (<italic>pariṇāma</italic>) theory in particular, see Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 489–90 and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>See Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 381, lines 1–2: “kūṭasthaṃ ca nityaṃ brahma sarvavikriyāpratiṣedhād ityavocāma” (We said that brahman was immutable and eternal, on account of the prohibition of all modifications).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>Ibid., 381, lines 9–10: “kūṭasthabrahmātmavādina ekatvaikāntyād īśitrīśitavyābhāva īśvarakāraṇapratijñāvirodha iti cet” (Thanks to their insistence on the principle of absolute unity, the proponents of a changeless brahman, by effectively denying both the ruler and the ruled, contradict the proposition that the Lord is the world cause).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>Ibid., 382, line 1: “sā pratijñā tadavasthaiva na tadviruddho ʿrthaḥ” (This proposition still stands; the meaning is not contradicted by this).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn69">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>Vetter,<italic>Studien</italic>, 129, nicely summarizes what is at stake for Śaṅkara in proposing the<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>concept: “An einigen Stellen des BrSūBh, wo Ś entsprechend der Tradition der BrSū das Hervorgehen der Welt aus dem Brahman lehrt, versucht er die Gefahr, die der Unberūhrtheit des Brahman als der Entität der Erlösung droht, dadurch abzuschwächen, dass er Name‐und‐Gestalt (<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>), von denen man nicht sagen kann, dass sie [mit dem Brahman] identisch, aber auch nicht, dass sie [von ihm] verschieden sind (<italic>tattvānyatvābhyām anirvacanīya</italic>), als den eigentlichen Ursprung der Dinge hinstellt” (In certain places in the BrSūBh, where Śaṅkara, conforming to the tradition of the BrSū, teaches the emergence of the world from brahman, he tries to mitigate against the threat this poses to the impassability of brahman as the “entity” of liberation. This he does by setting forth name and form [<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>]—that about which one cannot say either that it is identical [with brahman] or that it is different [from him;<italic>tattvānyatvābhyām anirvacanīya</italic>]—as the actual origin of things).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
               <label>69</label>
               <p>Thereby rendering it conditional. See Bakhtin,<italic>Problems of Dostoevsky’s Poetics</italic>, 190: “The original direct and unconditional meaning now serves new purposes, which take possession of it from within and render it conditional.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
               <label>70</label>
               <p>Paul Hacker, “Distinctive Features of the Doctrine and the Terminology of Śaṅkara,” in<italic>Philology and Confrontation: Paul Hacker on Traditional and Modern Vedānta</italic>, ed. Wilhelm Halbfass (Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1995), 77–78; Ingalls, “Bhāskara the Vedāntin,” 64. See, e.g., Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 884, lines 7–8 (IV.3.14): “tāsām ekatvapratipādanaparatvāt. mṛdādidṛśṭāntair iha sato brahmaṇa ekasya satyatvaṃ vikārasya cānṛtatvaṃ pratipādayac chāstraṃ notpattyādiparaṃ bhavitum arhati” (For the concern of the Upaniṣadic texts is to establish the unity [of brahman]. The scripture here is establishing, with the help of illustrations like that of the clay, the reality of the one true brahman, and the unreality of the modifications. It is not concerned with [establishing] creation and so forth); see also I.4.14 and II.1.33.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn72">
               <label>71</label>
               <p>See Paul Hacker, “Śaṅkara the Yogin and Śaṅkara the Advaitin,” in Halbfass,<italic>Philology and Confrontation</italic>, 101–34; Vetter,<italic>Studien</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn73">
               <label>72</label>
               <p>Taber, “Reason, Revelation, and Idealism,” 285, 293, and passim. Taber suggests that such developmental theories reflect a one‐sided preoccupation with a philological‐historical, as opposed to a properly philosophical, approach to Indian materials. In citing Taber’s essay I do not mean to suggest that he would necessarily approve of the genealogical, as opposed to strictly philosophical, approach to Śaṅkara that I have taken in this article.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn74">
               <label>73</label>
               <p>I withhold final judgment on both Vetter's and Hacker’s theories, since both are grounded in a careful study of texts lying outside the scope of this essay. This withholding of judgment is especially appropriate with respect to Hacker’s theory, which arises out of the problematic of the authorship of the<italic>Yogasūtrabhāṣya‐Vivaraṇa</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn75">
               <label>74</label>
               <p>Hacker, “Śaṅkara the Yogin,” 104–8, 127–28, and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn76">
               <label>75</label>
               <p>Ibid., 115, 122, 126, 127.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn77">
               <label>76</label>
               <p>Srinivasa Rao, “Two Myths in Advaita,”<italic>Journal of Indian Philosophy</italic>24, no. 3 (1996): 265–79.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn78">
               <label>77</label>
               <p>Rao, following Śaṅkara, reconciles the immutability of brahman with the nondifference (<italic>ananyatva</italic>) of brahman and the world—and hence the affirmation of the reality of the world—by effectively denying what Aristotle would call “substantial change.” Change occurs only with respect to the accidental “features,” the “names and forms,” of things (see “Two Myths in Advaita,” 266, 275). Rao’s analysis, based as it is on a denial of substantial change, simply begs the question: is the world we know—that is, as constituted by name and form—unreal for Śaṅkara? Thus, the thesis that Śaṅkara affirmed the reality of this world holds only as long as one accepts a rather counterintuitive concept of “the world.” The uncertainty and ambiguity concerning the question of whether Śaṅkara denied the world is simply displaced to the question of how one describes the world.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn79">
               <label>78</label>
               <p>Ibid., 266–67, 271, and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn80">
               <label>79</label>
               <p>Bakhtin,<italic>Problems of Dostoevsky’s Poetics</italic>, 221. To the extent that Śaṅkara’s works are double voiced, the perspective of the particular text he is commenting on is constitutive of his thought at that time. This notion of the inseparability of text and commentary would account for the differences that appear when Śaṅkara’s works are placed side by side. It seems to me that Sengaku Mayeda’s explanation for the differences between the<italic>Gauḍapādīya</italic>‐ and the<italic>Brahmasūtra Bhāṣyas</italic>, as summarized by this quote from Gregory Darling, hits the nail on the head: “Mayeda’s point, however, is that the Gauḍapādīyabhāṣya represents an attempt to reinterpret the Buddhistic tendencies of the Gauḍa tradition along Advaita lines, whereas in the Brahmasūtrabhāṣya, Śaṅkara tries to reinterpret a bhedābheda text along Advaita lines” (Gregory J. Darling,<italic>An Evaluation of the Vedāntic Critique of Buddhism</italic>[Delhi: Motilal, 1987], 114; Mayeda’s original article is “On the Author of the<italic>Māṇḍūkyopaniṣad</italic>‐ and the<italic>Gauḍapādīya‐bhāṣya</italic>,” in<italic>Dr. V. Raghavan Felicitation Volume</italic>, ed. V. Raghavan and N. Sri Ram [Madras: Adyar Library and Research Center, 1967–68]). Moreover, the perspective of the particular text Śaṅkara is commenting upon—whether it be the<italic>Gauḍapāda‐kārikā</italic>, the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>, or, if authentic, the<italic>Yogasūtrabhāṣya</italic>—is such a major factor in determining the shape of his thought in a given work that I have doubts whether a distinct developmental factor can be realistically discerned, especially in the absence of a certain chronology of Śaṅkara’s authentic works.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn81">
               <label>80</label>
               <p>The conventional characterization of Śaṅkara’s<italic>nirguṇa</italic>brahman as impersonal has not gone unchallenged. Richard De Smet in particular has proposed a nonanthropological concept of personhood (informed by the tradition of Christian Trinitarian speculation) that is compatible with Śaṅkara’s concept of<italic>para</italic>brahman (see “Radhakrishnan’s Interpretation of Śaṅkara,” 65–66). For a thoughtful overview of the debate in Śaṅkara studies over whether it is appropriate to ascribe personhood to Śaṅkara’s concept of<italic>para</italic>brahman, see Bradley Malkovsky, “The Personhood of Samkara’s ‘Para Brahman,’”<italic>Journal of Religion</italic>77, no. 4 (October 1997): 541–62.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn82">
               <label>81</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 382, lines 10–12: “tad evam avidyātmakopādhiparicchedāpekṣam eveśvarasyeśvaratvaṃ sarvajñatvaṃ sarvaśaktitvaṃ ca na paraṃārthato vidyayāpāstasarvopādhisvarūpa ātmanīśitrīśitavyasarvajñatvādivyavahāra upapadyate” (The lordship, omnipotence, and omniscience of the Lord depend on separated, conditioning factors constituted by ignorance. From the perspective of ultimate reality, experiences oriented toward divine attributes like omniscience—that is, attributes presupposing a distinction between the ruler and the ruled—are not worthy of the self, whose nature it is to have all conditioning factors swept away by knowledge).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn83">
               <label>82</label>
               <p>Ibid., 381, lines 5–6: “brahmaprakaraṇe sarvadharmaviśeṣarahitabrahmadarśanād eva phalasiddhau satyāṃ” (In this discussion concerning brahman, the attainment of the result [i.e., liberation] becomes actual only from the realization of brahman devoid of all distinctions and qualities).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn84">
               <label>83</label>
               <p>Ibid., 123, line 3 (I.1.16): “itaścānandamayaḥ para evātmā netaraḥ” (Hence the bliss sheath is the highest self, nothing else); see also 125, lines 4–5 (I.1.19): “tasmādānandamayaḥ parātmeti sthitaṃ” (Therefore it is established that the bliss sheath is the highest self).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn85">
               <label>84</label>
               <p>Ibid., 130, line 1 (I.1.19): “sarvasya vikārajātasya sānandamayasya kāraṇatvena brahma vyapadiśyate—idaṃ sarvam asṛjata” (The text, “He created all that is,” represents brahman as the cause of all things born of modification, including the self consisting of bliss).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn86">
               <label>85</label>
               <p>Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedānta</italic>, 52.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>Again, see Bakhtin,<italic>Problems of Dostoevsky’s Poetics</italic>, 190, 233, and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn88">
               <label>87</label>
               <p>On the reduction of the<italic>siddhānta</italic>to an<italic>uttarapakṣa</italic>, see Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedānta</italic>, 52.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn89">
               <label>88</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 116, lines 3–7: “‘janmādyasya yataḥ’ ityārabhya ‘śrutatvācca’ ityevam antaiḥ sūtrair yānyudāhṛtāni vedāntavākyāni teṣāṃ sarvajñaḥ sarvaśaktir īśvaro jagato janmasthitilayakāraṇam ityetasyārthasya pratipādakatvaṃ nyāyapūrvakaṃ pratipāditam. gatisāmānyopanyāsena ca sarve vedāntāścetanakāraṇavādina iti vyākhyātam. ataḥ parasya granthasya kimutthānamiti” (The point of those Vedāntic sentences, which were cited by the sutras beginning with I.1.2 and ending with I.1.11, was to establish the omniscient and omnipotent brahman as the cause of the creation, maintenance, and destruction of the world. And inasmuch as they share the same intention, all the Upaniṣads are explained as teaching a sentient principle as the world cause. From these considerations, what is the point of going through with the rest of the text?).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn90">
               <label>89</label>
               <p>Ibid., 116, lines 7–8: “dvirūpaṃ hi brahmāvagamyate, nāmarūpavikārabhedopādhiviśiṣṭaṃ, tadviparitaṃ ca sarvopādhivivarjitam” (For brahman is understood to have two forms. The first is distinguished by differentiating, conditioning factors, that is, the modifications of name and form. The second form, by contrast, is free of all conditioning factors).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn91">
               <label>90</label>
               <p>Ibid., 118, lines 10–12: “evaṃ sadyomuktikāranam apy ātmajñānam upādhiviśeṣadvāreṇopadiśyamānam apy avivakṣitopādhisaṃbandhaviśeṣaṃ parāparaviṣayatvena saṃdihyamānaṃ vākyagatiparyālocanayā nirṇetavyaṃ bhavati” (Even if the knowledge of the self instantly brings about liberation, this knowledge is imparted with the help of distinctions and conditioning factors. Though [the intention of the Upaniṣads] is not to impart knowledge as characterized by a connection with conditioning factors, still the doubt arises as to whether this knowledge has as its object the lower or the higher brahman. This is to be determined through a deliberation on the sense of the [Upaniṣadic] sentences).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn92">
               <label>91</label>
               <p>Halbfass,<italic>Tradition and Reflection</italic>, 150.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn93">
               <label>92</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn94">
               <label>93</label>
               <p>Compare also Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 353, line 7–354, line 1 (II.1.3): “nirākaraṇaṃ tu na sāṃkhyajñānena vedanirapekṣeṇa yogamārgeṇa vā niḥśreyasamadhigamyata iti” (The refutation [of Sāṃkhya and Yoga] amounts to this: salvation is not to be attained through the yogic path or the knowledge of Sāṃkhya inasmuch as these means are independent of the Veda).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn95">
               <label>94</label>
               <p>We must, however, put Śaṅkara’s apparent denigration of<italic>upāsana</italic>into perspective. Śaṅkara does acknowledge the value of<italic>upāsana</italic>, if only to wean the adherent from a habitual preoccupation with action (see Darling,<italic>Evaluation</italic>, 139, following Raghavan). Following the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>—which, unlike Śaṅkara, viewed meditation as the main purpose of Upaniṣadic teaching (see Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 519)—Śaṅkara devotes considerable attention to meditation in III.3. Vetter,<italic>Studien</italic>, 119–29, has a nice discussion of Śaṅkara’s handling of the problematic of affirming the value of meditative practice in the context of the doctrine of instantaneous liberation. See also Clooney’s careful analysis of Śaṅkara’s exegetical mode of reasoning in III.3 in “Principle of Upasaṃhāra.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn96">
               <label>95</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 119, lines 2–3: “evam ekam api brahmāpekṣitopādhisaṃbandhaṃ nirastopādhisaṃbandhaṃ copāsyatvena jñeyatvena ca vedānteṣūpadiśyate” (The Upaniṣads speak of the one brahman, on the one hand, as an object to be meditated upon and thus as connected with conditioning factors, and, on the other, as an object to be known, with all conditioning factors cast away).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn97">
               <label>96</label>
               <p>Halbfass,<italic>Tradition and Reflection</italic>, 228.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn98">
               <label>97</label>
               <p>Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 519, 520; see also III.3.5.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn99">
               <label>98</label>
               <p>On Śaṅkara’s apparent discomfort with the concept of bliss in connection with brahman, see Halbfass,<italic>Tradition and Reflection</italic>, 255; Andrew O. Fort, “Beyond Pleasure: Śaṅkara on Bliss,”<italic>Journal of Indian Philosophy</italic>16 (1988): 177; Hacker, “Distinctive Features,” 86.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn100">
               <label>99</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 127, line 16–128, line 1: “na tvānandamayasya brahmatvam asti, priyaśirastvādibhir hetubhirityavocāma” (But we have said that the blissful self is not brahman because [brahman] stands at the head of human joys [as their ultimate principle], as well as for other reasons). For an analysis of this notion of brahman as the source of all human experiences of bliss, see Fort, “Beyond Pleasure,” 179, 182, and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn101">
               <label>100</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 124, line 6; ibid., 124, lines 6–8: “kāmayitṛtvanirdeśān nānumānikam api sāṃkhyaparikalpitam acetanaṃ pradhānam ānandamayatvena kāraṇatvena vāpekṣitavyam” (From the mention of wishfulness [in the Taittirīya text], the insentient<italic>pra</italic>
                  <italic>dhāna</italic>, that inferred entity imagined by the Sāṃkhyas, is not to be relied upon [for an understanding] of either the blissful self or the world cause).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn102">
               <label>101</label>
               <p>For a persuasive argument that the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>regarded brahman as a personal principle, see Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 488.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn103">
               <label>102</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 381, lines 9–10: “kūṭasthabrahmātmavādina ekatvaikāntyād īśitrīśitavyābhāva īśvarakāraṇapratijñāvirodha iti cet.” See n. 66 above.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn104">
               <label>103</label>
               <p>Hacker, “Distinctive Features,” 85–96.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn105">
               <label>104</label>
               <p>Ibid., 94. G. A. Jacob had made the same observation earlier in his preface to the<italic>Vedāntasāra of Sadānanda</italic>(Varanasi: Chaukhamba, 1893), vii–ix.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn106">
               <label>105</label>
               <p>Hacker, “Distinctive Features,” 63–64. When Śaṅkara does find himself speaking of the cosmological product of<italic>avidyā</italic>, namely, name and form (<italic>nāmarūpe</italic>), in a way suggestive of material causality (i.e., as being the seeds of the samsaric world—<italic>saṃsāraprapañcabījabhute</italic>), he is quick to assert the difference between these and the Lord (<italic>īśvara</italic>), thus compromising a bit on the Advaitic<italic>ananayatva</italic>principle. See Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 382, lines 2–4: “sarvajñasyeśvarasyātmabhūta ivāvidyākalpite nāmarūpe tattvānyābhyām anirvacanīye … tābhyām anyaḥ sarvajña īśvaraḥ” (Name and form, inexpressible as either “this” or something other than this, and imagined through ignorance, are, as it were [<italic>iva</italic>], the nature of the omniscient Lord). Note that the little particle<italic>iva</italic>(like) here is doing a great deal of theological work: it prevents brahman from collapsing into Sāṃkhya‐esque prime matter. Govindānanda’s comment makes this function of the<italic>iva</italic>clear (Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 382, lines 16–17): “nāmarūpe ced īśvarasyātmabhūte tarhīśvaro jaḍa ityata āha—tābhyāmanya iti” (If name and form were of the nature of the Lord, then the Lord would be inanimate. Therefore, he says, “Different from these two”).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn107">
               <label>106</label>
               <p>For many adherents of Puranic Sāṃkhya (among others),<italic>avidyā</italic>was a name for prime matter (Hacker, “Distinctive Features,” 84). See Rao, “Two Myths in Advaita,” 271–72, who interprets the Śaṅkara school’s doctrine of<italic>māyā</italic>, since it posits an insentient principle as the world cause, as a kind of backslide into Sāṃkhya.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn108">
               <label>107</label>
               <p>Shastri,<italic>BSūBh</italic>, 119, lines 2–3: “yacca ‘gatisāmānyāt’ ityacetanakāraṇanirākaraṇam uktaṃ tadapi vākyāntarāṇi brahmaviṣayāṇi brahmaviparitakāraṇaniṣedhena prapancate” (The refutation of an insentient world cause in<italic>Brahma‐sūtra</italic>I.1.10 above is here elaborated upon. This is done by rejecting any candidate for world cause opposed to brahman, while at the same time explaining other [Upaniṣadic] statements that have brahman as their object).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn109">
               <label>108</label>
               <p>See the texts cited in V. Raghavan, “Bhāskara’s Gītabhāṣya,”<italic>Wiener Zeitschrift für die Kunde Süd‐ und Ostasiens und Archiv für Indische Philosophie</italic>12–13 (1968–69): 286: “sarva‐karma‐tyāginām sāṃkhyānām jñānād eva kevalād niśśreyasaprāptir uktā” (Those Sāṃkhyas, who abandon all works, say that final beatitude is attained form knowledge alone); ibid., 287: “yathā idam eva sāmkhyadarśanam āśritya sarvadharma‐tyāgam ekavaiṇavino vadanti” (Having committed themselves to the Sāṃkhya philosophy, those [renunciants] of the single‐staff speak of abandoning all rites [dharma]). The significance of these Sāṃkhya references is noted by Olivelle,<italic>Renunciation in Hinduism</italic>, 52.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn110">
               <label>109</label>
               <p>On the early kinship between the two schools, see, e.g., Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 409–13.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn111">
               <label>110</label>
               <p>The emergence of the Advaita interpretation of the Vedānta and the concomitant antagonism toward Pūrva‐mīmāṃsā teachings predated Śaṅkara. Already Kumārila, who writes before Śaṅkara, refers to pre‐Śaṅkara forms of nondualist Vedānta (Nakamura,<italic>History</italic>, 339–40).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn112">
               <label>111</label>
               <p>Ingalls, “Śaṅkara’s Arguments,” 299.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Concluding Remarks</title>
         <p>A reading of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>that insists on its irreducibly “polyphonic” nature has the advantage of distancing Śaṅkara from two closely related notions that have formed the basis of many an invidious and essentializing contrast between Advaita, assumed to epitomize the religious thought of India, and the philosophical and religious thought of the West. The first of these is the illusory nature of the phenomenal world, a presupposition of the alleged quietism and ethical indifference of the Brahmin sage.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn113">112</xref>The second is the understanding of brahman as an inert and pallid abstraction, an “abstract unity without determination,” as Hegel puts it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn114">113</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Against the first characterization of Advaita teaching, the recognition of the double‐voiced character of Śaṅkara’s interpretation of the<italic>anayatvam</italic>sutra (II.1.14)—that is, as internally constituted by the realist cosmological discourse that it subverts—suggests that the interpretation of the<italic>Bhāṣya’s</italic>teaching in terms of the illusionist doctrine of<italic>māyāvāda</italic>is reductionistic. Moreover, well‐intentioned attempts to dissociate Śaṅkara from<italic>māyāvāda</italic>that presume a monological conception of the<italic>Bhāṣya’s</italic>discourse, attempts such as that of Srinivasa Rao mentioned above, end up effectively conceding the claim they set out to deny; their affirmation of the reality of the world typically appeals to a denial of substantial change, a claim that implicitly relegates changing, finite existences to the realm of the unreal.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn115">114</xref>As for the static and abstract conception of brahman, this notion can be seen as the result of the later tradition’s attempt to impose a rigid, categorical distinction between the concepts of<italic>īśvara</italic>and the highest (<italic>paraṃ</italic>) brahman. This effort to systematize Śaṅkara’s somewhat inconsistent, fluid, and intuitive use of the term<italic>īśvara</italic>with respect to the various expressions for brahman effectively pulls apart the dialectical interplay between the personalistic and impersonalistic aspects of brahman in the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>. What Hacker characterizes as an “illogical” combination of intuitive theism and intellectual monism can perhaps be better understood as an instance of what Michael Sells, in a discussion of apophatic language in the West, calls “a discourse of double propositions.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn116">115</xref>A reading of the<italic>Brahma‐sūtra‐Bhāṣya</italic>that appreciates the creative interplay among this text’s multiple voices preserves the vitality and intensity of the<italic>Bhāṣya’s</italic>discourse on brahman, a liveliness of expression that we may assume more accurately reflects Śaṅkara’s religious vision.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn113">
               <label>112</label>
               <p>On the Western tendency to depict the essence of Hinduism, as epitomized in the thought of Śaṅkara, as a world‐negating, illusionary pantheism, see Ronald Inden’s<italic>Imagining India</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1990), 101–8. A classic example of the dichotomization of an ethical, life‐affirming Christianity and a quietistic, life‐denying Hinduism is Albert Schweitzer’s<italic>Indian Thought and Its Development</italic>, trans. C. E. B. Russell (Boston: Beacon, 1956).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn114">
               <label>113</label>
               <p>As quoted in Wilhelm Halbfass,<italic>India and Europe</italic>(Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1988), 89. The contrast between the dynamic, living God of Christianity and the abstract and inert Absolute of Vedānta is a prominent theme in Rudolf Otto’s classic comparison between Eckhart and Śaṅkara,<italic>Mysticism East and West</italic>, trans. Bertha L. Bracey and Richenda C. Payne (New York: Collier, 1962), 187–98 and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn115">
               <label>114</label>
               <p>See n. 77 above. For an argument similar to Rao’s, see D. M. Datta, “Some Realistic Aspects of the Philosophy of Śaṅkara,” in<italic>Recent Indian Philosophy</italic>, ed. Kalidas Bhattacharya (Calcutta: Progressive, 1963); concerning the denial of substantial change, see esp. 347, 349. Note that Hegel’s critique of the concept of<italic>māyā</italic>easily accommodates an acknowledgment of the substantial identity between the world and the absolute. The presence of the divine being in all finite things still “does not secure them in their finite individuality, nor is the finite a real factor in or for the infinite. On the contrary, the abstract self‐identity of the finite existences, which identifies them with the abstract absolute, is incompatible with their concrete individual identity” (Halbfass,<italic>India and Europe</italic>, 90).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn116">
               <label>115</label>
               <p>Hacker, “Distinctive Features,” 95 and passim; Michael A. Sells,<italic>Mystical Languages of Unsaying</italic>(Chicago, 1994), 1–13, esp. 12. Note that Hacker acknowledges that Śaṅkara’s discourse on brahman is all the more alive (<italic>lebendiger</italic>) for its terminological imprecision (“Distinctive Features,” 95).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
