<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">fscotfitzrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The F. Scott Fitzgerald Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">15433951</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">17556333</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">fscotfitzrevi.12.1.0067</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/fscotfitzrevi.12.1.0067</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reading Nostalgia</article-title>
            <subtitle>Textual Memory in<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>
            </subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Salmose</surname>
                  <given-names>Niklas</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <bold>Niklas Salmose</bold>is associate professor of English literature at Linnaeus University in Växjö, Sweden. His research and publications revolve around nostalgia, emotions, and sensorial aesthetics particularly in the modernist period. He is a member of the Forum for Intermedial Studies at Linnaeus. In addition to his teaching and research he is also a translator and publisher, and recently translated Fitzgerald's<italic>All the Sad Young Men</italic>into Swedish.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">12</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">fscotfitzrevi.12.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>67</fpage>
         <lpage>87</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/fscotfitzrevi.12.1.0067"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>F. Scott Fitzgerald's<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>is undoubtedly a novel<italic>about</italic>nostalgia; it explores themes such as the impossibilities of recapturing the past, the role of myths in our lives, the shattered dreams of our youth, and the unrealized ambitions of the founders of America. Much has been written about these issues. However, this essay will argue that<italic>Gatsby</italic>is also a<italic>nostalgic</italic>novel, using the work of French philosopher Paul Ricœur, who made a distinction between a<italic>novel about time</italic>and a<italic>time novel</italic>(101)<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>1</sup>
         </xref>: Fitzgerald's 1925 classic generates a nostalgic, phenomenological experience in the reader with its thematic content, through its deliberate style and form. Jay Gatsby's nostalgic inclinations are thus mimicked, paralleled, and enhanced by the novel's structure and style, creating a profound effect on a reader responsive to the novel's devices.</p>
      <p>Fitzgerald uses several tools to create<italic>the nostalgic aesthetic of Gatsby</italic>. The plot is fundamentally analeptic in construction (told in flashbacks), while the narration is subsequent (narrated<italic>after</italic>the main story takes place). The narrator, Nick Carraway, fits the definition of a homodiegetic perspective (a narrator who is also part of the story he tells): as countless commentaries have discussed, Nick is a distanced observer, retelling the events of the summer of 1922 in first-person singular, infusing through his commentary value into their importance, a technique that creates a distinct “now” and “then” between the time of the story and the time of the narration. Additionally, the<italic>order</italic>of the narration is not chronological but jumps back and forth in time in order to support the emotional experience of inner time instead of clock time.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>Furthermore, the choice of words in<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>is often undeniably romantic, alluding to Keats or simply evoking nostalgic sentiments using romantic conventions: “For a moment the last sunshine fell with romantic affection upon her glowing face” (<italic>Gatsby</italic>14). This essay will not deal with all of Fitzgerald's nostalgic strategies in his most famous novel but will focus on one particular and highly original method: the use of the reader's textual memory in order to create a nostalgic experience within the text as an enhancement of the novel's nostalgic themes.</p>
      <p>Textual memory can be explained by taking into account how the reading process works. In order to make narrative sense, reading is dependent on remembering what came before the present sentence—the past events of the reading—and assessing this memory in the present reading situation. Wolfgang Iser writes that “what has been read shrinks in the memory to a foreshortened background, but it is being constantly evoked in a new context” (111). Reading does not merely flow forward, but the recalled segments also have a retroactive effect, with the present transforming the past. The deliberate use of past narration in order to create a specific effect in present narration invokes the reader's<italic>textual memory</italic>. Menakhem Perry writes in his illuminating article “Literary Dynamics: How the Order of a Text Creates Its Meanings” that “a ‘backward’ directed activity, even only in the mind, plays a major role in the reading-process” (58). He makes the important distinction between retrograde movements that are forced more explicitly by the text through flashbacks or narrative directions toward past narrative events and more implicit patterns in the present text that, in conjunction with the reader's own investments, trigger past textual memories.<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>In order fully to comprehend what constitutes a literary nostalgic experience, we need to define the nostalgic experience. The nostalgic experience can be simplified into a two-fold experience. The emotional content of the nostalgic experience consists of two emotional phases. The first is the remembrance of an idealized image or event that brings immediate happiness and great emotional affection as the senses unite in recreating something past and perhaps even lost. We can call this element<italic>happiness</italic>. It is soon transformed into a more intellectual and reasoning second state, which we can call<italic>reflection</italic>. When we leave the spontaneity of the first emotion and enter the more reflective state where one is reminded of the passing status of the idealized image or event, what could be referred to as a<italic>hyper-memory</italic>, a melancholia, is created; ultimately nostalgia ends in the bittersweet. In literature it is possible to use these two elements of the nostalgic experience and create a literary nostalgic experience. One part can engage and thrill the reader into experiencing it as a present. A second part confronts the reader through melancholia and reflection upon his or her own textual memory of the first part. What is gained here is a fictional creation, or substitution, of the nostalgic experience.</p>
      <p>In experiencing the narrative of<italic>Gatsby</italic>, the reader encounters two divided and opposing structural halves. The first one (chapters 1–4) enhances the imagination of the reader through a set of stylistic and narratological devices such as movement, speed, narrative coherence, atmospheric imagery, and the trigger of reader sensations in order to stimulate a creation of a reader's<italic>textual hyper-memory</italic>(an idealized memory of the text).<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>These strategies are fulfilled through a literary presence, a prose that captures and involves the reader in the present literary events. Chapter 5 forms an obvious zenith, where not only dreams but also memories crash along with the present through Gatsby's effort to recreate the past: “‘Can't repeat the past?’ he cried incredulously. ‘Why of course you can!’” (110). At this point, the novel also begins to employ a more sober, distanced, commenting style.</p>
      <p>The second half of the narrative (chapters 6–8) creates a strong movement and longing back to this textual hyper-memory, both voluntarily and involuntarily. The style of the narration is more distanced, reflective, mimetic, and filled with direct speech and flashbacks that slow down its speed. The past textual memory in the reader is not only evoked through the very change of style, but also through the reuse of common symbols that were developed in the first part. This strategy is called literary distance. This division mimics that of the division of the nostalgic reaction. The first part represents the happiness of the memory, and the second part illustrates the melancholic reflection on this memory. Thus, the process of reading<italic>Gatsby</italic>is similar to the process of a nostalgic reaction. One way to dramatize how these halves function is through Leonard Baird's description of the structure of<italic>Gatsby</italic>as a party followed by a hangover: “[W]hen you get through with the story you feel as if you'd been some place where you had a good time, but now entertain grave doubts as to the quality of the synthetic gin” (208). The sense of a party giving way to a hangover corresponds very well with the binaries of presence and distance.</p>
      <p>Since the first part of<italic>Gatsby</italic>is so direct and so immediate, closely simulating a selected memory of our own, we confront the latter part of the novel with great emotion. This confrontation, one could argue, is really an encounter with our own textual hyper-memory—the idealized memory of the events of the first part of the book. The dream, not only Gatsby's but our own as well, recedes further and further away from us until it freezes into the effects of nostalgia—the reflective and distanced melancholia of the last chapter. As Gautam Kundu has recognized, the world in the first part is “made gorgeous by the magic touch of a romantic imagination that nevertheless moves inexorably toward eventual disintegration and dissolution” (34). The following two sections of this essay will explore this progression in a more detailed way.</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>The Never-Ending Party: The Creation of a Textual Hyper-memory</title>
         <p>In<italic>Gatsby</italic>, chapters 1 to 4 have spontaneity, a stylistic directness that seduces the reader into the<italic>happiness</italic>element of nostalgia. The aura of mystery, the uncertainty about the characters, the romantic lyricism, and the narrative coherence transfer the reader to the summer of 1922 in a way that turns this summer not only into Nick's memory, but also into the reader's own textual memory. This, together with a more attentive reading in the beginning due to a lack of expectations, gives the earlier part of the text greater importance and increases the possibility of emotional inclusion (Perry 52–53).<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>This is a never-ending party.</p>
         <p>In order to create a lasting impression on the reader, which will form the reader's textual hyper-memory, Fitzgerald uses several narrative and stylistic techniques. It is crucial to include the reader in the textual experience, to draw him into the narrative emotionally and eliminate the distance between narrative and reader, in order to seduce him. In order to accomplish this, the narrative has to exert a strong impression on the reader. One of Fitzgerald's most important techniques is the carefully constructed and coherent narrative structure in the novel's first part. The narrative flow, the feeling of narrative consciousness and order that comforts the reader in the first three chapters, is constructed through different “relations between the structural units” (Doyno 103). This coherence is achieved in three different ways.</p>
         <p>Several critics, among them James E. Miller Jr., have noted that the first three chapters of<italic>Gatsby</italic>depict three different parties: “The first three chapters of the book, for example, are devoted to the preparation for and presentation of three scenes: the comparatively ‘proper’ dinner party at the Buchanan's in East Egg, the wild drunken party at Tom and Myrtle's apartment in New York, and the huge, extravagant party at Gatsby's mansion in West Egg” (100). Although Miller regards this as evidence of Fitzgerald's “art of selection” in which the author introduces the key characters of the novel as well as its main themes and locations, his point is similar to Norman Holmes Pearson's, when he argues that these chapters introduce the reader into a world of illusions and a sense of one long, never-ending party. The three parties “blend into a stereopticon of the illusions which give color to the world in which all of these people live” (Pearson 25). In addition, the chapters are interlaced through a continuous temporal progression, even though they take place on different days, “a continuance in time” as Robert Emmet Long describes it. The Buchanan party takes place from lunch to afternoon, the hotel party from afternoon to evening, and Gatsby's party from evening until long after midnight. Thus, there is a time progression from lunch to after midnight, a structure that “binds the opening chapters together and adumbrates the novel's movement from day into night, from light into darkness” (Long 112).</p>
         <p>Finally, in much the way a detective story works, Fitzgerald creates reader curiosity thanks to a technique that links the different chapters to each other, reminiscent of the cliff-hangers of mystery fiction. In each chapter, Fitzgerald introduces a theme, an event, or a character that creates curiosity about the next chapter. This tension increases as we approach the chapter's coda. One such example occurs in chapter 1, when Gatsby is introduced almost as a mythic figure during the dinner at the Buchanans’ estate:<disp-quote>
               <p>“You live in West Egg,” she [Jordan] remarked contemptuously. “I know somebody there.”</p>
               <p>“I don't know a single—” [said Nick]</p>
               <p>“You must know Gatsby.”</p>
               <p>“Gatsby?” demanded Daisy. “What Gatsby?”</p>
               <p>Before I could reply that he was my neighbor dinner was announced. (11)</p>
            </disp-quote>The reader is certainly well aware of Gatsby through the title of the novel, and through Nick's passing mention of him in the opening of the introductory chapter (2); but nothing concrete has been revealed about him. As a result, the reader's curiosity is aroused by Daisy's strong reaction when his name is mentioned. Gatsby is mentioned once again before the end of the chapter when Nick tells Jordan that Gatsby is his neighbour (14). Even here, the dialogue abruptly shifts because Jordan is more interested in listening in on Daisy and Tom's conversation: “This Mr. Gatsby you spoke of is my neighbor,” Nick says, but Jordan cuts him off: “Don't talk. I want to hear what happens” (14).</p>
         <p>Reader curiosity about Gatsby reaches a climax at the end of chapter 1 when the reader stands in West Egg with Nick and gazes out over Gatsby's garden:<disp-quote>
               <p>The silhouette of a moving cat wavered across the moonlight, and turning my head to watch it, I saw that I was not alone—fifty feet away a figure had emerged from the shadow of my neighbor's mansion and was standing with his hands in his pockets regarding the silver pepper of the stars. Something in his leisurely movements and the secure position of his feet upon the lawn suggested that it was Mr. Gatsby himself, come out to determine what share was his of our local heavens.</p>
               <p>I decided to call to him. Miss Baker had mentioned him at dinner, and that would do for an introduction. But I didn't call to him, for he gave a sudden intimation that he was content to be alone—he stretched out his arms toward the dark water in a curious way, and, far as I was from him, I could have sworn he was trembling. Involuntarily I glanced seaward—and distinguished nothing except a single green light, minute and far away, that might have been the end of a dock. When I looked once more for Gatsby he had vanished, and I was alone again in the unquiet darkness. (20–21)</p>
            </disp-quote>This scene creates an atmosphere of mystery. It includes several words associated with the gothic: “silhouette of a moving cat,” “moonlight,” “figure,” “mansion,” “stars,” “dark water,” “nothing,” “unquiet darkness.” Gatsby remains enigmatic, a “figure” since Nick chooses not to address him. Gatsby's physical pose is quite peculiar: “he stretched out his arms toward the dark water in a curious way.” Then he disappears into the darkness like a Mephisto, leaving Nick alone in the dark, wondering, together with the reader: “Who is Gatsby” and “What does the green light represent”?</p>
         <p>In chapter 2, Gatsby is not even mentioned, so reader curiosity is further stimulated by his absence. Inquisitiveness about Gatsby is further reawakened in the very first paragraph of chapter 3: “There was music from my neighbor's house through the summer nights” (39). Readers hope that they will learn more about Gatsby through this repeated mention that he is Nick's “neighbor,” but this turns out to be a faulty presumption because even though Nick describes in great detail the first party he attends, Gatsby remains a figure in the shadows. Reader desires are further deferred at this point through rumors and false statements. A woman relates an incident when Gatsby bought her a new dress when her old one had been ruined at one of his parties. Her friend answers: “There's something funny about a fellow that'll do a thing like that…. He doesn't want any trouble with<italic>any</italic>body.” The woman disagrees: “I don't think it's so much<italic>that</italic>… it's more that he was a German spy during the war” (43–44). Guests then testify about a host nobody seems to know or recognize. And when Gatsby finally appears, he does so in a shimmer of anonymity:<disp-quote>
               <p>I turned again to my new acquaintance. “This is an unusual party for me. I haven't even seen the host. I live over there—” I waved my hand at the invisible hedge in the distance, “and this man Gatsby sent over his chauffeur with an invitation.”</p>
               <p>For a moment he looked at me as if he failed to understand.</p>
               <p>“I'm Gatsby,” he said suddenly. (47–48)</p>
            </disp-quote>This technique of mystery runs through the whole novel. As with most mysteries, however, the curiosity is more intriguing in the beginning than toward the end if only because the eventual revelation of the “true story” resolves rather than increases the suspense. We have seen how Gatsby's background and economic enterprises have been purposely obscured through repeated narrative frequency, by having the information being retold and repeated with different content by several characters. This mystification of Gatsby is an important part of creating narrative movement and progress and therefore sustains a flow in the early chapters that encourages the reader's inclusion.</p>
         <p>Another inclusive strategy, identified by Kundu, is the speed and movement in the first three chapters (75). This motion is realized through a summarizing style based on elliptical montage techniques and a distinct style that Kundu compares to that of a movie camera. The inclusive character is a result of these strategies’ effect on “the reader's sense impressions” and creates a reader's “happening” (75). This is similar to Ronald Berman's assertion that the “first half-dozen pages of the novel are an atlas of impressions” (44). This summary, leaving out important information, engages the reader and intensifies the prose to a more effective and elevated style. The quick narrative pace in the opening chapters is partly a result of the many ellipses and numerous scenes in these chapters; the long flashbacks that we find later in the novel are almost absent. In chapter 1, beginning with Nick's arrival in West Egg, there are four ellipses. In chapter 2, there are twenty-four, several due to Fitzgerald's capturing of Nick's drunkenness at Myrtle's apartment. Chapter 3 contains about twenty-nine ellipses. This count has to be approximate since it is difficult to separate scenes with any accuracy in Nick's repetitive and summarizing style. The approximation allows a comparison to chapter 6, which contains ten scenes, chapter 7 (six scenes), and chapter 8, whose innumerable flashbacks retrace the past more than the living present.</p>
         <p>The rich texture of Fitzgerald's prose in the first part of<italic>Gatsby</italic>also creates much visual stimuli in its exploration of colors and texture through its extensive use of adjectives. The gardens are “burning gardens,” windows are “glowing … with reflected gold” or “gleaming white against the fresh grass” (6, 8). Even the Valley of Ashes is inviting in its textured descriptions, despite its bleakness (Kundu 38–39). This visual appeal suggests the motion of a camera that transforms the fluid prose into a sensation of awe. Thus the traditional slow narrative speed of a heavily descriptive narrative paradoxically creates a sense of movement and speed.<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>Both Kundu and Berman describe this when Nick for the first time visits the Buchanans (Kundu 34–35; Berman 137–38). The initial description of the house is like a cinematic long shot, covering a wide scope of the surroundings over the bay: “Across the courtesy bay the white palaces of fashionable East Egg glittered along the water” (5). When Nick actually arrives at the house, the long shot has been replaced with a tighter one: “a cheerful red-and-white Georgian Colonial mansion overlooking the bay.” Then Fitzgerald's prose moves further inward:<disp-quote>
               <p>The lawn started at the beach and ran toward the front door for a quarter of a mile, jumping over sun-dials and brick walks and burning gardens—finally when it reached the house drifting up the side in bright vines as though from the momentum of its run. The front was broken by a line of French windows, glowing now with reflected gold and wide open to the warm windy afternoon, and Tom Buchanan in riding clothes was standing with his legs apart on the front porch. (6)</p>
            </disp-quote>This inward motion toward Tom, simulating that of a movie close-up, creates a sense of textual motion that is seductive in the way it emphasizes motion, speed, and a three-dimensional world.</p>
         <p>This cinematic form of motion is also present in the scene in which Nick sees Gatsby for the first time. It is can be seen as a pan shot, where the cat's movement reinforces the horizontal movement of Nick's head (Kundu 37): “The silhouette of a moving cat wavered across the moonlight and turning my head to watch it I saw that I was not alone” (20). This movement is continued through Gatsby's stretching out his arms towards the sea: “I glanced seaward—and distinguished nothing except a single green light” (21). Similarly, Berman identifies this scene as “intensively cinematic” in not only its movements but also its staging, lightning, and framing (151–52). Its romantic allure to the audience is due to the reader being a “silent witness” to Gatsby's trembling arms (Berman 152). These “tracking shots” and their cinematic quality create the kind of motion that engages and draws the reader into the textual world. This further establishes an envisioning, a participation in the action of the first part of the book, which reinforces the textual hyper-memory.</p>
         <p>The long never-ending party, from the reader's perspective, is thus a result of narrative strategies. The vagueness of such an atemporal party facilitates possibilities of reader associations with their own biographical past and is therefore important in heightening the emotional content of the textual hyper-memory. The fact that these parties take place during the summer further encourages nostalgic identification since summer is often linked to our own nostalgic memories. One technique that serves to emphasize the feeling of a long, never-ending party (the party of a lifetime) is Fitzgerald's use of<italic>iterative frequency</italic>, or more specifically<italic>pseudo-iterative frequency</italic>. Iterative frequency involves referring to narrating events as if they occurred more than once. Instead of relating to an event as “happened,” Fitzgerald says, it “used to happen.” Pseudo-iterative frequency occurs when the detailed description of an event appears to be not completely truthfully presented.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>In chapters 1 and 2 the frequency is<italic>singulative</italic>in that what is told once in the narrative also happens once in the story.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>However, in the beginning of the third chapter, Fitzgerald departs from this classic narrative strategy and starts telling once in the narrative what happens several times in story time.<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>There was not music from Gatsby's house once, but “through the summer nights” (39). Before Nick arrives at Gatsby's party, Nick briefly summarizes all parties of the summer. That passage is a cavalcade of events and experiences as these illustrative fragments show: “In his blue gardens men and girls came and went like moths among the whisperings and champagne and the stars, … [o]n week-ends his Rolls-Royce became an omnibus, bearing parties to and from the city, … [and e]very Friday five crates of oranges and lemons arrived from a fruiterer in New York—every Monday these same oranges and lemons left his back door in a pyramid of pulpless halves” (39). Fitzgerald's nouns remain indefinite— “week-ends” and “men and girls”—or through the use of the word “every” before the nouns. Iterative time is a summarizing time, a “best-of” summary of the memories and festivities of the summer. The pseudo quality arises out of the unbelievably detailed repetitiousness of the acts. This pseudo-iterative further creates a sense of idealized timelessness through its unreliable narration, relating it to the idealized time of nostalgia.</p>
         <p>In the midst of this iterative description, something occurs that further accentuates the feeling of presence in these opening chapters. Fitzgerald abandons his faithful use of a sober past tense in favor of a more direct present tense—shortening the<italic>distance</italic>in French narratologist Gérard Genette's terms.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>10</sup>
            </xref>The transition is marked only with an indentation:<disp-quote>
               <p>In the main hall a bar with a real brass rail was set up, and stocked with gins and liquors and with cordials so long forgotten that most of his female guests were too young to know one from another.</p>
               <p>By seven o'clock the orchestra<italic>has</italic>arrived, no thin five-piece affair, but a whole pitful of oboes and trombones and saxophones and viols and cornets and piccolos, and low and high drums. The last swimmers<italic>have</italic>come in from the beach<italic>now</italic>and<italic>are dressing</italic>up-stairs; the cars from New York<italic>are parked</italic>five deep in the drive, and already the halls and salons and verandas<italic>are</italic>gaudy with primary colors, and hair<italic>shorn</italic>in strange new ways and shawls beyond the dreams of Castile. The bar<italic>is</italic>in full swing, and<italic>floating</italic>rounds of cocktails<italic>permeate</italic>the garden outside, until the air<italic>is</italic>alive with chatter and laughter, and casual innuendo and introductions forgotten on the spot, and enthusiastic meetings between women who never knew each other's names. (40; emphasis added)</p>
            </disp-quote>Fitzgerald continues his lyrical meditation upon these nostalgic summer parties in the present tense for a dozen lines before he returns to the past tense when Nick arrives at the party. The return to the past tense also concludes the iterative form, and the parties become<italic>the party</italic>, as in the first party in which Nick participates. This shift in tense also becomes a shift from a more distanced narration to a more immediate prose that brings the reader closer to relating Nick's experience to his own. With the split narrative, the reader's experience of this first part<italic>must</italic>be so strong that when the second element of nostalgia (reflection) is manifested in the second half of the novel, he reacts with a feeling of loss, a textual loss since it is fundamentally linked to the deprivation of the past literary experience of the text rather than to his personal biography.</p>
         <p>Further, the method of triggering nostalgia through music is appropriate since music and sound communicate directly to a reader's feelings. In doing so, they often become important connotations of memory. The long quotation above represents a good example of the musicality in Fitzgerald's prose, a matter discussed by Langman (31–40) and Bryer (123–27). This musicality is especially noticeable in the first half of the novel when it is designed to pull the reader into the ecstasy and presence of the narrative, as well as at the very end when there is a resolution of the two different nostalgic elements. The long winding sentences, where the subordinate clauses play with and complement each other, are not unlike the instruments in a string quartet. In the passage above, we find only four periods, which means there is a flow and a rhythm amidst repetitions. Asyndeton and polysyndeton function as pausing elements instead of periods. Asyndeton connects clauses through the use of comma, while polysyndeton primarily uses the word “and.” The repeating rhythm is most prominent in the enumeration of instruments in the beginning of the passage or in the phrase “the air is alive with chatter and laughter and casual innuendo and introductions forgotten on the spot and enthusiastic meetings between women who never knew each other's names”; the several “and[s]” create a feeling of breathlessness, which can be compared to the hyper-excitement so often found in children when they experience something important and immediately want to try to tell someone about it. The specific phrasing in this case seems to emphasize action and eventfulness in an almost impressionistic manner, so that the atmosphere of the actual scene is syntactically transferred into the reader's experience. This is further enhanced by the aforementioned switch into present tense in the middle of the description, which minimizes the distance between the reader and the narrated impressions.</p>
         <p>Asyndeton increases the sense of speed and energy by disregarding normal punctuation. It can be valuable if one attempts to convey motion, tumult, and vigor as part of an exceptional memory. This device also helps to involve the reader in the scene. However, it is actually the use of polysyndeton that carries the most nostalgic value. “And” in normal context signals both the oral and the ordinary, such as a single occurrence in an opening phrase such as, “And then we went there.” The repetitive “and” has another connotation: that of pathos and expansive emotions. In Genesis 1:2 we find it contributing to the high-toned style: “And the earth was waste and void; and darkness was upon the face of the deep: and the Spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters.” Polysyndeton has the capacity, as in the example from<italic>Gatsby</italic>, to infuse a text with awe, pathos, and poignancy. Its general seriousness combines well with lyricism or symbolism to establish the gravity of the nostalgic emotion, as opposed to more ironic or satirical moods.</p>
         <p>In addition to the numerous references to music there is also much in the style that is associated with music. Bryer calls attention to Fitzgerald's use of verbs to create movement. As examples, he quotes words like “splash” and “slit” (Bryer 126). In the sequence above we find fifteen verbs, a fact that would not be worth noting if they were not in a paragraph that usually is characterized as descriptive and illustrative. At least one of these verbs, “shorn,” also contains onomatopoetic phonetic qualities. The sound imagery is otherwise based on phrases such as “the bar is in full swing” and “the air is alive with chatter and laughter.” The rich texture of Fitzgerald's prose is thus not only reflected in its visual qualities but also in its descriptions of sounds, which further work inclusively in that they add atmosphere and sensuality to the narrative. The sounds of the summer are constantly infiltrating and fortifying our physical reading experience. It is the “whip and snap” of curtains, white dresses “rippling and fluttering,” and the “groan” of a picture on the wall in the windy summer room at the Buchanans. It is the “boom” and death of the “caught wind” when the door is shut (8). The nightingale sings outside (15). Jordan Baker reads a newspaper, her words “murmurous and uninflected, running together in a soothing tune,” turning pages with “a flutter of slender muscles in her arms” (17). At night the “wind had blown off, leaving a loud, bright night, with wings beating in the trees and a persistent organ sound as the full bellows of the earth blew the frogs full of life” (20).</p>
         <p>In this coherent first part of the book, where readers are drawn into the never-ending party, our nostalgia is reinforced by the obvious contrast between the mysterious, dreamy backgrounds of Daisy and Gatsby and “the ash heap” in chapter 2:<disp-quote>
               <p>This is a valley of ashes—a fantastic farm where ashes grow like wheat into ridges and hills and grotesque gardens; where ashes take the forms of houses and chimneys and rising smoke and, finally, with a transcendent effort, of men who move dimly and already crumbling through the powdery air. Occasionally a line of gray cars crawls along an invisible track, gives out a ghastly creak, and comes to rest, and immediately the ash-gray men swarm up with leaden spades and stir up an impenetrable cloud, which screens their obscure operations from your sight. (23)</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>This descriptive prose is just as extravagant in its abundance of adjectives and metaphors as in the romantic passages, although it is bleaker. Instead of drawing the reader into the atmosphere of nostalgia, Fitzgerald scares them into the nightmare of the present through dark dissonant words such as “grotesque,” “men who move dimly,” “powdery air,” “gray cars crawls,” and the use of the present tense. In emphasizing the realities of life found in the description of the gray, dull environment where Wilson and his wife live under the constant supervision of Dr. T. J. Eckleburg, the exquisitely beautiful parties become even more exquisite and suggestive. The ash heap represents the present, what readers inevitably long to leave, while the parties are a sharply defined past. In nostalgia there is always a core of something positive, a never-ending party, but it is not until readers connect it to the present that nostalgia is complete. This is even more apparent in the second part of<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>The Nostalgic Hangover</title>
         <p>Euphoric, debauched happiness disappears in chapter 5. Instead of continuing the joyful summer of 1922, the reader is moved backward in time more and more often through multiple flashbacks. These shifts disturb the seductiveness and presence in the experience and bring, in addition to Nick's more diagnostic narrator's voice, a more sober and reflective style. Since readers have been dependent on the romantic prose in the first half of the book, they miss it now; everything has become duller. Fitzgerald achieves this effect in several different ways.</p>
         <p>Early in chapter 6 we notice the difference, since it is the first time that Nick is not present in the very opening of a chapter. All previous chapters have opened with an emphasis on Nick as a subject; it has always been certain that he is the narrator. Chapter 1 starts with “In<italic>my</italic>younger” (1; emphasis added); in chapter 3, “There was music from<italic>my</italic>neighbor's house” (39; emphasis added). It takes ten lines in chapter 4 until Fitzgerald gets to Nick as the subject: “Once<italic>I</italic>wrote down” (61; emphasis added) but in chapter 5 Nick returns to his early prominent position with “When<italic>I</italic>came home” (81; emphasis added). I have deliberately avoided mentioning chapter 2 since it is an exception. It begins with an introductory description of the ash heap before Nick's presence is revealed after one page with “that<italic>I</italic>first met” (24; emphasis added). It is not strange, in this case, that Fitzgerald delays Nick's arrival, because, as noted above, chapter 2 is a contrast to the otherwise flowing first half of the novel. As in chapter 2, in the second part of<italic>Gatsby</italic>, the relative absence of Nick creates uneasiness; the reader has been used to having their cicerone by their side.</p>
         <p>There are also an increase of distance and a decrease of presence in the narrative mood and voice in the second part of<italic>Gatsby</italic>. This increased distance is established through a more analytical narration. The impressionistic descriptions of events and characters are replaced by reasoning. Nick's narrating distance increases when he penetrates the emptiness, superficiality, and alienation around him. He is no longer seduced by what he sees, and, by extension, he no longer seduces the reader. What is more, we are now in autumn. The early summer's promises of happiness and exciting happenings transform into a blues of melancholia, decadence, and a remembrance of the forgotten when the leaves turn yellow. The presence of autumn reverberates in the prose in phrases such as “disappearing under the August foliage” and “The next day was broiling, almost the last, certainly the warmest, of the summer” (106, 113). Further into the narrative the entrance of autumn becomes more tangible: “there was an autumn flavor in the air” (153), “the yellowing trees … an unfamiliar sky through frightening leaves” (161). The melancholy is also more implicit: “Her glance left me and sought the lighted top of the steps where ‘Three o'Clock in the Morning,’ a neat sad little waltz of that year, was drifting out the open door” (108). Furthermore, it is not by pure chance that Gatsby's first meeting with Daisy, retold by Gatsby, takes place during autumn, with all the clichés of autumn: “One autumn night, five years before, they had been walking down the street when the leaves were falling” (110). The autumn of memory corresponds with the narrative autumn and contrasts with the earlier textual memory of summer and summer flashbacks.</p>
         <p>The divided narrative in<italic>Gatsby</italic>is essential for the reader to create and reflect upon his own textual memory. However, in preventing this division from being too abrupt, symmetry must assist the reader in the reverberation of his or her textual memory. In fact, this symmetry is essential in revoking the literary nostalgic experience since it works as a textual trigger. The usage and re-usage of simple symbols or motifs create this symmetry and it becomes the skeleton of the novel. Fitzgerald gradually transforms these symbols in order to play with our textual memory and emotionally distort it. They resemble, in an artificial way, the triggers of memories.</p>
         <p>One such recurring motif is the use of flowers in general and pink roses in particular. They connect the reader's experiences from the first part with the second part in a way that he, perhaps subconsciously, is reminded of that first experience and the happiness of that textual memory. Langman writes that this motif functions “as a simple unifying device, reminding us of one scene as we read another” (43). There are several rose motifs in the opening of the novel. The first that attracts Nick's attention at the Buchanans’ home is the rose garden: “a half acre of deep pungent roses.” Later, Nick and Tom enter “into a bright rosy-colored space” (7); they look through “a rosy-colored porch” (11); and Daisy (herself named after a flower) calls Nick “a rose, an absolute rose” (14).</p>
         <p>In the second part of the novel these rose motifs reappear with regularity and remind the reader of the beginning of the novel: “Our eyes lifted over the rosebeds” (118), “I could think of nothing except the luminosity of his pink suit under the moon” (142), and “the pink glow from Daisy's room” (144). But it is not only through the noun “rose” that Fitzgerald reminds readers of the past. His vocabulary is over-represented by “rose” the verb: “With an effort her wit rose faintly” (125), “a tiny gust of powder rose from her bosom” (116). Even a melody assists our chain of associations: “someone had begun to whistle ‘The Rosary’” (170).</p>
         <p>Gradually these symbols change. Where once they represented love and passion, they will be exchanged for resignation as in the “crushed flowers” and “fruit rinds” (109) at the end of the final party, the flower-laden hearse of Gatsby's funeral, or Gatsby's recollection of them: “He must have looked up at an unfamiliar sky through frightening leaves and shivered as he found what a grotesque thing a rose is” (161). Likewise, now roses recall Robert Herrick's “Gather ye rosebuds while ye may” for Daisy when Gatsby leaves for the war:<disp-quote>
               <p>All night the saxophones wailed the hopeless comment of the Beale Street Blues while a hundred pairs of golden and silver slippers shuffled the shining dust. At the gray tea hour there were always rooms that throbbed incessantly with this low, sweet fever, while fresh faces drifted here and there like rose petals blown by the sad horns around the floor. (151)</p>
            </disp-quote>In J. S. Westbrook's words, “the world cannot be made to bloom perpetually”; it is as if there is “an over-ripeness, an unnatural plenitude in this new Eden” (81), or a “buried fertility” (83) that carries over into the last symbols of the vanished promises of the New Land.</p>
         <p>Another color motif used frequently by Fitzgerald is “white,” and this color helps to mythologize Daisy for Gatsby and for the reader with its connotations of childhood and innocence. White is used in phrases such as “the white palaces of fashionable East Egg” (5); “[t]he windows … ajar and gleaming white against the fresh grass” (8); Jordan's voice that is “as cool” as her and Daisy's “white dresses” (12); and their innocent childhood: “[o]ur white girlhood was passed together there. Our beautiful white—” (19). References to “white” appear with regularity throughout<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>. In the second part of the novel, “six pair of white duck trousers” (100) are displayed, an actress sits under “a white-plum tree” (104), and Gatsby remembers his autumn night with Daisy when “the sidewalk was white with moonlight” and “Daisy's white face came up to his own” (110). At the end of the novel, Nick stares at Gatsby's “white steps” (179).</p>
         <p>These later motifs associated with “white” effectively trigger the reader's earlier reminiscences of the glorious, promising, and innocent past such as the snow in Nick's story about his youth: “When we pulled out into the winter night and the real snow, our snow, began to stretch out beside us” (175). Another example is the description of Daisy, who is “gleaming like silver” on her veranda, “bright with the bought luxury of star-shine” (149). Likewise, the meaning of the color yellow is transformed, most obviously through Gatsby's yellow car that first transports guests to and from his dazzling parties, but in the end turns into the death car Daisy uses when she kills Myrtle (Westbrook 81). In fact, the first description of the car does not refer to it as yellow but as a “rich cream color” while it later becomes an autumnal, murky, and mundane yellow (64).</p>
         <p>In the use of sounds, we also see a change between part one and two in order to assist the reader's longing back to his earlier textual memory. In the transitional fifth chapter, the summer rain subtly changes from soft and wonderful to a windy and loud thunder as the story progresses toward the ultimate fate of Gatsby's nostalgic dream. It is the zenith, the narrative breaking point, when the reader suddenly emotionally becomes aware of the impossibility of Gatsby's project. The “faint flow of thunder along the Sound” suggests this feeling of irrecoverable moments, a loss that even Gatsby seems to realize when “Daisy tumbled short of his dreams—not through her own fault but because of the colossal vitality of his illusion” (95). Later, after Myrtle's death, the merry sounds of the summer birds have completely changed into singing “ghostly birds” (152). As Kundu has observed, “[t]he hiatus between beauty and the romance of nature and humanity's tragic fate” is established through the diverse use of sounds and descriptions of nature (101).</p>
         <p>Another change is that the second part of the novel is more inclined to use close-ups rather than the inclusive seductive tracking, or “zooming” shots of the first part, thus entering into a more psychological tensional discourse. When Nick finds Gatsby in the pool, the camera eye does not change focal lengths from long shot to close-up in order to create a sense of awe, but instead moves closely between certain symbols:<disp-quote>
               <p>There was a faint, barely perceptible movement of the water as the fresh flow from one end urged its way toward the drain at the other. With little ripples that were hardly the shadows of waves, the laden mattress moved irregularly down the pool. A small gust of wind that scarcely corrugated the surface was enough to disturb its accidental course with its accidental burden. The touch of a cluster of leaves revolved it slowly, tracing, like the leg of transit, a thin red circle in the water. (162)</p>
            </disp-quote>The emotional response to this stylistic close-up technique differs radically from the one of motion that worked so inclusively in the first part. Since Gatsby lies dead in the pool, there is no mystery anymore. The movement of the camera eye from one image to another slows down the duration of the scene drastically. Fitzgerald's literary technique “resembles filmmakers’ metaphorical use of the moving camera as a consumer of time,” Kundu suggests. This implies that Gatsby “is a victim not only of his impossible dream, but also of time's cruel prodigality, indeed, of the tragic flux and mutability of life itself” (Kundu 42). It also contradicts the novel's relation to movement in general; Berman describes the motion of the leaves as “moving, but going nowhere” (44).</p>
         <p>The inherent distance, boredom, and looming tragedy climax at Gatsby's last party. Nick depicts his feelings toward this party with sober sadness: “There were the same people, or at least the same sort of people, the same profusion of champagne, the same many-colored, many-keyed commotion, but I felt an unpleasantness in the air, a pervading harshness that hadn't been there before” (104). As usual, Nick's emotions are suggested by the language. Words such as “harshness,” “desolate” and “crushed,” which phonetically sound unattractive, are not found in the first part of<italic>Gatsby</italic>. These words not only communicate emptiness and regret for the passing summer, but also convey a more symbolic meaning, the tragedy of life: today is tomorrow's past. The potent boats that “slit” the water in the beginning are replaced by “one small sail [that] crawled slowly toward the fresher sea” (118). And if the first parties revealed that those in attendance were exactly where they wanted to be, they seem restless now. Inspired by the pioneer spirit and “the moon … in the western sky,” they want to go west just like Wilson, who wants to take Myrtle with him (120).</p>
         <p>These sentiments are cemented in words such as “overripe” (125), “motionless” (138), and “restless” (128); and the sound imagery changes character from a feeling of remembrance to one of forgetfulness: “She turned to me and her voice, dropping an octave lower, filled the room with thrilling scorn” (131); “hollow, wailing sound” (138); and “I heard a low husky sob” (141). Even the wedding orchestra from the ballroom seems to be playing in a headwind: “From the ballroom beneath, muffled and suffocating chords were drifting up on hot waves of air” (132).</p>
         <p>In the end, Gatsby's dream dies in a manifestation of every man's past, rather than one individual's fate; the conclusion prepares us for a transcendence from an individual fate to a universal one, from a presence to a distance, creating a microcosm of the themes of the entire novel: “the dead dream fought on as the afternoon slipped away, trying to touch what was no longer tangible, struggling unhappily, undespairingly, toward that lost voice across the room” (134). The reader, together with the key characters of the book, travel by car toward the verge of destiny, in the most brilliant prolepsis of the novel: “So we drove toward death through the cooling twilight” (136). The party is over; enter the hangover.</p>
         <p>Fitzgerald's particular structural and stylistic approach to nostalgia in<italic>Gatsby</italic>, dividing the narrative into two distinct parts and thus creating both a textual nostalgia and evoking a phenomenological nostalgic experience in the reader, are masterly and consciously accomplished, but they are not unique. Modernist writers used a palette of nostalgic strategies in order to stage their experience of the modern world. Although nostalgia can be considered conservative or reactionary as an idea, the influence it had on modernist literary style is, on the contrary, quite radical. “The melancholic sense of loss,” writes Svetlana Boym, “turned into a style” (16). The sense of transcendental homelessness in combination with nihilism and universal grief that was accentuated by the war and contemporary ideas necessitated a literary style that both confronted the whole project of progress as well as provided a space for emotions that were not considered desirable in a world moving distinctly forward. The nostalgic aesthetic is heavily based on strategies that are formed out of the basic nostalgic and modern dichotomy between future and past, now and then, here and there, which included such varied techniques as temporal re-ordering of events, the nostalgic use of both flashbacks and flash-forwards, the dichotomy between inner time and clock time. Furthermore, the modernists favored inner or outer landscapes of utopian and idealized spaces. Such landscapes could be either simply another past, or more intricately, a phenomenological experience of childhood.</p>
         <p>The nostalgic strategies that Fitzgerald used in<italic>Gatsby</italic>are then part of a more general nostalgic inclination in modernist writing. Jay Gatsby's peculiar and pathetic gesture, stretching “out his hand desperately” (153) toward the past, illustrates both modern nostalgia's teleological concern and entropic vision of modernity, and the melancholia and pain involved in this retrospection. However, Fitzgerald's particular use of narrative aesthetics integrated in a grander nostalgic scheme of creating a phenomenological experience of nostalgia, a nostalgic novel rather than a novel about nostalgia, is only rivalled, in his own time, by Virginia Woolf. In<italic>To The Lighthouse</italic>(1927) she uses a similar structure. The death of Mrs. Ramsay, as well as the whole middle chapter in which it occurs, titled “Time Passes,” becomes a structural break in the narrative, clearly dividing the story to<italic>before</italic>and<italic>after</italic>the war. Although not entirely uncritical of the Victorian manners of pre-war Britain, what remains is still an idyllic “airy sunny garden” (141) that is constantly revoked by the surviving characters in the last chapter, “The Lighthouse.”</p>
         <p>Fitzgerald's nostalgic style, though, set an example of how a nostalgic narrative could be structured, and in its aftermath it was used by such different authors as Evelyn Waugh in<italic>Brideshead Revisited</italic>(1945), Anthony Burgess in<italic>A Clockwork Orange</italic>(1962) and the works of Kazuo Ishiguro. The author's own later work employs it as well. The technique of using the reader's textual memory in order to evoke a phenomenological nostalgic experience is very evident in both versions of<italic>Tender Is the Night</italic>(the 1934 original, and Malcolm Cowley's 1951 restructuring). In the 1951 version, the structure of the narrative closely follows the pattern of happiness and reflection. An early description of a Swiss valley communicates an awe of life and nature: “The sun swam out into a blue sea of sky and suddenly it was a Swiss valley at its best—pleasant sounds and murmurs and a good fresh smell of health and cheer” (9). In the transitory third book, “Casualties: 1925,” the tone has changed from appreciative to melancholic, as in this description of the small town of Amiens: “In the day-time one is deflated by such towns, with their little trolley cars of twenty years ago crossing the great grey cobble-stoned squares in front of the cathedral, and the very weather seems to have a quality of the past, faded weather like that of old photographs” (138). At the end of the novel both Dick and Nicole Diver become obsessed with youth and the past as well as with time: “for Nicole the years slipped away by clock and calendar and birthday, with the added poignance of her perishable beauty” (228). Toward the end of the novel, Nicole's last sight of Dick—“her eyes followed his figure until it became a dot and mingled with the other dots in the summer crowd” (386)—forces the reader to reflect in a reversed movement. Instead of vanishing like Dick, this image suggests a backward recollection of what was a Swiss valley “at its best.”</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricœur talks extensively, inspired by Mendilow, in<italic>Temps et Rècit Vol. 2</italic>[<italic>Time and Narrative Volume 2</italic>] (1984) about the crucial difference between tales of time and tales about time. He writes: “All fictional narratives are ‘tales of time’ inasmuch as the structural transformations that affect the situations and characters take time. However only a few are ‘tales about time’ inasmuch as in them it is the very experience of time that is at stake in these structural transformations” (101). He means that there are a few novels (modernism and later) that actually give readers a phenomenological experience of time, where the actual experience of fictive time is at the heart of the work's themes and meaning (Ricœur 62).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The famous dichotomy of clock time and inner time (Bergsonian duration) has proven a common strategy to exploit the teleological aspects of nostalgia. The occurrence of time markers, flagging clock time as an impatient but steady beat towards decay and death, are common enough. The most famous example is the use of clock time in Woolf's<italic>Mrs Dalloway (1925)</italic>in which the recurring sound of Big Ben constantly reminds the reader of time, and this, in turn, becomes a contrast to the subjective Bergsonian time of the characters which enables a temporality that fights against clock time.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a more detailed account of textual memory, see Salmose 298–305.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>A<italic>hyper-memory</italic>is any memory that is nostalgically enhanced or idealized, and thus nostalgic. A<italic>textual memory</italic>is any recollection of past textual events. A<italic>textual hyper-memory</italic>is a nostalgic memory of past textual events, a textual memory that is enhanced and idealized.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Perry argues that there is “an essential difference between the initial and subsequent stages of reading” (52). Reading in the beginning of a text is slowed down because one enters the text without expectations, but with curiosity and a need to make sense of setting, plot and characters. He is basing his argument on several psychological experiments (53–56).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See also Berman 101–6, who discusses Fitzgerald's stylistic technique of replacing description with perception.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Narratolgist Gérard Genette recognizes that iterative frequency is a very common form of narration in the first three sections of<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>(117). Instead of the common use of past tense “happened,” things “used to happen” instead. The iterative is a sort of summarizing form; it explores rituals and recurring events and therefore evokes the nostalgic idea of how rituals and seasons trigger nostalgic memories. It also regards memory as nostalgic rather than memorial, since it lacks the specificity of memory and embraces the vagueness of nostalgic memory. A phrase such as “I remember the day in June 1942 when dad caught that big fish” is less nostalgic than “I remember that dad and I used to fish in the summers.” Sometimes the iterative frequency is so detailed that one suspects that this is not exactly how it happened each time, but in reality there were certain variations of it. This is what Genette calls pseudo-iterative (121). The pseudo quality arises out of the unbelievable detailed repetitiousness of the acts. In Genette's words, “pseudo-iterative—that is, scenes presented, particularly by their wording in the imperfect, as iterative, whereas their richness and precision of detail ensure that no reader can seriously believe they occur and reoccur in that manner, several times, without any variation” (121). The pseudo quality of the iterative removes it even further from that of real memory into the sphere of nostalgic idealization and positions it into the sphere of nostalgic idealization; some details come to represent a memory that more vaguely embraces a certain time or era in one's life.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>
               <italic>Frequency</italic>according to Genette deals with the quantative relationship between story and narrative. The different relationships are: (1) narrating once what happened once; (2) narrating several times what happened several times; (3) narrating several times what happened once; (4) narrating once what happened several times (Genette 114–16).<italic>Singulative frequency</italic>corresponds with the first relationship: narrating once what happened once in the story.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Story time refers to time of the plot, which is contrasted to narrative time, which refers to time of narration. These two times rarely correspond, and their discrepancy is called<italic>anachronies</italic>. According to Genette, a study of anachronies is a study of the “connections between the temporal<italic>order</italic>of succession of the events in the story and the pseudo-temporal order of their arrangement in the narrative” (35).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In terms of distance in mood, Genette identifies two divergences: narrative of events, and narrative of words (164). Narrative of events can never be totally mimetic because that would be utopic; instead we talk about different degrees of detail and the amount of the narrator's emotions and thoughts that are narrated. Literary nostalgia depends more on lyrical and descriptive prose, and the importance of commentary and evaluation of the narrative from the narrator is crucial as well. Therefore, there seems to be a dependence on scene (detailed narrative) and a narrator who is involved in what he narrates as opposed to a more transparent narration as is often the case with Hemingway. Narrative of words deals with speech (both dialogue and thoughts), and compared to the narrative of events, we can speak about true mimetic style, reported speech, or direct speech, (“I will get married,” I said to my mother) as well as more distanced, indirect speeches such as narrated speech (I informed my mother that I would get married) and transposed speech (I told my mother that I would get married) (Genette 171). The nostalgic mood favors generally more distanced speeches, since that does not obliterate the role of the narrator and the time of the narrating. The distance reinforces the pastness of the narrative. Thus, narratives that use a high degree of reported speech, both as standard dialogue and in flashbacks, are less nostalgic.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="references">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Baird, Leonard</string-name>. Rev. of<source>
                  <italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>
               </source>, by<string-name>F. Scott Fitzgerald</string-name>.<italic>Life</italic>85, 30 Apr.<year>1926</year>.<source>
                  <italic>F. Scott Fitzgerald. The Critical Reception</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<string-name>Jackson Bryer</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Burt Franklin</publisher-name>,<year>1978</year>. 208. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Berman, Ronald</string-name>.<source>The Great Gatsby<italic>and Modern Times</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of Illinois P</publisher-name>,<year>1994</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Boym, Svetlana</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Future of Nostalgia</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Basic</publisher-name>,<year>2001</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Bryer, Jackson R</string-name>.<chapter-title>“Style as Meaning in<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>: Notes Toward a New Approach.”</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Donaldson</publisher-name>
               <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Donaldson, Scott</string-name>, ed.<source>
                  <italic>Critical Essays on F. Scott Fitzgerald's</italic>
               </source>
               <chapter-title>The Great Gatsby</chapter-title>.:<publisher-name>Hall</publisher-name>,<year>1984</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Doyno, Victor A</string-name>.<chapter-title>“Patterns in<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>.”</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Donaldson</publisher-name>
               <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Fitzgerald, F. Scott</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>
               </source>.<year>1925</year>.:<publisher-name>Scribner's</publisher-name>,<year>2004</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Fitzgerald, F. Scott</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Tender Is the Night</italic>
               </source>.<year>1951</year>. Ed.<string-name>Malcolm Cowley</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Gray Walls</publisher-name>,<year>1955</year>. Print</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Genette, Gérard</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>Jane E. Lewin</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Cornell UP</publisher-name>,<year>1983</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Herrick, Robert</string-name>.<chapter-title>“To the Virgins, to Make Much of Time.”</chapter-title>
               <year>1648</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Hesperides: or, The Works Both Humane and Divine of Robert Herrick, Volume 1</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>William Pickering</publisher-name>,<year>1846</year>. 110. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Iser, Wolfgang</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Act of Reading: A Theory of Aesthetic Response</italic>
               </source>.<year>1978</year>.:<publisher-name>John Hopkins UP</publisher-name>,<year>1980</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kundu, Gautam</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Fitzgerald and the Influence of Film: The Language of Cinema in the Novels</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>McFarland</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r13">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Langman, F. H</string-name>.<chapter-title>“Style and Shape in<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>.”</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Donaldson</publisher-name>
               <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r14">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Long, Robert Emmet</string-name>.<chapter-title>“<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>: The Intricate Art.”</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Donaldson</publisher-name>
               <fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r15">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Miller, James E., Jr</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Fictional Technique of Scott Fitzgerald</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Nijhoff</publisher-name>,<year>1957</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r16">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Pearson, Norman Holmes</string-name>.<chapter-title>“Reading a Novel—<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>.”</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Donaldson</publisher-name>
               <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r17">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Perry, Menakhem</string-name>.<article-title>“Literary Dynamics: How the Order of a Text Creates Its Meanings [With an Analysis of Faulkner's ‘A Rose for Emily’].”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Literature, Interpretation, Communication</italic>. Spec. issue of<italic>Poetics Today</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>1</volume>.<issue>1–2</issue>(<year>1979</year>):<fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>,<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r18">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricœur, Paul</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>[<italic>Temps et Rècit</italic>]</source>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>and<string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>.<volume>Vol. 2</volume>.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1985</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r19">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Salmose, Niklas</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Towards a Poetics of Nostalgia: The Nostalgic Experience in Modern Fiction</italic>
               </source>..<publisher-name>U of Edinburgh</publisher-name>,<year>2012</year>. Web. 5 July 2014.<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="https://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/7728/2/Salmose2012.pdf">https://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/7728/2/Salmose2012.pdf</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r20">
            <mixed-citation>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Holy Bible</italic>
               </source>. American Standard Version. Ed.<chapter-title>American Revisory Committee</chapter-title>.:<publisher-name>Nelson</publisher-name>,<year>1901</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r21">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Westbrook, J. S</string-name>.<article-title>“Nature and Optics in the Great Gatsby.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>American Literature</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>32</volume>.<issue>1</issue>(<year>1960</year>):<fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r22">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Woolf, Virginia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Mrs. Dalloway</italic>
               </source>.<year>1925</year>. Ed.<chapter-title>Jeanette Winterson and Margaret Reynolds</chapter-title>.:<publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>,<year>2000</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r23">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Woolf, Virginia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>To the Lighthouse</italic>
               </source>.<year>1927</year>. Ed.<string-name>Stevie Davis</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>,<year>1989</year>. Print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
