<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">shaw</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Shaw</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">07415842</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15291480</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">shaw.34.1.0001</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/shaw.34.1.0001</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dilemmas and Delusions</article-title>
            <subtitle>Bernard Shaw and Health</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Wixson</surname>
                  <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <bold>
                     <sc>christopher wixson</sc>
                  </bold>is professor of English at Eastern Illinois University and teaches courses in early modern, modern, and contemporary drama. He has staged plays by Edward Albee, Samuel Beckett, Anton Chekhov, Harold Pinter, William Shakespeare, John Webster, Christopher Durang, and Sarah Kane. His work has appeared in<italic>Modern Drama</italic>,<italic>Studies in English Literature</italic>,<italic>Comparative Drama</italic>,<italic>ELT</italic>,<italic>Notes on Contemporary Literature</italic>,<italic>Pamphlet</italic>, the<italic>Harold Pinter Review</italic>, the<italic>SHAW</italic>,<italic>American Drama</italic>, and the<italic>Columbia Encyclopedia of Modern Drama</italic>.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">shaw.34.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>15</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/shaw.34.1.0001"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
         <disp-quote content-type="epi">
            <p>His marvelous accomplishment, in solid contribution to thought and light stimulation to gayety, is so immense in volume as to have one explanation: perfect health.</p>
            <attrib>—Archibald Henderson,<italic>Bernard Shaw: Playboy and Prophet</italic>
            </attrib>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote content-type="epi">
            <p>His essential healthy-mindedness and peculiar buoyancy never allowed him to sink into [the fin de siècle writers'] bogs of glorified decay, [and] the very mention of his name seems to clear the poisoned air a little.</p>
            <attrib>—Maurice Colbourne,<italic>The Real Bernard Shaw</italic>
            </attrib>
         </disp-quote>Beguiling a Victorian public obsessed with the pursuit of fitness, the International Health Exhibition opened in South Kensington in May 1884. Its expressed intent, to educate the public on a broad range of wellness topics, was greatly overshadowed by its dazzling display of proprietary medical commodities, salutary appliances, and faddish cures. While there were legitimate exhibits that dealt sincerely with issues of sanitation, hygiene, food, drink, and even child care, the event illuminated the extent to which personal and systemic therapeutic remedy and indeed health itself had become a lucrative industry. Less than three weeks before he joined the Fabian Society, the fledgling novelist Bernard Shaw visited one of the exhibition's prominent attractions, Francis Galton's Anthropometric Laboratory, to be quantified and measured. Chart 3655, created on 16 August 1884, contains the following collected data:<disp-quote>
            <title>THE MAN</title>
            <p>Colour of eyes, blue-grey.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Eyesight.</title>
            <p>Greatest distance in inches of reading “Diamond” type—Right eye, 23; left eye, 27.</p>
            <p>Colour sense (goodness of)—Good.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Judgment of Eye.</title>
            <p>Error per cent. In dividing a line of 15 inches—in three parts, 1 1/2; in two parts, 1/2.</p>
            <p>Error in degrees of estimating squareness—1/4.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Hearing.</title>
            <p>Keenness can hardly be tested here owing to the noises and echoes.</p>
            <p>Highest audible note—Between 30,000 and 40,000 vibrations per second.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Breathing Power.</title>
            <p>Greatest expiration in cubic inches—298.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Strength.</title>
            <p>Of squeeze in lbs. of—right hand, 83; left hand, 80.</p>
            <p>Of pull in lbs.—57.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Span of Arms.</title>
            <p>From finger tips of opposite hands—5 feet 11.7 inches.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Height.</title>
            <p>Sitting, measured from seat of chair—3 feet 1.8 inches.</p>
            <p>Standing in shoes…………………………………6 feet 0.8 inch</p>
            <p>Less height of heel………………………………… 0.7 inch</p>
            <p>____________</p>
            <p>Height without shoes...................................6 feet 0.1 inch.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <title>Weight.</title>
            <p>In ordinary indoor clothing in lbs.—142.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>1</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>Fittingly, Shaw's exposition occurs under the auspices of an exhibition as simultaneously invested in health and product marketing as he would soon become.</p>
      <p>What to me is most striking about the Galen lab report is that it captures an unusually quiescent image of Shaw, a stasis that is discordant with our sense of him as a vivacious, frenetic blur during those first decades in London, what Archibald Henderson deems “the quintessence of vital energy.”<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>Throughout most of his life, Shaw was an active walker, cyclist, and swimmer, not to mention a compulsive reader, writer, and speaker whose engagement with the world around him was marked by a robust, ferocious vigor. Shaw's use of language is itself acrobatic, his agile balancing of ideas, his graceful rhetorical athleticism across genres. In this sense, it is precisely his<italic>sanus agitatus</italic>that draws and sustains our interest, the rigor of his writing challenging us to keep up, work out, and stay in shape. In 1897, the<italic>Vegetarian</italic>noted of Shaw that “in the pursuit of his duties he has to work frequently under most unhealthy conditions and to face all weathers yet any observant stranger would turn and take a second look at Shaw's virile figure in the street.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>Indeed, more than a century later, we are still eagerly looking and, in some cases, still trying to catch up. Arguably, health was the fundamental preoccupation of Shaw's work, Shavianism's probiotic elixir the unifying thread of a prolific and expansive career.</p>
      <p>The subject of health winds its way through every part of Shaw's early London years, from committing to vegetarianism and contracting smallpox in 1881 to an exhaustive breakdown in 1898 resulting in a marriage to his ostensible nurse. Salient controversies of health, particularly during the last two decades of the nineteenth century, served Shaw well in providing foundational linchpins for his GBS persona and for buttressing claims of Shavian exceptionalism. During those years of activism on behalf of public health reform, he writes and speaks compellingly and prolifically against a scientific system predicated on germ theory, an economic system that mandated poverty, malnourishment, and squalor for a large swath of the population, and a medical service driven by potion pushers, outright frauds, and needless, invasive procedures (in particular vivisection and inoculation) performed by “flesh plumbers and carpenters.”<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>These perspectives anchor countless speeches, newspaper op-eds, and magazine pieces but also infuse his work for the theater, including many of his early plays but most directly<italic>The Doctor's Dilemma</italic>(1906). In blending artistic language with the discourse of health, Shaw is merely responding to his theatrical environment. In chronicling the furor around the English production of Ibsen's<italic>Ghosts</italic>in 1891, T. Carlo Matos notes that “the theater world of 1890s London is a powerful example of how contagion and epidemiology can work in an aesthetic context, not merely as content but as a means of responding to and mediating art and its role in shaping public attitudes towards a variety of socio-cultural phenomenon.”<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>5</sup>
         </xref>Even in his criticism, especially during his tenure at the<italic>Saturday Review</italic>, Shaw often used his attitudes on health and his wellness practices as rhetorical frames that enabled him to diagnose what he viewed as a moribund theater.</p>
      <p>In an 1896 review, for instance, he explicitly parallels doctors and actors in their professional practice, beginning by characterizing the former in his usual terms: “The average doctor is a walking compound of natural ignorance and acquired witchcraft, who kills your favorite child, wrecks your wife's health, and orders you into habits of nervous dram-drinking before you have the courage to send him about his business.”<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>6</sup>
         </xref>After similarly chastising attorneys, boot makers, and tailors, Shaw asserts that, while we “imagine that these people have professions,” we discover that “what they have is only, in the correct old word, their ‘mystery’—a humbug, like all mysteries. And yet, how we help to keep up the humbug! … Men believe in the professions as they believe in ghosts, because they want to believe in them” (423–24, 425). For Shaw, human beings had redirected their desire for faith in idols and priests toward doctors and marketing men. The commercial theater had also fed upon this need, and even the critic himself is susceptible to their hypnotic prowess. Calling himself the “most ridiculous of all dupes,” Shaw confesses in the review his mistaking of the actor as a skilled craftsman, a “civilizing agent [and] spiritual doctor,” when in fact “it is all a delusion: there is no profession, no art, no skill about the business at all” (425). Just as those who are exploited by the medical industry, Shaw's “desire and hope got the better of [his] observation[, his] imagination of [his] experience” (428). The fraud perpetuated by doctors is akin to the “mystery” of theater; if doctors are ghosts, actors and managers are similar spirits who have offended. For Shaw, then, the critic's job is to “sift the gold of fact and efficiency out of the huge rubbish-heap of professionalism” (425).</p>
      <p>Gastronomical practice and his dramaturgical philosophy charmingly intertwine in his 1897 review of John T. Day's explicitly antivegetarian play<italic>The Fanatic</italic>. In it, Shaw expresses his bemusement with “a dramatist who makes the whole interest of his play depend on a passionate faith in the nutritiousness of a cutlet and a glass of wine.”<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>7</sup>
         </xref>Its plot concerns a young woman newly married to a rabid vegetarian and teetotaler who immediately proceeds to feed her such enormous quantities of meatless fare that only, as Shaw writes, “if she were an elephant working out a sentence of hard labor [would] she … possibly be able to get exercise enough to keep pace” (352–53). (The playwright himself had outlined the perils of such overeating in an 1886<italic>Pall Mall Gazette</italic>op-ed titled “Failures of Inept Vegetarians.”) When she sickens, a doctor is called in who earnestly if predictably prescribes cutlets and wine. Clear in its answer to, in Shaw's words, the “question … of cucumbers versus corpses” (354),<italic>The Fanatic</italic>culminates in the doctor's impulsive elopement proposition to his patient and the husband's mysterious yet gracious gesture of dropping dead.</p>
      <p>Representing in his review the struggle between the husband and the doctor as a “wrangle between … witches as to the merits of their rival incantations,” Shaw asserts that Day's fatal misstep is to misunderstand the collision between “lay ignorance” and “academic error and prejudice” and to “take sides” (354–55). Shaw's appreciation of staging the conflict between one individual “right in theory and wrong in practice” and another “wrong in theory and right in practice” (354) anticipates verbal skirmishes he would soon create in<italic>Major Barbara</italic>and<italic>The Doctor's Dilemma</italic>. While he praises the grotesque caricature of the doctor (perhaps unintentional on Day's part), Shaw faults the play's ultimate reliance on “an unsound theory of alimentation” and its concurrent “unhappy relapse” into sentimentality in its conclusion (352). Shaw frequently linked diet and excessive romantic imagination. In an 1898 interview with<italic>Vegetarian</italic>, he attributes the outbreak of “fire-eating fiction and Jingo war worship, bloody-minded novels [and] cheered music-hall tableaux” to “the spread of meat-eating,” explicitly gesturing to one of its tragic products, the strife on the Sudan that would eventually catalyze the Boer War.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>8</sup>
         </xref>If for Shaw vegetarianism is essential to counter narcotic sentimentality in general, it is equally imperative in the struggle for a vital theater, similarly sodden with melodramatic convention. When asked in that interview how “vegetarianism and dramatic criticism blend,” Shaw responded, “meat-fed criticism is the best for the managers. The vegetarian article is best for the public.”<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>9</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>During periods when Shaw was debilitated by illness, injury, and outright prostration, GBS reconceives convalescence and medical procedures as occasions of revelation and rejuvenation. In another<italic>Saturday Review</italic>piece, written in May 1898, the playwright describes being subject to a practice he execrated, vivisection to remedy his infected foot, but, through it, he finally achieves an “[understanding of] the British drama and the British actor.”<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>10</sup>
         </xref>The sedative so splits his character that, when he awakens, only his “sentimental side” initially returns, without his “morality,” “common sense,” or “incorrigible Protestant respectability”: “For the first time in my life, I tasted the bliss of having no morals to restrain me from lying, and no sense of reality to restrain me from romancing…. I acted and lied in the most touchingly sympathetic fashion…. Artistically, I was an immense success: morally, I simply had no existence.”<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>11</sup>
         </xref>Shaw describes a zombie state, bereft of “the chill of a moral or intellectual impulse,” in which his “consciousness [became] absolutely fictitious,”<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>12</sup>
         </xref>and equates it to the anesthetic rather than aesthetic effect of actors, managers, and playwrights in British theater. Inveighing against theatrical bathos as a dangerous blend of vapid conformity and blinding romanticism, it is, for Shaw, the responsibility of the critic to rouse patients etherized on a table and endeavor to cultivate a dialectic theater poised for social reform.</p>
      <p>Nonetheless, the cost of what increasingly felt like a quixotic struggle for a mere critic was high. In a November 1897 review titled “On Pleasure Bent,” Shaw views his job as corporeal trauma, concluding that “trials [as a theater critic] have injured my brain.”<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>13</sup>
         </xref>He relates that he has lately “suffered … from seeing Shakespeare butchered to make a cockney's holiday” and determined to have a “real experience of some kind, under conditions, especially as regards fresh air, as unlike those of the stalls as possible” (378, 372). To remedy the toxic, stuffy artificiality of the theater, he heads “into the country, [selects] a dangerous hill, and [rides] down it on a bicycle at full speed in the darkest part of the night” (373, 372–73). When the doctor apologizes for the pain attendant upon stitching up the resulting “excessive openness of [his] countenance,” Shaw proclaims that “to him who has endured points made by actors for nearly three years, the point of a surgeon's darning needle comes as delicious relief” (373). In his review, GBS is unable to resist an opportunity to contrast implicitly the modern urban doctor and health system predicated on the profit motive with the care delivered by an Irish rustic physician possessing an “unperverted consciousness of [a] benevolent and sensible life” (375). He also is concerned that his treatment will irrevocably alter his relationship to his job as a critic:<disp-quote>
            <p>I doubt if I shall ever see a play again without longing for the comparative luxury of that quiet country surgery, with the stillness without broken only by the distant song and throbbing drumbeat of some remote Salvation Army corps, and the needle, with its delicate realism, touching my sensibilities, stitch, stitch, stitch, with an absolute sincerity in the hands of an artist who had actually learned his business and how to do it. (373)</p>
         </disp-quote>When the physician refuses to charge for the services rendered (allegedly when he detects the playwright's ethnicity through his accent), Shaw acknowledges that his seat in the theater is also provided<italic>gratis</italic>but lacking salutary intent:<disp-quote>
            <p>to expect me to feel towards the manager who lacerates my nerves, enfeebles my mind, and destroys my character, as I did towards the physician who healed my body, refreshed my soul, and flattered my vocal accomplishments when I was no more to him than an untimely stranger with an unheard-of black eye, is to dethrone justice and repudiate salvation. Besides, he said it was a mercy I was not killed. Would any manager have been of that opinion? (374)</p>
         </disp-quote>Although Shaw returns from this adventure with renewed indomitable spirit, “[recommending] it confidently for imitation,” he succumbs six months later to feelings of futility (375). In his final piece for the<italic>Saturday Review</italic>titled “Valedictory,” Shaw despairs that, rather than “looking up to [him] as their guide, philosopher, and friend,” theater managers still regard him as “the author of a series of weekly outrages on their profession and their privacy.”<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>14</sup>
         </xref>He is clear that it isn't his temporary convalescence due to an infected foot that condemns him to this maudlin meditation; rather, it is his vegetarianism: “When a man of normal habits is ill, everyone hastens to assure him that he is going to recover. When a vegetarian is ill (which fortunately very seldom happens), everyone assures him that he is going to die, and that they told him so, and that it serves him right…. Ten times a day I am compelled to reflect on my past life, and on the [resulting] prospect of [surviving] three [more] weeks.”<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>15</sup>
         </xref>Going on to admit that he has decided to cease spending his life “fighting a windmill,”<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>16</sup>
         </xref>Shaw puckishly raises the expectation that he will renounce his diet. Instead of giving in to carnivorous pressure, he quits the business of dramatic criticism. In 1900, he would recall the overall septic effect of his years at the<italic>Saturday Review</italic>that “very nearly killed” him, how repeatedly crossing the “fatal threshold of a London playhouse” had caused his “soul [to] become inane and [feed] unnaturally on his body.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>17</sup>
         </xref>The cure, he maintains, came from writing books and plays, and the experience became a crucible through which GBS reanimated his physical and artistic stamina.</p>
      <p>The resonance of Shaw's perspectives on health deepens in his later writings, from<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>(1921) and<italic>The Intelligent Woman's Guide to Socialism and Capitalism</italic>(1928) to<italic>Doctors' Delusions</italic>(1932) and<italic>Farfetched Fables</italic>(1948–50). In them, with an eye toward collective wellness, progressive growth, and enduring fitness, he promulgates interrelated theories of metabiology, socialism, despotism, and evolution. His constellation of superabundant vitality, political and metaphysical sensibilities, and practices of diet, exercise, and dress evokes a Victorian construction of healthiness, understood, according to historian Bruce Haley, as “a state of constitutional growth and development in which the bodily systems and mental faculties interoperate harmoniously under the direct motive power of vital energy or the indirect motive power of the moral will, or both. Its signs are, subjectively recognized, a sense of wholeness and unencumbered capability, and, externally recognized, the production of useful, creative labor.”<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>18</sup>
         </xref>For many at the time,<italic>mens sana in corpore sano</italic>conceptualized the healthy body as a vivarium for intellectual and moral growth while others were more radically materialist in positing happiness and good living as dependent upon the physiological self. In any case, as Haley maintains, the “practice of analogically or metaphorically connecting [spiritual health and bodily health] was habitual in Victorian epistemology[,] … the ideal of personal health a way of grasping the proper relation between the self as a whole … and the unity of moral and physical laws which transcend the self.”<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>19</sup>
         </xref>If consistent with their yoking of vivacity, integrity, and volition, Shaw flipped the hierarchy that privileged the corporeal, figuring the intellectual will as the unifying and driving force in health; in his words, “it is the mind that makes the body and not the body the mind.”<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>20</sup>
         </xref>Malaise indicated deficiencies of purpose and dedication as well as a failure of visionary scope; “the moment a man begins to think about himself,” Shaw claimed, “he's an invalid [just] as the moment he thinks about his conscience, he's a scoundrel.”<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>21</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Along the same lines, in the preface to<italic>Man and Superman</italic>, he draws a distinction between two states of corporeal infirmity. The first, what he calls “the true joy of life,” results from “the being used for a purpose recognized by yourself as a mighty one; the being thoroughly worn out before you are thrown on the scrap heap, the being a force of nature.” The second is engendered by a failure of will and perspective, producing “a feverish selfish little clod of ailments and grievances, complaining that the world will not devote itself to making you happy.”<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>22</sup>
         </xref>Scholars and biographers have taken both views of Shaw. Countless testimonies of friends and acquaintances as well as innumerable pronouncements by GBS himself laud the extraordinary vibrancy of the “active young revolutionist” following his typical schedule of prolific writing and speech giving.<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>23</sup>
         </xref>At the same time, Shaw's private diaries are replete with meticulous physiological self-examination, documenting his crippling headaches as well as myriad illnesses, injuries, changes in weight and appetite, and suspected symptoms. Robert Brustein attributes “a kind of Swiftian disgust at the human body and its functions” to the playwright, while Sally Peters pathologizes his interest in health, arguing its origin in latent psychosis, specifically an obsessive fear of contagion.<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>24</sup>
         </xref>His commitment to vegetarianism, teetotalism, and Jaegerism, she argues, was founded as much upon hygienic paranoia as moral principle: “Fueled by a “desperate revulsion from body and biology[,] … Shaw's was an ever-lasting defense against dirt, poison, and contamination[,] whatever symbolized to him the form-destroying potencies of existence.”<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>25</sup>
         </xref>In any case, the vexed body, on its way to evolutionary elimination, assiduously preoccupied Shaw, and matters of personal and public wellness remained an idée fixe until the end of his life.</p>
      <p>As the decades pass, many of Shaw's antiscientific views, having ossified to a large degree in the 1880s, look increasingly eccentric and seem as mired in superstitious delusion as he claimed the field was. Peters imagines Shaw's “dazzling display of partial truths [isolating] him in a moated tower from which he staged offensive forays against the medical world.”<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>26</sup>
         </xref>If his vehement rejection of germ theory and his sartorial preferences have proven as misguided as his beliefs on authoritarianism and eugenics, other commitments have fared better. Vegetarianism, for instance, is a common lifestyle choice nowadays, and Shaw enjoys a certain prominence in the history of the practice as well as on websites and blogs devoted to it. Characterizing the Edwardian medical system in the preface to<italic>Doctor's Dilemma</italic>as a “murderous absurdity,” he lived long enough to see the institution of the National Health Service in 1948, although still argued for a greater lay presence within its administration of physician licensing and training. In the twenty-first century, amid protracted health care debate in both the United States and the United Kingdom, proposed government regulation of medical apps on smartphones and tablets, and alarming physiological trends including skyrocketing obesity rates, many of Shaw's observations and positions speak almost as urgently to our time as they did to his.</p>
      <p>Discussions of health these days, in both popular and academic discourse, are increasingly turning toward the concept of sustainability. Indeed, interdisciplinary academic programs as well as institutes and foundations dedicated to “sustainability studies” have sprung up around the world, ambitiously seeking to connect global politics, economics, and environmentalism. They proceed from the assumption that the capacity to endure demands a long-range, integrated vision of social justice, economic equity, and ecological health, necessitating cooperation among individuals in the humanities, the sciences, and corporate industry. A recent essay in<italic>American Literary History</italic>entreats ecocritics to abjure the “retreat to the bower, the plough, or the graduate seminar, issuing the same familiar jeremiads against science and industrial capitalism, [in] recognition that sustainability studies in the humanities is the natural companion of sustainability science, not its antagonist.”<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>27</sup>
         </xref>While he is guilty at times of stultifying pigheadedness about science, considering the ecological grounding of his wide-view epidemiology, Shaw certainly thought in these epic terms and sought solutions to those very challenges. From<italic>Major Barbara</italic>to<italic>Farfetched Fables</italic>, Shaw displays his attentiveness to a program of health in which scientists, industrialists, political leaders, and scholars commit to (repurposing Andrew Undershaft's line) “looking after the drainage.”</p>
      <p>As Michel Pharand's bibliography in this issue of SHAW reminds us, Shaw's wellness practices and his engagement with health debates, medical theory and institutional practice, and quackery in all of its forms over the course of his lifetime have been documented extensively by biographers, scholars, reporters, critics, friends, and of course GBS himself. In order to avoid mere reiteration of Shaw's own views and of that earlier work on the topic, “health” was conceived for this issue of<italic>SHAW</italic>in deliberately broad terms, and its elasticity as an organizing conceit has enabled us to collect essays that employ a variety of critical approaches and provide insight on sometimes unexpected topics. The mixture of senior, midlevel, and emerging scholars among the contributors underscores the ongoing salubriousness of Shaw's corpus and all extend the scholarly conversation in productive directions, discovering new pockets of biographical and historical inquiry and continuing to develop innovative contexts within which his creative work speaks in new ways. Considering the steady proliferation of Shaviana and the continued myriad revivals of his plays on international stages, Shaw studies is in fine fettle.</p>
      <p>The issue begins with Bernard Dukore's “Environmental Shaw,” a pioneering piece that examines Shaw's views on a range of “green” topics, from pollution to clean air to alternative energy. Analyzing the degree to which Shaw is a part of nascent bionomic thought and activism at the time and how much he is formulating a distinctive vision that sets him ahead of the curve, Dukore persuasively positions Shaw as an environmentalist of sorts and thus raises a new set of questions about the ecology of his thinking and writing and its dialogue with public environmental discourse, then and now. In that sense, the essay inaugurates a novel line of inquiry and looks forward to future scholarship that will articulate ecocritical readings of individual plays and provide closer scrutiny of the ways in which Shaw's environmentalism intersected with (among other things) his socialism and feminism. Immediately following this introduction is a reproduction from<italic>The Chicagoan</italic>(1926–35), the windy city's brief counter-weekly to the<italic>New Yorker</italic>. Photographer A. George Miller and artist Ben Schafer collaborated three times for the magazine in the early 1930s, supplying uniquely rendered visual profiles of famous people. Page 28 of the 1 June 1934 issue features a series of four of their photographs, each a shadow caricature created from repurposed ordinary, even abject objects. The “personalities photographed in the hard light of truth” are Walter Winchell, Primo Carnera (world heavyweight boxing champion 1933–34), John Barrymore, and GBS. The latter's, composed from “spinach and other greenage,” is titled “George Bernard Shaw, Vegetarian.” The combination of a “green” artist working in recycled materials and a literally “green” GBS struck me as a very apt visual supplement to Dukore's essay.</p>
      <p>The volume's next two essays address issues of physiology and representation, albeit in very different ways. In “The Playwright's Perplexity: Constitution, Contagion, and Consumption in<italic>The Doctor's Dilemma</italic>,” Alexis Soloski traces Shaw's ambivalence toward the figure of the stage consumptive. Through Louis Dubedat, she argues, the play “somewhat in spite of itself” endorses the “conventional, sentimental narrative of the typical fictional tubercular” even as it “succeeds as a satire of medics and morals.” Sonya Freeman Loftis's “The Superman on the Spectrum: Shaw's Autistic Characters and the Neurodiversity Movement” assesses the efficacy of the provocative appropriation of Shaw by a contemporary movement, anxious to reify a distinctive public identity and history while at the same time avoid reaffirming stereotypical perceptions and anachronistic spin-doctoring. Examining Saint Joan and Henry Higgins as characters on the spectrum, her essay seeks to illuminate what is interpretively at stake within the plays they inhabit and the extrapolative implications of reading<italic>through</italic>those characters to produce an “Autistic Shaw.” (As a side note, surely underscoring the fecundity of Shaw studies, these two contributors each had a first child during the gestation of this<italic>SHAW</italic>issue. The Life Force does not believe in mere coincidence.)</p>
      <p>Alice McEwan, in “The ‘Plumber-Philosopher’: Shaw's Discourse on Domestic Sanitation,” synthesizes Shaw's chronic difficulties with the plumbing at Shaw's Corner, the Shaws' country home in the village of Ayot St. Lawrence, with his reformist views on public health and the “wider implications of how sanitation might link civilization and hygiene to aesthetics.” While connections can be drawn between the playwright and the avant-garde theories of modernist architects, Shaw (as usual) emerges in McEwan's essay with a distinctive vision in which “modern sanitary arrangements … have the power to operate as a cultural trope, revealing truths about how we attempt to organize ‘health’ and manage our bodies in modern society.”</p>
      <p>Other contributors set out to explore the playwright's more expansive visions of health and the interconnection of corporeal and spiritual wellness. “I also expect a doctor to be an evolutionist,” Shaw wrote in<italic>Doctors' Delusions</italic>, and referred anyone for whom his views on medical practitioners were unclear to “read the preface to [his]<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>until it<italic>is</italic>clear.”<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>28</sup>
         </xref>Taking such a cue in a slightly different direction with “An Imperfect Butlerite: Aging and Embodiment in<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>,” Glenn Clifton provides an overview of the playwright's understanding of the body within the larger context of evolution, set against the backdrop of Samuel Butler's and Henri Bergson's notions on both topics. Doing so enables him to track the body's vexed abjection through the entire cycle, arguing that Shaw's asomatous fantasizing is both apprehensive about mortality and ethically humane.</p>
      <p>The two essays that follow situate their gaze on Shaw's cosmology. Jay Tunney's moving, evocative piece, “The Spiritual Shaw,” again affirms the profundity of Shaw's close relationship with his father, Gene. The extraordinary experience on the island of Brioni was a powerful moment in Shaw's ongoing reflection about the intersection of the physical and metaphysical, manifested (among other places) in his keenness for boxing. Witnessing Polly Tunney's painful and near-fatal appendicitis attack, Gene's faith, and the miraculous arrival of two medical saviors, Shaw was deeply affected by what Tunney describes as the “simplicity and enormity of the circumstance,” and thereafter “prayer broadened his definition of the human spirit.” With the reputed interconnection between health and hope as his starting point, Howard Ira Einsohn also explores Shaw's moral and religious philosophy in “Bernard Shaw and Paul Ricoeur: Emissaries of Hope, Faith, and Wellness.” Einsohn's commentary traces convergences in the thinking of both figures to articulate how Shaw's tragic-optimism acts as “his equilibrium, his wellness, in a world wildly out of kilter.”</p>
      <p>Finally, around the turn of the seventeenth century, the meaning of the word “health” expanded to include the sense of a toast imbibed in someone's honor. In that spirit, rather unusually, the issue ends with a late veteran Shavian, Sidney Albert, speaking to us from the great beyond, correcting some previous misconceptions regarding the Shaw/Salvation Army relationship. The indefatigable Albert provides us with original insight into the decidedly musical origins of<italic>Major Barbara</italic>.</p>
      <p>One of my favorite anecdotes comes from Bertrand Russell, whose afternoon ride in the country with Shaw one day ended in a terrific collision that permanently disabled his bicycle but left the playwright's two-wheeler relatively unscathed. Forced to take the slow train back home alone, Russell recalled that “at every station[,] Shaw with his bicycle appeared on the platform, put his head in the carriage and jeered.” While the philosopher muses that Shaw probably “regarded the whole incident as proof of the virtues of vegetarianism,”<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>29</sup>
         </xref>for me, the story is emblematic of how, as we move forward and arrive at each new juncture in intra- and international discussions of matters of health, politics, technology, economics, and humanity, we discover that Shaw is already there, insistently provoking us with just how far Shavian thought can reach.</p>
      <fig id="f1" position="float">
         <label>Fig. 1</label>
         <caption>
            <p>
               <italic>Chicagoan</italic>, 1 June 1934, 28. Courtesy of Quigley Publishing Company, a division of QP Media, Inc.</p>
         </caption>
         <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                  xlink:href="shaw.34.1.0001-f01.tif"/>
      </fig>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref>
            <mixed-citation>Thank you to everyone who worked hard to produce this issue of<italic>SHAW</italic>, especially Michel Pharand, the contributors, the editorial board, Julie Lambert, the staff at Penn State University Press, and Jean Reynolds.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Archibald Henderson,<italic>George Bernard Shaw: His Life and Works</italic>(Cincinnati, OH: Stewart &amp; Kidd, 1911), 493.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 503–4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>
               <italic>Vegetarian</italic>, 13 February 1897, 14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Farfetched Fables</italic>in<italic>Complete Plays with Prefaces</italic>, vol. 6 (New York: Dodd, Mead, 1963), 455–56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>T. Carlo Matos,<italic>Ibsen's Foreign Contagion: Henrik Ibsen, Arthur Wing Pinero, and Modernism on the London Stage, 1890–1900</italic>(Palo Alto, CA: Academica Press, 2012), 1.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Henry IV,” in<italic>Dramatic Opinions and Essays</italic>(New York: Brentano's, 1928), 6:423. All further references are to this edition and are given parenthetically in the text.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Vegetarian and Arboreal,” in<italic>Dramatic Opinions and Essays</italic>, 2:352. All further references are to this edition and are given parenthetically in the text.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Quoted in<italic>Shaw: Interviews and Recollections</italic>, ed. A. M. Gibbs (Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1990), 401. Later, in<italic>Back to Methuselah</italic>, Shaw, through Franklyn Barnabas, will trace the genealogy of war back indirectly to Cain's shocked abhorrence of Abel's meaty dietary habits.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gibbs,<italic>Shaw</italic>, 402.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “G.B.S. Vivisected,” in<italic>Our Theatres in the Nineties</italic>(London: Constable, 1948), 3:380.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 3:381–82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 3:383.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “On Pleasure Bent,” in<italic>Dramatic Opinions and Essays</italic>, 7:372. All further references are to this edition and are given parenthetically in the text.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw, “Valedictory,” in<italic>Our Theatres in the Nineties</italic>, 3:385.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r015">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 3:386.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r016">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 3:384.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r017">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Three Plays for Puritans</italic>(London: Penguin, 1946). 7–8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r018">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bruce Haley,<italic>The Healthy Body and Victorian Culture</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1978), 21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r019">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 253, 255.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r020">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Everybody's Political What's What?</italic>(London: Constable, 1944), 247.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r021">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“Vegetarian: An Interview by Leonard Henslowe,”<italic>Good Housekeeping</italic>45, no. 4 (4 October 1907): 372.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r022">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Man and Superman: A Comedy and a Philosophy</italic>(Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1977), 32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r023">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Shaw,<italic>Three Plays for Puritans</italic>, 7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r024">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Robert Brustein,<italic>The Theatre of Revolt: Studies in Modern Drama from Ibsen to Genet</italic>(Chicago: Ivan R. Dee, 1991), 203.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r025">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sally Peters,<italic>Bernard Shaw: The Ascent of the Superman</italic>(New Haven: Yale University Press, 1996), 73, 70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r026">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r027">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gillen D'Arcy Wood, “What Is Sustainability Studies?,”<italic>American Literary History</italic>24, no. 1 (Spring 2012): 13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r028">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Shaw,<italic>Doctors' Delusions</italic>, in<italic>The Collected Works of Bernard Shaw</italic>(New York: Wm. H. Wise, 1932), 22:xiv.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r029">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gibbs,<italic>Shaw</italic>, 278.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
