<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">jpubladmiresethe</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100869</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory: J-PART</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">10531858</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14779803</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23321342</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Hermeneutic Approach to Explaining and Understanding Public Controversies</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Raul P.</given-names>
                  <surname>Lejano</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Ching</given-names>
                  <surname>Leong</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>22</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23319479</issue-id>
         <fpage>793</fpage>
         <lpage>814</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory, Inc.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:role="external-fulltext-any"
                   xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jopart/mus001"
                   xlink:title="an external site"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Notwithstanding the growing use of interpretive analysis in public administration and policy research, its fullest potential for evaluating intractable public conflict has yet to be tapped. We develop a mode of narrative analysis, partly based upon Paul Ricoeur's hermeneutics, that shows promise for analyzing public disputes. We illustrate this with a case study in Los Angeles involving a contentious proposal to inject recycled wastewater into the city's water supply. The analysis reveals that, by representing opposing interests with a simplistic narrative, the water industry's response has been superfluous. The latter assumes that impasse simply results from the public's lack of information, the logical response being an information dissemination campaign. We employ a hermeneutic approach to reveal a set of persistent issues that project proponents have hitherto failed to address. By respecting the inherent plurivocity and intertextuality of narrative, hermeneutics provides new inroads into controversial public issues. We close the discussion with implications for practice.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d4120e155a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d4120e162" publication-type="other">
Leong 2010</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="d4120e178a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e182" publication-type="other">
Agranoff, Robert, and Michael McGuire. 2003. Collaborative public management: New strategies for
local governments. Washington, DC: Georgetown Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e192a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e196" publication-type="other">
Bal, Mieke. 2009. Narratology: Introduction to the theory of narrative, 3rd ed. Toronto, Canada: Univ. of
Toronto Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e206a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e210" publication-type="other">
Balfour, Danny L., and William Mesaros. 1994. Connecting the local narratives: Public administration as
a hermeneutic science. Public Administration Review 54:559-64.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e220a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e224" publication-type="other">
Ball, William. 1995. A pragmatic framework for the evaluation of policy arguments. Policy Studies
Review 14:3—24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e235a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e239" publication-type="other">
Barthes, Roland. 1974. S/Z. Translated by Richard Miller. New York, NY: Noonday.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e250" publication-type="other">
Barthes, Roland, and Lionel Duisit. 1975. An introduction to the structural analysis of narrative. New
Literary History 6:237—72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e260a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e264" publication-type="other">
Bennett, W. Lance, and Martha S. Feldman. 1981. Reconstructing reality in the courtroom. London, UK:
Tavistock Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e274a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e278" publication-type="other">
Berger, Peter L., and Thomas Luckmann. 1966. The social construction of reality. New York, NY:
Random House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e288a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e292" publication-type="other">
Blankstein, Andrew. 2000. County to test water for chromium 6. The Los Angeles Times, September 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e299a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e303" publication-type="other">
Boje, David M. 1991. The storytelling organization: A study of story performance in an office-supply firm.
Administrative Science Quarterly 36:106-26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e314a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e318" publication-type="other">
Bourdieu, Pierre. 1977. Outline of a theory of practice. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e325a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e329" publication-type="other">
Boyce, Mary E. 1996. Organizational story and storytelling: A critical review. Journal of Organizational
Change Management 9:5—26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e339a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e343" publication-type="other">
Bruner, Jerome S. 1990. Acts of meaning. Cambridge: Harvard Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e350a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e354" publication-type="other">
Cavanaugh, Kerry. 2004. OC takes up plan flushed by L.A. Los Angeles Daily News, October 23.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e361a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e365" publication-type="other">
—. 2008a. Angelenos slow to swallow purified sewage. Los Angeles Daily News, June 22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e372a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e376" publication-type="other">
—. 2008b. L.A. may flush old fears of toilet to tap. Los Angeles Daily News, June 22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e384a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e388" publication-type="other">
Cooke, Bill and Uma Kothari, eds. 2006. Participation: The new tyranny? London, UK: Zed Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e395a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e399" publication-type="other">
Crotty, Michael. 1998. The foundations of social research: Meaning and perspective in the research
process. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e413" publication-type="other">
Czarniawska-Joerges, Barbara. 1998. A narrative approach to organization studies. Thousand Oaks, CA:
SAGE Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e423a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e427" publication-type="other">
Day, Diane. 1997. Citizen participation in the planning process: An essentially contested concept? Journal
of Planning Literature 11:421—34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e437a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e441" publication-type="other">
Denzin, Norman K., and Yvonna S. Lincoln 1994. Handbook of qualitative research. Thousand Oaks, CA:
SAGE Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e451a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e455" publication-type="other">
Douglas, Mary. 1966. Purity and danger: An analysis of the concepts ofpollution and taboo. London, UK:
Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e466a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e470" publication-type="other">
Dryzek, John. 1982. Policy analysis as a hermeneutic activity. Policy Sciences 14:309-29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e477a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e481" publication-type="other">
Editorial Staff. Editorial swamp thing city hall's plans to flood the sepulveda basin are an insult to the
valley. 2001. Los Angeles Daily News, July 19.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e491a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e495" publication-type="other">
Feldman, Martha S., Anne Khademian, and Kathryn S. Quick. 2009. Ways of knowing: Inclusive
management, and promoting democratic engagement: Introduction to the special issue. International
Public Management Journal 12:123—36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e508a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e512" publication-type="other">
Feldman, Martha S., Kaj Sköldberg, Ruth Nicole Brown, and Debra Horner. 2004. Making sense of stories:
A rhetorical approach to narrative analysis. Journal of Public Administration Research Theory
14:147-70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e525a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e529" publication-type="other">
Feldman, Martha S., and Kathryn S. Quick. 2009. Generating resources and energizing
frameworks through inclusive public management. International Public Management Journal
12:137-71.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e542a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e546" publication-type="other">
Fischer, Frank. 2003. Reframing public policy: Discursive polities and deliberative practices. Oxford, NY :
Oxford Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e557a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e561" publication-type="other">
Fischer, Frank, and John Forester. 1993. The argumentative turn in policy analysis. Durham, NC: Duke
Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e571a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e575" publication-type="other">
Fisher, Walter. 1994. Narrative rationality and the logic of scientific discourse. Argumentation 8:21—32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e582a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e586" publication-type="other">
Forester, John. 1999. The deliberative practitioner: Encouraging participatory planning processes.
Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e596a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e600" publication-type="other">
—. 2008. Policy analysis as critical listening. Goodin, R., M. Rein, and R. Moran, eds. 2008. Oxford
handbook ofpublic policy. Oxford, NY : Oxford Univ. Pres.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e610a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e614" publication-type="other">
Frege, Gottlob. 1948. Sense and reference. The Philosophical Review 57:209-30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e621a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e625" publication-type="other">
Gadamer, Hans G. 1975. Truth and method, 2nd ed. London, UK: Sheed and Ward.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e633a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e637" publication-type="other">
Garvey, Megan. 1998. Issue of racial motivation raised in secession forum. The Los Angeles Times, April
19. http://articles.latimes.com/1998/apr/19/local/me-40913 (accessed April 28, 2011).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e647a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e651" publication-type="other">
Geertz, Clifford. 1973. The interpretation of cultures. New York, NY: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e658a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e662" publication-type="other">
Getzlaff, J. A. 2000. L.A. to serve toilet water. Salon, May 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e669a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e673" publication-type="other">
Glick, Deanna. 2008. The distance between toilet and tap. Official, March/April.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e680a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e684" publication-type="other">
Goldberg, Orith. 2000. DWP session allays fears. Los Angeles Daily News, June 8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e691a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e695" publication-type="other">
Goldstein, Bruce E. 2010. Epistemic mediation: Aligning expertise across boundaries within an
Endangered Species Habitat Conservation Plan. Planning Theory and Practice 11:523-47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e706a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e710" publication-type="other">
Gunderson, Jeff. 2008. The language of water. WE&amp;T Magazine 20:July, http://www.wef.org/publica-
tions/page_wet.aspx?id=4423&amp;page=news (accessed April 28, 2011).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e720a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e724" publication-type="other">
Hajer, Maarten. 1993. Discourse coalitions and the institutionalization of practice: The case of acid
rain in Great Britain. In The argumentative turn in policy analysis and planning, ed. F. Fischer
and J. Forester, 43—76. Durham, NC: Duke Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e737a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e741" publication-type="other">
Hajer, Maarten, Wagenaar, H., eds. 2003. Deliberative policy analysis: Understanding governance in the
network society. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e751a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e755" publication-type="other">
Hampton, Greg. 2009. Narrative policy analysis and the integration of public involvement in decision
making. Policy Sciences 42:227-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e765a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e769" publication-type="other">
Healey, Patsy. 1993. Planning through debate: The communicative turn in planning theory. In The
argumentative turn in policy analysis and planning, ed. F. Fischer and J. Forester, 233—53. Durham,
NC: Duke Univ.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e782a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e786" publication-type="other">
Hiestand, Jesse. 1999. Y2K test causes stink; Computer sends sewage into park. Los Angeles Daily News,
June 18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e797a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e801" publication-type="other">
Hummel, Ralph. 1991. Stories managers tell: Why they are as valid as science. Public Administration
Review 51:31-4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e811a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e815" publication-type="other">
Innes, Judith E., and David E. Booher. 2010. Planning with complexity: An introduction to collaborative
rationality for public policy. New York, NY: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e825a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e829" publication-type="other">
Irvin, Renée, and John Stansbury. 2004. Citizen participation in decision making: Is it worth the effort?
Public Administration Review 64:55—65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e843" publication-type="other">
Jameson, Fredde. 1984. The politics of theory: Ideological positions in the postmodernism debate. New
German Critique 33:53—65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e853a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e857" publication-type="other">
Kaplan, Thomas. 1986. The narrative structure of policy analysis. Journal of Policy Analysis and
Management 5:761—78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e867a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e871" publication-type="other">
Kristeva, Julia. 1980. Desire in language: A semiotic approach to literature and art. New York, NY:
Columbia Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e882a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e886" publication-type="other">
Latour, Bruno. 2005. Reassembling the social: An introduction to actor-network-theory. Oxford, NY:
Oxford Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e896a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e900" publication-type="other">
Lazarova, Valentina, Bruno B. Levine, Jacobo Sack, Giovanni Cirelli, Herbert Muntrau, Miguel Salgot,
and Francois Brissaud. 2001. Role of water reuse for enhancing integrated water management in
Europe and Mediterranean countries. Water Science and Technology 43 (10): 25—33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e913a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e917" publication-type="other">
Lejano, Raul P. 2006. Frameworks for policy analysis: Merging text and context. New York, NY:
Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e927a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e931" publication-type="other">
Lejano, Raul P., and Anne Taufen Wessells. 2006. Community and economic development: Seeking
common ground in discourse and in practice. Urban Studies 43:1469-89.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e941a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e945" publication-type="other">
Los Angeles Department of Water and Power (LADWP). 2005. 2005 Urban water management plan. Los
Angeles, CA: Department of Water and Power.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e955a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e959" publication-type="other">
Lyotard, Jean-Francois. 1979. The postmodern condition: A report on knowledge. Minneapolis, MN: Univ.
of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e970a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e974" publication-type="other">
Maguire, Lynn A., and E. Allan Lind. 2003. Public participation in environmental decisions: Stakeholders,
authorities and procedural justice. International Journal of Global Environmental Issues 3:133—48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e984a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e988" publication-type="other">
Margolis, Jude. 2007. Demand safe water! The Beachwood Voice, Brochure No. 1, August 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e995a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e999" publication-type="other">
Martin, Joanne. 1982. Stories and scripts in organizational settings. In Cognitive social psychology, ed. A.
Hasdorf and A. Isen, 225-305. New York, NY: Elsevier—North Holland.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1009a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1013" publication-type="other">
Miller, G. Wade. 2006. Integrated concepts in water reuse: Managing global water needs. Desalination
187:65-75.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1023a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1027" publication-type="other">
National Research Council. 1998. Issues in potable reuse: The viability of augmenting drinking water
supplies with reclaimed water. Committee to Evaluate the Viability of Augmenting Potable Water
Supplies with Reclaimed Water. Washington, DC: National Academy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1040a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1044" publication-type="other">
Nussbaum, Martha. 1990. Love's knowledge: Essays on philosophy and literature. New York, NY : Oxford
Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1055a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1059" publication-type="other">
Oppenheimer, Steven. 2007. Augmenting drinking water with reclaimed water. The Beachwood Voice,
Brochure No. 1, August 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1069a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1073" publication-type="other">
Ospina, Sonia M., and Jennifer Dodge. 2005. It's about time: Catching method up to meaning—The
usefulness of narrative inquiry in public administration research. Public Administration Review
65:143-57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1086a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1090" publication-type="other">
Palmer, Richard E. 1969. Hermeneutics. Evanston, IL: Northwestern Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1097a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1101" publication-type="other">
Patriotta, Gerardo. 2003. Sensemaking on the shop floor: Narratives of knowledge in organizations.
Journal of Management Studies 40:349-76.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1111a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1115" publication-type="other">
Quick, Kathryn S., and Martha S. Feldman. 2009. Generating resources and energizing frameworks
through inclusive public management. Journal of Planning Education and Research 31:272—90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1125a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1129" publication-type="other">
—. 2011. Distinguishing inclusion and participation. Journal of Planning Education and Research.
31:272-90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1140a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1144" publication-type="other">
Rabinow, Paul, and William M. Sullivan. 1979. The interpretive turn: Emergence of an approach. In
Interpretive social science: A reader, ed. Paul Rabinow and William M. Sullivan, 1—21. Los
Angeles, CA: Univ. of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1157a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1161" publication-type="other">
—. 1987. The interpretive turn: A second look. Rabinow, Paul and William M. Sullivan, eds. 1987.
Interpretive social science: A second look, 2nd ed., Lo Angeles, CA: Univ. of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1171a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1175" publication-type="other">
Recycled Water Task Force. 2007. Policy recommendations for the county of Los Angeles Board of
Supervisors. Paper for the County of Los Angeles Board of Supervisors, January 30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1185a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1189" publication-type="other">
Reuters. 2000. Californians may soon drink recycled toilet water. Reuters Wire Agency, April 18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1196a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1200" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1974. The conflict of interpretations. Edited by Don Ihde. Translated by Kathleen
Mclaughlin. Evanston, IL: Northwestern Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1210a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1214" publication-type="other">
—. 1976. Interpretation theory: Discourse and the surplus of meaning. Fort Worth, TX: Christian
Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1225a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1229" publication-type="other">
—. 1981. Hermeneutics and the human sciences: Essays on language, action and interpretation.
Edited and translated by John B. Thompson. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1239a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1243" publication-type="other">
—. 1984. Time and narrative. Volume 1. Trans. Kathleen McLaughlin and David Pellauer. Chicago,
IL: Univ. of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1253a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1257" publication-type="other">
—. 1991. On interpretation. Ricoeur, Paul, ed. 1991. From text to action: Essays in hermeneutics, II.
Evanston, IL: Northwestern Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1267a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1271" publication-type="other">
Roberts, Nancy. 2004. Public deliberation in an age of direct citizen participation. Public Administration
Review 34:315-352.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1281a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1285" publication-type="other">
Roe, Emery M. 1989. Narrative analysis for the policy analyst: A case study of the 1980-1982 medfly
controversy in California. Journal of Policy Analysis and Management 8:251—73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1295a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1299" publication-type="other">
—. 1994. Narrative policy analysis: Theory and practice. Durham, NC: Duke Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1307a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1311" publication-type="other">
Rowe, Gene, and Lynn J. Frewer. 2005. A typology of public engagement mechanisms. Science Tech-
nology &amp; Human Values 30:251—90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1321a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1325" publication-type="other">
Ryan, Marie-Laure. 2007. Toward a definition of narrative. In The Cambridge companion to narrative, ed.
David Herman, 22—35. Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1335a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1339" publication-type="other">
Saussure, Ferdinand de. 1916. Cours de linguistique générale, ed. C. Bally and A. Sechehaye, with the
collaboration of A. Riedlinger, Lausanne and Paris: Payot; trans. W. Baskin, Course in general
linguistics, Glasgow: Fontana/Collins, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1352a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1356" publication-type="other">
Schmidt, Mary R. 1994. Grout: Alternative kinds of knowledge and why they are ignored. In Research
in public administration: Reflections on theory and practice, ed. Jay D. White and Guy B. Adams,
213-24. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1369a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1373" publication-type="other">
Schön, Donald. 1983. The reflective practitioner. New York, NY: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1380a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1384" publication-type="other">
Schräm, Sanford F., and Philip T. Neisser. 1997. Tales of the state: Narrative in contemporary U. S.
politics and public policy. Lanham, MD: Rowman and Littlefield.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1395a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1399" publication-type="other">
Silver, Gerald. 2010. Sepulveda Basin Parkland eyed for treatment plant. Sherman Oaks Studio City
Encino News April.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1413" publication-type="other">
Sköldberg, Kaj. 1994. Tales of change: Public administration reform and narrative mode. Organization
Science 5:219-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1423a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1427" publication-type="other">
Star Ledger, The. 2000. Californians aren't swallowing water recycling plan. The Star Ledger, April 24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1434a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1438" publication-type="other">
Stone, Deborah A. 1997. Policy paradox: The art of policy decision making. New York, NY: W. W.
Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1448a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1452" publication-type="other">
Susskind, Lawrence, McKearnan Sarah, and Jennifer Thomas-Larmer, eds. 1999. The consensus building
handbook: A comprehensive guide to reaching agreement. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1462a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1466" publication-type="other">
Van Wagoner, William T. 2000. East Valley Water Recycling Project challenges of implementation.
Paper presented at the Water Environment Federation® Technical Exhibition and Conference
(WEFTEC®), Session 51 through Session 60, Anaheim, CA, January 1.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1480a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1484" publication-type="other">
Weick, Karl E. 1995. Sensemaking in organizations. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1491a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1495" publication-type="other">
Yanow, Dvora. 1992. Silences in public policy disclosure: Organizational and policy myths. Journal of
Public Administration Research and Theory 2:399-423.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d4120e1505a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d4120e1509" publication-type="other">
—. 2007. Interpretation in policy analysis: On methods and practice. Critical Policy Studies
1:110-22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
