<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmodernhistory</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Modern History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222801</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375358</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3874478</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/505801</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JMH780203</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Contemporary Issues in Historical Perspective</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Mausoleum of Georgi Dimitrov as<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Todorova</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of Illinois at Urbana‐Champaign</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>June 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>78</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>jmh.2006.78.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>377</fpage>
         <lpage>411</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 by The University of Chicago.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/505801"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Reminiscence</title>
         <p>“Years ago” (the formula that best introduces “memory”) I used to meet my friends at choice locations in Sofia. A meeting place reserved for one of my best friends was the space between “our Goethe and Schiller”: that was what we called the huge bronze statues of Khristo and Evlogi Georgievi, two wealthy nineteenth‐century merchants whose endowment provided the basis for building Sofia University—my alma mater—and who today are comfortably seated on either side of the main entrance. The statues' name was our idiosyncratic designator. The problem is that my friend later decided that everything before 1989 would be encompassed in her personal amnesia; in her words, “I don't remember anything before that.” And while in my mind I still call the two bronze giants “our Goethe and Schiller,” I cannot use this any longer as a designator: its function of denoting a common space for two minds has been dispelled. I still meet people there, but we meet between “the brothers Georgievi.” So, the question arises: does my earlier site exist? Physically, of course, it does, but its significance is completely different now. For all practical purposes “our Goethe and Schiller” have disappeared, although Khristo and Evlogi Georgievi are still there (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg1">fig. 1</xref>).<fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg1" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 1.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>The University of Sofia with the statues of the brothers Georgievi</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg1"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>Another preferred location was the pharmacy at the corner of my own San‐Stefano Street and the Bridge of Eagles. The pharmacy no longer exists; it has been transformed into a store for so‐so women's clothes with the flashy name “Aggression.” Yet there is some vestige of the pharmacy: the huge letters<italic>PHARAMACIE</italic>have not been taken off the building. I still easily meet friends there. The ones who remember the original store wink with complicity; the others need some explanation, but then they are helped by the physical trace of the site.</p>
         <p>The last location I used as a meeting place was the mausoleum of Georgi Dimitrov. I did not use it often since I did not live nearby, but it was nonetheless my usual marker for the space in the center of town. In the summer of 1999 the mausoleum was blown up, and today its blank space serves in regular succession as a garden, a summer opera stage, and a location for stalls for the<italic>Bierfest</italic>(the local version of the<italic>Oktoberfest</italic>beer drinking festival, which happens at unpredictable times of the year in Sofia). The square between the mausoleum and the old king's palace (now housing the National Gallery) was formerly called “September 9” commemorating the government takeover in 1944; now it has been duly renamed “Battenberg Square,” in honor of Bulgaria's first prince after 1878, the German Alexander Battenberg. There is no physical artifact in place where the mausoleum once stood, nor is there any sign to remind passersby of its long presence. Yet, in a curious way, the mausoleum still exists, and the joking “Let's meet at / in front of / behind the mausoleum” needs no explanation: even the younger generation knows its ghostly location. It seems to be still there—no longer as a site of historical memory but still as a marker for everyday orientation. To paraphrase Derrida, it is “the presence of an absence.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Sites of Memory</title>
         <p>All three locations can literally be described as places of memory. When Pierre Nora introduced his notion of<italic>lieu de mémoire,</italic>he probably did not expect that it would become a catchphrase. It is variously rendered in English as a site, place, or realm of memory, and it is used and misused, although not nearly as much as “imagined communities” or “orientalism.” As happens with many French intellectual products, the transmission of Nora's work has resulted in its removal from its local context: it has been universalized and rendered into abstract theory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>In its original inception, the grand opus of Nora and his team of 120 leading French historians was conceived as a huge historiographical response to the crisis of French national identity two centuries after its most defining event: the French Revolution.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>Nora and his colleagues set themselves the task of helping construe French national memory for the contemporary age, at a time when the Revolution no longer resonated as its central event and when there were broader prospects to be uncovered and recovered from the more distant past. It was in this context that Nora's team began locating sites of memory where the French collective identity had materialized over time.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>
         </p>
         <p>These sites formed an exhaustive inventory of architectural and textual artifacts: monuments and shrines, histories and textbooks, museums and archives. In Nora's words: “It is no longer genesis we seek but rather the deciphering of who we are in light of who we are no longer.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>This situates the whole project squarely at the intersection of two types of historiographies: the traditional (or modern) nineteenth‐century positivist historiography, with its obsession with origins and the national telos, and deconstructivist postmodern historiography. In Nora's reading, in modern historiography there is an organic link between inwardly experienced values and the places of their external commemoration. This link has been broken in the postmodern period. Nora maintains, therefore, that a shift has occurred from a kind of natural collective memory to a self‐conscious, uninspired, and rather mechanistic activity of preserving memory. He posits a transformation from sites of internalized, social collective memory (<italic>milieux de mémoire</italic>) to fixed, externalized locations (<italic>lieux de mémoire</italic>). For the postmodern historian, “history ceases to be a mnemonic reconstruction and becomes instead an archaeological deconstruction.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>
         </p>
         <p>At the same time, one has to note that Nora engages in something much more than simple deconstruction. As Patrick Hutton notes, postmodernist historians focused exclusively on memory's significance for political mobilization, dismissing—or at least underestimating—the value of tradition itself. They accordingly developed a very functionalist approach, in which commemoration was treated as “a form of mnemonics for the modern age, self‐consciously designed by leaders of the nation‐state to prompt the desired recall.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>In reaction to the one‐sidedness of this approach, scholars began devoting more attention to tradition and countermemory, using Foucault's “archaeology of knowledge” as their philosophical basis. Nora belongs to this distinct frame of mind.</p>
         <p>The fundamental distinction that Nora introduces concerns<italic>milieux de mémoire</italic>and<italic>lieux de mémoire.</italic>English does not translate<italic>milieux,</italic>and there are quibbles over<italic>lieux,</italic>some translating it as “realms,” “sites,” or “places” and others preserving the French original.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>The phrase<italic>milieux de mémoire</italic>indicates sites of living or lived memory—or, rather, sites that provide direct access to living traditions. Once these traditions have passed away, the sites evoke only intimations, often nostalgic ones: in the words of Nora, “The true sadness is to suffer no longer from what one has suffered so much, and henceforth to understand only with the mind's reason, no longer with the unreason of the heart.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The difficulty is to understand exactly Nora's use of the term<italic>lieux de mémoire.</italic>Nora borrowed it from Frances Yates, but he did not employ it, as Yates did, to designate the tangible ordered places/palaces to which information is attached in order to be individually preserved as memory in oral tradition. Instead, he used it to designate the exterritorialized sites of collective memory. The category “collective memory” itself is utilized as a metaphor for history, which imposes on society one particular vision to be remembered. Nora captures the whole process at a moment when the identification with living memory has disappeared. The sites of memory he describes are like “moments of history torn away from the movement of history, then returned. No longer quite alive, not yet dead, they are like seashells on the shore from which the sea of living memory has retreated.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>When<italic>Le Grand Robert</italic>included the phrase in 1993, it used this explanation by Nora as its definition. Nora approached<italic>les lieux de mémoire</italic>as objects, places, or ideals transformed by human agency or time into “symbolic element[s] of the inherited touchstones of memory of a community.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As already mentioned, this is a particularly French context. A single event—the French Revolution—was granted foundational status, but toppling this event from its pedestal after two centuries of contested but nonetheless unthreatened primacy did not entail social destabilization and collective anomie. French society at the bicentennial of the French Revolution could complain of all kinds of malaise, but it was without doubt one of the most successful and affluent societies in the post–Second World War era. Introspection and deconstruction are affordable indulgences in this context, but they are not readily, or at least not innocently, exportable.</p>
         <p>This is not to deny the magnificent achievement of Nora's work and the universal significance of many of his insights. Particularly valuable is his historicizing of the nineteenth‐century historiographical project. Even though his interpretation is based entirely on French examples, the predominant place and influence of France and French culture in the nineteenth century secures its general significance. Nora interprets this modern historiographical project as an attempt to take possession of collective memory. In the previous oral tradition, memory had focused on habits, cultures, and mores and was passed on unreflectively from generation to generation. In the modern period, memory is recorded rather than voiced; thus, by taking possession of it, history materializes it. In this written tradition, however, even after the Revolution, which “brutally distanced the past and lumped together several centuries as the<italic>ancien régime,</italic>” historians tried to find ways to link history to memory. The French historians of the early and mid‐nineteenth century were, according to Nora, the last generation of historians to experience the coincidence of history and memory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This abruptly changed in the last third of the nineteenth century, “when history became a science and the Republic turned it into a national institution.” What this brought about was a conscious privileging of history over memory: “National history was becoming the French memory.” This state of affairs continued until at least the 1930s, when both the<italic>Annales</italic>school and Marxism challenged the national project and “set out on a divergent path, signaling the moment when history, abruptly and quite self‐consciously, ceased to coincide with the nation's memory.” It was taken up in the 1960s by the “New History” and then again in the 1980s with the “acceleration” of history, “the increasingly rapid disappearance of things and the move into an increasingly uncertain future.” As far as France is concerned, Nora maintains, there is a clear sign that “the present is being enslaved to memory, that is, to the fetishism of signs, an obsession with history, an accumulation of the material remains of the national past, and to the infinite ways of expressing the national life—not only its history, but also its landscapes, its traditions, its ways of eating, and its long‐gone methods of production. Everything is historical, everything is worth remembering, and everything belongs to memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The memory palace of oral tradition, as splendidly described by Frances Yates, had been an imaginary structure where factual knowledge was interiorized in specific places and thus internalized (committed to memory). But the postmodern historian visits these palaces in order to unveil their mechanism, not to partake in their function. He deconstructs not only the archive but also other architectural places of memory: museums, monuments, shrines. He visits them to disassemble them, not to reconfirm the message that a generation of earlier historians would have found there.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As an interpretation of a common intellectual endeavor, this is surely valid far beyond France's borders, although one could argue about the details and emphases in different national and regional historiographies. We can hardly expect Iraqi historiography to take up soon the tired posture of the “self‐conscious, uninspired, and rather mechanistic activity of preserving memory” when the country's patrimony is swiftly and mechanically disappearing in the direction of the capitals of Old Europe and New York.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>It is hardly to be expected that a historian in Eastern Europe will obsess over “long‐gone methods of production” or “ways of eating” when these methods are hurled back on the existential scene involuntarily and without a hint of nostalgia. The domestic canning industry, for instance, is flourishing not because there is all of a sudden a quirky notion of boredom with the present and an appetite for “grandmother's ways” but because people have to make ends meet. The first time in my life that I saw a working plow outside of a museum or a textbook was after the fall of communism. Ironically, for parts of Eastern Europe, it is in this particular respect that the Communist episode may have set the scene for the role of the postmodern voyeur. For a couple of generations the immediate link to the premodern past had been broken and its artifacts had served as sites merely of pedagogical memory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>Still, it may be possible to domesticate these counterexamples as temporary deviations from an otherwise systemic phenomenon.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>
         </p>
         <p>So, then, how should we employ this seemingly innocuous notion of “places of memory” in a post‐Nora historiographical era? Do we cling in a pedantic—although, one can maintain, also purist—manner to the meaning that Nora has conferred on the phrase, which leaves us with the option of applying the definition structurally to non‐French contexts and seeking out convergences and divergences? This has happened over time with notions such as feudalism, capitalism, imperialism, industrial revolution, nation, and modernity, not to speak of the numerous categories defining ideological, philosophical, artistic, and other intellectual trends. Each was created initially by extrapolation from a local (usually West European) context whose factual or historiographical priority made it a model to be applied systemically. Choosing this option would be very much in a tradition that is today slighted by many as Eurocentric, although, employed with some sophisticated caveats, it seems almost unavoidable.</p>
         <p>Another option would be to “naturalize” the category and elevate it in its most abstract parameters to a systemic status, overlooking the original context in which it was created. That original context would thus revert to the status of a case study (although one with a temporal priority), one hypostasis of a “multiple” phenomenon. This is a procedure that has been practiced lately with considerable success, especially around the category of modernity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>It avoids the problems of the previous option, but at the price of a certain ahistoricism.</p>
         <p>Finally, one can stick to the most conventional, everyday, literal, common‐sense use of the term “places of memory,” consciously disregarding the fact that the category has become invested with a particular meaning in a particular historiography. These are all possibilities, but the choice between them has to be made. A good historian today is plagued much more by “historiography” than every human being is by “history,” because, in the end, despite declarations and protestations, the historian knows that there is no difference between the two. But let us go back to the Dimitrov mausoleum, a site that was meant to have great historical significance, to be a veritable Communist<italic>lieu de mémoire,</italic>and that, relegated to a<italic>lieu d'oubli,</italic>continues to have all the makings of a place of memory.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>David P. Jordan, the editor and author of the thoughtful introduction to the Chicago edition of<italic>Les lieux de mémoire,</italic>who does a lot to carefully contextualize the project, cannot resist introducing Nora in his opening sentence as “the theoretician of historical memory.” Pierre Nora,<italic>Rethinking France: Les lieux de mémoire,</italic>ed. David P. Jordan, trans. Mary Trouille, 4 vols. (Chicago, 2001), 1:xxiii.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt explain this renewed interest in memory as “a response to the acceleration of history, to rapid social change, and to the problems of identity that such changes are pressing home with growing urgency.” It is noteworthy that this erupted at a time when France, “a country blessed with, if not overwhelmed by, a long and glorious past … , moved from the front ranks to the status of a middling power. The rise of memory is thus contemporary with a cruel twist in the nation's history” (Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt, eds.,<italic>Histories: French Constructions of the Past</italic>[New York, 1995], 631). Nora himself considers the explosion of memory a worldwide phenomenon, but he thinks it came earlier to France because of the confluence of three major factors: the aftereffects of the economic crisis of the 1970s, the fallout from the post–de Gaulle (d. 1970) era, and the exhaustion of the revolutionary idea (Nora, “General Introduction,” in<italic>Rethinking France,</italic>1:x–xi).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Pierre Nora,<italic>Les lieux de mémoire</italic>(Paris, 1997). This second, three‐volume edition comprises the seven volumes of the same title published from 1984 to 1992. This first publication was conceived as a three‐part, three‐volume work around three grand topics:<italic>La République</italic>;<italic>La Nation</italic>;<italic>Les France. La République</italic>came out in 1984.<italic>La Nation</italic>swelled into three volumes and came out in 1986. So did the final part,<italic>Les France,</italic>whose three volumes were published in 1992. There are two American translations: the three‐volume set<italic>Realms of memory: The Construction of the French Past,</italic>ed. Lawrence B. Kritzman, trans. Arthur Goldhammer (New York, 1996), which rearranged the French material and presented 44 of the original 127 French chapters; and the above‐mentioned, Chicago‐published<italic>Rethinking France,</italic>which groups 45 articles in four volumes with a different organization. Among the numerous reviews, see Nancy Wood, “Memory's Remains:<italic>Les lieux de mémoire,</italic>”<italic>History and Memory</italic>6, no. 1 (1994): 123–49.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Pierre Nora, “Entre mémoire et histoire,” in<italic>Les lieux de mémoire</italic>(Paris, 1984), 1:xxxiii, cited in Patrick Hutton,<italic>History as an Art of Memory</italic>(Hanover, NH, 1993), 148.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Hutton,<italic>History as an Art of Memory,</italic>149.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Ibid., xv–xvi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>As David Jordan points out, in French itself Nora's neologism—<italic>lieux de mémoire</italic>—finally entered<italic>Le Grand Robert de la langue française</italic>only in 1993. The first English translation (Columbia University Press) employed the notion of “realms of memory,” whereas the Chicago one refrained from translating it at all. Apparently there was much agonizing over the title, as Nora had first approved<italic>Memory of France</italic>for the Chicago edition, but it was then changed to<italic>Rethinking France</italic>(Nora,<italic>Rethinking France,</italic>1:xxv).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Nora, “Entre mémoire et histoire,” 1:xlii, cited in Hutton,<italic>History as an Art of Memory,</italic>149.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Nora, “Entre mémoire et histoire,” 1:xxiv, cited in Hutton,<italic>History as an Art of Memory,</italic>152. One cannot desist from the temptation of pointing out that maritime metaphors are particularly favored among French memory writing, especially by Maurice Halbwachs.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Nora, “Comment écrire l'histoire de la France,” in<italic>Les France</italic>(Paris, 1992), 1:20, cited from Nora,<italic>Rethinking France,</italic>1:xxx. Jordan also notes that Nora did not think the word “touchstone” entirely rendered his idea (1:xxxiii, n. 21).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Nora, “General Introduction,” 1:xv–xvi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Ibid., 1:xvi–xviii.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Hutton,<italic>History as an Art of Memory,</italic>9, 149–50; Frances Yates,<italic>The Art of Memory</italic>(Chicago, 1966).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>See the excellent summary of the Iraqi losses in Timothy Potts, “Buried between the Rivers,”<italic>The New York Review of Books</italic>50, no. 14 (September 25, 2003): 18.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Such an evaluation clearly fits into an interpretive framework emphasizing primarily the modernizing aspects of the Communist episode. There have been many contending approaches trying to fit communism/socialism as a historical phenomenon into a broader theoretical perspective: communism as totalitarianism, as state capitalism, as hypermodernity, as a specific version of paternalism, as the economy of shortage, as elitist political voluntarism, etc. If I obviously privilege the modernization paradigm, it is because for me it gives the most convincing overall framework. This, however, does not mean that it has to be applied in an unimaginative rational‐choice model to the exclusion of a host of other explanations, complicating and enriching our understanding, especially with anthropological and psychological insights.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>For the United States specifics vis‐à‐vis the French template, see David Jordan, “Introduction,” in Nora,<italic>Rethinking France,</italic>1:xxxi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Samuel N. Eisenstadt, “Multiple Modernities,” in the special volume with the same title of<italic>Daedalus</italic>129, no. 1 (2000): 1–29; also the whole issue of<italic>Current Sociology</italic>42, no. 2 (1994), which published the trend report of Raymond L. M. Lee, “Modernization, Postmodernism and the Third World.” See also Jan N. Pieterse, “Hybrid Modernities: Mélange Modernities in Asia,”<italic>Sociological Analysis</italic>1, no. 3 (1998): 75–86.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>The Absent Site: Facts</title>
         <p>This section introduces the facts about Dimitrov and his mausoleum that are needed as a basis for analysis and evaluation. I am not theorizing on the notion of facts here; rather, I am using the term simply to refer to the stock of concrete incontrovertible data.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>It seems appropriate to begin this exposition with the figure of the protagonist himself: Georgi Dimitrov.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>Since encyclopedia entries are supposed to be (at least in theory) the briefest, most neutral compendia of facts, I have chosen the entry on Dimitrov from the online version of the<italic>Encyclopaedia Britannica</italic>as an ostensibly unbiased source, one that is certainly above any suspicion of procommunist leanings. The caption of its brief article reads: “Bulgarian communist leader who became the post–World War II prime minister of Bulgaria. He also won worldwide fame for his defense against Nazi accusations during the German Reichstag Fire trial of 1933.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>Here immediately it links Dimitrov's hypostases in the collective memories of Bulgaria and Germany, as well as in the international memories of fascism and communism.</p>
         <p>After a prolonged and acute illness, Georgi Dimitrov, the first prime minister of Communist Bulgaria, died in Moscow on July 2, 1949.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>The next day the Council of Ministers decided “to construct a special mausoleum in which the body of the great deceased will be put to rest and further preserved. The mausoleum will be built on the ‘9 September' square in the front part of the City garden and will be completed by July 10.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>In one night, a group of architects and engineers under the leadership of the architects Georgi Ovcharov and Racho Ribarov and the engineer Nisimov prepared a plan for the building, which was approved on July 4. The design for the interior decorations was the work of Ivan Penkov, with the participation of a group of eminent artists and sculptors, notably Dechko Uzunov, Ivan Neshev, and Valentin Starchev.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The structure was erected in six days, and the work was overseen by Major General Blagoi Ivanov, the commander of the army's labor corps.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>The army provided the bulk of the construction force, supplemented by professionals (engineers, technicians, construction workers, architects, sculptors, artists) and a host of volunteers. Even heavy rains could not delay the work, and on July 10, 1949, Dimitrov's embalmed body was laid in the mausoleum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg2">figs. 2</xref>and<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg3">3</xref>). The building itself covered 560 square meters; its height was 12 meters, and its solid outer walls were 1.2 meters thick. It contained a cubic inner hall encircled by a 2‐meter‐wide corridor. Under the memorial hall there was a laboratory and a small room for the doctors. There were also several smaller rooms for the air‐conditioning unit, for instruments, and so on. An underground tunnel was added later to connect the mausoleum with the party headquarters (which today houses the offices of Parliament).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>The exterior was covered with white stone from the Vratsa region, and the side tribunes were made of granite. On the inside there were precious stone mosaics by the artist Dechko Uzunov and his group. The structure was renovated and consolidated several times, with a major reconstruction of the façade and the interior in 1974–75 and the installation of a highly sophisticated lighting system in 1984.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>
            <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg2" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 2.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>The funeral demonstration</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg2"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
            <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg3" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 3.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Final respects</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg3"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>While the mausoleum was being erected, Dimitrov's body was returned by train from Moscow to Sofia and was embalmed in the Vranya Palace, itself a veritable<italic>milieu</italic>and<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>: it was the tsarist residence in the interwar period and one of the government residences in the Communist period, and it is presently the residence of the former prime minister of Bulgaria, Simeon Saxcoburtgotski, the son of the last Bulgarian king, Boris III. The embalmers were a group of Soviet specialists led by Boris Il'ich Zborskii, who had been an assistant in the team of V. P. Vorobev during the 1924 embalming of Lenin.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>Dimitrov's was only the second such embalming in the twentieth century, the first after Lenin's. The embalming process, known and practiced by some ancient civilizations, notably the Egyptians, had fallen into disuse, mostly because it was not part of the Christian burial tradition. In addition, the ancient methods could not preserve facial features; that had not been a goal previously since the mummies were inaccessible to outside viewers. After Lenin's death on January 21, 1924, a method was sought that would preserve the physical appearance of the Communist leader and create an accessible monument with a strong, immediate effect. Numerous scientific proposals for the preservation of Lenin's body (among them a French one) were submitted, and that of the Kharkov professor Vorobev was approved. Vorobev's embalming of Lenin was in fact the second one, following the first, temporary one by Academician Abrikosov. Vorobev started work on Lenin's body in March 1924 and finished in June. On August 1, 1924, Lenin's mausoleum was officially opened to the public, and it is still functioning today. While the technology of embalming has been further refined since then, the secret appears to be a particular solution of alcohol, formalin, glycerin, acetic acid, and some organic ingredients, whose nature and exact proportions were long kept secret (and were recently patented, as behooves a commercial society).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Dimitrov's embalming was carried out using exactly the same technology that had been employed by the Soviet specialists. So were the ensuing embalmings of Stalin (1953), Klement Gotwald in Czechoslovakia (1953), Ho Chi Minh in Vietnam (1969), Augustino Neto in Angola (1979), Guyana's leader Linden Forbes Burnham (1985), and Kim Il Sung in North Korea (1994).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>The only exception is the body of Mao Tse‐tung (1976), which was embalmed by a team of exclusively Chinese specialists.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The preservation of Dimitrov's body required constant care. Twice a week doctors refreshed the face and the hands, and once every two years the body was reembalmed.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>The mausoleum opened for visitors on December 11, 1949, and it was open regularly from 3 p.m. to 5 p.m. each Wednesday, Friday, and Sunday. During the fifty years of its existence, 18 million people passed through the commemorative chamber, among them political figures like Mikhail Gorbachev, Boris Yeltsin, Aleksey Kosygin, Fidel Castro, Indira Gandhi, Angela Davis, and many others. There was a strict protocol concerning the laying of wreaths at the mausoleum, the movement of visitors, and the arrangement of the party leaders during public events, and a veritable ritual was created for the military honor guard, specifying everything from their stylized uniforms to their poses and the specific music to be used for different occasions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg4">fig. 4</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>
            <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg4" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 4.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Cover pages of Gergov's book</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg4"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>The mausoleum became an important fixture of the communist landscape of the capital, and it was featured in all the guidebooks. It was the site for all important celebrations and military parades: September 9 (the beginning of the People's Democracy), November 7 (the October Revolution), May 1 (Labor Day), May 24 (Cyril and Methodius Day, or the Day of Culture and Education).</p>
         <p>Following the changes of 1989, and after the removal of Dimitrov's body, the mausoleum's raison d'être came into question. It still served as an important symbolic site, but now one for rallying anti‐Communist forces. Throughout the 1990s there were numerous debates concerning its meaning and potential future. The building itself was not kept up and became one of the prime sites of anti‐Communist and/or antigovernment graffiti, second only to the Monument of the Soviet Army.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>In the late 1990s, it was used with great success as a splendid theatrical set for opera performances in the open, notably for Verdi's<italic>Aida.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>Then in August 1999, all of a sudden, without any previous public discussions and at the height of the vacation season, when Sofioters were away on vacation, Parliament was in recess, and most of the public institutions (the National Library, the University, etc.) were closed, the newspapers published an order issued by the Ministry for Regional Development and Planning and signed by its minister, who was also vice premier, Evgeni Bakîrdzhiev:<disp-quote>
               <p>Order no. RD‐02‐14‐1531 from August 9, 1999</p>
               <p>With the purpose of accomplishing the provisions of the Law for Regional Reconstruction, approved with Order no. RD‐50‐09‐100/05.04.1998 of the Chief Architect of Sofia, and based on article 66 of the Law of State Property and article 31 of the Law of Architecture, it is ordered that the destruction of the building of the mausoleum and the [subsequent] shaping of the space should begin. The dismounting work should begin on August 13, 1999, and should finish by September 8, 1999.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The order was immediately put into practice, and the inside walls of the mausoleum were drilled to place explosives. Some of the mosaics on the inside were dismantled. In the following weeks the newspapers regularly covered the deconstruction and even carried out interviews and surveys, although the process never reached the front pages until the day of the explosion.</p>
         <p>This came in the early afternoon of August 21, a very hot Saturday with temperatures between 35 and 40 degrees Celsius (95 to 105 degrees Fahrenheit), when many of the few Sofioters who had remained in the city in August had finally moved to their village or vacation homes. Prime Minister Ivan Kostov came back from his vacation for the occasion, and, together with Speaker of Parliament Yordan Sokolov and assorted ministers, he observed the explosion from the roof balcony of the adjacent building of the National Archives. At precisely 2:35 p.m. a loud explosion caused clouds of dust; but after the dust had settled, it turned out that “the mausoleum, like the Tower of Pisa slightly bent toward Hotel ‘Bulgaria,' had not even cracked.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>A second explosion followed at 4:50 p.m., but the building remained intact. Some papers even reported that it had straightened up (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg5">fig. 5</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>Journalists couldn't resist the humor of the situation. One of them suggested that Vice Premier Bakîrdzhiev call on the North Atlantic Treaty Organzation (NATO) for help; NATO planes should bomb the site, he suggested, and this would not be considered an act of aggression but rather “a peaceful contribution to our civilizational choice.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>Finally, it was decided to dismantle the building mechanically, with the help of smaller detonations. This was finally accomplished during the next few days, and in the late afternoon of August 27 the last debris was removed from the square. The demolition had taken seven days, longer than it had taken to erect the building. For the first time in fifty years, the view from the former king's palace across from the mausoleum was unbroken.<fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg5" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 5.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>After the second explosion</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg5"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>Emile Durkheim, in particular, distinguishes between several classes or categories of facts (among them biological, social, psychological, etc.), of which he focuses specifically on the notion of social fact. This he defines as “every way of acting, fixed or not, capable of exercising on the individual an external constraint; or again, every way of acting which is general enough throughout a given society, while at the same time existing in its own right independent of its individual manifestations” (Emile Durkheim, “The Rules of Sociological Method,” in<italic>Emile Durkheim: Selections from His Work, with an Introduction and Commentaries by George Simpson</italic>(New York, 1963), 28. While there is a whole array of social facts enumerated in this text, my criterion for their inclusion is that they are generally accepted, no matter what the evaluation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>The literature on Dimitrov is extensive, although, as is to be expected in the period dominated by the Cold War, the bulk of this historiography was produced in Bulgarian and Russian, with some translations in French, English, or German, and mostly published in Bulgaria. The late 1940s and early 1950s constitute an exception, when his name was still a byword in revolutionary and leftist circles and biographies had been published in many languages around the world. One intriguing late exception is a splash of interest in Dimitrov in the 1980s in India, when several monographs were published in Delhi. In German, in the former German Democratic Republic, at least a couple of serious studies were published, mostly linked to the Leipzig trial, and a documentary series was initiated to coincide with the fiftieth anniversary of the event: Alfred Kurella,<italic>Dimitroff gegen Göring, nach Berichten Georgi Dimitroffs über den Reichstagsbrandprozess, 1933</italic>(Berlin, 1963), also translated into Russian, and<italic>Der Reichstagsbrandprozess und Georgi Dimitroff: Dokumente</italic>(Berlin, 1982). Lately, with the opening of Soviet and other former Communist archives, the interest was taken up by the Annals of Communism series, and two volumes have appeared thus far:<italic>Dimitrov and Stalin, 1934–1943: Letters from the Soviet archives,</italic>ed. Alexander Dallin and F. I. Firsov (New Haven, CT, 2000); and<italic>The Diary of Georgi Dimitrov, 1933–1949,</italic>ed. Ivo Banac (New Haven, CT, 2003).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>The full entry is available online at<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.britannica.com/seo/g/georgi-mikhailovich-dimitrov"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.britannica.com/seo/g/georgi‐mikhailovich‐dimitrov</ext-link>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>There have been persistent, but hitherto officially unsubstantiated, suspicions that Dimitrov, though ailing, did not die a natural death but was poisoned by Stalin. Most of the rumors have been in the oral domain, chiefly among Russians and Bulgarians who were close to Dimitrov. It was only recently that a detailed written account appeared in a book by Nasko Petrov, who reports on the different versions of Dimitrov's end and concludes that it is quite possible that he was indeed removed by Stalin. However, Dimitrov suffered from a number of diseases—diabetes, kidney, asthma—and his close friend and adviser Iliya Kiuliovski believed that he died a natural death. Most accounts that support this opinion point out that Dimitrov had been Stalin's obedient henchman; Stalin himself had visited him in the sanatorium and had held warm conversations with him. Petrov, however, suggests from a close reading of Dimitrov's diary as well as a handful of memoirs and conversations with family members that there had always been tension between the two. The strongest argument in Petrov's book, which I have not checked independently, concerns tests performed on samples of Dimitrov's hair after his body was removed from the mausoleum. Three independent tests in three different laboratories concluded that the mercury content in the hair was far above normal. This tallied with rumors that the writing desk in Dimitrov's room had a double bottom filled with mercury, which caused or at least hastened the death of the asthmatic Dimitrov. Nasko Petrov,<italic>Stalin i razgromît na bîlgarskata politicheska emigratsiya</italic>(Plovdiv, 2002), 117–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Cited in Georgi Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya</italic>(Sofia, 2000), 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>8;<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>According to different sources, between two and six people died during the construction works.<italic>Standart</italic>11, no. 3817 (August 19, 2003): 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>It was the existence of this tunnel, as well as the difficulties in blowing up the mausoleum, that produced the rumors that the mausoleum had been constructed as a nuclear bomb shelter for the Politburo. See<italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 224 (August 25, 1999): 17. Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>38, categorically denies this, maintaining that the tunnel was meant only for evacuation purposes.<italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>the official government paper, itself admitted that even if the building was a bunker, there should be no problem in blowing it up, and the fault was with bad planning and bad work on the part of the detonators (no. 221 [August 22, 1999]: 3, no. 223 [August 24, 1999]: 3).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>9, 35, 37–38;<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>9–12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Ibid., 10–11, 35. Today, the institute in charge of Lenin's body has offered its embalming techniques for sale. They have signed a contract with a funeral parlor for the provision of all services to prepare corpses for burial, including long‐term embalming (Alan Little, “Embalming the New Russian Revolution,” BBC News, January 27, 1999,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/264087.stm"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/264087.stm</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Ho Chi Minh's body was placed in a mausoleum very reminiscent of Dimitrov's, and it remains there today. Stalin's body was removed from the mausoleum on Red Square following the denunciation of the cult of personality in 1956. Gotwald's mummy was cremated in 1956 and his mausoleum destroyed, and the bodies of Dimitrov and Neto were removed in response to pleas from the relatives of the deceased (in 1990 and 1992, respectively). The Mongol leader Marshall Choibalsan was embalmed, but he was entombed next to Suhe Bator rather than displayed in a mausoleum. There are also cases in which virtual mausoleums were erected as sacred shrines but without containing the mummy, as is the case with Kemal Atatürk. The most comical story is that of Guyana's leader Burnham, who was embalmed by Soviet specialists in 1985. His mausoleum in Georgetown was built on an American design, but the U.S. State Department threatened to stop its aid program if the body went on display. Burnham was eventually buried there.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>There is also a mausoleum in Nankin preserving the remnants of Sun Yat‐sen.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>32–34. During the reembalming process, the body was immersed for thirty‐five days in a special bath. Until 1954 it was managed by an exclusively Soviet team; after that, Bulgarian doctors were trained to manage all procedures (24).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Ibid., 12, 14–21, 41–44. According to Colonel Gergov, who served as the mausoleum's commandant from 1980 until 1988, the guards underwent special selection for both their physical appearance and their family background. They were supposed to originate from antifascist and communist families, and they were not supposed to come from Sofia or nearby towns (16).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Radost Ivanova, “‘Vsichki zhabi sa zeleni, samo nashta e chervena': Grafitite vîrkhu pametnika na sîvetskata armiya i mavzoleya,” in her<italic>“Sbogom dinozavri, dobre doshli krokodili”: Etnologiya na promyanata</italic>(Sofia, 1997).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 159 (August 17, 1999): 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>This was the information of the official government newspaper<italic>Demokratsiya</italic>, no. 221 (August 22, 1999): 2.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 165 (August 24, 1999): 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Valentin Georgiev, “Bakîrdzhiev da vika na pomosht NATO,”<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 165 (August 24, 1999): 7. It has to be noted that the destruction of the mausoleum came only a couple of months after the bombing of Serbia by NATO.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Meanings</title>
         <p>The mausoleum as an institution was controversial from the very outset, and while it would be an exaggeration to speak of an actual struggle over its meaning, given the authoritarian atmosphere that prevailed wherever this type of monument was installed, there was certainly a latent conflict. Some of those who were embalmed had themselves given explicit instructions for the fate of their bodies. Thus, Lenin had wanted to be buried next to his mother at St. Petersburg's Volkovo Cemetery, and Ho Chi Minh had wished to be cremated and to have his ashes buried in three parts of the country.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>In the case of Dimitrov, we have no special document testifying to his last will in this regard, but his family always maintained that he had desired to be buried.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref>
         </p>
         <p>How did people look at the whole event when it took place? Naturally there were supporters and detractors, but how was each position actually articulated? As an important party/government decision, the determination to embalm Dimitrov and display him in a mausoleum emulating the one on Red Square was not meant to be publicly discussed, only publicly appreciated. Disapproval could hardly be articulated in a written form at the time, except outside the country, so evidence for that reaction exists mostly in the form of actions and personal memories. In 1956, for instance, there was a plot to blow up the mausoleum during a demonstration so that the whole Politburo of the Bulgarian Communist Party (BCP) could be eradicated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref>This was a case where the mausoleum was targeted less as a symbol than as a functional site, one that was more accessible than other places where the party assambled.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref>Beyond that, the commandant of the mausoleum, Colonel Gergov, reported only two serious incidents of disrespectful behavior: one anonymous, the other involving a foreigner. The first took place when a bag was abandoned in the mausoleum's wardrobe but, after a brief period of concern, it turned out to be full of stones and bricks. The other occurred when the rather inebriated deputy military attaché of the French embassy began marching behind the mausoleum's honor guard. He was sent away but returned in half an hour and tried to take one of the soldiers' guns.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Disapproval of the mausoleum came not only—and not even principally—from anti‐Communist circles. Among many Communists it was disliked as a symbol of Stalinism and the cult of personality. Gergov notes, for example, that Dr. Vasilev, the first secretary of the regional Communist Party in Botevgrad and a personal favorite of Zhivkov, had voiced his opinion that “the mummy should be taken away.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In my own family, Dimitrov was never held in high esteem. This was especially true of my grandfather, who had been adamantly opposed to the 1923 September revolt, which he blamed on Dimitrov and Vasil Kolarov's irresponsibility and on their acquiescence in the dictates of the Comintern.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">44</xref>For my parents, both Communist believers and active participants in the antifascist resistance, the mausoleum was a repellent symptom of primitive idolatry, and unenlightened practices that emulated the megalomania of the pharaohs. The phrases they actually used included “Oriental despotism,” “Asiatic megalomania,” “barbaric idolatry,” “Egyptian mummy,” and “pharaonic pretensions.”</p>
         <p>I have never visited the mausoleum with my family. The only time I was inside was with my classmates in elementary school. I do not believe my grandparents ever set foot in the mausoleum, despite the fact that they were lifelong Communists and lived into the 1970s and early 1980s respectively. I am not sure about my parents, simply because I know that they had visited Lenin's mausoleum as graduate students in the Soviet Union while Stalin's body was still there. I distinctly remember my mother's revulsion over the presence of Stalin, whom she blamed for the whole “idolatry.” At the same time, while my parents were all for the closure of every mausoleum, Lenin's included, they showed nothing like disrespect for Lenin's mummy; they regarded Lenin more as Stalin's posthumous victim.</p>
         <p>I combed through our family albums, which are numerous but well arranged and which have detailed photo coverage from the beginning of the twentieth century, with sporadic entries as far back as the mid‐nineteenth century. Obviously, the bulk of the photos come from the post–Second World War period, but the mausoleum was nowhere to be seen. Finally, in a small album containing stray images with no obvious theme, I found a small photograph of my parents with my Greek uncle Dimitris Trakidis from Thessaloniki. The photograph was taken at the mausoleum on my uncle's camera during his visit to Sofia in March 1957 and then sent by him to my parents. This “uncle” was really my father's cousin from Varna, who had emigrated to Greece as a high school student with his parents in the late 1930s but had continued his involvement with the Left. In the early 1960s, as a lawyer, he was one of the defendants in the famous Lambrakis case, and he remains a Communist to this day. The photograph I found is not only a gesture of memory from my uncle but also a gesture of defiance of his own authoritarian regime in Greece in the 1950s, which banned and persecuted Communism. Ironically, then, as a<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>it would be classified more properly under the rubric of “remembering unrealized Communism” (in Greece) than under that of “remembering real Communism” (in Bulgaria;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg6">fig. 6</xref>).<fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg6" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 6.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Family photo, March 1957</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg6"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>Apart from this, there is no other family photo‐memory of the mausoleum in the pre‐1989 period. From my childhood, naturally, I remember it as the parade square, the mimesis of Red Square. But it is not merely, and arguably not even chiefly, this public memory that dominates my recollections. It is not so much the image of Politburo members waving to the crowds or the slogan shouting, the songs, and the posters that I remember. It is rather the boys who were selected to be banner bearers in the school, and the fierce competition among us girls to be elected to flank the “heroes,” and the dilemma of what kinds of shoes, socks, or hair bands we would be able to select from the rather limited assortment dictated by the uniforms. This was when we were nine or ten years old and were members of the pioneer organization. A little later, as teenagers, we referred to Dimitrov in our circles, but without any venom, as “George‐in‐the‐can.” In my own album, the mausoleum figures only from the post‐1989 period. I first recorded it for the sake of the graffiti in 1994, and particularly the one targeting the then‐president Zhelev: “All frogs are green, only ours is red.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref>I also took photographs a few days before the destruction in August 1999.</p>
         <p>The already‐mentioned memoirs of the mausoleum's last commandant give the best summary of the official motives for the building of the mausoleum. It was erected because “we wanted to preserve Georgi Dimitrov's image,” because he was to be added to “mother Bulgaria's iconostasis,” because it was a way to preserve the sense of memory, because it was to serve as a symbol, as a locus of worship.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">46</xref>This was the array of official generic motives internalized by a number of people, most notably Communist supporters.</p>
         <p>There were also some more obviously nationalist motives. In a paragraph following his description of the many foreign leaders who had laid wreaths in front of the mausoleum, Gergov concludes, “Let future generations remember that the tribute paid by Europe and the world is not simply before a sarcophagus in a mausoleum, not a simple ritual, demanded by protocol! Let our children know that the respect for Dimitrov was respect for proud and strong Bulgaria.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">47</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Gergov is very much aware of the pharaonic analogy, but, amazingly, he is not defensive about it. For him this is simply “part of human culture.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">48</xref>Here is what he has to say:<disp-quote>
               <p>This human experience [embalming] has been passed on from remote antiquity. The unique Egyptian art erected the famous Egyptian pyramids. … These monuments were erected in order to aggrandize the pharaoh and his relatives, to emphasize his divine nature, and to perpetuate his power. … This amazing cult existed more than 5,000 years ago. In an unprecedented way, it was revived in the new twentieth century. The idea is not so much the significance or genius of a given person but the revival of a monument dedicated to a cult, which is supposed to impart immortality. In such a way, the pharaohs' ghosts emerge through the millennial dusk and enter the mausoleums of Lenin, Ho Chi Minh, Augustino Neto, and Mao. … Today we don't know who begot the idea to embalm Lenin's body, to erect a mausoleum, to make a sarcophagus for the tiny body, so that millions of people would believe in his immortality. Whoever these initiators, it is an indubitable fact that they were atheists, partaking in the construction of a symbol that would remind one of immortality, greatness, everlasting power.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">49</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The more unexpected motive and/or rationalization that emerges from Gergov's memoirs—unexpected because so abundantly evoked—is the mausoleum as the apotheosis of science. The constant refrain of his reports on the mausoleum staff's activities is that “everything was put on a strictly scientific basis.” Many more pages in these brief memoirs are devoted to the secrets of embalming than to the ideological significance of the mausoleum. A good quarter of the text deals with the intricate lighting with its halogen lamps and reverse mirrors, the special angles at which the lamps were installed, the electronic installations that preserved the exact temperature and humidity. What emerges from these pages is an uncanny pride in a purely scientific achievement: the embalming and preservation of the body was unprecedented in global science; the staff serving the mausoleum did everything based on scientific principles. This portrayal reminds one more of a surgeon's team than of a high priest's assistants.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">50</xref>Amazingly, the whole memoir closes not with comments on Dimitrov or the mausoleum but with a two‐page eulogy of Nikolai I. Pirogov, the nineteenth‐century Russian surgeon and scientist who took part in the Russo‐Turkish war of 1877–78 and after whom one of Sofia's premier hospitals is named. Pirogov was a champion of embalming and had done fundamental research in this field, as well as introducing antiseptics and ether anesthesia. His own body had been embalmed and then buried in 1881 in his home town of Vinitsa.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">51</xref>
         </p>
         <p>There is one more interpretation that ought to be covered in this survey of meanings, but since it is centered on the mummy rather than on the building itself, and since it inevitably evokes the category of balkanism, it merits its own section.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>All through the 1990s, debates have gone on in Russian society about the possibility of reburying the body of Lenin, not only to fulfill his own will but also in keeping with Christian tradition (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/world/europe/264087.stm"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/world/europe/264087.stm</ext-link>). However, some believe that Lenin's explicit will may be a myth. I owe the last piece of information to Ron Suny.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>It is curious to add that all existing evidence points to the conclusion that Todor Zhivkov never harbored the idea of joining Dimitrov in the mausoleum. Such a proposal had never even been rumored, let alone discussed or circulated (Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>44).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>This information comes from the State Security archives and was filed under the code name “Mushrooms” (<italic>Gîbi</italic>), no. 255, February 27, 1956, mentioning a certain T. Z. as the chief organizer. It was published after 1989 in the newspaper<italic>Trud</italic>by the journalist R. Bîchvarov (cited in Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>21).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>That it was widely taken as the most powerful symbol of the new regime is beyond doubt. The famous Gorunya plot (of the former partisan and acting general Ivan Todorov‐Gorunya) in 1965 had envisaged two tanks appearing on the square in front of the mausoleum. On a personal note, I remember Nina Zhelyazkova—then a researcher at the Institute of Balkan Studies, later a participant in the dissident group around Zhelyu Zhelev, and now the director of the nongovernmental organization for minority issues—making a statement in private circles to the effect that she would burn herself in front of the mausoleum were Bulgaria to become the Soviet Union's sixteenth republic.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>21–22.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Ibid., 45. The commandant writes that the information was shared with him in one of the subterranean rooms of the mausoleum by a friend to whom Vasilev had personally spoken, and Gergov was afraid because of the ubiquitous microphones.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>In June 1923, the agrarian government of Alexander Stamboliiski was ousted following a coup d'état of the army, and Stamboliiski himself was cruelly murdered. At the time, the then‐renamed Communist Party announced its “neutrality” in what it pronounced to be a fight between two factions of the bourgeoisie. That this was a tactical explanation for its passivity and weakness, rather than a rigid and dogmatic ideological stance, can be discerned from its attempts before June 1923 to warn the agrarians of the coming coup and ask that the government be armed so that the coup could be prevented. Stamboliiski's government refused—no doubt a costly mistake, but one that was completely understandable, given the suspicions it harbored against the Communists for having organized a devastating strike in 1919 against the newly established agrarian government. In June 1923, the left‐wing forces were completely powerless, and the “neutrality” formula was just the cover for their impotence. However, the Moscow‐based Comintern, at that time still hoping to foment a “permanent revolution,” ordered the Bulgarian Communists to rise. After bitter discussions, which divided the leadership of the BCP, the faction represented by Dimitrov and Kolarov prevailed. The accusations of acquiescence in the dictates of the Comintern and conscious adventurism, which were raised against them by other Communists in the country, were based on the fact that they organized the uprising hastily and in the most remote western province of the country, from which they quickly escaped by emigration, whereas the subsequent “White terror” threw the country into bloody reprisals.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>An obvious allusion to Zhelev's physical appearance, this graffito was mounted by backers of the Union of Democratic Forces (UDF) at a time of exacerbated political polarization. Zhelev was crucified between his two incompatible roles as, on the one hand, the leader of the anti‐Communist opposition and, on the other hand, the president of the whole nation and thus a unifying symbol aside from political sympathies. He was perceived by the anti‐Communist forces as too soft on the Communists.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>5, 7, 12, 15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>Ibid., 14.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Ibid., 48.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Ibid., 46.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Ibid., 11–12, 32–37, 47.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Ibid., 47–48.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Balkanism as Memory</title>
         <p>Earlier in this article I observed that sites serve as orientation markers, and as such they are reminiscent of the helpful function of stereotypes, which assist us through the unpredictable chaos of daily life by ordering it in a more or less familiar fashion. I would like to argue a concrete case of such juncture based on an example of anthropological exegesis. The symbolic language of monuments and how it is mobilized in bringing about or sanctioning social change has become a favorite topic of research, especially with the rich variety of examples that have accompanied the nervous transformation of the cultural landscape in the post‐Communist world.</p>
         <p>A few years ago, an Austrian anthropologist and historian, Bertold Unfried, published an article on the fate of Stalinist monuments in Eastern Europe, with special attention to the Czech Republic and Bulgaria.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">52</xref>In the Czech case, he was looking at the dismantling of monuments and particularly at what preceded this dismantling: the satirical graffiti, the splashes of paint converting a tank into a pink Elvis‐like automobile, the added artifacts that turned symbols into their opposites. All this was interpreted within a framework that the author himself defined as “between iconoclasm and museifying [<italic>Musealisierung</italic>],” the point being that the symbols are exposed or subverted within the same language of expression: the rhetoric of modern art, a centerpiece of modern identity.</p>
         <p>While Sofia abounds with analogous examples, Unfried chose to make a different case for Bulgaria. He focused on the fate of Dimitrov's mummy, which had been kept in the mausoleum since his death in 1949. On July 18, 1990, Dimitrov's family decided to remove the mummy for cremation and burial in the family grave in the Orlandovtsi Cemetery. Here is Unfried's reading of the events: “Under the pressure of permanent profanity, one night Dimitrov's mummy was removed, burnt [the verb used in German is<italic>verbrannt,</italic>not<italic>kremiert</italic>or<italic>eingeäschert</italic>] and buried in the family grave. The burning of a mummy is the worst thing that can happen to it in the belief of mummifying death rituals, because it means the second, final death. In popular belief the mummy is also linked with the fear of ghouls. In Sofia, however, there was an additional consideration in the air: the purification of a corrupt relic in the dazzling flames.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">53</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Based on this analysis of the cremation of Dimitrov, the author concluded: “Thus, we witness in Sofia a more archaic form of dealing with the symbols and monuments of the old regime. The enemy is burnt in effigy, and there is a dance of celebratory oblivion around the fire.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">54</xref>This latter sentence must be an allusion to the so‐called dances of the<italic>nestinari,</italic>walking barefooted and in a trance on burning coal, which have been convincingly interpreted as an ancient Thracian and Greek ritual. These dances had been preserved into this century in some outlying areas of the Strandzha Mountains in southwestern Bulgaria, and in the last few communist decades they were revived exclusively as part of a commercial enterprise: they were favored stage shows in cabarets and restaurants catering to foreign tourists, one of the few sources of a steady flow of hard currency for the major Bulgarian tourist agency, Balkanturist.</p>
         <p>Unfried's analysis is very learned but patently untrue. Dimitrov's mummy was burnt not in effigy and not in public but in a private cremation ceremony by his immediate family.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">55</xref>Actually, the burning of the mummy should be approached from a standpoint that is diametrically opposite to that of Unfried. Far from being a symptom of archaic beliefs, it is actually the most modern, secularized action imaginable. Cremation is not particularly popular in Bulgaria, especially not among practicing Christians. It is considered to be either a pagan ritual or a secular innovation, but in any case distinctly un‐Christian, and people resort to it nowadays simply because of lack of space. In fact, it is a privilege to have a place for a real burial, and cremation is accepted very reluctantly, although nowadays with resignation. In the case of Dimitrov's family, a shortage of cemetery space would not have been a problem: they have their family graves, and there is also reserved cemetery space for statesmen. The mummy was removed from the mausoleum during the first mandate of the socialist (former communist) government of Andrei Lukanov, in which Boiko Dimitrov, Georgi Dimitrov's son, served as foreign minister. By opting for cremation, the family, with its long atheist and communist past, actually chose the nonreligious, nontraditional, “Western” mode of dealing with the corpse.</p>
         <p>Unfried's article itself can be approached in different ways. One can see it as a case of speculative interpretation, based not on first‐hand research but on a priori models. This is, of course, a more charitable way of saying that it is a case of sloppy research, given the fact that by the time he was writing his article there had already been numerous Bulgarian publications on the novel cultural treatment of former monuments, the mausoleum included.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">56</xref>But one can also treat it as a case of scholarly balkanism: the notion that explanatory approaches to phenomena in southeastern Europe often rest upon a discourse (in the Foucauldian sense)—or upon what might be called a stable system of stereotypes by those who shun the notion of “discourse”—that places the Balkans in a cognitive straitjacket. In<italic>Imagining the Balkans,</italic>I refrained from generalizing about scholarly output, maintaining that the scholarly project moves along different lines than does the production of popular mythology and only occasionally intersects with it. My caveat was: “This is not to say that a great number of the scholarly practitioners of Balkan studies in the West do not share privately a staggering number of prejudices; what it says is that, as a whole, the rules of scholarly discourse restrict the open articulation of these prejudices.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">57</xref>I still believe this to be true, and if I have erred, it is only in the direction of too much leniency.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Bertold Unfried, “Denkmäler des Stalinismus und ‘Realsozialismus' zwischen Ikonoklasmus und Musealisierung,”<italic>Österreichische Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenschaften</italic>5, no. 2 (1994): 233–58.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Ibid., 257.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Ibid., 258.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>Dimitrov's adopted son, Boiko Dimitrov, had been a career diplomat, and his grandson was a history student in the 1980s. The remains may have been cremated principally to avoid desecration in the highly politically charged atmosphere of the moment; but, in any case, it is illogical that the immediate family would want to burn the mummy in effigy.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>M. Elchinova and V. Raicheva, “Kîm kharakteristikata na edin vid novi kulturni yavleniya (Grafichnite tekstove na studentskata okupatsionna stachka i ‘Grada na istinata'),”<italic>Bîlgarski folklor,</italic>no. 3 (1990): 22–40; Radost Ivanova, “‘Sbogom dinozavri, dobre doshli krokodili': Politicheskite mitingi i tekhnite lozungi prez pogleda na folklorista,”<italic>Bîlgarski folklor</italic>(1991): 63–71, and “‘Down with BCP, Down with UDF, and Down with Both BAP Parties!': Political Slogans through the Eyes of the Folklorist,”<italic>Journal of Folklore Research</italic>28, no. 1 (1991): 23–34; K. Mikhailova, “Fotorazkaz za novoto litse na mavzoleya,”<italic>Bîlgarski folklor</italic>4 (1993): 104–9. See also the aforementioned article of Ivanova, “‘Vsichki zhabi sa zeleni, samo nashta e chervena.’”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Maria Todorova,<italic>Imagining the Balkans</italic>(New York, 1997), 20.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc6">
         <title>Memory Holes</title>
         <p>In<italic>1984,</italic>George Orwell described the shredding machine, which was supposed to erase all inappropriate memories. Remembering and forgetting are, naturally, two sides of the same coin, and memory holes are constructed with as much effort as memories themselves. Small wonder that the destruction of the mausoleum—this symbolic blowing up of the past—produced polarized opinions. What is more surprising is that this polarization remained almost entirely in the verbal (written and, to some extent, oral) domain. There was no significant public debate about the future of the mausoleum. Moreover, there was no debate in the parliament or on the cabinet level. As already mentioned, it was the abrupt publication of Order no. RD‐02‐14‐1531 on August 9, 1999, that set the events in motion. The only political force that could be expected to stage some resistance—the Bulgarian Socialist Party (BSP)—made only halfhearted pronouncements about the illegality of the decision and the ensuing act. It never even attempted to gather mass support against the move, to stage demonstrations, protests, and so on. The one public event it organized was an open discussion about the future of the mausoleum that took place ten days after the publication of the order and two days before the actual blowing up. The event reportedly gathered about three hundred people, mostly veterans of the party who came with red flags and Che Guevara images.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">58</xref>
         </p>
         <p>One can only surmise that the BSP wisely gauged that it would never be able to muster a large public following and made only the minimum expected gestures so as not finally to drive away any of its already alienated supporters. As pointed out earlier, even among devoted Communists the mausoleum was not a popular site, let alone a site of vested interest. The decision to remove Dimitrov's mummy in 1990 did not encounter any protest; on the contrary, it was accepted as long‐overdue respect for the wishes of Dimitrov's immediate family. At the same time, it went hand in hand with a general and genuine respect for the figure of Dimitrov among socialist supporters. Dimitrov's stature in Communist Bulgaria never suffered the vicissitudes of extreme adulation and equally extreme rejection, and more than anything else this had to do with his life history. When he returned from exile to Bulgaria in 1945, he came with the international aura of the “lion of the Leipzig trial” and the leader of the Third International. While the suppression of non‐Communist as well as intraparty opposition occurred during and under his leadership as prime minister, the whole period from 1945 to 1948 had nonetheless been characterized by a certain pluralism in public life. In fact, the open Stalinist grip on the country occurred after Dimitrov's death (July 1949) and after the show trial of Traicho Kostov and his group (December 1949), although it had already been prepared with Dimitrov's active participation. The very circumstance, however, that Dimitrov was not alive at the time of the trial and subsequent assassination of the very popular Kostov, coupled with the rumors that he himself might have fallen victim to Stalin, explains why, in the aftermath of the de‐Stalinization process and the rehabilitation of Kostov, his reputation did not suffer. The roles of Stalinist henchman and bogeyman in Bulgaria were played by Vîlko Chervenkov, who had concentrated power in his hands as prime minister and general secretary (1950‐56) and whose rule saw, besides his personality cult, a drastic collectivization of agriculture and far‐reaching purges and police terror. He also became the scapegout on whom all Stalinist excesses were blamed, and he was even expelled for some time from the Communist Party before his death in 1981. After 1956 and the rise of Zhivkov, the latter was careful to preserve the unblemished reputation of Dimitrov, although in an ever‐receding background.</p>
         <p>This explains why the ceremony in July 1990, when the body was removed and then buried, attracted a staggering number of people who gathered to pay their last homage to a prominent historical figure. Dimitrov the figure and Dimitrov the mummy had been totally decoupled in the imagination of these people. (That is clearly not the case with the mummy and mausoleum of Lenin; its symbolic value is still very high, and any talk of its removal is perceived by a majority of Communists as a direct onslaught on the personality of Lenin and the overall ideology, as well as a nihilist attack on a whole historical period.)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">59</xref>This, I think, also explains why the square in front of Dimitrov's mausoleum did not become the exclusive space for communist demonstrations, while the square in front of the Alexander Nevski Cathedral did become the symbolic opposition site in the early days of democracy. The September 9 (later Alexander Battenberg) Square between the palace and the mausoleum was a shared political space, the playground of different political and nonpolitical performances. A couple of other places in Sofia did become preferred locations that were reserved for socialist demonstrations, however: one is the area around the monument marking the common grave (<italic>bratskata mogila</italic>) in the former Liberty Park (now the Boris Garden), and the other is a sort of self‐fashioned communist Hyde Park corner in the South Park, unmarked by a special monument but nonetheless drawing a steady crowd, especially on weekends.</p>
         <p>The battle over the mausoleum was exclusively a press affair, and it triggered the expression of a number of strong opinions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">60</xref>Some of the defenders' arguments were purely political. They accused the mausoleum's destroyers of fascism, barbarism, vandalism, restoration, and so on. One of the most effective posters was run in the BSP newspaper<italic>Duma</italic>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg7">fig. 7</xref>). It drew an explicit parallel with the rise of Nazism in Germany, and the caption, composed as a rhymed limerick, read: “The Leipzig trial is continuing. Today the mausoleum is on trial. Coming from Leipzig, in our state today, Goering's grandsons are destroying it.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">61</xref>Other objections were legalistic, stressing the fact that there was no previous public discussion and that the decision itself was illegal according to the existing rules.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">62</xref>
            <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg7" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 7.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>
                     <italic>Duma,</italic>August 19, 1999</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg7"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>Most of the objections, however, were historical and preservationist. One journalist caustically remarked that nobody touches the pyramids, despite the fact that most house the mummies of rather undemocratic pharaohs.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">63</xref>Another commented on the fact that the destruction of the mausoleum would cost around forty thousand leva (about twenty thousand dollars), which would be gathered from donations. The first one thousand leva having been donated by Bakîrdzhiev himself, the journalist added: “Throughout the world as well as according to Bulgarian tradition, donors give for construction, not for destruction.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">64</xref>Prominent public figures spoke against the destruction. The now‐deceased Petîr Dertliev, leader of the Social Democratic Party, a political prisoner after 1944 and one of the most revered leaders of the democratic transition, exclaimed: “We are going to stun the world with our narrow‐mindedness and political savagery.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">65</xref>Stefan Gaytandzhiev, the leader of Ekoglasnost (the ecological movement), as well as the member of parliament Rumen Vodenicharov; the cinematographer Anzhel Wagenstein; the historian Ilcho Dimitrov; one of the BSP leaders, Nikolay Kamov; and the writer Kalina Alena, all spoke and wrote against the destruction as an uncivilized act, bespeaking antihistoricism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">66</xref>Some of the strongest arguments stressed that the Communists did not destroy the palace but transformed it into a National Gallery. Moreover, they left intact the mausoleum dedicated to Alexander Battenberg, the Prince of Bulgaria from 1878 to 1887, even though it did not have any public function during the Communist era.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">67</xref>
         </p>
         <p>On the other side of the barricade, the supporters of the destruction also had a variety of motivations. Some were unabashedly anti‐Communist, considering the mausoleum an arrogant symbol of totalitarianism. Prime Minister Kostov said the mausoleum created a false impression of Bulgarian identity; it was a negation of parliamentary democracy and therefore had to go.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">68</xref>The most ardent activist of the destruction campaign, Bakîrdzhiev, regretted that he had not pushed the button for the explosion himself: “Then it would surely have worked the first time.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">69</xref>The other vice premier, Alexander Bozhkov, clearly identified the blowing up with democracy, and he commented: “In Bulgaria nothing happens the first time. Everything is tortured, difficult: democracy, the transformations, the destruction of the mausoleum. Everything we do we have to do twice.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">70</xref>The journalist Georgi Daskalov hailed the blowing up as a spiritual liberation for all Bulgarians, who were previously “forced to pay homage to fabricated, mythical [<italic>izmisleni</italic>] deities” (apparently implying that there are unfabricated ones).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">71</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Yet the political argumentation did not carry much weight. After all, according to Reinhart Koselleck, “memorials are taken down when they are felt to be a threat or when a tradition that is still living is intended to be suppressed.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">72</xref>The political force and tradition of which the mausoleum had been a symbol was certainly not, nor was it perceived to be, a threat. Besides, as an alternative vision, it was hardly still linked symbolically to the mausoleum.</p>
         <p>There were more weighty and convincing arguments revolving around aesthetic and functional considerations. The controversial but popular mayor of Sofia, Stefan Sofiyanski, rightly accused the BSP of having neglected its own symbol. He pointed out that it had been the ruling party several times and that between 1993 and the end of 1996 it had an absolute parliamentary majority. Yet never once did it come up with a plan for the future of the mausoleum, which could have easily gathered support. Sofiyanski's objections to the mausoleum were based on what he characterized as its illegal construction, because it had been built on land donated almost a century earlier for a garden. He recognized the nostalgic value of the mausoleum for a great number of people but, in yet another analogy to Germany, noted that the destruction of the Berlin wall also had its opponents: “Yet its destruction became, in its turn, the symbol for the unification not only of Germany but also of Europe.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">73</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The art scholar Dimitîr Avramov expressed his aesthetic aversion toward the mausoleum, calling it “the ugliest building in Bulgaria.” Moreover, he added, “I would say there is no uglier building in Europe, although I know many European capitals.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">74</xref>Its demolition, according to him, would return some of the “old European spirit” to Sofia. Entitled as he was to his aesthetic tastes, Avramov added a curious “analytical” pronouncement. He based his main objection to the mausoleum on the fact that it was not original and authentic but “foreign” and a case of “architectural plagiarism.” The project was meant to emulate Lenin's mausoleum in Moscow and therefore copied its base and upper colonnade. There has never been a question that the mausoleum was meant as a mimesis of Red Square, and, quite apart from its doubtful aesthetic basis, the argument against “architectural plagiarism” would consign all churches, palaces, and public and private buildings, not only in Sofia but all over the world as well, to demolition.</p>
         <p>The most interesting, if not necessarily the most logical, comments on the mausoleum (because they focused on historical and social memory) came in an interview with Georgi Fotev, the director of the Institute for Sociology. He began on an acceptable note, arguing that, in contrast to Rome, where Mussolini's architecture was preserved, Sofia could not bear the presence of the mausoleum architecturally. This was so because of the smaller size of the city, whose center was overwhelmed anyway with totalitarian architecture. If the mausoleum had been erected somewhere in the outskirts, or at least not in the very center of the city, one could still debate its removal, but under the circumstances it was simply “thrust in the heart of the capital” and had to go.</p>
         <p>Fotev stressed that while the mausoleum had lost its function as a sepulchre almost ten years ago, making it redundant, “the historical and social memory refuses to forget precisely that.” He therefore concluded that, even though he was tolerant of the preservationist views of many intellectuals, he could accept them only in the abstract: they failed to recognize the social reality and negative symbolic significance of the mausoleum. At the same time, in an illogical and symmetrical volte‐face, Fotev opined that the destruction was not necessitated by a fear of restoration or the danger that a totalitarian symbol could mislead the younger generations, for whom “communism does not mean anything and has become an incomprehensible memory.”</p>
         <p>He reiterated the argument of Avramov that the mausoleum was a “foreign body” in authentic Bulgarian sensitivity, identity, and culture and that it burdened “our historical memory.” Asked whether the demolition of the mausoleum would not also obliterate the important memories of the evils of communism, as well as the historical memory of communism itself, Fotev responded that there was no alternative to the destruction of the mausoleum. It could not be successfully transformed, according to him. At the same time, he asserted a duty “to preserve the memory of this darkest page in our modern history, which lasted close to a century.” An authentic Bulgarian monument dedicated to the victims of totalitarianism was mandatory. In the years after this interview, a monument was indeed erected in the garden of the People's Palace of Culture to commemorate the victims of Communist terror. It is an almost exact replica of the Vietnam War Memorial on the Mall in Washington, D.C. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg8">fig. 8</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">75</xref>
            <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg8" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 8.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Monument to victims of Communism</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg8"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>Summarizing the reasons for the urgency of the demolition, Fotev enumerated three chief ones: “First, this is something foreign, planted in the Bulgarian identity in a manner that is absolutely unacceptable. Second, this is a symbol which, naturally, could be reinterpreted, and this is very interesting, but we should not forget that this is [not “was”] the tomb of the Bulgarian statesman who crushed Bulgarian democracy in our most recent history. Third, after all, we continue to be partial to Modern Europe and aspire to become part of it. The mausoleum's very existence contradicts the basis of Christian civilization that is valid for the whole Old Continent.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">76</xref>Clichés are a natural and expected resort for politicians, but their presence in the statement of a prominent scholar is somewhat embarrassing.</p>
         <p>It was not only the opinions of the famous that the press disseminated. In the absence of a genuine public debate, the mass media tried, in the ten days after the decision to blow up the mausoleum had been published, to substitute opinion polls and random street interviews. An express poll taken by the National Center for the Study of Public Opinion among 528 citizens of Sofia showed that, while 64 percent did not like the mausoleum (as against 36 percent who did), only 34 percent wanted it removed. A full 42 percent thought it could be transformed into something different, while 24 percent wanted it preserved as it was.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">77</xref>A Gallup poll, without disclosing its sample, published the following results: 43 percent for the preservation of the mausoleum, 27 percent for its destruction, 16 percent for a transformation, and 14 percent without an opinion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">78</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The narrative reactions, as usual, were more personal and more interesting. Dolya Stoilova, a retiree, didn't particularly like the mausoleum and preferred a garden in its place, but she thought it was a pity to blow it up. She suspected that it was a preelection move on the part of the government.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">79</xref>Miglena Stoicheva, a student, liked it in its function as an opera set. Toni, a saleswoman, opined: “I am not sure, but it seems to me that the mausoleum is a historical monument and should be preserved.” She was not sure why it was going to be removed but “if they have decided, we cannot stop them.” The businessman Krassimir Sendov heard of the blowing up only after the fact: “Good or bad, the mausoleum is an architectural artifact, which is part of our history. I think it was not right to destroy it.” Zheko Khubenov, working in a private business, approved of the demolition: “It ought to have been removed because it disturbs the city. I've never been there. The building is ugly and there shouldn't be a grave in the center of Sofia.” Ivo Matrakchiev, a computer programmer, also had never been in Dimitrov's mausoleum and didn't think he particularly needed it but added that he had seen Lenin in his mausoleum. Elka Koleva, an engineer, was adamant: “This is a historical monument and I don't understand why it should be destroyed. Everywhere, all the great capitalist countries preserve all their historical monuments. This is our history. Besides, the building is an excellent set for the open air operas.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">80</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Indeed, references to what the “civilized” countries were doing often cropped up in the discussions: Franco's monument was evoked, as were Mussolini's buildings. Interestingly, none of the defenders of the demolition ever brought up as an honorable example the obliteration of Carthage by civilized Rome. Another example that no one mentioned, but that struck me during the time I lived in Vienna in 2001, was the continued presence of the monstrous Flacktürme, the antiaircraft towers built during the Nazi period to house up to thirty thousand troops (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg9">fig. 9</xref>). There are five of them in Vienna, two of which I could not avoid seeing regularly: one in the Augarten in the Leopoldstadt, where I often used to take walks; the other in a prominent location in the very heart of Vienna, dwarfing the big baroque Mariahilferkirche behind which it was built. True, there had been public discussions, and many Viennese feel hugely embarrassed by the presence of these ugly giants, but for whatever reason—the price of the demolition not the least—they are there to stay.<fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg9" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 9.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Vienna,<italic>Flackturm</italic>
                  </p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg9"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>In Germany, in contrast to Bulgaria, the memory of Dimitrov is preserved, at least at the official level, not perhaps as collective memory but certainly as historical memory. A plaque serves as a<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>at the building where Dimitrov used to live in Charlottenburg in Berlin between 1930 and 1933. It had been put there by the former Senate of West Berlin, and it stands at its place to this day. If it is true that Germans today would hardly know who Georgi Dimitrov is, it is not because he has been officially removed from historical memory—that is, the memory produced by historians and state institutions and meant to be internalized by the population through the channels of school education and propaganda, thus becoming what we call collective memory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">81</xref>This may point to one of the few but significant distinctions between historical and collective memory: the first is actively produced by individual historians, who tend to see themselves as ventriloquists for and preservers of collective memory; the second is frequently, but not exclusively, triggered by the official historical narrative, and while it is often passively received and sometimes excessively manipulable, it also has its own autonomous sphere and unpredictable agency.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">82</xref>
         </p>
         <p>A last example comes from a country that, in a humorous extension of Bush's juvenile pronouncement about the Axis of Evil (Iraq‐Iran‐North Korea), was joined with Serbia and the Sudan in the troika of the Axis‐of‐Somewhat‐Evil: Cuba. Along the broad Boulevard Paseo in the Vedado district of Havana there is a small garden, and in a little corner, almost hidden under the rich foliage, is a monument to Dimitrov. It consists of a huge bronze bust mounted on a concrete obelisk. A graffitist has added in black, above the bronze letters<sc>jorge dimitrov</sc>1882–1949, the words<sc>los huevos de</sc>(the eggs/balls of) and has adorned the stone with a depiction of a penis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg10">fig. 10</xref>). Cuba is a country in which the project of “remembering Communism” is still in the future, albeit in the near future, but it already has begun its good‐humored transformations.<fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg10" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 10.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
               </label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Havana, Cuba, January 2003</p>
               </caption>
               <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fg10"
                           mimetype="image"
                           position="float"
                           xlink:type="simple"/>
               </fig>
            </fig-group>
         </p>
         <p>Not that there were no suggestions for the transformation of the mausoleum in Bulgaria. They were plentiful and diverse. Some were in line with the Havana spirit: turn the mausoleum into a brewery, a discotheque, public toilets. There was an elaborate proposal to create a Madame Tussaud museum in the mausoleum with the figures of kings, political and revolutionary leaders, writers, composers, athletes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">83</xref>Most were serious, even solemn. The famous artist Svetlin Rusev thought the structure could become a museum of sculpture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">84</xref>The British historian of Bulgaria Richard Crampton, in an interview with the British Broadcasting Corporation, suggested that the mausoleum be turned into a monument for victims of totalitarianism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">85</xref>The historian Nikolay Genchev thought it would be appropriate to make it into a monument dedicated to the fallen in various wars.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">86</xref>The BCP leader Alexander Paunov wanted it transformed into a pantheon of martial glory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">87</xref>The political movement Gergyovden initially suggested that the mausoleum be left alone and made into a futuristic symbol.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88">88</xref>Later, it backed the initiative of its members from Dimitrovgrad, a city that was built by the enthusiastic labor of Communist brigades in the 1940s and 1950s and that refused to change its name in the 1990s: these citizens asked for the remains of the mausoleum, which they wanted to place in a “lane of the rejected” together with other Communist monuments that had been pulled down in the past decade in different parts of the country.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89">89</xref>Other suggestions involved turning it into the largest disco club in the Balkans, or a department of the National Library or of the National Historical Museum, or an exhibition place with a large sundial measuring the time after the regime's collapse.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90">90</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Trying to make sense of the square between the National Gallery/former palace and the mausoleum as a semiotic space, the cultural historian Dafina Dicheva laments the victory of destruction. She notes that, while the two buildings were indeed entangled in an epic metaphoric struggle, their physical presence side by side secured not only a synchronic but also a diachronic representation of the city's historical meanings, like a palimpsest. Transition periods always vacillate between rewriting and reassessment, but one would hope that any act would bring in some new meaning. The demolition of the mausoleum, according to Dicheva, left only a “desemioticized center and the debilitating power of the symbol of destruction, threatening in its insistence that anything can disappear.” In this context, she interprets the subsequent<italic>Bierfest</italic>in the square as a symbolic demolition in the wake of the physical one. It does not invert reality into the carnivalesque and thus integrate culture; instead, it disintegrates culture by transforming reality into carnival, where the<italic>Bierfest</italic>is experienced as total reality. “Destruction does not allow the reconstruction of the social and cultural order. … On the contrary, it is a mirror inversion, which blocks the social and individual experience at the level of anticulture.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91">91</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The fact that the destruction of the mausoleum came not as a spontaneous act on the heels of a popular upheaval at the time of the “velvet revolution” but as a hastily organized and sloppily executed performance a full decade after “the changes” contributed, of course, to the general indifference to the fate of this particular site, despite the emotional pathos of some of the articulated opinions. Most important, it explains the richness and diversity of nuanced assessments as well as the complete freedom of their expression. Indeed, if the demolition had taken place in the fall of 1989 or even at the beginning of 1990, one would be tempted to make sense of it in the framework of revolutionary struggles over meaning.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92">92</xref>The destruction of the Vendôme Column on May 16, 1871, came two and a half weeks after the proclamation of the Commune. It was a highly theatricalized spectacle, with a crowd of over twenty thousand assembled, waiting for three hours while a brass band played “La Marseillaise.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93">93</xref>In contrast, the 1999 mausoleum spectacle was a poorly staged mimicry of a revolutionary act, minus the music, minus the public, exactly ten years after the triggering event—a mimicry that raised again all the conceptual questions of how exactly the original event of 1989 should be designated and assessed. Should it be called a revolution (even if a “velvet” one), thus focusing on its quality of rupture? Or should it be seen as an internal coup that, despite denoting a break, emphasizes the agents' continuity? Or can its significance best be captured by the innocuous and meaningless term “changes,” which, however, has in its favor the fact that it has become the preferred and most widely utilized expression by the public, no matter what their political preferences, and has thus withstood the withering effects of time?</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 219 (August 20, 1999): 10. The Socialist Party newspaper maintained that the number was seven hundred:<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 162 (August 20, 1999): 2.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>See the striking Web site of the Lenin Mausoleum, which provides an opportunity to vote for or against the mausoleum, offering six different options (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.aha.ru/mausoleu/"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.aha.ru/mausoleu/</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>In the following exposition I have confined myself exclusively to the two newspapers symbolizing the polarized attitudes:<italic>Duma,</italic>the official publication of the Socialist Party (at that time in opposition), and<italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>the official organ of the UDF and, at the time, the government newspaper. I am excluding the huge number of other papers—<italic>Trud, 24 Chasa, 168 Chasa, Monitor, Sega, Pari, Kapital,</italic>etc.—that might be characterized as occupying the political middle ground between the two poles simply because their coverage was much poorer, essentially reiterating (often literally) the information in the two main newspapers. The “middle‐ground” papers actually testify to the relative apathy about the issue in the broad public. What is remarkable is that even<italic>Duma</italic>and<italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>while openly standing for preservation versus destruction, both provided rather objective coverage of the spectrum of public opinion, ironic and polemic jibes notwithstanding.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>“Protsesît v Laiptsig oshte prodîlzhava: Izpravyat Mavzoleya dnes na sîd; Doshli ot Laiptsig, v nashata dîrzhava pravnutsite na Gyoring go rushat,”<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 16. The images on the poster recall the famous photograph of Dimitrov at the Leipzig trial in 1933 and the figures of Prime Minister Ivan Kostov and Vice Premier Evgenii Bakîrdzhiev. A few days later, the same paper, no. 167 (August 26, 1999), published a photograph of Kostov as “Gauleiter” and made a visual comparison between the Reichstag fire in 1933, the fire at the party headquarters in 1990, and the attempt to raid the parliament in Sofia in 1997.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>These objections were voiced by architects such as Ventsislav Yochkolovski and Khristo Genctchev and by Velo Mirchev, the chief secretary of the Union of Bulgarian Artists, as well as by political figures such as Velko Vîlkanov, Atanas Bogdanov, and Georgi Pirinski. The last three deposited a letter of protest to that effect with the chief prosecutor, Nikola Filchev.<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3, no. 162 (August 20, 1999): 2, no. 167 (August 26, 1999): 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>Plamen Enchev in<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 159 (August 17, 1999): 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>Vasil Popov in<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 160 (August 18, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 160 (August 18, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>Interviews and essays in<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 160 (August 18, 1999): 3, no. 162 (August 20, 1999): 7, no. 163 (August 21, 1999): 3, no. 164 (August 23, 1999): 16, no. 166 (August 25, 1999): 5.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>The mausoleum does not contain the remains of Battenberg, who had been forced to abdicate, and whose grave is in Graz, Austria.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 221 (August 22, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn69">
               <label>69</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
               <label>70</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 222 (August 23, 1999): 3. Symptomatically, the president Petîr Stoyanov never publicly opined on the fate of the mausoleum.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
               <label>71</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 222 (August 23, 1999): 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn72">
               <label>72</label>
               <p>Reinhart Koselleck,<italic>The Practice of Conceptual History: Timing, History, Spacing Concepts,</italic>trans. Todd Samuel Presner et al. (Stanford, CA, 2002), 325.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn73">
               <label>73</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 219 (August 20, 1999): 10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn74">
               <label>74</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 224 (August 25, 1999): 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn75">
               <label>75</label>
               <p>The inscription specifies that the list of names includes people who lost their lives as well as those who served prison sentences, were sent to labor camps, or were relocated. The names do not follow any obvious arrangement, alphabetical or otherwise, except that they are grouped under administrative regions. A quick perusal of names grouped under the city of Sofia reveals the presence of Bogdan Filov, who served as prime minister to Tsar Boris III between 1940 and 1943 and who became one of the regents to Simeon after the king's death. A well‐known archaeologist with strong pro‐German leanings, Filov brought the country onto the side of the Axis powers. Along with other members of the regency, he was sentenced to death and shot by the Communist‐dominated People's Court in 1945. Another name that stands out is that of the retired general Khristo Lukov, who was assassinated by a Communist cell (the urban counterpart of the partisan formations during the Second World War) on February 13, 1943. Lukov had been leader of the Legion, the pronounced racist, antisemitic, pro‐Nazi organization in Bulgaria. Even in these days of antiterrorist fetishism, eyebrows would be raised if a monument appeared in France, Italy, or Germany commemorating the “victims” of the antifascist resistance.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn76">
               <label>76</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 223 (August 24, 1999): 12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn77">
               <label>77</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 219 (August 20, 1999): 10;<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 164 (August 23, 1999): 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn78">
               <label>78</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 166 (August 25, 1999): 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn79">
               <label>79</label>
               <p>There were municipal elections scheduled for the fall in an atmosphere of general political apathy, when the anti‐Communist edge after the fall of the Videnov government in early 1997 had been considerably blunted. In these circumstances, the destruction of the mausoleum can be seen as a gesture on the part of the government to placate the hard‐core anti‐Communist electorate of the UDF and mobilize it politically.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn80">
               <label>80</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 221 (August 22, 1999): 3;<italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 160 (August 18, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn81">
               <label>81</label>
               <p>However, the memory of Dimitrov in Leipzig, where the trial of 1933 was held, is minimal. The imposing building of the Federal Administrative Court, where the trials against Karl Liebknecht in 1907 and Dimitrov in 1933 took place, was transformed after the Second World War into the Museum of Fine Arts; it also housed the special museum devoted to the memory of Dimitrov, which had opened in 1952. In 2002, the building was given back to the Administrative Court. While a new building is being constructed to house the artifacts of the Museum of Fine Arts, nobody could answer my inquiries about the whereabouts of the materials from Dimitrov's museum during my visit in Leipzig in December 2003. A plaque in front of the federal building explains its history and mentions the Leipzig trial, but there is no explanation in the famous trial room.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn82">
               <label>82</label>
               <p>This view clearly departs from the standard notion of collective memory as an important and formative agent, the principal feeding ground for historical memory, “le sol d'enracinement de l'historiographie” in the words of Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Le mémoire, l'histoire, l'oubli</italic>(Paris, 2000), 83.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn83">
               <label>83</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3. The letter with the proposal, signed by Petîr Shurkov, included these names: the khans Kubrat, Asparukh, and Krum; the tsars Boris and Simeon; the national heroes Paisii, Petîr Beron, Rakovski, Levski, Botev; the nineteenth‐century rulers and leaders Prince Battenberg, King Ferdinand, Stambolov; the war generals; the twentieth‐century political leaders Alexander Stamboliiski, Alexander Tsankov, Georgi Gimitrov, Nikola Petkov, Todor Zhivkov; as well as the soccer stars Georgi Asparukhov, Nikola Kotkov, Stoichkov. The names of famous writers, poets, artists, actors, composers, singers, etc., were not mentioned.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn84">
               <label>84</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3, no. 164 (August 23, 1999): 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn85">
               <label>85</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 167 (August 26, 1999): 2.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn86">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 163 (August 21, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>87</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 161 (August 19, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn88">
               <label>88</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 164 (August 23, 1999): 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn89">
               <label>89</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Duma</italic>10, no. 165 (August 24, 1999): 1;<italic>Demokratsiya,</italic>no. 222 (August 23, 1999): 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn90">
               <label>90</label>
               <p>Nikolai Voukov, “Monuments beyond the Representations of Power: Monuments of the Socialist Past in Post‐1989 Bulgaria,” in<italic>Neue Staaten—neue Bilder? Visuelle Kultur im Dienst staatlicher Selbstdarstellung in Zentral—und Osteuropa seit 1918,</italic>ed. Arnold Bartetzky, Marina Dmitrieva, and Stefan Troebst (Weimar, 2005), forthcoming.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn91">
               <label>91</label>
               <p>Dafina Dicheva, “Genealogiya na bîlgarskata stolitsa—resemiotizatsiya i desemiotizatsiya na konteksta,” in<italic>Gradît: simvoli, obrazi, identichnosti,</italic>ed. Svetlana Khristova (Sofia, 2002), 140–42.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn92">
               <label>92</label>
               <p>As Christopher Winks appropriately observes: “Revolutions are as much struggles over meaning (symbolic and semantic alike) as over the allocation of social wealth” (Winks, “Ruins and Foundation Stones: The Paris Commune and the Destruction of the Vendôme Columns,” in<italic>Revolutionary Romanticism,</italic>ed. Max Blechmand [San Francisco, 1999], 103).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn93">
               <label>93</label>
               <p>Winks, “Ruins and Foundation Stones,” 107–8.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc7">
         <title>Recalling the Reminiscence</title>
         <p>Memory has been defined in philosophical terms as “our capacity to retain what we sense, enjoy, and suffer, and thus to become knowing in our perception and other activities.” But retention is only one part of the memory process: its other aspect is recall, the capacity to recollect past events and to recognize people, places, and facts. Psychologists refer to these two aspects as semantic memory, the basis for procedural knowledge (i.e., knowledge of how to do something, which may be retained even in amnesiacs), and episodic memory, the basis for declarative knowledge (i.e., knowledge of specific facts). It is the attempt to characterize the connection between experience and episodic memory, or recall, that has attracted most of the current research on memory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94">94</xref>
         </p>
         <p>It is appropriate at this point to go back and “recall” the opening reminiscences of this text. This recollection is no longer the same as the initial experience, of course; it is inflected by the thoughts that have come in between. Strictly speaking, only the statues in front of the university would correspond entirely to the notion of<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>as utilized and defined by Nora. For the generations who were part of the institution‐building efforts of the young state and for whom the figures of the “pre‐Liberation period” were an important component of their immediate childhood memories, and not just textbook entries, the monument to the Brothers Georgievi (placed in 1934) used to be a veritable<italic>milieu de mémoire.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95">95</xref>To didactic historians, probably the most widely distributed breed among the species, these figures stand as symbols of genuine patriotism and selfless charity to be admired and emulated. To contemporary students, their names mean very little, and few actually know anything about their lives and other exploits. If not entirely forgotten, their huge bronze images, “like seashells on the shore from which the sea of living memory has retreated,” tease the historical memory of college students who pass by them every morning. There is nothing exceptional or unexpected in this. As Reinhart Koselleck has remarked: “Memorials, like all works of art, have a surplus potential to take on a life of their own. For this reason, the original meaning of countless memorials is no longer recognizable without recourse to inscriptions or other empirically comprehensible reference signals.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96">96</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In some sense, the statues could have served as an appropriate, though ironic<italic>milieu de mémoire</italic>for the present moment. During the Communist decades bourgeois charity was despised as hypocritical, a means of soothing the guilty conscience of the wealthy. While the brothers Georgievi were celebrated during that period, they were seen as “patriots” and “revival figures,” if not quite revolutionaries, in contrast to today's emphasis on their role as “donors.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97">97</xref>After all, we are now in the era when the merchant and banker is seen as the social hero, not the revolutionary. After 1989, especially with the new “primary accumulation” of capital, one would have hoped, even expected, that charitable activities would be revived and that many would be directed toward education, but that is not happening—at least, not yet.</p>
         <p>Could perhaps my “Goethe‐Schiller” site have acquired some collective significance, at least as a sign or a name, since it utilizes a public historic monument and a monumental metaphor? Theoretically this is not impossible, although it is most unlikely, even as I make it public with this text. It may be borrowed, but it is too idiosyncratic, too ironic, too much a parody of conflated layers of historical memory from different national contexts to be turned successfully into a shared historical site and memory. This, of course, poses the question of the relationship between the personal and the collective.</p>
         <p>By no definitional stretch, except in the most conventional sense, can the pharmacy qualify as a<italic>lieu de mémoire.</italic>Yet, the pharmacy is the only one of these examples that, with its immediacy and its firsthand, not transmitted, significance, can be seen as a<italic>milieu de mémoire,</italic>albeit an individual one: my own. Of course, it can never become collective memory, if collective memory is individual memory shared by a significant number of people. The pharmacy is a<italic>lieu</italic>whose functions were always exclusively orientational, purely ones of convenience, without any symbolic value, and it is precisely symbolism that invests a place with some transcendent meaning.</p>
         <p>Yet, while this site cannot become one of collective experience, let alone collective memory, by subjecting it to this analysis I am dealing with it as a historical fact or place. In a different context, Susan Crane asked: “When is the personal historical?” She replied to her own question: “Whenever one is thinking about oneself historically.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98">98</xref>Crane herself was concerned primarily with the nature of historical consciousness as perceiving individually but signifying collectively and with the fine line running between autobiography and historiography. By both looking at myself as a historian describing and reflecting on a certain period and approaching myself as an agent of this period who is utilizing my own living memory as a historical source, I inevitably make some of the personal historical. For the duration of this text, at least, even the pharmacy assumes some historical meaning—metaphorically embodying, with its makeover from medical to clothing store, and with the physical although not functional presence of its former designation, the complex story of rupture and continuity between the Communist and post‐Communist era.</p>
         <p>The mausoleum, although there is no trace of it any longer, may still qualify as a<italic>lieu de mémoire,</italic>or, rather, a<italic>lieu de mémoire détruite,</italic>a curious site of destroyed memory with the preserved memory of the destruction. If it had not been blown up, it too would have still been a<italic>milieu de mémoire,</italic>given that it was erected within the living memory of several generations. Now, with its disappearance, it is but a phantom without even a trace of its existence to serve as a sign of memory—unless, as behooves the changing nature of our times, we designate the garden, the stalls of the<italic>Bierfest,</italic>and the opera stage constructions as the shifting signs of memory through which lurks the silhouette of the phantom structure.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99">99</xref>
         </p>
         <p>So, in the end, maybe the destroyers were correct. It is only by removing the sign altogether that one can assure the lifting of a site as<italic>milieu de mémoire</italic>or<italic>lieu de mémoire.</italic>Of course, this cannot happen immediately. For those with the living memory, it will not happen at all. For someone so closely entangled with the life of the mausoleum as its commandant Gergov, “in the evening, when the night falls on the adjacent buildings and the sky is clear, the silhouette of the mausoleum rises with the first stars. One can still see passersby leaving a bunch of flowers … to memory. One can destroy a building, with hatred one can even kill, but historical memory cannot be erased by any mortal.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100">100</xref>Well, actually it can. It can be and is being erased precisely by mortals, either physically or intellectually, because historical memory is itself the creation of mortals.</p>
         <p>But the mausoleum is alive even for those who have been indifferent to it or may have loathed it, as long as they belong to the generations that have seen it. A young twenty‐five‐year‐old architect in Sofia, Julia, laughingly tells her American colleague, pointing to the empty space: “The vacuum should contain the now vacant Georgi Dimitrov mausoleum.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101">101</xref>She had no strong feelings about it and was musing over the reasons for its demolition: maybe lack of public funding for renovation, maybe other urban plans, most likely a political gesture. She described herself as anti‐Communist, but she thought that there should be reconciliation between the past and the future and that there was no need for drastic exorcisms. Commenting on the demolition of monuments as well as on the renaming of cities and streets, Julia said she liked New York, where she and her boyfriend wanted to emigrate, “because all the streets are straight and there are only numbers and letters to remember.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102">102</xref>History becomes unbearable occasionally.</p>
         <p>The paradox is that the mausoleum was imposed in 1949 as a public symbol and barely existed as private thought. Today, it is physically excised from the public space but is present as an architectural specter in one's private spatial memory: “Let's meet at the mausoleum!”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103">103</xref>This will be the case until the generations that have seen it will themselves have passed away, and with them any trace of individual memory of the mausoleum will be demographically cleansed. This should bring at last the private and public closure of the mausoleum of Georgi Dimitrov in Sofia. Koselleck has remarked that “political experiences or messages can only be passed down beyond the death of a particular generation with great effort. To this end, societal institutions are required. In any case, the memorial, the supposed guarantor of sensory transmission beyond death, does not appear to be capable of achieving this task by itself. A conscious adoption of the message is always necessary.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104">104</xref>The demolishers seem to have overestimated the power of the memorial.</p>
         <p>To follow up on Koselleck, the centerpiece of the memory process is not the material object. The structure of King Mausolus at Halicarnassus has perished but its name has not, and many of us carry memories of its imagined reconstructed appearance from art and history textbooks. Examples can be added ad infinitum, but the objection rests not only on analogies. In contemporary work on memory, significant attention is also paid to the role of imagery. Until about a century ago, the dogma was that “memory is a present image within which one must discern pastness and valid indications of the past.” Philosophers like Wittgenstein, Ryle, and J. L. Austin demonstrated, however, that remembering has little to do with imagery: “The recall may leave us with images; images of the past need not have provided the recall.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105">105</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The act of the destroyers was based on a somewhat passé theory of memory. It presumed that by erasing the artifact, recall is prevented because there is no direct image—except, of course, for the generation where the image has left a trace. But the recall, as new research demonstrates, need not be produced by a literal trace; recall itself, prompted by a context—a book, a discussion, a thought—can produce an image.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106">106</xref>What is even more essential is the emotional component. In the absence of specific imagery, it is feelings that become essential in reliving the past. “So, while memory does not consist in a memory image, the existence of a complex interplay of image and affect in the processes of recall is important to the cluster of ideas brought together under memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107">107</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The mausoleum will remain as an image in the purview of the collective and personal memories of the generation that has seen it. It is likely to remain at least in the verbal memory of the next generation as one of the prime symbols of the period. After all, as Umberto Eco observed: “Language—like all semiotic systems—has the ability to render present what is not present.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108">108</xref>This is quite apart from the evaluative component of how we remember communism. Remembering communism, however, is not easily blown up with powder: the processes are far too complex and the stakes too high. One is tempted to conclude that one can remain skeptical about the success of Orwell's shredding machine. Oblivion cannot be imposed by decree.</p>
         <p>And yet again, one is compelled to add this qualification: at least for the near future, at least for a number of people. True, Umberto Eco has declared a putative<italic>ars oblivionalis</italic>(the art of forgetting) to be part of either the Department of Adynata or the Department of Impossibilia, containing the sciences that are historically impossible. Or, if we were seriously to consider it as a semiotic project, it might be part of the Department of Oxymoronica, containing sciences that are self‐contained and analytically impossible. For Eco, there can be no phenomenology of forgetting.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109">109</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Paul Ricoeur, in contrast, is one of a few philosophers who offer, however briefly, a phenomenology of forgetting, although he too voices skepticism about an<italic>ars oblivionalis</italic>on par with the<italic>ars memoriae.</italic>He distinguishes between three levels or approaches to memory and forgetting. These are obstructed memory and forgetting (<italic>l'oubli et la mémoire empêchée,</italic>on the level of the psychopathological), manipulated memory and forgetting (<italic>l'oubli et la mémoire manipulée,</italic>on the practical or instrumental level), and controlled memory and forgetting (<italic>l'oubli et la mémoire commandée/obligée,</italic>on the ethical‐political level).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn110">110</xref>In the last context, forgetting and pardoning are intrinsically linked through the problematic of the past: forgetting, to memory and fidelity to the past; pardoning, to culpability and reconciliation with the past. “Indeed, a happy forgetting is the horizon of the pacified memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn111">111</xref>Ricoeur further differentiates between forgetting through deletion and a more measured, reserved kind of forgetting, closely connected to the opposition between amnesia and amnesty. In considering amnesty as institutional forgetting, Ricoeur notes that it aims at reconciliation and civil peace.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn112">112</xref>In this sense one can hypothesize by analogy that persecution, punishment, and eradication, even if explicitly articulated as forgetting, may serve as institutional reminders but can also (sometimes consciously) exacerbate societal tensions.</p>
         <p>Eco, while dismissing what Harald Weinrich calls a lethatechnics (as the obverse counterpart to mnemotechnics), still allows for the possibility to forget “on account not of defect but of excess.” He gives the simple example of an assertion pronounced aloud: its meaning cannot be destroyed, but it can be distorted if another assertion is pronounced at the same moment and the two are superimposed. “There are no voluntary devices for forgetting, but there are devices for remembering badly; it is necessary to multiply the semiosis.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn113">113</xref>
         </p>
         <p>All the numerous proposals to convert the structure of the mausoleum into something with a different function were intuitively based on this semiotic rule: “One forgets not by cancellation but by superimposition, not by producing absence but by multiplying presences.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn114">114</xref>This could have been the only intelligent and effective strategy to transform the mausoleum of Georgi Dimitrov from a<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>into a<italic>lieu d'oubli.</italic>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn94">
               <label>94</label>
               <p>Max Deutscher, “Memory,” in<italic>Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy,</italic>ed. Edward Craig (New York, 1998), 296; Mark H. Ashcraft,<italic>Human Memory and Cognition</italic>(New York, 1994), 77–79, 352–53; Daniel L. Schacter,<italic>Searching for Memory: The Brain, the Mind, and the Past</italic>(New York, 1996), 163–76.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn95">
               <label>95</label>
               <p>“Pre‐Liberation period” is the matter‐of‐fact term with which the period before the secession of the autonomous Bulgarian Principality from the Ottoman Empire in 1878 is designated in Bulgarian historiography and everyday speech. It has the same status as<italic>ancien régime</italic>in French history. Dochka Kisyova‐Gogova, “Skuplturnite figuri na daritelite na Sofiiskiya universitet i tekniyat avtor,” in<italic>Daritelite: Evlogii i Khristo Georgievi,</italic>ed. Elka Drosneva (Sofia, 1998).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn96">
               <label>96</label>
               <p>Koselleck,<italic>The Practice of Conceptual History,</italic>324.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn97">
               <label>97</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>The Donors</italic>is the title of the excellent collection of scholarly articles dedicated to the 175th anniversary of Khristo's birth, the 170th anniversary of Evlogii's birth, and the 110th anniversary of Sofia University in 1995. Drosneva,<italic>Daritelite</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn98">
               <label>98</label>
               <p>Susan A. Crane, “(Not) Writing History: Rethinking the Intersections of Personal History and Collective Memory with Hans von Aufsess,”<italic>History and Memory</italic>8, no. 1 (1996): 22.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn99">
               <label>99</label>
               <p>I have borrowed the category “sign of memory” from an excellent article by Mikhail Yampolsky, “In the Shadow of Monuments: Notes on Iconoclasm and Time,” in<italic>Soviet Hieroglyphics: Visual Culture in Late Twentieth‐Century Russia,</italic>ed. Nancy Condee (Bloomington, IN, 1995), 101. He employs it when describing the nonexistent buildings of the Cathedral of Christ the Savior and the Palace of Soviets in Moscow—one demolished, the other never erected—and discussing how their phantom structures are inscribed into the swimming pool, which is transformed into a sign of memory.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn100">
               <label>100</label>
               <p>Gergov,<italic>Istinata za mavzoleya,</italic>6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn101">
               <label>101</label>
               <p>Elisabeth Dubin, “Ever Forget: A Story of Monumental Confusion in the Eastern Bloc,”<italic>Paranoia</italic>3, no. 3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.binginit.com/loudpaper/articles/ever_forget.html"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.binginit.com/loudpaper/articles/ever_forget.html</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn102">
               <label>102</label>
               <p>Ibid. Here the interesting issue of the frequent change of urban and rural place names is being raised. Yet clearly the changing of names and the changing of landmarks, despite being seemingly identical, evoke different emotional responses, although both have had a long historical tradition in all societies. Somehow the changing of names is accepted, no matter whether triumphantly or grudgingly. So is the changing function of a landmark, as long as it is still preserved. In both cases, the signifier is changed, but the signified stays. However, the signified's complete erasure is strongly and passionately contested, probably because of its imposing materiality.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn103">
               <label>103</label>
               <p>There is a comic poignancy in the expression “to meet behind the mausoleum,” because the garden behind the mausoleum was used during the Communist period as a meeting place for gay couples.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn104">
               <label>104</label>
               <p>Koselleck,<italic>The Practice of Conceptual History,</italic>324–25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn105">
               <label>105</label>
               <p>Deutscher, “Memory,” 297.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn106">
               <label>106</label>
               <p>As Christopher Winks perceptively observes: “Buildings and monuments can inspire leaps of memory and association, but they are not the stuff of which memory is made. That belongs to lived moments: a word, an encounter, a glance” (Winks, “Ruins and Foundation Stones,” 118).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn107">
               <label>107</label>
               <p>Ibid., 298. The field of memory studies is still underdeveloped, although most efforts today are concentrated in the direction of neurobiology. Some research circles have revived the ancient idea of a memory trace, which preserves the information received from experience. Only when there is activation of such a trace does the highly specific causal connection occur that is required for true remembering. Others contest this idea, based on the very little knowledge we have about the physiological processes involving the memory of specific events. They insist that memory is highly dispersed in alternative neural networks rather than encoded in specific brain cells.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn108">
               <label>108</label>
               <p>Umberto Eco, “An Ars Oblivionalis? Forget It!”<italic>Proceedings of the Modern Language Association</italic>103, no. 3 (May 1988): 258. Eco invokes the famous example given by Abelard—“nulla rosa est” (there is no rose, such a thing as a rose never existed)—that actually brings to mind the image of a rose. He also brings in the dialectic of contiguity and similarity, according to which “if object<italic>x</italic>has been in some way imagined to be in contact with object<italic>y,</italic>or if object<italic>x</italic>presents any sort of homology with object<italic>y,</italic>every time object<italic>x</italic>is evoked, object<italic>y</italic>will be as well” (254).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn109">
               <label>109</label>
               <p>Eco, “An Ars Oblivionalis? Forget It!” 254, 260. Eco does not deny natural and accidental forgetting, such as cases induced by drugs, cerebral trauma, or repression. But he maintains that there cannot be a conscious technique for forgetting on par with the memory techniques, because semiotics is “by definition a mechanism that presents something to the mind and therefore a mechanism for producing<italic>intentional</italic>acts … a device that stalls natural processes of oblivion” (259, 260).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn110">
               <label>110</label>
               <p>Ricoeur,<italic>La mémoire, l'histoire, l'oubli</italic>(Paris, 2000), 83–97, 575–89.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn111">
               <label>111</label>
               <p>Ibid., 536.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn112">
               <label>112</label>
               <p>Ibid., 586, 650–56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn113">
               <label>113</label>
               <p>Eco, “An Ars Oblivionalis? Forget It!” 259. Compare Harald Weinrich,<italic>Lethe: Kunst und Kritik des Vergessens</italic>(Munich, 1997).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn114">
               <label>114</label>
               <p>Ibid., 260. It was only at the last stages of correction of this manuscript that I learned about the work of Nikolai Voukov on the destruction of Dimitrov's mausoleum. While I find it an excellent contribution, Voukov's take on the event and its meaning is somewhat different than my own. I would like to express my gratitude to the author for sending me his manuscript, whose shorter version was published as “The Destruction of Georgi Dimitrov's Mausoleum in Sofia: The ‘Incoincidence' between Memory and Its Referents,” in<italic>Places of Memory,</italic>ed. Augustin Ioan, special issue of<italic>Octogon</italic>(Bucharest, 2003).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
