<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">afrijinteafriins</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100045</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Africa: Journal of the International African Institute</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00019720</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">17500184</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">40027294</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Authenticity Remodelled in West African Popular Religion</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Manimory and the Aesthetics of Mimesis: Forest, Islam and State in Ivoirian dozoya</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
                  <surname>Hellweg</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2006</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>76</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>i40001513</issue-id>
         <fpage>461</fpage>
         <lpage>484</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2006 International African Institute</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40027294"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article explores the hunting aesthetics of initiated Jula hunters of Côte d'Ivoire who call themselves dozos. It explains how their hunting aesthetic structures their relationship to Islam and the Ivoirian state. Although many Africans approach Islam in the context of tensions between local ritual traditions and modernizing Muslim reform, dozos approach Islam the way they approach the forests where they hunt, assimilating to both in order to tame them. They organize their hunting activities around an aesthetic centred on notions of sweetness and fullness; their contraries, difficulty and emptiness; and the process of mimetic transformation (shape-shifting) that mediates between these extremes. With these categories dozos assimilate themselves to and appropriate power from the forest to kill game. They also link themselves to pre-Qur'anic Muslim figures to legitimize themselves as Muslims. More recently, they tried to assimilate to the Ivoirian state to become a parallel police force. Stories of their tutelary spirit, Manimory, and the texts of their hunting songs, incantations, and epics encode diverse ways for dozos to relate to Islam, leaving room for dozos to eschew it as well. Their texts reveal a dynamic sense of history that defies classification in terms of tradition, modernity or postmodernity. /// Cet article examine l'esthétique de la chasse chez les chasseurs initiés julas de Côte d'Ivoire, qui se donnent le nom de dozos. Il explique comme leur esthétique de chasse structure leur rapport à l'islam et à l'État ivoirien. Alors que de nombreux Africains abordent l'islam dans le contexte de tensions entre traditions rituelles locales et réforme musulmane modernisatrice, les dozos abordent l'islam de la même manière qu'ils abordent les forêts dans lesquelles ils chassent, s'assimilant aux deux pour les maîtriser. Ils organisent leurs activités de chasse autour d'une esthétique centrée sur des notions de douceur et de plénitude, des notions contraires de difficulté et de vide, ainsi que sur le processus de transformation mimétique (métamorphose) qui assure la médiation entre ces extrêmes. Avec ces catégories, les dozos s'assimilent à la forêt et s'en approprient les pouvoirs pour tuer le gibier. Ils s'associent également à des figures musulmanes pré-coraniques pour se justifier en tant que musulmans. Plus récemment, ils ont essayé de s'assimiler à l'État ivoirien pour devenir une force de police parallèle. Les récits de leur esprit tutélaire, Manimory, ainsi que les textes de leurs chants de chasse, incantations et récits épiques codifient les différentes manières qu'ont les dozos de se situer par rapport à l'islam et qui leur laissent également latitude pour l'éviter. Leurs textes révèlent un sens dynamique de l'histoire qui défie la classification en termes de tradition, de modernité ou de postmodernité.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d41360e123a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d41360e130" publication-type="other">
Hellweg 2001,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d41360e137a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d41360e144" publication-type="other">
Hellweg 2001, 2004,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d41360e151a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d41360e158" publication-type="other">
Hellweg 2001, 2004,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d41360e174a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e178" publication-type="other">
Amselle, J.-L. 1985. 'Le Wahabisme à Bamako (1945-1985)', Canadian Journal
of African Studies 10 (2): 345-57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e188a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e192" publication-type="other">
Appadurai, A. 1996. Modernity at Large: cultural dimensions of globalization.
Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e202a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e206" publication-type="other">
Bassett, T. 2003. 'Dangerous pursuits: hunter associations (donzo ton) and
national politics in Côte d'Ivoire', Africa 73 (1): 1-30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e216a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e220" publication-type="other">
--- 2004. 'Containing the Donzow: the politics of scale in Côte d'Ivoire',
Africa Today 50 (4): 31-49.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e231a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e235" publication-type="other">
Boas, F. 1982. 'On alternating sounds', in George W. Stocking (ed.), A Franz
Boas Reader: the shaping of American anthropology, 1883-1911. Chicago:
University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e248a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e252" publication-type="other">
Boddy, J. 1989. Wombs and Alien Spirits: women, men, and the zar cult in the
Northern Sudan. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e262a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e266" publication-type="other">
Bourdieu, P. 1977. Outline of a Theory of Practice. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e276a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e280" publication-type="other">
Brenner, L. 1988. 'Concepts of tarīqa in West Africa: the case of Qādiriyya',
in Donal B. Cruise O'Brien and Christian Coulon (eds), Charisma and
Brotherhood in African Islam. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e293a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e297" publication-type="other">
--- 1933. 'Constructing Muslim identities in Mali', in Louis Brenner (ed.),
Muslim Identity and Social Change in Sub-Saharan Africa. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e310a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e314" publication-type="other">
Cashion, G. A. 1984. 'Hunters of the Mande: a behavioral code and
worldview derived from the study of their folklore, part 1'. Unpublished
PhD dissertation, Bloomington: Indiana University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e328a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e332" publication-type="other">
Cissé, Y. T. 1994. La Confrérie des chasseurs Malinké et Bambara: mythes, rites et
récits initiatiques. Ivry: Editions Nouvelles du Sud.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e342a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e346" publication-type="other">
Comaroff, J. 1985. Body of Power, Spirit of Resistance: the culture and history of
a South African people. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e356a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e360" publication-type="other">
Comaroff, J. and J. Comaroff. 1997. Of Revelation and Revolution: the dialectics
of modernity on a South African frontier. Vol. 2. Chicago: University of Chicago
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e373a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e377" publication-type="other">
--- 1999. 'Introduction', in John L. and Jean Comaroff (eds), Civil Society
and the Political Imagination in Africa. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e387a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e391" publication-type="other">
Conrad, D. 1995. 'Blind man meets prophet: oral tradition, Islam, and funé
identity', in David Conrad and Barbara Frank (eds), Status and Identity in
West Africa: nyamakalaw of Mande. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e404a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e408" publication-type="other">
Coote, J. 1996. 'Aesthetics is a cross-cultural category: for the motion', in Tim
Ingold (ed.), Key Debates in Anthropology. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e419a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e423" publication-type="other">
Crocker, C. 1977. 'The social functions of rhetorical forms', in J. David Sapir
and J. Christopher Crocker (eds), The Social Use of Metaphor: essays on the
anthropology of rhetoric. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e436a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e440" publication-type="other">
Derive, M. J. 1978. Bamori et Kowulen: chant de chasseurs de la région
d'Odienné. Abidjan: Institut de Linguistique Appliquée.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e450a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e454" publication-type="other">
Ellis, S. 1999. The Mask of Anarchy: the destruction of Liberia and the religious
dimension of an African civil war. New York: New York University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e464a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e470" publication-type="other">
--- 2003. 'International elements of West Africa's wars: the role of sub-
regional and non-African actors'. Unpublished paper from the OECD
conference, 'Conflict and development policy in the Mano River region
and Côte d'Ivoire: "The regional stakes for stability and reconstruction'".
Paris, 13-14 May. &lt;&lt;http://www.oecd.Org/dataoecd/19/0/33904967.pdf&gt;&gt;
accessed 14 November 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e493a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e497" publication-type="other">
Ferme, M. 2001a. 'La Figure du chasseur et les chasseurs - miliciens dans le
conflit sierra-léonais', Politique africaine 82: 119-32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e507a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e511" publication-type="other">
--- 2001b. The Underneath of Things: violence, history, and the everyday in Sierra
Leone. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e522a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e526" publication-type="other">
Ferme, M. and D. Hoffman. 2004. 'Hunter militias and the international
human rights discourse in Sierra Leone and beyond', Africa Today 50 (4):
73-95.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e539a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e543" publication-type="other">
Gausset, Q. 1999. 'Islam or Christianity? The choices of the Wawa and the
Kwanja of Cameroon', Africa 69 (2): 257-78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e553a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e557" publication-type="other">
Geurts, K. L. 2003. Culture and the Senses: bodily ways of knowing in an African
community. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e567a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e571" publication-type="other">
Gibb, H. A. R. 1982. Mohammedanism: an historical survey. London: Oxford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e581a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e585" publication-type="other">
Gow, P. 1996. 'Aesthetics is a cross-cultural category: against the motion', in
Tim Ingold (ed.), Key Debates in Anthropology. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e595a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e599" publication-type="other">
Grosz-Ngaté, M. 2002. 'Memory, power, and performance in the construction
of Muslim identity', Political and Legal Anthropology Review 25 (2): 5-20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e610a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e614" publication-type="other">
Hagberg, S. 1998. Between Peace and Justice: dispute settlement between Karaboro
agriculturalists and Fulbe agro-pastoralists in Burkina Faso. Uppsala: Acta
Universitatis Upsaliensis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e627a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e631" publication-type="other">
--- 2004. 'Political decentralization and traditional leadership in the Benkadi
hunters' association in western Burkina Faso', Africa Today 50 (4): 51-70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e641a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e645" publication-type="other">
Hale, T. 1998. Griots and Griottes: masters of words and music. Bloomington:
Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e655a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e659" publication-type="other">
Hardin, K. L. 1993. The Aesthetics of Action: continuity and change in a West
African town. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e669a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e673" publication-type="other">
Hellweg, J. 1997. 'Like the Leaves of the Trees: hunters stalk security in urban
Côte d'Ivoire', Anthropology Newsletter 38 (5): 61-2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e683a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e687" publication-type="other">
--- 2001. 'The Mande hunters' movement of Côte d'Ivoire: ritual, ethics, and
performance in the transformation of civil society, 1990-1997'. Unpublished
PhD dissertation, Charlottesville: University of Virginia.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e701a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e705" publication-type="other">
--- 2004 'Encompassing the state: sacrifice and security in the hunters'
movement of Côte d'Ivoire', Africa Today 50 (4): 3-28.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e715a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e719" publication-type="other">
Ibn 'Abd al Wahhāb, M. 1992. Kitāb al Tawhīd. Riyadh: International Islamic
Publishing House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e729a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e733" publication-type="other">
Jackson, M. 1990. 'The man who could turn into an elephant: shape-shifting
among the Kuranko of Sierra Leone', in Michael Jackson and Ivan Karp
(eds), Personhood and Agency: the experience of self and other in African cultures.
Uppsala: Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e749a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e753" publication-type="other">
Johnson, J. W. 1992. The Epic of Son-Jara: a west African tradition.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e763a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e767" publication-type="other">
Kaba, L. 1974. The Wahhabiyya. Evanston: Northwestern University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e774a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e778" publication-type="other">
Lambek, M. 1990. 'Certain knowledge, contestable authority: power and
practice on the Islamic periphery', American Ethnologist 17 (1): 23-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e789a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e793" publication-type="other">
--- 2002. 'Nuriaty, the saint and the sultan: virtuous subject and subjective
virtuoso of the postmodern colony', in Richard Werbner (ed.), Postcolonial
Subjectivities in Africa. London: Zed Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e806a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e810" publication-type="other">
Lanternari, V. 1963. The Religions of the Oppressed: a study of modern messianic
cults. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e820a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e824" publication-type="other">
Launay, R. 1992. Beyond the Stream: Islam and society in a west African
town. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e834a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e838" publication-type="other">
Leach, M. 2000. 'New Shapes to Shift: war, parks and the hunting person
in modern West Africa', Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute 6 (4):
577-95.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e851a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e855" publication-type="other">
LeBlanc, M. N. 2000. 'Versioning Womanhood and Muslimhood: "fashion"
and the life course in contemporary Bouaké, Côte d'Ivoire', Africa 70 (3):
442-81.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e868a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e872" publication-type="other">
Lévi-Strauss, C. 1966. The Savage Mind. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e880a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e884" publication-type="other">
Lewis, I. 1989. Ecstatic Religion: a study of shamanism and spirit possession.
Second edition. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e894a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e898" publication-type="other">
--- 1996. Religion in Context: cults and charisma. Second edition. Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e908a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e912" publication-type="other">
Makarius, L. 1969. 'Observations sur la légende des griots malinké', Cahiers
d'études africaines 4 (4): 626-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e922a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e926" publication-type="other">
Masquelier, A. 2001. Prayer Has Spoiled Everything: possession, power, and
identity in an Islamic town of Niger. Durham: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e936a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e940" publication-type="other">
Mbembe, A. 2001. On the Postcolony. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e947a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e951" publication-type="other">
McNaughton, P. 1982. 'The shirts that Mande hunters wear' African Arts 12
(2): 65-71, 91.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e962a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e966" publication-type="other">
--- 1988. The Mande Blacksmiths: knowledge, power, and art in West Africa.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e976a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e980" publication-type="other">
Morphy, H. 1996. 'Aesthetics is a cross-cultural category: for the motion', in
Tim Ingold (ed.), Key Debates in Anthropology. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e990a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e994" publication-type="other">
Mudimbe, V. Y. 1988. The Invention of Africa: gnosis, philosophy, and the order
of knowledge. London: James Currey.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1004a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1008" publication-type="other">
Niane, D. T. 1965. Sundiata: an epic of old Mali. Harlow: Longman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1015a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1019" publication-type="other">
Niezen, R. W. 1990. 'The "Community of Helpers of the Sunna": Islamic
reform among the Songhay of Gao (Mali)', Africa 60 (3): 399-424.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1029a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1033" publication-type="other">
Nyamnjoh, F. B. 2002. 'A child is one person's only in the womb:
domestication, agency and subjectivity in the Cameroonian Grassfields',
in Richard Werbner (ed.), Postcolonial Subjectivities in Africa. London: Zed
Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1050a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1054" publication-type="other">
Overing, J. 1996. 'Aesthetics is a cross-cultural category: against the motion',
in Tim Ingold (ed.), Key Debates in Anthropology. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1064a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1068" publication-type="other">
Person, Y. 1968. Samori, une révolution dyula. Volume I. Dakar: IFAN.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1075a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1079" publication-type="other">
Piot, C. 1999. Remotely Global: village modernity in West Africa. Chicago:
University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1089a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1093" publication-type="other">
Reed, D. 2003. Dan Ge Performance: masks and music in contemporary Côte
d'Ivoire. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1103a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1107" publication-type="other">
Ricœur, P. 1981. Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences, John B. Thompson
(ed.). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1117a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1121" publication-type="other">
Robinson, D. 2004. Muslim Societies in African History. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1132a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1136" publication-type="other">
Sahlins, M. 1981. Historical Metaphors and Mythical Realities: structure in the early
history of the Sandwich Islands kingdom. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1149a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1153" publication-type="other">
Sanneh, L. 1994. 'Translatability in Islam and in Christianity in Africa: a
thematic approach', in Thomas Blakely, Walter van Beek, and Dennis
Thomson (eds), Religion in Africa: experience and expression. London: James
Currey.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1169a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1173" publication-type="other">
Sapir, J. D. 1977. 'The anatomy of metaphor', in J. David Sapir and
J. Christopher Crocker (eds), The Social Use of Metaphor: essays on the
anthropology of rhetoric. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1186a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1190" publication-type="other">
Stoller, P. 1989a. Fusion of the Worlds: an ethnography of possession among the
Songhay of Niger. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1200a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1204" publication-type="other">
--- 1989b. The Taste of Ethnographic Things: the senses in anthropology.
Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1214a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1218" publication-type="other">
--- 1995. Embodying Colonial Memories: spirit possession, power, and the hauka
in West Africa. New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1229a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1233" publication-type="other">
Taussig, M. 1993. Mimesis and Alterity: a particular history of the senses. New
York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1243a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1247" publication-type="other">
Taylor, C. C. 1999. Sacrifice as Terror: the Rwandan genocide of 1994.
Oxford: Berg Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1257a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1261" publication-type="other">
--- 2004. 'Deadly images: king sacrifice, President Habyarimana, and the
iconography of pregenocidal Rwanda', in Neil Whitehead (ed.), Violence.
Santa Fe: School of American Research Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1274a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1278" publication-type="other">
Thoyer, A. 1995. Récits épiques des chasseurs bamanan du Mali. Paris:
L'Harmattan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1288a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1292" publication-type="other">
Traoré, K. 2004. 'The intellectuals and the hunters: reflections on the
conference, "La Rencontre des Chasseurs de l'Afrique de l'Ouest'", Africa
Today 50 (4): 97-111.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1305a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1309" publication-type="other">
Trimingham, J. S. 1959. Islam in West Africa. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1317a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1321" publication-type="other">
--- 1962. A History of Islam in West Africa. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1328a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1332" publication-type="other">
Triaud, J.-L. 1986. 'Abd al-Rahman l'Africain (1908-1957), pionnier et
précurseur du Wahhabisme au Mali', in Olivier Carré and Paul Dumont
(eds), Radicalismes islamiques II: Maroc, Pakistan, Inde, Yougoslavie, Mali.
Paris: L'Harmattan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1348a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1352" publication-type="other">
van Binsbergen, W. 1981. Religious Change in Zambia. London: Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1359a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1363" publication-type="other">
Wagner, R. 1978. Lethal Speech: Daribi myth as symbolic obviation. Ithaca
NY: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1373a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1377" publication-type="other">
--- 1991. 'The fractal person', in Maurice Godelier and Marilyn Strathern
(eds), Big Men and Great Men. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1387a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1391" publication-type="other">
Zemp, H. 1968. 'La légende des griots malinké', Cahiers d'études africaines 6
(4): 611-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d41360e1402a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d41360e1406" publication-type="other">
Zobel, C. 1996. 'Les génies du Kòma: identites locales, logiques religieuses et
enjeux socio-politiques dans les monts Manding du Mali', Cahiers d'études
africaines 144: 625-57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
