<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">iyyun</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50004970</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Iyyun: The Jerusalem Philosophical Quarterly / עיון: רבעון פילוסופי</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>החברה הפילוסופית בירושלים</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00213306</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23303155</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>THE IDEA OF REASON UNITY OF MANKIND AND DIGNITY OF MAN IN THE PHILOSOPHY OF JASPERS / תבונה, אנושות וערך האדם בפילוסופיה של יאספרס</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>אברהם חיים</given-names>
                  <surname>ליכטיגפלד</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>A.</given-names>
                  <surname>LICHTIGFELD</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1960</year>
      
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>1960</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>י"א</volume>
         <issue>א'/ב'</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23303150</issue-id>
         <fpage>67</fpage>
         <lpage>73</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/23303155"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Jaspers' thesis (while rejecting the claim of philosophers of the Western tradition to universal validity and Truth, yet conceding that their metaphysical systems express an awareness of Being) is as follows: "Reality is neither the object nor the subject, but that which encompasses both, the Encompassing which is illuminated in the division between subject and object"; He — the One God — is Encompassing and the greatest closeness which has its place within the inwardness of man". The whole inquiry leads Jaspers to claim that the existential self is rooted in Transcendence and the ground of all things lies in the real ization of the existential self in freedom in which eternity and time coalesce. In this freedom time — far from being the "moving image of eternity" — becomes the actual scene of the existential self's moral striving with the forces of this world, and by seizing the cipher (= the language of Transcendence) as the symbol of Transcendence, the existential self achieves authentic existence, thus endowing the historical process of time with unique and ultimate meaning. 1) Reason: It is because of reason with which God has endowed man that any content of a pretended revelation possesses any self-evidencing power: "In diesem Menschwerden durch Vernunft wird das Eine der Transzendenz fühlbar dem Einen der jeweils geschichtlichen Existenz". Yet by abandoning belief in universal Truth we become open for Truth, realised and determined in its concrete historic form for each individual by means of communication. Communication therefore becomes "the universal condition of man's being". It follows that Truth cannot be separated from communicability. It only appears in time as a realitythrough-communication so much so "that I can not even become myself alone without emerging out of my being with others". Now the element in which existential communication lives and moves and has its spiritual being is — reason ("reason is what penetrates everything"). 2) Unity of Mankind: The discovery of the unreality of man's existence apart from God, is the discovery at the same time of the fact that God is the ultimate ground of the unity of mankind. According to Jaspers the fact of life are to conform to the principle of that wider order of reality disclosed to us in the experience of communication in which the reality of each person's likeness to the image of God finds its practical application. The development of communication depends on the principle of correlation of Existenz and Transcendenz which is the property of no finite existential self, but manifests itself alike in all. Though we may be confronted with the question "Is it God or the devil who governs the world?", it remains equally true that even "failure is no argument against the truth that is rooted in transcendence". 3) Ultimate Dignity of Man: Jaspers' unequivocal emphasis on freedom, stating that "Freedom and God are inseparable" serves to assure this ideal its place in human society. Thus man's exercise of freedom knits him up into the transcendental design. The claim that certain facts and experiences yield a basis for the recognition of the ultimate dignity of man is justified precisely by this evidence that through God, as inseparable from freedom, we discern the ultimate significance of both man and humanity.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>heb</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>[הערות שוליים]</title>
         <ref id="d12756e132a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e139" publication-type="other">
*יין Η. Bergman, S. Maiaron's Philosophy, East and West Library, London, 1954,
p. 201.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e149a1310">
            <label>'</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e156" publication-type="other">
עיי! S. H. Bergman, Between East and West, East and West Library, 1959, p. 27</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e163a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e170" publication-type="other">
״מטרתה של הפינומנולוגיה היא השגת ידיעה מוחלטת על העולם, על ידי החריגה אל מעבר לכל
צורות ההסבר המקובלות״ עיין M. Faber, The Foundation of Phenomenology, Harvard
University Press, 1943, p. 547.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e183a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e190" publication-type="other">
P. A. Schilpp, The Philosophy of Karl Jaspers, Library of Living Philosophers, New
York, 1957, p. 790.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e201a1310">
            <label>s</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e208" publication-type="other">
K. Jaspers, Von der Wahrheit, quoted by J. I. Loewenstein in Schi pp's Jaspers-
Volume, p. 662.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e218a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e225" publication-type="other">
Schilpp's Jaspers-Voiume, p. 790 (תשובתו של יאספרס למבקרים)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e232a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e239" publication-type="other">
הצופן הוא לפי יאספרס לשונה של הטיאנסצנדנציה. עלינו להבחין אצל יאספרם בין שלושה מיני
לשון. לשונה הבלתי־אמצעית של הטראנסצנדנציה הנוכחת רק לגבי התודעה המחלטת של האכ0ים8נציה!
לשון זו נשמעת על־ידי הפרט בהתרחשות חד־פעמית מבחינה היפטורית, כלומר נלתי־חתדת. אקט
ההידברות מבוצע בלשון זו בדרך מכלילה: מי שהדיבור הופנה אליו פעם יכול להבינו גם עכשיו. הלשו
השנייה — זו של הידביות ציורית בין ׳אניים" אכסיסטנציאליים — מנתקת את עצמה ממקור ראשוני זה
ויוצרת תוכן בר־מסירה — סיפור, או דמות או תמונה,— של מר, שנראה תחילה כבלתי־ניתן־למפירה. מה
שהיה תחילה לשון הטראנסצנדנציה נעשה קניין משותף לכולם ויכול למלא מהדש—על־ידי התייחסות
למקור—את תפקידו המקורי. ולבסוף, אם החשיבה מכוונת למקורה של אותה לשון ציורית, עתידה זו
לבטא בהדרגה בצורת הספקולאציה המיטאפיסית את שאינו־ניתן־לידיעה, וליעשות ללשון שלישית —
לשונה של ההידברות הפילוסופית (עי יאספרס, שם, עמי 129 — 140, ויאספרס Von der Wahrheit
עמי 1030 ואילך) בהקשר זה חשוב להזכיר: בפענחנו את הצופן אין אנו תופשים מציאות הקיימת ללא
תלות בנו. הפיענוח תלוי תלות מהותית בכך שאני נעשה אכסיסטנציאלי. הווייתה של הטראנצנדנציה
כשאינה תלויה בי אינה נקנית לי בתור כזאת. קניין כזה חל על דברים של העולם הזה בלבד, ואילו
את הטראנסצנדנציה יכולים אנו לסגל לעצמנו רק במידה שאנו נעשים אנו־עצמנו. מה החושים
צריכים להיות במצב תקין על־מנת לחוש את המציאות הפיסית, אף האני, שהוא אכסיסטנציה־נכוח,
עליו להיות במצב בו הוא יוכל לפגוש בטראנסצנדנציה. הנה כי־כן, אם אני חיש מבחינה אכסיסטנ־
ציאלית לא אשמע את קול הטראנסצנדנציה. מטעם זה איני יכול לחדור לכוונת כתב הצופן על ידי
חקירה שכלית גרידא, כי אם־רק בהתווסף אליה חנועת החיים האכסיסטנציאליים. על־ידי עיצוב עצמי
בלבד הנני עומד על הטראנסצנדנציה של הצופן. פעניה של הצופן הוא איפוא פעולה פנימית.
יאפפרס מגיע לכלל מסקנה שלעולם אין ההווייה בתיר חירות יכולה ללבוש צורה קבועה בקיום
אמפירי. גורלה למעשה הוא כנראה זה, שבהגיעה אל מטרתה, עליה לפרוש מן הבמה. העובדה שרעיון
ההתמדה—בתור שהות אינסופית ותוקף אל־זמני— סופו להיכשל נעשית נקודת־המוצא לחירות המבטלת
את עצמה כל רגע, בתור קיום אמפירי. משום־כך נעשה הצופן של אותה התבדות לצופן מוחלט ופירושה
״להכיר את ההווייה האמיתית בתודעת כשלוננו״. (יאספרס, שם, עמי 237). אבל— כפי שטוען יאספרס—
כון הוא כמו־כן שבשלב זה נהפך חיוב הטראנסצנדנציה להבטחה של הקיום האמפירי, בהעניקו שלוות
נפש ששוב אינה יכולה להביא אכזבה.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e325a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e329" publication-type="other">
K.Jaspers, Einfiihrung In Die Philosophic, Artemis Verlag, Zurich, 1949, p. 85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e336a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e340" publication-type="other">
Schilpp, Philosophic, 1949, p. 67.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e347a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e354" publication-type="other">
Ewing, Reason And Emotion, Oxford University Press, p. 31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e362a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e369" publication-type="other">
Jaspers, Vernunft und Widervernunft. p. 37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e376a1310">
            <label>ls</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e383" publication-type="other">
Jaspers, The Perennial Scope of Philosophy, Routledge and Kegan Paul, London,
1950, p. 173.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e393a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e400" publication-type="other">
Jaspers, Einfiihrung etc., p. 45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e407a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e414" publication-type="other">
שם, עמי Λ3</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e421a1310">
            <label>״</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e428" publication-type="other">
עיין גם Vleeschauwer, L'evolution de la pensee Kantienne, F. A'cane, Paris, p. 134:
"Le sujet itant consider£ dans son conditionnement temporal, ses actes sont
physiquement, decerminees et soumis des lors aux conditions de la connaissance
des phdnomenes'; H. Arendt, Sechs Essays,.Lambert Schneider, Heidelberg, 1948,
(ρ.58/59 מגיע למסקנה כי 'Kant, als er den Menschen zura Herrn und Massstab des
Menschen machte, hat er ihn gleichzeitig zum Sklaven des Seins erniedrigt'.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e451a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e458" publication-type="other">
Jaspers, Einfiihrung, etc., p.45; see a. F. Heinemann, Jenseits Des Existentialismus,
pp. 142.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e469a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e476" publication-type="other">
Dewey, The Quest For Certainty, Allen andUnwin, London, pp.221 cf. Dufrenne
and Ricoeur, K. Jaspers, p. 356.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e486a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e493" publication-type="other">
Jaspers, Einfiihrung etc., p. 120</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e500a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e507" publication-type="other">
שם, עמי 19.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e513" publication-type="other">
"י שם, ע«׳</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e519" publication-type="other">
101. 21 שם,שם.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12756e526a1310">
            <label>״</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e533" publication-type="other">
שם, עמי 102.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e539" publication-type="other">
״ מם, עמי 103.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e545" publication-type="other">
״ שס, עמי «10.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d12756e552" publication-type="other">
״ שם, עמי Ϊ8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
