<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Stanley Cavell, Religion, and Continental Philosophy</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DAHL</surname>
               <given-names>ESPEN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253012029</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253012067</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253012066</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Espen Dahl</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz98c"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The American philosopher Stanley Cavell (b. 1926) is a secular Jew who by his own admission is obsessed with Christ, yet his outlook on religion in general is ambiguous. Probing the secular and the sacred in Cavell's thought, Espen Dahl explains that Cavell, while often parting ways with Christianity, cannot dismiss it either. Focusing on Cavell's work as a whole, but especially on his recent engagement with Continental philosophy, Dahl brings out important themes in Cavell's philosophy and his conversation with theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Why are the most unlikely people, including myself, suddenly talking about God?” Terry Eagleton asks, referring to the return of religion among intellectuals, in affirmation as well as criticism of it.¹ Stanley Cavell also has quite a bit to say about God, as attested by the very existence of this book. But since religion is notably not one of the topics on which Cavell’s fame as a thinker rests, it seems reasonable to count Cavell among the “unlikely people” Eagleton has in mind. Nonetheless, such a characteristic would be misleading. Cavell has not “suddenly” or recently started “talking about God”;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Modernism and Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Right from his entrance on the philosophical scene in the late 1960s, Stanley Cavell has insisted that philosophy is confronted with the same cultural problems, burdens, and commitments—collectively known as modernism—that confront art. From some moment during the nineteenth century, artistic conventions for representation and composition no longer seemed to be adequate bearers of contemporary expression; along with the corrosion of the given framework of conventions, the stable relation between artist and audience also became more fragile, at times broken. As Cavell sees it, this situation is mirrored in philosophy: after Kierkegaard, Nietzsche, and Wittgenstein, there is no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>The Ordinary Sublime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have argued that Cavell’s ambiguous relation to religion should be understood against a wider cultural backdrop of modernism. If religion and thus theology have become problematic yet not impossible, then we must expect such possibility to show up within what Cavell terms the ordinary. However, the ordinary does not provide the location for experiences of incontestable divine revelations, nor does it unfailingly offer clear criteria by which we can assess such experiences. Nevertheless, the ordinary must be so inhabited as to provide glimpses, events, or perspectives from which religious orientation can gain a foothold in our form of life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Acknowledging God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having presented Cavell’s openness toward the problem of religion, I now proceed to more theologically charged territory in order to explore some possibilities offered by Cavell’s philosophy. In doing so, I focus on one of Cavell’s signature concepts, namely acknowledgment. Although acknowledgment has a wide application in Cavell’s thinking—including our relation to the world, others, different modernist artistic media, and our own conditions as speaking animals—it was initially developed in response to the skeptical problem of other minds. Since the problem of other minds has remained at the center of Cavell’s concerns, and since this problem highlights features</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Skepticism, Finitude, and Sin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Acknowledgment is an interpretation of knowledge, Cavell insists, or perhaps an interpretation of what lies at the heart of any knowledge, entailing a certain sense of receptivity or responsiveness, a willingness to confess and reveal oneself in a practical and responsible reply to the other, the world, or as I have suggested, to God. But such acknowledgment presupposes a separation from that which one responds to, or more generally, it presupposes finitude. Central to Wittgenstein’s philosophy, and thus also to Cavell’s own philosophy, is therefore the acknowledgment of human limitation, an acknowledgment that, however, seems hard to achieve. A significant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Tragic Dimension of the Ordinary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the Augustinian tradition, original sin is something that we are responsible for and hence guilty of, yet in another sense it is a destiny that befalls us. At stake is hence a fine balance between necessity and freedom, between personal guilt and delivery to destructive structures. Accordingly, acknowledging sin takes a personal sense of the I, confessing or revealing itself as the originator of deeds and speech, while acknowledging that this I is indebted—for better and for worse—to the inheritance of and continuous participation in a form of life that bestows coherence to those deeds and utterances.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The Other and Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whereas the previous chapter elaborated what might be thought of as a destiny to which we must be answerable, I now turn to another, more active face of skepticism or sin, namely violence. What is the connection between violence and my relation to the other? How can the motives behind violence be understood, and how is it entangled with religion? Levinas’s understanding of how violence is bound up with the face of the other provides a rich phenomenological account, one that I believe can be supplemented with Cavell’s subtle understanding of its motivation.</p>
                     <p>Despite the fact that Levinas and Cavell</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Forgiveness and Passivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous three chapters, I have attempted to outline what I have sometimes called an anthropology of finitude. The basic findings seemed less than cheerful, such that we are finite and mortal and yet revolt against our conditions (chapter 4), that we are vulnerable to tragic consequences because we speak and act in ways that outrun our previews (chapter 5), and that we, confronted with the otherness of the other, harbor violent impulses (chapter 6). If one holds these considerations together, one reaches a reasonable backdrop of what makes forgiveness important to human affairs—that is, why humans stand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Last Question: Self-redemption or Divine Redemption?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this book I have tried to elaborate the analogies and overlappings between Cavell’s philosophy and his religious perspective, either expressed philosophically or theologically. If such an undertaking might be deemed risky, it is because of Cavell’s own repeated resistance toward certain Christian depictions of the human state as helpless, fixed, awaiting supernatural aid, pursuing untimely theologizing, and the like. This resistance has been emphasized by his commentators and has often been taken as Cavell’s prevalent attitude. Especially in chapter 1 but also in the subsequent chapters, I have tried to oppose such interpretations—not because they are wrong (indeed,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz98c.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
