<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Descartes Otherwise: Blind, Mad, Dreamy, and Bad</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lee</surname>
               <given-names>Kyoo</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823244843</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823250493</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x0b2f"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Focusing on the first four images of the Other mobilized in Descartes' Meditations--namely, the blind, the mad, the dreamy, and the bad--Reading Descartes Otherwise casts light on what have heretofore been the phenomenological shadows of "Cartesian rationality." In doing so, it discovers dynamic signs of spectral alterity lodged both at the core and on the edges of modern Cartesian subjectivity. Calling for a Copernican reorientation of the very notion "Cartesianism," the book's series of close, creatively critical readings of Descartes' signature images brings the dramatic forces, moments, and scenes of the cogito into our own contemporary moment. The author patiently unravels the knotted skeins of ambiguity that have been spun within philosophical modernity out of such cliches as "Descartes, the abstract modern subject" and "Descartes, the father of modern philosophy"--a figure who is at once everywhere and nowhere. In the process, she revitalizes and reframes the legacy of Cartesian modernity, in a way more mindful of its proto-phenomenological traces.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES AND ABBREVIATIONS FOR THE WORKS OF DESCARTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PREAMBLE I</label>
                     <title>If Descartes Remains Overread and Underexplored …</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has been almost a decade—or two if I keep counting.</p>
                     <p>Reading, or otherwise sitting on, the work of René Descartes (March 31, 1596–February 11, 1650) with the quiet plea sure I see in a g(r)azing cow, I have been savoring, and saving somewhere, this nagging thought: His philosophy—his “Cartesianism,” his “rationalism,” his “methodological” doubt, his theoretical “self-centeredness,” his historicized him-ness—seems to remain overread and underexplored. I have been sensing that something else is going on, too, in those usual pages, in that familiar picture. And here, I am inviting you, my readers, to read with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PREAMBLE II</label>
                     <title>Descartes Needs Rereading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me flip open Descartes again.</p>
                     <p>My mind seems to have been actively suspended by certain constantly slippery gaps and cinematic interplays between the memory of my own first unschooled encounter with Descartes, the shock of the<italic>Meditations</italic>(1641) on the one hand, and the usual scholarly scenes of interpretation, or scholastic “filters” around that philosophical time bomb, on the other. As John Carriero put it,</p>
                     <p>CAN SOMEONE today take up a work of philosophy written over 350 years ago and engage with it on its own terms? This book is an attempt to do so with Descartes’<italic>Meditations concerning</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A STAGE SETUP:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reframing “Jeux Descartes”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where is René Descartes today—one who “lived, thought and died”?¹</p>
                     <p>“Descartes, a French national icon,”² once an epochal<italic>wunderkind</italic>and now nearly indistinguishable from the history of reading him, is for many scholars today a poster boy or a whipping boy, a hero or a villain: a “solipsist,” “narcissist,” “rationalist,” “idealist,” “reductionist,” “deductivist,” “dualist,” “closeted skeptic/atheist/materialist,” and so on. Biographically, compositionally, geographically, historically, politically, psychoanalytically, scientifically, theologically (etc., etc., etc.), he remains a fascinatingly troubling source for and a manifold index to modern philosophy and beyond. Everyone, thinker or not, as long as he or she is thinking, readily</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SCENE 1</label>
                     <title>Blind Vision:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Photographic Touch</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Indeed, “how easy it is to be mistaken” (<italic>s’y tromper</italic>) (O, 6:147/113), how easy it is to see<italic>that</italic>truth: “How crystal clear everything would be in our philosophy if only we would exorcise these specters, make illusions or objectless perceptions out of them, brush them to one side of an unequivocal world!”¹ That is, Merleau-Ponty and I fantasize with Descartes, whose “<italic>Dioptrics</italic>is an attempt to do just that.”²</p>
                     <p>To have “clear and distinct” perceptions or ideas—to guard ourselves against falsities or fantasies as Descartes recommends—seems relatively easy. Tricky is the attempt itself.</p>
                     <p>For some evidence, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SCENE 2</label>
                     <title>Elastic Madness:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Allegorical Comedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I know myself—save that knowledge.</p>
                     <p>In the four-page opening passage of chapter 2 of the<italic>History of Madness</italic>¹ and later in the essay “My Body, This Paper, This Fire,”² Michel Foucault launched a point-by-point self-defense against Derrida. Previously, in his forty-six page essay “The<italic>Cogito</italic>and the History of Madness,”³ Derrida had pointed to some traces of Cartesianism ironically but unwittingly enacted by Foucault.</p>
                     <p>In that madness chapter of the<italic>History of Madness</italic>, Foucault advances an insightful point on Descartes’ thought-experiment in question, a passage that anyone who has taken Modern Philosophy 101 would readily recognize, perhaps too quickly.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SCENE 3</label>
                     <title>Philopoetic Somnambulism:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Imaginary Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An insatiable appetite for life: With this, we might understand, at least in part, why one dreams.</p>
                     <p>By “dream,” I mean both the projective kind, futural, as in “my dream is to become an American Idol,” and the retrospective kind, nocturnal, as in “I was a Kafka in my dream last night.” Either way, the dreamer can imagine, think, otherwise. For dream is an excess and a necessary excess that shapes desire. It knows neither bounds nor depths. Fulfilled, it immediately generates a higher level of<italic>telos</italic>from within (e.g., Now I should become a Global Idol); interpreted, it leads</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SCENE 4</label>
                     <title>Cornered Reflection:</title>
                     <subtitle>With and around an Evil Genius</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“I don’t believe in God but I miss him,” says Julian Barnes.¹ “I don’t believe he exists but I dislike him anyway,” says Wendy Lesser.² While working on a project, the completion of which seems to take much longer than expected, Descartes says to his fiend Mersenne, “I too am too much in love with the fable of my<italic>World</italic>to give it up if God lets me live long enough to finish it; but I cannot answer for the future” (C, 1:179/3:28).</p>
                     <p>Why “but”? That is the question; explored here is a Cartesian version of those more or less</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0b2f.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
