<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1995 .F457545 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Motion picture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Film as Philosophy</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Herzogenrath</surname>
               <given-names>Bernd</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>EDITOR</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781517900519</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781452953458</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1452953457</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1mmft20"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Film and philosophy have much in common, and books have been written on film and philosophy. But can films be, or do, philosophy? Can they "think"?<italic>Film as Philosophy</italic>is the first book to explore this fascinating question historically, thematically, and methodically.</p>
         <p>Bringing together leading scholars from universities across the globe,<italic>Film as Philosophy</italic>presents major new research that leads film studies and philosophy into a productive dialogue. It provides a uniquely sweeping, historical overview of the confluence of film and philosophy for more than a century, considering films from Jean Renoir, Lars von Trier, Jørgen Leth, David Lynch, Michael Haneke, and others; the written works of filmmakers who also theorized on the medium, including Sergei Eisenstein and Jean Epstein; and others who have written on cinema, including Hugo Münsterberg, Béla Balázs, André Bazin, Henri Bergson, Gilles Deleuze, Stanley Cavell, Alain Badiou, Jacques Rancière, and many more.</p>
         <p>Representing a major step toward establishing a media philosophy that puts the status, role, and function of film into a new perspective,<italic>Film as Philosophy</italic>removes representational techniques from the center of inquiry, replacing these with the medium's ability to "think." Hence it accords film with "agency," and the dialogue between it and philosophy (and even neuroscience) is negotiated anew.</p>
         <p>Contributors: Nicole Brenez, U of Paris 3-Sorbonne; Elisabeth Bronfen, U of Zurich; Noël Carroll, CUNY; Tom Conley, Harvard U; Angela Dalle Vacche, Georgia Institute of Technology; Gregory Flaxman, U of North Carolina, Chapel Hill; Alex Ling, Western Sydney U; Adrian Martin, Monash U; John Ó Maoilearca, Kingston U, London; Robert Sinnerbrink, Macquarie U, Sydney; Murray Smith, U of Kent, Canterbury; Julia Vassilieva, Monash U, Melbourne; Christophe Wall-Romana, U of Minnesota; and Thomas E. Wartenberg, Mount Holyoke College.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Film and/as Philosophy: AN ELECTIVE AFFINITY?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herzogenrath</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Media and thinking are intimately related. Our memory, perception, and cognition are not just a given, as weightless, immaterial processes taking place purely mentally behind the walls of our skull, but also always already rest on a medial basis. As Nietzsche claims, “Our writing equipment takes part in the forming of our thoughts” (Unser Schreibzeug arbeitet mit an unseren Gedanken).¹ From here we can derive the media-philosophical insight that a new medium makes us think differently. Media thus reveal themselves as the body or, better, the different bodies of thought. It is important to note these bodies are not retroactive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Striking Poses:</title>
                     <subtitle>GESTURE, IMAGE, AND REMAKE IN THE CINEMATIC BERGSON</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maoilearca</surname>
                           <given-names>John Ó</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to Gilles Deleuze, “Cinema is Bergsonian.”¹ Despite the fact that Henri Bergson critiques the cinematographic mechanism in his magnum opus,<italic>Creative Evolution</italic>(on account of its movement being one<italic>applied</italic>to still images rather than being immanent to them), Deleuze correctly realizes how central the moving image nonetheless is to Bergson’s philosophy. Yet this is clear in Bergson’s own testimonies: “When I first saw the cinematograph I realized it could offer something new to philosophy. Indeed we could almost say that cinema is a model of consciousness itself. Going to the cinema turns out to be a philosophical experience.”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Hugo Münsterberg, Film, and Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sinnerbrink</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is ironic that Hugo Münsterberg, one of the pioneering intellectual figures in the history of film theory and the philosophy of film, was ignored for the best part of a century, a period during which cinema developed into the defining art form of modern times. Even more striking is that his approach to film theory, already a century ago, was thoroughly steeped in philosophical reflection on the psychological, aesthetic, and cultural significance of the new medium. As a Harvard professor of psychology and philosophy, Münsterberg published<italic>The Photoplay: A Psychological Study</italic>(1916), a book widely regarded as the first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Different, Even Wholly Irrational Arguments:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE FILM PHILOSOPHY OF BÉLA BALÁZS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent roundtable discussion organized and published by the highbrow American art magazine<italic>October</italic>on the topic of a current return to the archives of classical film theory, the scholar Anton Kaes asks a good, provocative question:</p>
                     <p>How do we actually define classical film theory? Is it really a unified, coherent body of texts that can be set against contemporary film theory? Are the theories of [Siegfried] Kracauer, [Walter] Benjamin, [Béla] Balázs, [Rudolf] Arnheim, and [André] Bazin “classical film theory”?¹</p>
                     <p>Kaes cites Balázs’s<italic>Visible Man</italic>from 1924 as a significant instance of the lively disruption of the concept of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>This Is Your Brain on Cinema:</title>
                     <subtitle>ANTONIN ARTAUD</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Flaxman</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poet and critic, sometimes surrealist and sublime schizophrenic, Antonin Artaud has been the subject of vastly greater posthumous interest than he ever enjoyed during his relatively short life. His fame derives primarily from his poetry, plays, letters, and essays—above all, from the revolutionary Theater of Cruelty he developed “to restore a passionate and convulsive conception of life” to the stage.³ Still, his writings acquired a significant readership only after he died, alone in a psychiatric clinic, in 1948.⁴ Thus, Artaud was as much discovered as rediscovered in the subsequent decades, when the initial publication of the<italic>Oeuvres complètes</italic>introduced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>From Lyrosophy to Antiphilosophy:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE THOUGHT OF CINEMA IN JEAN EPSTEIN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wall-Romana</surname>
                           <given-names>Christophe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean Epstein (Warsaw 1897 to Paris 1953) was a cinephile, poet, writer, filmmaker, and philosopher of the cinema. Not only was he among the few in the silent era to consider cinema as an object for thought—a daring position in those days—but he espoused the more radical view that it altered experience, thinking and philosophy, generating an original, nonhuman mode of thinking about the universe: an antiphilosophy. It is fair to say the questions of whether and how radically cinema might change our thought were first posed in earnest and depth by Epstein.</p>
                     <p>Arguably the most innovative director</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Montage Eisenstein:</title>
                     <subtitle>MIND THE GAP</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vassilieva</surname>
                           <given-names>Julia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The artist may be known rather by what he omits,” as Eisenstein quotes Schiller in a diary entry dated June 20, 1947, almost exactly six months before his death in February 1948.¹ The quotation might strike us as incongruous, coming from the master who was never shy to voice his opinion or illustrate his points—in both his directorial work and his theoretical commentaries. Yet at this late stage of his career, Eisenstein becomes preoccupied with the issue of what he termed “great nothingness”—the opposite, the emptiness, the nonidentity against which we can define what is present and given.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>André Bazin’s Film Theory and the History of Ideas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vacche</surname>
                           <given-names>Angela Dalle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>André Bazin was influenced by many philosophical figures. This range of influences was no gratuitous eclecticism. Rather, it stemmed from Bazin’s need to develop a critical discourse that would address the impure ontology of the cinema. Because the medium involves nature and culture, it perforce requires insights into art, religion, science, and technology. Without a doubt, the history of philosophy helped Bazin bring together all these dimensions, even if he seldom identified his sources. As a critic he did not seek a perfect fit between his overall film theory and a single philosopher. Bazin never mentioned the names of Saint</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Strange Topologics:</title>
                     <subtitle>DELEUZE TAKES A RIDE DOWN DAVID LYNCH’S LOST HIGHWAY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herzogenrath</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cinema thinks. Film is a medium of philosophical investigation and exploration. Propositions such as these distinguish Gilles Deleuze from most other film philosophers, granting film an<italic>immanent</italic>power of thinking much at odds with the idea that film and philosophy are totally different (and sometimes opposed) disciplines, with one (film) at best able to illustrate the ideas and doctrines of the other (philosophy). Although this essay is not the place to fully zoom in on Deleuze’s two cinema books (<italic>Cinema 1: The Movement-Image</italic>and<italic>Cinema 2: The Time-Image</italic>),¹ I would like to refer first to some basic ideas of these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Hurray for Hollywood:</title>
                     <subtitle>PHILOSOPHY AND CINEMA ACCORDING TO STANLEY CAVELL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bronfen</surname>
                           <given-names>Elisabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his essay “The Thought of Movies,” seeking to explain how he, as a philosopher, came to start thinking about Hollywood films, Stanley Cavell turns the question around to ask instead: “How is it that someone whose education was as formed by going to the movies as by reading books, gets to thinking about philosophy professionally?”¹ Taking his own autobiography as point of departure, he explains that for his father, an uneducated immigrant from eastern Europe, and his mother, who was a prominent pianist in Atlanta, the movies they went to weekly with their son were the most reliable source</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Thinking Cinema with Alain Badiou</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ling</surname>
                           <given-names>Alex</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alain Badiou is, by any measure, one of the most original and exciting voices in continental philosophy today. His ambitious project (which involves not only a wholesale rethinking of ontology and phenomenology but also a radical reconfiguring of the place of philosophy itself ) has moreover gained considerable currency in Anglophone academia in recent years. While the inaugural English translation of one of his books only appeared comparatively recently, in 1999, the uptake of his philosophy since then has been swift indeed, and today, a very respectable (and ever-increasing) number of Badiou’s works are available in English, together with numerous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Thinking as Feast:</title>
                     <subtitle>RAYMONDE CARASCO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brenez</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicole</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary and cinematic work of the French philosopher and filmmaker Raymonde Carasco-Hébraud (1939–2009) comprises a thorough analysis of the theoretical and practical circulations, intersections, and interrelations between verbal and audiovisual thinking. Author of sixty articles and three books, two published during her lifetime and one posthumously; editor of two collected volumes; and codirector, with her husband, Régis Hébraud, of sixteen films in both 16 mm and 35 mm, Carasco is perhaps the only professional philosopher to have created such an extensive literary and cinematic body of work. Some overlap between filmmakers and philosophers does exist. Jean-François Lyotard made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Rancière’s Film Theory as Deviation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Conley</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If it existed in French, the word that follows might be called a portmanteau fashioned from<italic>cartography</italic>and<italic>deviation</italic>:<italic>écartographies</italic>. The neologism would designate a mix of theory and interpretive practice that could be described as a mapping of errant reflection. Steeped in Hegel and Marx and trained in dialectics, Jacques Rancière studies phenomena that an egalitarian ethic compels him to call into question or for which, in the interest of the ethics of investigation, he would wish that a critical distance or even dissentient position be taken. Disagreement, what he calls<italic>dissensus</italic>, prods the drive for equality: Where he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Movie-Made Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carroll</surname>
                           <given-names>Noël</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Currently, the philosophy of the moving image is flourishing. It has already spawned a number of subfields. First, there is what might be thought of as “the philosophy<italic>of</italic>the moving image proper”—the domain of inquiry where the classic questions of philosophy, including those of ontology, epistemology, and ethics, are applied to the case of the moving image. Philosophers<italic>of</italic>the moving image proper, for example, ask, What is the moving image? Can documentary motion pictures be objective? and Can evil films, like<italic>The Triumph of the Will</italic>, nevertheless, at the same time, be aesthetically excellent?</p>
                     <p>However, coexisting with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>“Not Time’s Fool”:</title>
                     <subtitle>MARRIAGE AS AN ETHICAL RELATIONSHIP IN MICHAEL HANEKE’S AMOUR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wartenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Amour</italic>(2012) is the latest in a series of films made by the Austrian director Michael Haneke that center on a couple whose partners are Georges and Anne. The films are not in any sense sequels, since despite sharing the same names, the characters in the different films are not different versions of the same people, a fact indicated, for example, by the different actors playing them, the different professions they have, and the very different circumstances in which they live. Nonetheless, it is fair to say that the films do exhibit a certain unity, for each film focuses on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Experience and Explanation in the Cinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Murray</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>306</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the beginning, cinema has been held up as a unique medium partly by virtue of the kind of attention it seems to demand. Appreciating a film involves a special combination of perception, cognition, imagination, and emotion. Cinema engages us across a wider range of our embodied mental capacities than any other medium of representation, extending from low-level reflexes to abstract reflection. Cinema engages not only our visual and auditory senses, in a direct fashion, but also our senses of touch and balance and, perhaps, even those of taste and smell, in an indirect fashion. Films can physically startle and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mmft20.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
