<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D804.348.G6513 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939–1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939–1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Personal narratives</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World War, 1939–1945</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Personal narratives</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jews</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Diaries</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Trauma in First Person</book-title>
         <subtitle>Diary Writing during the Holocaust</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GOLDBERG</surname>
               <given-names>AMOS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">Translated from Hebrew by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SERMONETA-GERTEL</surname>
               <given-names>SHMUEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GREENBERG</surname>
               <given-names>AVNER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253029744</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253030214</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253030218</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Amos Goldberg</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz15p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What are the effects of radical oppression on the human psyche? What happens to the inner self of the powerless and traumatized victim, especially during times of widespread horror? In this bold and deeply penetrating book, Amos Goldberg addresses diary writing by Jews under Nazi persecution. Throughout Europe, in towns, villages, ghettos, forests, hideouts, concentration and labor camps, and even in extermination camps, Jews of all ages and of all cultural backgrounds described in writing what befell them. Goldberg claims that diary and memoir writing was perhaps the most important literary genre for Jews during World War II. Goldberg considers the act of writing in radical situations as he looks at diaries from little-known victims as well as from brilliant diarists such as Chaim Kaplan and Victor Klemperer. Goldberg contends that only against the background of powerlessness and inner destruction can Jewish responses and resistance during the Holocaust gain their proper meaning.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="306"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>“If This Is a Man”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his homily for<italic>Shabbat Shuvah</italic>5702 (27 September 1941), delivered in the Warsaw ghetto (and transcribed after the conclusion of that same Sabbath), Rabbi Kalonymus Kalman Shapira, the Rebbe of Piaseczno, wrote the following:</p>
                     <p>We said the following on the holy Sabbath: [Before the holiday] I thought that with trou bles such as these, when Rosh Hashanah [the Jewish new year] would come, the sound of our prayers would be tumultuous and that our hearts would pour out to God like a stream of water. . . . Nevertheless our eyes are witness to the fact that before the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>HOLOCAUST DIARIES:</title>
                     <subtitle>Between Life Story and Trauma</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Humans are storytelling creatures. We tell stories throughout our lives—about ourselves, our families, our communities, our past, and our future. Some stories we tell aloud to others and some we tell to ourselves, within the confines of our own consciousness. Through the stories we tell about ourselves, we constitute our identities because it is through our stories that we organize the events of our lives—disparate in time and place—into a coherent form. For example, stories allow us to create a causal relationship between different events, or to make certain events central and others secondary. The story is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>READING THE DIARIES AS A CRITIQUE OF HOLOCAUST HISTORIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction, we saw that Leni Yahil (1964), as well as other historians and thinkers, considered the “ image of man” during the Holocaust the central question with which scholarship of the period must contend. As noted, Yahil claimed, “the main thing that prompts us to study history—even of the distant past, but certainly in the case of the Holocaust—is the problem of the figure of man. . . . It is, therefore, inconceivable that research of the Holocaust period would not focus primarily on man, evaluating human actions and be havior.”¹ In reality, however, historical research</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE DYNAMIC OF THE TEXT BETWEEN THE TWO DEATHS:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Theoretical Model for the Reading of Traumatic Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is, to a large extent, the theoretical heart of the entire book. Here I propose a semiotic model for understanding the dynamic of autobiographical writing during the course of per sis tent, brutal, and massive trauma, as experienced by victims of the Holocaust and other events of mass vio lence and harsh discrimination. The model I have used is based on concepts borrowed from the work of the French psychoanalyst Jacques Lacan, which may not be intuitive to some readers, but which I have sought to make accessible even to those who are not conversant with this discourse.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>THE LIFE STORY OF VICTOR KLEMPERER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part II is dedicated to the reading of the diaries kept by Victor Klemperer in Dresden during the Nazi years focusing on the temporal experience, as reflected during the course of the protracted traumatic event. As we shall see, the autobiographical structure of time that underlies these diaries underwent a fundamental disruption but was reorganized in a very different way in the context of documentary writing. In order to understand the disruptions in Victor Klemperer’s life story during the Nazi period, and the way in which the story took shape in his diaries, we must first devote a few words</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE DISRUPTION OF LIFE-STORY TIME IN THE KLEMPERER DIARIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>September 1944 was a relatively calm month for the remaining Jews of Dresden. The deportations had stopped, incidents of blatant violence had decreased, and Germany’s defeat seemed certain. On 14 September, Klemperer found the peace of mind to write a sort of reflective summary of past events. The entry begins with encouraging reports of the Allies’ progress on the various fronts. In this context, he describes how his friend and neighbor at the Jews’ House, Neumark, found a newspaper from 1943, in which a series of reports all point to the military and political collapse of Germany. After noting some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>FROM AUTOBIOGRAPHICAL TO DOCUMENTARY DIARY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I will suggest that in the wake of the breakdown of autobiographical temporality, as described in the previous chapter, a new temporal order emerged, deeply connected to the documentary character of the Naziera diary. Before reaching this conclusion, however, the chapter will take a rather long detour. The first parts of the chapter are dedicated to depicting the radical transformation that Klemperer’s diaries underwent—from the personal-autobiographical to the documentary—the far-reaching ramifications of which will be described at length. Only in the last part of the chapter will I return to the issue of temporality, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>CHAIM KAPLAN AND HIS DIARY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part III focuses on the war time diary of the Warsaw Jew Chaim Aron Kaplan. Kaplan’s diary, written in Hebrew, covers the period from the Nazi invasion of Poland on 1 September 1939, when Kaplan was age fifty-nine, until 4 August 1942, a few days before he was deported to Treblinka. The following chapters discuss the complex relations that the diary reveals between the writer, a Jewish victim; Nazism; and the Nazis, his persecutors (in other words, between the Jewish “I” and the Nazi “Other”).¹ Kaplan’s war diary was a continuation of the diary that he had begun keeping in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>THE JEWS AND NAZI “LAW”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 8 January 1940, Chaim Kaplan asserted in his diary: “Nazism cancelled all law and justice; in particular, with regard to the Jews who have been excluded from all legal jurisdiction. . . . When one born of a ‘low race’ is brought before Nazi justice, he is judged not on the basis of the law that applies to every one, but on the basis of ‘judicial sentiment.’”¹ This notion is anything but unusual in the diary. Unlike most other Warsaw Jewish diarists, Kaplan was obsessed with understanding the Nazis and Nazism. He was haunted and preoccupied by their evil</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>BETWEEN PERPETRATORS AND VICTIMS:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Gray Zone of consciousness in the diary of chaim Kaplan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 18 May 1941, Chaim Kaplan wrote in his diary: “Nazism came to annihilate us. It is the enemy of Judaism in its spirit and in its practice. We fight it and await its defeat. However—the human spirit is inexplicable.<italic>Unconsciously, we accept its ideology and follow in its ways. Nazism has conquered our entire world.</italic>It severely damages our public life. And yet we do not cease to declare day and night that it is ugliness and that one ought to distance oneself from it.”¹ This startling passage deserves close examination. As perhaps the keenest observer of ghetto</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Believing she had succeeded in recovering from the traumas of her life, Anaïs Nin wrote the following in her diary: “Stories are the only enchantment possible, for when we begin to see our suffering as a story, we are saved.”¹ These words reflect the optimistic approach to the power of stories to deliver the victim from the suffering of trauma. Nin refers both to fictional writing and to autobiographical, diary writing. There are situations, however, in which narrative appears to lack sufficient power—situations in which the force of shock is so great that it disintegrates even the story and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz15p.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
