<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN3341.P7 1983</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Characters and characteristics in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and morals</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Forms of Life</book-title>
         <subtitle>Character and Moral Imagination in the Novel</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PRICE</surname>
               <given-names>MARTIN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>1983</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300028676</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300156843</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW HAVEN; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1983</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dr37p0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The novel contains imagined lives that achieve a kind of meaning and intensity our own lives do not. Out of the novelist's moral imagination-the breadth and depth of his awareness of human motivations, tensions, and complexities-emerge fictional persons through whom we learn to read ourselves. This eloquent book, exploring fictional lives in crucial moments of choice and change, stresses both their difference from and their deep connections with life.</p>
         <p>Martin Price writes here about ways in which character has been conceived and presented in the novels of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Beginning with chapters that cogently argue the artistic value of character, Price then deals with the different forms character has taken in individual novels. His first discussions center on authors-Jane Austen, Stendhal, Charles Dickens, George Eliot, and Leo Tolstoy-who define individuals by their adherence or opposition to social norms. The next chapters deal with novelists for whom the moral world is largely internalized. The characters of Henry James, Joseph Conrad, D.H. Lawrence, and E.M. Forster live in society and act upon it, but the authors are particularly concerned with the confusions, terrors, and heroism that lie within consciousness. The last chapter uses novels about the artist by James Joyce, Virginia Woolf, and Thomas Mann in order to apprehend the process by which experience is transformed into art.</p>
         <p>Avoiding both formalistic and moralistic extremes, this new book by a distinguished critic helps us recover a fuller sense of literary form and the forms of life from which it emerges.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="396"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book about ways in which character has been imagined and presented in some novels of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. It is not an historical survey of the idea of character but rather an exploration of how much of the spectrum of attitudes and feelings we loosely call human is used by different writers, and to what ends.</p>
                     <p>“Character, in any sense in which we can get at it,” Henry James wrote in an essay on Anthony Trollope, “is action, and action is plot, and any plot which hangs together … plays upon our emotion, our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Fictional Contract</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are all of us born into a world with social and linguistic rules. We inherit both kinds of rules, and each of them shapes us even as it supplies us with the means of becoming ourselves: ourselves, but not any selves. And yet selves that can question the system they inherit. We may question the contracts that have been made for us—whether, in fact, they are contracts at all, to which we have never given assent and to which there are no alternatives. “We may as well assert,” David Hume wrote, “that a man, by remaining {aboard} a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Relevance and the Emergence of Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every realistic novel gives us innumerable details: how people look, what they wear, where they live. We generally accept these details as what Henry James called “solidity of specification.”¹ They give us the air of reality, the illusion of life, without which the novel can hardly survive. Yet clearly there can be no end to such specification if we allow it full range. At what point do we set limits and by what means? Can there be pure irrelevance? And, if not, what degrees of irrelevance can we admit?</p>
                     <p>When we read a novel, we adjust more or less insensibly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Other Self:</title>
                     <subtitle>Problems of Character</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If characters exist for the sake of novels, they exist only as much as and in the way that the novel needs them. Jane Austen’s world is a strikingly limited one. It is a world of visits and conversations, which usually take place in houses and gardens. We do not see people at work; we do not directly encounter violent action or violent passion. The limits of what may be said are fairly narrow. We are given, in effect, a shallow and well-lighted stage where we can see the comedy of manners played out with great attention to speech and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Austen:</title>
                     <subtitle>Manners and Morals</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jane Austen’s novels present a world more schematic than we are accustomed to find in more recent fiction. The schematism arises in part from her “vocabulary of discrimination,”² those abstract words which classify actions in moral terms. Wittgenstein’s remarks recall the adaptability of our responses, the readiness of our minds to discover how a literary work conveys its meanings and to make insensible adjustments to the forms its signs may take. Black-and-white photography can make discrminations and tonal gradations that cannot be achieved by color, just as, in another case, an engraving can define a structure through line that a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Stendhal:</title>
                     <subtitle>Irony and Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stendhal’s irony is more radical than Jane Austen’s. His characters tend to be unstable compounds, and they demand a shifting and flexible response from the reader. That response is enacted for us by the narrator, who regards his hero from constantly varying distances and directions. Stendhal’s rhetoric recalls, in its shifts and dodges, the example of Byron’s<italic>Don Juan</italic>. That poem, like Stendhal’s novels, is a work of an age of reaction and political repression, of institutionalized banality. Behind both lie the French Revolution and the remarkable career of Napoleon. The vitality of the revolution and of the young Napoleon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Dickens:</title>
                     <subtitle>Selves and Systems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dickens’s novels circle around the theme of dehumanization. The social system is large in scale and impersonal, hardened into institutions inherited from the past, manageable only by those who have a clear view of their interest. The system is a fusion of aristocratic privilege and middle-class commercialism, supported by a legal structure that can be used to preserve or extend power. Its scale is so great that no one need feel personal responsibility; the system perpetuates itself, and it buries in oblivion both victims and rebels. But it survives only through the passive assent of those it exploits, and it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Eliot:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Nature of Decision</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The notion that peasants are joyous, that the typical moment to represent a man in a smock-frock is when he is cracking a joke and showing a row of sound teeth, that cottage matrons are usually buxom, and village children necessarily rosy and merry, are prejudices difficult to dislodge from the artistic mind, which looks for its subjects into literature instead of life.” George Eliot evokes, as one alternative, the “slow gaze, in which no sense of beauty beams, no humour twinkles—the slow utterance, and the heavy slouching walk.” She scorns sentimental idealization. “The selfish instincts are not subdued</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Tolstoy and the Forms of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is difficult to account for the remarkable sense of depth as well as breadth we feel in reading Tolstoy. Sir Isaiah Berlin, in describing that sense, has come closer than anyone else to explaining it. Tolstoy’s heroes achieve a kind of serenity through coming to accept “the permanent relationships of things and the universal texture of human life.” Through them we become aware of an order underlying and perhaps girding the world of our experience. It is an order which “ ‘contains’ and determines the structure of experience, the framework on which it—that is, we and all we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>James:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Logic of Intensity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his later novels, Henry James leaves some crucial portion of his action, and of his characters, indeterminate. He does this, in part, by giving us characters’ conscious responses—at a somewhat shallow level of awareness—without accounting for their deeper motives or even, in some cases, indicating whether the surface awareness is consistent with what lies below. By a shallow level I mean only that the principal action of his novels takes place close enough to the surface of consciousness to alert us to meanings that are almost evident and therefore the more frustrating for their elusiveness. We are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Conrad:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Limits of Irony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Fable of the Bees</italic>Bernard Mandeville created a dazzling paradox: private vices are public benefits. The more self-indulgent a nation, the more trade it generates: the more people it must employ in the manufacture and transport of luxuries, the more services it will require and reward. On the contrary, an abstemious people are content with little, live on their own productions, remain a self-subsistent nation with little need for commerce or expansion and of little note in the world. Clearly such a paradox seems to undermine morality; and it was designed, in fact, to reveal the confusions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Lawrence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Levels of Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>He sat still like an Egyptian Pharaoh, driving the car. He felt as if he were seated in immemorial potency, like the great carven statues of real Egypt, as real and as fulfilled with subtle strength, as these are, with a vague inscrutable smile on the lips. He knew what it was to have the strange and magical current of force in his back and loins, and down his legs, force so perfect that it stayed him immobile, and left his face subtly, mindlessly smiling. He knew what it was to be awake and potent in that other basic mind,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Forster:</title>
                     <subtitle>Inclusion and Exclusion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One may as well begin with Miss Bartlett’s words to Lucy Honeychurch. The scene is Florence, the Pension Bertolini. The ladies have been given rooms that overlook an interior court. Mr. Emerson and his son offer their own rooms in exchange: rooms with a view. Miss Bartlett is offended by the indelicacy of the proposal, but Lucy is less certain how to take it: “ ‘No, he is not tactful; yet have you noticed that there are people who do things which are most indelicate, and yet at the same time—beautiful?’ ”“ ‘Beautiful?’ said Miss Bartlett, puzzled at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Beauty of Mortal Conditions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce, Woolf, Mann</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Sceptically, cynically, mystically, he had sought for an absolute satisfaction and now little by little he began to be conscious of the beauty of mortal conditions.”</p>
                     <p>The sentence is from the sketch which was Joyce’s earliest version of his portrait of the artist.¹ It reveals some of the difficulty of that process by which the work of art emerges from the conditions of its creation and the artist from the natural man. Artistic creation may be one of the ways of most fully realizing the self, but it is achieved only as the artist is freed of impediments within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr37p0.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
