<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HX806 .U79325 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Utopias</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Utopias</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Utopias</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Utopian Horizons</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ideology, Politics, Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Czigányik</surname>
               <given-names>Zsolt</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789633861813</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789633861820</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Zsolt Czigányik</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt1pq340t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The 500th anniversary of Thomas More’s Utopia has directed attention toward the importance of utopianism. Utopian Horizons investigates the possibilities of cooperation between the humanities and the social sciences in the analysis of 20th century and contemporary utopian phenomena. The papers deal with major problems of interpreting utopias, the relationship of utopia and ideology, and the highly problematic issue as to whether utopia necessarily leads to dystopia. Besides reflecting the interdisciplinary nature of contemporary utopian investigations, the papers effectively represent the constructive attitudes of utopian thought, a feature that not only defines late 20th- and 21st-century utopianism, but is one of the primary reasons behind the rising importance of the topic.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Utopianism: Literary and Political</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Czigányik</surname>
                           <given-names>Zsolt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2016 we celebrated the five-hundredth anniversary of Thomas More’s<italic>Utopia</italic>. The year 1516 is significant, even though it marks only the birth of a neologism and a literary genre that evolved into a very rich tradition, while utopian thought, the ability to think in alternatives about human life, is probably as old as human thinking itself. Utopia has always been in the no man’s land between literature and the social sciences: literary works, including utopias, are often ignored by the social sciences, while works of imaginary literature are sometimes used as illustrations. This volume tries to look at utopian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ideology and Utopia:</title>
                     <subtitle>Karl Mannheim and Paul Ricoeur</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sargent</surname>
                           <given-names>Lyman Tower</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The two concepts ideology and utopia were first and most famously brought together as the title of Karl Mannheim’s 1929 book<italic>Ideologie und Utopie</italic>.¹ Since then only one other thinker, Paul Ricoeur, has discussed the two concepts together while also making original contributions to our understanding of both concepts and their relationship.² For Mannheim ideology and utopia were central to his thinking up to his exile to London in the early 1930s and the publication in 1936 of the English translation of<italic>Ideology and Utopia</italic>. Although they were not as important, he continued to use them after he arrived in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>When Does Utopianism Produce Dystopia?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Claeys</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Friedrich Hayek once observed that “Utopia, like ideology, is a bad word today.”¹ Yet like the Christian devil, bad words may indeed rule this world like some inescapable curse on humanity. Their joint sovereignty over us is usually associated with the twentieth-century regimes called totalitarian, and it is the relation between utopia and Nazism and Stalinism that is accordingly explored here. Writers like Hayek have assumed that the quest for utopia, usually conceived of as some form of near-perfect society, is causally linked to such regimes, and is practically synonymous with the excesses of Hitler and Stalin. My own perspective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Political Utopia to the Philosophical Utopia—and Rescuing the Political Utopia, on Second Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vieira</surname>
                           <given-names>Fátima</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the chapter I wrote for the<italic>Cambridge Companion to Utopian Literature</italic>, I set out to offer an outline of the history of the concept of utopia by highlighting the way the meaning of the neologism created by Thomas More has changed over the centuries.¹ As I evinced then, after its deneologization the concept of utopia underwent several semantic renewals, having been used by different authors to refer to a variety of things. This fluctuation of meaning, I then tried to show, was largely due to the never-ending tension that prevails between the concept of<italic>utopia</italic>(literally a “nonplace”) and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Third Way Utopianism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anarcho-Democratic and Liberal Socialist Ideas in Central Europe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bozóki</surname>
                           <given-names>András</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sükösd</surname>
                           <given-names>Miklós</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we examine hybrid political ideas that bridged or even blended allegedly incompatible ideologies and created a new texture. The ideas to be discussed are “anarcho-democracy” and “liberal socialism” in twentieth-century Central Europe. These ideas came close to utopian thinking in that their representative proponents tried to find a non-existent third way between clear-cut models. Instead of hewing to either anarchism or liberal democracy, they tried to figure out a third way solution between the two. Instead of taking sides in the historic debate between liberalism and socialism, they tried to find a new blend, liberal socialism. Therefore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>George Orwell, Soviet Studies, and the “Soviet Subjectivity” Debate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Halavach</surname>
                           <given-names>Dmitry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most recent and important contributions to Soviet history is that of “Soviet subjectivity” literature. This approach originates in the works of Igal Halfin and Jochen Hellbeck, for both of whom Michel Foucault and post-structuralist theory are major sources of inspiration. Halfin and Hellbeck use the Foucauldian analysis of the creation of subjectivity by power to look at the Stalinist purges in a new way. The self that they write about is not a Cartesian or Kantian self, but rather an intersection of discourses and mechanisms of power. This is a radical version of the linguistic turn in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Marxist Utopianism and Modern Irish Drama, 1884–1904:</title>
                     <subtitle>William Morris, W. B. Yeats, and G. B. Shaw</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Remport</surname>
                           <given-names>Eglantina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Karl Marx’s<italic>Capital</italic>was the seminal work of nineteenth-century socioeconomic criticism, generating heated social and political debates in Britain and Ireland. There is a view according to which the social theories proposed by Marx and his friend, Friedrich Engels, were themselves utopian, although both social critics repeatedly emphasized their rejection of nineteenth-century utopian socialism—Marx himself claimed bluntly that it was simply “silly” and “stale” and “reactionary.”¹ During the second half of the nineteenth century, Marxism, in its various shapes and forms, emerged as a powerful movement, making its very palpable presence felt in late-Victorian economic, social, and political discourses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Civil Religion as Utopian Ideology:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study of H. G. Wells</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pintér</surname>
                           <given-names>Károly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Utopias have a controversial relationship with organized religions. As they are by definition seeking to present a social vision of a human community organized along significantly different rules and conventions than the author’s contemporary society, they implicitly or explicitly challenge the norms and habits of existing societies, including the moral code and spiritual goals, which are predominantly influenced by the majority religion of that particular community. In other words, utopias have an inherent heterodox tendency, which renders them suspect in the eyes of religious authorities. The Catholic philosopher Thomas Molnar summarized this phenomenon succinctly when he described utopias as “perennial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Negative Utopia in Central Europe:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kazohinia and the Dystopian Political Climate of the 1930s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Czigányik</surname>
                           <given-names>Zsolt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a curious book that keeps causing discomfort to its readers:<italic>A Voyage to Kazohinia</italic>, written in or around 1935 and first published in 1941, is often considered the single most important book of the Hungarian utopian (and dystopian) tradition. As part of a larger project of mapping Hungarian utopianism from a social and political perspective, this chapter analyzes this book of central importance by displaying its textual and structural parallels with contemporary political ideologies, especially nationalism, fascism, and anarchism.¹</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Kazohinia</italic>’s author, Sándor Szathmári (1897–1974), was not a professional writer, but a mechanical engineer, like Yevgeny Zamyatin (1884</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What They Were Going to Do About It:</title>
                     <subtitle>Huxley’s Peace Pamphlet in Pre-War Hungary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farkas</surname>
                           <given-names>Ákos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1936, two years after the establishment of the Peace Pledge Union (PPU), Britain’s largest pacifist organisation of the twentieth century, one of the organization’s founders, Aldous Huxley, undertook to write a pamphlet to promote the Union and its cause. In the thirty-one-page booklet, Huxley set out to persuade hard-headed opponents of pacifism that peace was not only a desirable, but also a practicable alternative to war. He pleaded that any kind of peace was preferable to any kind of war, even at the cost of rewarding the aggressor: Italy attacking Abyssinia, Japan devastating Manchuria and Germany bent on annexing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The City in Ruins:</title>
                     <subtitle>Post-9/11 Representations of Cataclysmic New York on Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benczik</surname>
                           <given-names>Vera</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since science fiction’s¹ advent in the early nineteenth century, concerns with humanity’s end have been one of the central issues thematized by the genre, abounding especially after World War II, when human self-destruction became a disturbing and looming possibility via the development of nuclear weapons and the mounting political tensions of the Cold War. These SF works, both printed and filmic, have certain things in common: they involve a cataclysmic event which brings about the epic destruction of humanity; they verbalize or visualize a collective trauma—human-induced disasters, natural catastrophes, or extra-terrestrial calamities; and depending on the scale of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Realism and Utopianism Reconsidered:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Political Theoretical Reading of A Song of Ice and Fire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Szűcs</surname>
                           <given-names>Zoltán Gábor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>George R. R. Martin’s fantasy book series,<italic>A Song of Ice and Fire</italic>(1996–, followed by the<italic>Game of Thrones</italic>TV series based on the books, 2011–) was critically acclaimed as a dystopian depiction of a world of dynastic wars, civil discontents, and feudal feuds. Its plot is centered around power hunger, violence, conspiracies, and treachery. Not surprisingly, many reviewers welcomed the series as a textbook example of Machiavellian political realism.</p>
                     <p>Self-contradictory as it may seem, a story of imagined lands, decadelong winters, zombies, magic, and dragons proves to be markedly realistic, at least in comparison with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Czigányik</surname>
                           <given-names>Zsolt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present volume offers interdisciplinary analyses of utopian phenomena. The interdisciplinary nature of studies in utopianism (and also in other fields) is becoming more and more accepted, yet the cooperation of the various disciplines in interpretation is not automatic, and their emphases and approaches may differ substantially. As Balázs Trencsényi argues, “historians of political thought try to renegotiate the relationship between history, literary studies and the social sciences, pointing out that the understanding of a political interaction might necessitate the use of a variety of different interpretative techniques and approaches.”¹ Yet interdisciplinarity is not only a technical issue. Ernest Gellner</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq340t.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
