<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR3592.P64N48 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Marvell, Andrew, 1621–1678</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apocalyptic literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apocalypse in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Revelation in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Change in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Lyric Apocalypse: Milton, Marvell, and the Nature of Events</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Netzley</surname>
               <given-names>Ryan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823263479</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823263509</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1287fr4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What's new about the apocalypse? Revelation does not allow us to look back after the end and enumerate pivotal turning points. It happens in an immediate encounter with the transformatively new. John Milton's and Andrew Marvell's lyrics attempt to render the experience of such an apocalyptic change in the present. In this respect they take seriously the Reformation's insistence that eschatology is a historical phenomenon. Yet these poets are also reacting to the Regicide, and, as a result, their works explore very modern questions about the nature of events, what it means for a significant historical occasion to happen. Lyric Apocalypse argues that Milton's and Marvell's lyrics challenge any retrospective understanding of events, including one built on a theory of revolution. Instead, these poems show that there is no "after" to the apocalypse, that if we are going to talk about change, we should do so in the present, when there is still time to do something about it. For both of these poets, lyric becomes a way to imagine an apocalyptic event that would be both hopeful and new.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lyric Apocalypses, Transformative Time, and the Possibility of Endings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“What happens now?” in modern parlance often means “What happens next?” This is not so much an error as it is a recognition of the centrality of a conception of the future, even an apocalyptic one, for any notion of the present.¹ We are accustomed to the notion that the present is always fleeting into the past or yearning for a better tomorrow, a nodal point defined via negation and ungraspable as such. This intuitive, geometric model of temporality is precisely what Milton and Marvell seek to unseat with their lyric presentations of an immanent apocalypse. To treat an eschatological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Apocalyptic Means:</title>
                     <subtitle>Allegiance, Force, and Events in Marvell’s Cromwell Trilogy and Royalist Elegies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One cannot pledge allegiance to a person, a position, or even a nation. One can declare allegiance only to a force or a movement. And it is lyric that allows one to locate and praise this present force, instead of reducing it to a wishful future or an inert past narrative. That, at least, is the lesson of Marvell’s Cromwell poems, as well as of his early royalist elegies. This chapter argues that “An Horatian Ode,” as well as his other political encomia, uses the apocalypse to reconsider the<italic>nature</italic>of allegiance, not just its ultimate object. If loyalism, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Hope in the Present:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paratactic Apocalypses and Contemplative Events in Milton’s Sonnets</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Milton’s sonnets are political not because they praise and advise political figures, comment on historical events, or surreptitiously air concerns about aristocratic patronage, but because they strike at the heart of the Petrarchan tradition’s devotion to an absolutist theory of power predicated on the temporal deferral of fulfillment. They accomplish this revolt by insisting that sonnets contain events, instead of simply reporting on the already past happening of those events or advocating for or prophesying their future occurrence. In this sense, Milton’s sonnets attempt to treat events as free happenings in the present, as opposed to an impotent retrospective postulation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>What Happens in Lycidas?</title>
                     <subtitle>Apocalypse, Possibility, and Events in Milton’s Pastoral Elegy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can we conceive of the apocalypse as something other than an ultimate compensation for defeat, loss, or weakness, as an event valuable and desirable for reasons other than the promised triumph of the godly? This is a particularly pressing question for a poem that promises (and, in its 1645 version, celebrates) the fall of its enemies and a future world of new pastures, all in the process of commemorating a friend’s death.<italic>Lycidas</italic>, instead of responding to loss with mourning, consolation, or revolution, imagines this temporal event as essentially apocalyptic, an immanently and immediately apprehensible revelation. Especially in its later,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>How Poems End:</title>
                     <subtitle>Apocalypse, Symbol, and the Event of Ending in “Upon Appleton House”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Upon Appleton House, To My Lord Fairfax” praises Thomas Fairfax for his conscience, humility, moderation, and fulfillment of a providential plan, all as part of its overarching occasion: Fairfax’s retirement from public life. We should not be surprised then that it is populated by images of reversal: inverted trees, boats sailing over bridges, and rational amphibii with canoes on their heads. Yet these proliferating inversions offer neither a secret indictment of Fairfax’s choice nor a hopeful anticipation of his return to a military command. Instead, Marvell’s reversals reveal that he is concerned with the same issues here as he is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion.</title>
                     <subtitle>Revelation: Learning Freedom and the End of Crisis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So ending, it turns out, is much more difficult than it appears. Modern popular psychology to the contrary, closure and resolution are actually quite easy, insofar as they turn the world into a series of problems to be solved, riddles to be unraveled. Ending is difficult, for humans at least, because it entails stopping something without being recognized for doing so, either with the praise of one’s fellows or the spoils of victory in a strategic contest. The modern discomfort with endings can be encapsulated in one concept: the “postapocalyptic.” The postapocalyptic, no matter how horrific, promises us that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1287fr4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
