<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">bron12608</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC574.B76 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Liberalism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Enlightenment</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reclaiming the Enlightenment</book-title>
         <subtitle>Toward a Politics of Radical Engagement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BRONNER</surname>
               <given-names>STEPHEN ERIC</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231500982</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">023150098X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/bron12608"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book tackles an obvious yet profound problem of modern political life: the disorientation of intellectuals and activists on the left. As the study of political history and theory has been usurped by cultural criticism, a confusion over the origins and objectives of progressive politics has been the result. Specifically, it has become fashionable for intellectuals to attack the Enlightenment for its imperialism, eurocentrism, and scientism, and for the sexism and racism of some of its major representatives. Although the fact that individual thinkers harbored such prejudices is irrefutable, Stephen Bronner argues that reducing the Enlightenment ethos to these beliefs is wholly unsustainable.</p>
         <p>With its championing of democracy, equality, cosmopolitanism, and reason -- and its vociferous attacks on popular prejudice, religious superstition, and arbitrary abuses of power -- the Enlightenment was once hailed as the foundation of all modern, progressive politics. But in 1947, this perspective was dramatically undermined when Max Horkheimer and Theodor Adorno published their classic work,<italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>, which claims that the Enlightenment was the source of totalitarianism and the worst excesses of modernity. Reclaiming the Enlightenment from purely philosophical and cultural interpretations, Bronner shows that its notion of political engagement keeps democracy fresh and alive by providing a practical foundation for fostering institutional accountability, opposing infringements on individual rights, instilling an enduring commitment to social reform, and building a cosmopolitan sensibility. This forceful and timely reinterpretation of the Enlightenment and its powerful influence on contemporary political life is a resounding wake-up call to critics on both the left and the right.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>INTERPRETING THE ENLIGHTENMENT:</title>
                     <subtitle>METAPHYSICS, CRITIQUE, AND POLITICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the aftermath of the terrorist attacks of september 11, 2001, amid the intellectual retrenchment consonant with the unending “war against terror,” the Enlightenment legacy has become—more than ever before—a contested terrain. Human rights is often used as an ideological excuse for the exercise of arbitrary power; the security of western states has served as a justification for the constriction of personal freedom; and, with flags flying, Christian fundamentalists have called for the defense of western “values.” The best of them—political liberty, social justice, and cosmopolitanism—are rooted in the Enlightenment, and they retain their radical character.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>IN PRAISE OF PROGRESS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Max Weber already envisioned the spirit of enlightenment “irretrievably fading” and a world comprised of “specialists without spirit, sensualists without heart.”¹ But he was bitter about this development, which places him in marked contrast to much of contemporary opinion. The Enlightenment always had its critics. Beginning with the Restoration of 1815 and the new philosophical reaction to the French Revolution, however, they were almost exclusively political—if not necessarily cultural—adherents of the right: intelligent conservatives committed to organic notions of development like Edmund Burke, elitists seeking a return to the sword and the robe like Joseph de Maistre, racists</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>INVENTING LIBERALISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Liberalism was the philosophical expression for the age of democratic revolution and the principal political theory of the Enlightenment. Its method was the critical deployment of “reason” and its goal was bettering the conditions of social life and expanding “freedom.”¹ No less than the Enlightenment itself, however, the liberal heritage is both underestimated and taken for granted. Often seen merely as an ideological veil for capitalist exploitation, this new political worldview legitimated the idea of “resistance” against established authority—which was already implicit within the scientific revolution initiated by Sir Francis Bacon, Galileo, and Descartes—and it gave members of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>THE GREAT DIVIDE:</title>
                     <subtitle>ENLIGHTENMENT, COUNTER-ENLIGHTENMENT, AND THE PUBLIC SPHERE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The Enlightenment celebrated the intellect and its representatives provided a new understanding of the intellectual. In earlier times, of course, intellectuals questioned the strictures of religious and political tradition. Some of them even served as the conscience of their epochs. But the self-perception of the intellectual as both the critic and the reformer of society, as committed to a communal project of social change, is the legacy of what the philosophe Pierre Bayle first called the “republic of letters.” Its citizens would endeavor to address popular audiences in addition to academic ones. They fervently believed that “the most fundamental ideas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>ABOLISHING THE GHETTO:</title>
                     <subtitle>ANTI-SEMITISM, RACISM, AND THE OTHER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Voltaire once noted in a justly famous quip that if God did not exist it would have been necessary to invent Him. It is the same with the Jews and the Enlightenment: if the “accursed race” did not invent it then they should have. Times have changed since the totalitarian attempt to annihilate the Jews—the <italic>other</italic> of western civilization since its inception—seemed to justify the belief that progress had culminated in the most radical form of reification: the number tattooed on an inmate’s arm. While this stance left <italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic> locked into identifying the <italic>absolute</italic> evil with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>THE ILLUSORY DIALECTIC:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM ENLIGHTENMENT TO TOTALITARIANISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The specter of totalitarianism still hovered over the political landscape when <italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic> was published in 1947. Nazism had conquered Europe and it nearly won the war. But the state structure of the Soviet Union, its secret police, military style, propaganda, and “cult of the personality” were roughly the same as that of its fascist enemy while its anti-fascist ally the United States, whatever of its formal commitment to democracy, was tainted by racism, imperialist ambitions, and the looming specter of McCarthyism. Max Horkheimer and Theodor Adorno saw the future appearing as present: and it was not the future</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>EXPERIENCING REALITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CULTURE INDUSTRY, SUBJECTIVITY, AND IDENTITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The culture industry first came under attack when capitalist society began to experience what Hendrik de Man termed the “massification” of society: the standardized production of goods and services in a world of interchangeable individuals stripped of their identity. Few on the left initially believed that the Enlightenment was the source of the problem and even fewer believed that “mass education” is the equivalent of “mass deception.” But the interwar period saw the individual subordinated to the collective, public opinion shaped by propaganda, responsibility identified with obeying orders, tastes structured by the media, sacrifice for the masses perceived as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>PATHWAYS TO FREEDOM:</title>
                     <subtitle>RIGHTS, RECIPROCITY, AND THE COSMOPOLITAN SENSIBILITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Human rights is the global expression of a demand for civil liberty. Its origins derive from natural law and the European Enlightenment. Opposition to “rights” from the <italic>ancien régime</italic> was fierce, however, and it took a few hundred ideas for the idea to permeate the mainstream discourse. Human rights only gained currency after Auschwitz and Hiroshima and, in fact, it became popular in the United States only during the presidency of Jimmy Carter in the aftermath of the Vietnam War. Once again, using the famous phrase of Hegel, the Owl of Minerva spread its wings only at dusk: the Universal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>RENEWING THE LEGACY:</title>
                     <subtitle>SOLIDARITY, NATURE, AND ETHICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>A new world presents itself with the new millennium: time is obliterating the limitations of space and the boundaries of community. Globalization is spreading the commodity form to the most remote regions of the world; transnational organizations are dwarfing the nationstate; travel is becoming easier; religions are multiplying; intermarriage is on the rise; new communications and information technologies are rendering the world more transparent. But there is no need to be overly optimistic. Numerous parochial religious, ethnic, and nationalist organizations are arrayed—as they always have been—against the assault on traditionalism. Understandable is their fear of the economic inequality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">bron12608.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
