<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccg6</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS476.B4928 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Hermeneutics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Reading</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Bible and Transformation</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Promise of Intercultural Bible Reading</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>de Wit</surname>
               <given-names>Hans</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dyk</surname>
               <given-names>Janet</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781628371062</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781628371079</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18z4h3g"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Engage the delightful and inspiring, sometimes rough and rocky road to inclusive and transformative Bible reading</p>
         <p>This book offers the results of research within a new area of discipline-empirical hermeneutics in intercultural perspective. The book includes interpretations from the homeless in Amsterdam, to Indonesia, from African Xhosa readers to Norway, to Madagascar, American youths, Germany, Czech Republic, Colombia, and Haitian refugees in the Dominican Republic.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>Interpretations from ordinary readers in more than twenty-five countriesBackground introduction with history of the textDiscussion of intertextual connections with Greco-Roman authors</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="486"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Wit</surname>
                           <given-names>Hans</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dyk</surname>
                           <given-names>Janet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Beginning as a grassroots movement, inspired by Latin American and other contextual hermeneutics, intercultural Bible reading has earned its own place within the field of biblical studies.</p>
                     <p>In 2001 the first phase of a worldwide initiative called “Through the Eyes of Another” was launched, and, with a focus on John 4, a method for bringing Bible reading groups to interact with one another was developed. The novelty of this project was not that readers from different cultures and contexts were asked to participate, nor that biblical scholars carefully began to listen or “read with” nonprofessional Bible readers. What was innovative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Intercultural Bible Reading as Transformation for Liberation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intercultural Hermeneutics and Biblical Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Segovia</surname>
                           <given-names>Fernando F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present study undertakes a critical analysis of intercultural Bible reading in biblical studies. This critical approach has marked for many years now the global project of scriptural interpretation developed and undertaken under the expert leadership of Hans de Wit and a superb circle of colleagues within the academic scholarly context of the<italic>Stichting</italic>(or foundation) set up in honor and memory of Dom Hélder at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam.¹ In 2013 I had the great honor and privilege of serving as the Visiting Professor of the Dom Hélder Câmara Chair and delivering the Dom Hélder Câmara Lecture.² That year,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Bible and Transformation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Many Faces of Transformation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Wit</surname>
                           <given-names>Hans</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much has been published on intercultural Bible reading over the past few years; the method has been applied in the most divergent variants, in the most diverse contexts involving forty countries—with varying results. A large quantity of often impressive empirical material has been produced.</p>
                     <p>The conference in Amsterdam in February 2013, with its central theme: “Bible and Transformation: The Promise of Intercultural Bible Reading,” was a moment of intensification in which we could make ourselves vulnerable and dare to change a nearly universal assumption into a critical question: To what extent and under what circumstances can cross-border Bible reading,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Ethics of Transformative Reading:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Text, the Other, and Oneself</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Prior</surname>
                           <given-names>John Mansford</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a cyber world rapidly globalizing economically and therefore also radically shifting socially, culturally, and politically, one clear reaction has been for some to recast themselves in a mythical past set in stone. Whether withdrawing into isolated enclaves or confronting the outside world violently, signs of cultural and religious fundamentalism can be seen everywhere. For as Paul Tournier (1968) pointed out long ago, however disrupting social change, everybody needs a sense of place, an awareness of belonging to a location, a culture, a community.</p>
                     <p>Another reaction is simply to go with the flow, to allow oneself to be swept along</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Transformation in Intercultural Bible Reading:</title>
                     <subtitle>A View from Practical Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schipani</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The connection between reading a sacred text and experiencing human transformation is an assumption inherent in the very value assigned by religious communities to certain texts deemed sacred. That is the reason for those communities to engage in reading, interpreting, and appropriating their message. This applies as well to the Bible, even though, strictly speaking, Christianity should not be considered a “religion of the Book” in ways that Judaism and Islam might. The expression “people of the Book” appears in the Qur’an (29:46) in reference to Jews and Christians. Recently it has become commonplace to characterize the so-called Abrahamic traditions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Toward Transformation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Factors in Transformative Reading</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Zyl</surname>
                           <given-names>Danie C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since its inception, the intercultural Bible reading project had a dual aim: to serve the academic community with insight in the way ordinary readers read the Bible and to achieve a practical result in such communities through their participation (see De Wit 2004). Behind this lies the acknowledgment that grassroots communities in particular read the Bible “for life” and that their readings have (transformative) consequences. The project seeks to open up the community of readers by linking groups that would otherwise have no knowledge of one another, in the hope that this interaction would serve transformation through reading the Bible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Growing Together:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Benefits of Intercultural Bible Studies at the Local Level</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kahl</surname>
                           <given-names>Werner</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>About one hundred years ago, in 1906, at Azusa Street Mission in Los Angeles, Christians at the margins of power shared the overpowering experience of celebrating the presence of God together as one people, in spite of the ideology of racial segregation so prominent in the United States at that time. This became one of the birthplaces of modern Pentecostalism. One chronicler of the movement, Frank Bartleman, captured that experience in the following words: “The colour line was washed away in the blood (of Jesus)” (1925, 54). The believers saw the Spirit of God at work. The phenomenon of “speaking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Effect of Cultural Setting:</title>
                     <subtitle>Semantics, the Role of the Father, and Gossip (A Dialogue between Indonesia and Germany)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sihombing</surname>
                           <given-names>Batara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay I focus on the effect of the combination of cultural setting, context, and personal experiences, using an intercultural exchange between two quite different reading communities. The Indonesian Metanoia group from Maumere, Flores, consisting of prisoners, read the story of the rape of Tamar together with the German partner group BibelWeltWeit (Bible World Wide). I analyze the extent to which this encounter transformed readers of both groups, looking at whether the exchange enabled the participants to become more aware of the importance of semantic conventions when dealing with issues of sexual abuse and whether this would aid in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Reading the Text—Reading the Others—Reading Ourselves (A Dialogue between Germany and Indonesia)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kessler</surname>
                           <given-names>Rainer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the process of reading 2 Sam 13:1–22 with German and Indonesian partner groups, it became clear that the German group did more than just read the text and the response of the partner group: they indeed<italic>read the others</italic>, and only by discussing this point did they begin to<italic>read themselves</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Due to her commitment to ecumenical contacts, I asked the minister of the small village of Oberrosphe to form a German group for the reading cycle of 2011–2012. The group comprised about ten persons, all from the rural area north of Marburg, a traditional university town</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Personal Application, Social Justice, and Social Transformation (A Dialogue between Myanmar and the Netherlands)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marip</surname>
                           <given-names>La Rip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A reading group from Myanmar consisting of participants from several different tribes was linked with a Dutch group from a rather homogeneous village near Amsterdam, the Netherlands. Together they read the story of 2 Sam 13. This essay shows how enormous the differences between both contexts and both groups are. It also shows how determinative the sociopolitical context, and awareness thereof, can be for Bible reading. Is the exchange process able to point to more than differences? Can common ground be found going beyond those differences? Can the connection between two separate local groups lead to more global awareness? Is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“Baby, It’s Cold Outside”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Coercive and Persuasive Discourse and Hegemony (A Dialogue between the United States and the Netherlands)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“What happens when Christians from radically different cultures and situations read the same Bible story and start talking about it with each other?” (De Wit 2004, 4). This question has many possible answers, most of which must be answered from within the contexts of particular groups engaged in particular readings. I propose here to provide some responses to the more specific question, “What happened when Christians from radically different cultures and situations read the story of the rape of Tamar in 2 Sam 13?”</p>
                     <p>Four primary issues arose in the course of this study. The first was that of<italic>solidarity</italic>.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>How to Share Stories of Trauma:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Tamar in Amsterdam</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Berkum</surname>
                           <given-names>Willemien</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay reflects on the exchanges between three pairs of groups in Amsterdam who read the Tamar story. Beforehand we anticipated having good exchanges, with mutual understanding. We hoped links would develop between separated worlds and that prejudices would be broken down. This hope proved vain. The exchanges between groups were difficult and brought little change in the thinking of the groups. It did not go as anticipated—it proved a failure.</p>
                     <p>In this essay I reflect on the course of the exchanges and the factors that contributed to the absence of a deepened understanding of oneself, of one another,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>“We Are All Tamar”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Transforming Culture through the Bible (A Dialogue within Amsterdam)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ejiogu</surname>
                           <given-names>Godian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this essay might seem strange for a Bible story that happened hundreds of years ago in the Middle East, with no connection to India at the time. I chose the title because of the contemporaneity of this story in worldwide news. At the time we were reading this story (2012), a twenty-three-year-old lady in India was raped and died. It could be that raping a lady without any consequences for the offender was normal at the time of Tamar. In present-day India, the justice system takes little or no action, just like King David in the case</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Stories Are Close, Reports Are Far:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Limits of Intercultural Bible Reading with Homeless People (A Dialogue within Amsterdam)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tanja</surname>
                           <given-names>Luc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Intercultural Bible reading assumes that one is able to see through the eyes of the other. The core question of the project regards what happens when small groups of readers of biblical texts from sometimes radically different contexts read the same Bible story and get involved in a dialogue about its meaning. Differing contexts are present not only in different countries but even among groups within the same city. In the present account, people familiar with living on the street were paired with a group of highly educated young Christians. These two groups from the same city, but with contexts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Making the Circle Safer:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intercultural Bible Reading in the Context of Sexual Violence (A Dialogue within South Africa)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van der Walt</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlene</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barker</surname>
                           <given-names>Kim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Empirical research</italic>as a term often conjures up images of strict clinical procedures and of painstakingly precise work conducted in sterile circumstances by a person wearing a white lab coat. Although certain types of research require such settings, in the present essay we trace a complex and often messy process that is characteristic of empirical qualitative research. Qualitative research has been described as messy, because it aims to account for the multiplicity of human experiences within a certain context:</p>
                     <p>The role of qualitative research is not to determine which account is the more accurate or “truthful,” but is rather to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>The Biblical Text as a Heterotopic Intercultural Site:</title>
                     <subtitle>In Search of Redemptive Masculinities (A Dialogue within South Africa)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>West</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have used Michel Foucault’s notion of “heterotopia” in an earlier essay to argue that space is an important component in enabling the poor and oppressed to forge an articulated response to domination (West 2009). There I argued that the question of whether the subaltern<italic>can</italic>speak (Spivak 1988) should be recast as a question that takes space seriously: “<italic>Where</italic>can the subaltern speak?” For, as James Scott so eloquently argues, subordinate classes are less constrained at the level of thought and ideology than they are at the level of political action and struggle “since they can in secluded settings</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>“It Has Been Ordained by Our Ancestors That Women Keep Quiet”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intercultural Reading as a Challenge to Cultural Roles (A Dialogue between Indonesia and Bolivia)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sihombing</surname>
                           <given-names>Batara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this volume, this is the second essay analyzing the reading experience of an Indonesian group in interaction with a foreign partner group. The Rogate group in Pekanbaru, Sumatra, Indonesia, was linked with the Buenas Nuevas group in Santa Cruz, Bolivia.</p>
                     <p>The sharing of the story of John 4 gives rise to a remarkable growth of insights in the text. Here, it is shown how faith itself touches the heart of the other reader and transforms the attitude toward the text. Personal experience and engagement with struggle and resistance emerge as significant hermeneutical factors for transformation. Hermeneutical courage is stimulated;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Ghosts, Women, and Evangelism (A Dialogue between Bolivia and Indonesia)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Autero</surname>
                           <given-names>Esa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The late Walter Wink stated in his book on the Bible and human transformation: “The model for students should be not the biblical scholar, but the biblical interpreter—a person competent to help any group of people understand the impact of the Bible in human transformation” (2010). He explains the reasons for the bankruptcy of traditional biblical criticism: “[it is] incapable of achieving what most of its practitioners considered its purpose to be: so to interpret Scriptures that the past becomes alive and illuminates our present with new possibilities for personal and social transformation” (2010). While everyone might not be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Easter at Christmas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading a Familiar Texts in Unfamiliar Ways (A Dialogue among Ghana, Colombia, and the Netherlands)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anum</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric Nii Bortey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John 20 is part of the familiar Easter story. “Familiar” refers to what is common, well known, household, or proverbial. It represents the traditional, typical, or frequent ways that John 20 is interpreted. “Unfamiliar” represents that which is different, new, and foreign in interpreting the text.</p>
                     <p>In the context of intercultural Bible reading, a text is not going to be read within the specific, well-instituted, and practiced traditions; rather, it is to be read specifically as a tool for exchange of meaning across different communities of readers. This method takes up the question, “Can intercultural reading of Bible stories result</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>“We Are So Beautiful”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Bible and Transforming Life (A Dialogue between Colombia and the Netherlands)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vargas</surname>
                           <given-names>Ignacio Antonio Madera</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The context in which the intercultural reading of John 20:1–18 took place is that of four grassroots ecclesial communities (CEBs; see Iriarte 1996).¹ Three of these communities have been meeting in their homes around the word of God every week for eighteen years to help clarify the reality in which they live, in their families and neighborhoods, in their country, and in the real world. The most recent of these communities has existed for two years to date. The participants are of various ages: the eldest of them are about fifty years old and belong to the oldest communities,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Looking beyond Secularism and Communism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Experiences from Eastern Cuba (A Dialogue between Cuba and the Netherlands)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kindelan</surname>
                           <given-names>Ricardo González</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay we offer a brief survey of the experiences of two reading groups, one from Utrecht, the Netherlands, and the other from Santiago de Cuba, Cuba, under the auspices of the international project “Through the Eyes of Another.”</p>
                     <p>Our essay is focused on the most important aspects of change occasioned by the exchange between these two partner groups as they read together John 20, using the method of intercultural Bible reading. It is necessary to include some background information, such as a description of the social and religious context in eastern Cuba, as well as some details about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Looking for the Body of Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mary Magdalene through the Eyes of an Ancestral Peruvian Culture (A Dialogue between Peru and India)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Díaz</surname>
                           <given-names>Marisol Ale</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perez</surname>
                           <given-names>Manuel Obeso</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A few decades ago, José Ortega y Gasset, a Spanish-speaking philosopher, argued that beliefs are like the firm ground on which we tread (2007; published originally in 1979). He was right, because we go through life—here, there, and everywhere—on the basis of our beliefs. We usually do not think out our beliefs; we live them: we are guided by them and move toward them. To feel accompanied, to feel motivated, to feel that what we do is important, to be sure that everything will go well for us—this all inevitably has to do with our beliefs.</p>
                     <p>Life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>The Complex Role of Views on the Bible in Intercultural Encounters (A Dialogue among Cuba, Colombia, Ghana, and the Netherlands)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Snoek</surname>
                           <given-names>Hans</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the past fifteen years a small miracle has happened: dozens of reading groups, thousands of miles apart, have read the same Bible text and corresponded with one another about it. This gives the impression that the Bible is a universal book that, despite differences in cultures and beliefs, can stimulate readers to look at a text differently. Although the success of the project of intercultural Bible reading has been surprising, it would be too simple to state that the exchanges have always led to transformation. Sometimes the distance between groups was too great, which showed up in traces of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>Am I My Brother’s Keeper?</title>
                     <subtitle>Justice and Transformation in a Malagasy-Norwegian Dialogue (Genesis 4)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holter</surname>
                           <given-names>Knut</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The plot of the Cain and Abel narrative in Gen 4 seems quite problematic. Each of the two brothers brings gifts to the Lord, who—to my mind, rather disturbingly, even quite unjustly—“looked with favor” on Abel and his offering of the firstborn of the flock but “did not look with favor” on Cain and his offering of the fruits of the soil (vv. 4–5). I would have preferred a narrative where God looks with favor on both the shepherd and the gardener, a narrative in which my ideas of divine and human justice would be more easily</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>Breaking Down the Boundaries That Appear to Make Us Enemies (A Dialogue between Dominicans and Haitians on Ruth)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Núñez</surname>
                           <given-names>Digna María Adames</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present essay presents the results of an intercultural Bible reading process in the Dominican Republic in 2009. This project was meant to generate face-to-face encounters between two populations—Haitians and Dominicans—who do not tend to associate with one another. What each population supposedly knows about the other is affected by images influenced by the social media and by groups with economic and political power on both sides of the island of Hispaniola, groups who propagate the idea that each of these two countries is a threat to the other.</p>
                     <p>As a result, the social imaginary¹ in each country</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>On Becoming a Family in South Africa:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intercultural Bible Reading as Transformative Power in Society (Luke 11:1–13)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jonker</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introduced with the liberation of Nelson Mandela from prison in February 1990, the new political dispensation in South Africa has brought an acknowledgment of the diversity of cultures, languages, and religions. The infamous success of the apartheid ideology as a social engineering process lay exactly in the area of cultural refutation in which the social interaction was regulated in terms of four “racial” groups—so-called white, black, colored, and Indian people. More recently, the acknowledgment of the diversity of culture, language, and religion has become one of the building blocks of the new democracy. Generally speaking, South Africans have come</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>An Intimate Revelation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Luke 15:11–32 with Adolescents</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wolverton</surname>
                           <given-names>Taggert E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2009 a pilot project was launched to determine whether adolescent readers could benefit from the process of intercultural Bible reading in ways similar to those reported by adult readers. The focus of the research with the adolescents also attempted to measure whether the reading process would be catalytic to the spiritual growth of the participants. For the purposes of the study, the concept of spiritual growth was originally defined along axes that included a deepened sense of belief, an observable increase in theological knowledge, and an increase in the amount of Christian activities. Due to the small size of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>Sharing Memories, Overcoming Solitude:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Story of the Widow and the Unjust Judge in Situations of Impunity in Latin America (Luke 18:1–8) (A Dialogue among Peru, Colombia, El Salvador, and Guatemala)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hoyos</surname>
                           <given-names>José Vicente Vergara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay I take a brief tour of contextual situations in which Latin American people live in the face of impunity; I also cover some interpretations of the biblical text, taking as a starting point the life of believing communities in our continent. It brings together the sincere and supportive interaction between those who share the same reality of pain, suffering, and the need to make claims so that impunity does not reign, but justice. I deal with three aspects: the impunity in Latin America, the struggle for justice, and the transformation toward an attitude of solidarity.</p>
                     <p>Some realities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Concluding Reflections</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Wit</surname>
                           <given-names>Hans</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dyk</surname>
                           <given-names>Janet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>447</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this volume—<italic>Bible and Transformation: The Promise of Intercultural Bible Reading</italic>—points to our search for an answer to the question: Can cross-border Bible reading become a catalyst for transformation of the readers themselves, of their understanding of the text, and of their perception of and openness towards the other reader? If so, under what conditions? In these final considerations we harvest the findings from the essays in this volume. What have been the results of reading biblical stories in places of global encounter and dialogue?</p>
                     <p>The first part of this book contributes to theory formation. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>461</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>469</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Modern Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>472</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4h3g.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Key Terms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>476</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
