<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7hbh97</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D16.8.R915 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>History</book-title>
         <subtitle>Narration, Interpretation, Orientation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rüsen</surname>
               <given-names>Jörn</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571816245</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782389675</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782389679</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jörn Rüsen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1x76fc2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Without denying the importance of the postmodernist approach to the narrative form and rhetorical strategies of historiography, the author, one of Germany's most prominent cultural historians, argues here in favor of reason and methodical rationality in history. He presents a broad variety of aspects, factors and developments of historical thinking from the 18th century to the present, thus continuing, in exemplary fashion, the tradition of critical self-reflection in the humanities and looking at historical studies as an important factor of cultural orientation in practical life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="236"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables and Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>How to Understand Historical Thinking</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History is much more than only a matter of historical studies. It is an essential cultural factor in everybody’s life, since human life needs an orientation in the course of time which has to be brought about by remembering the past. Historical studies are a systematic way of performing this function of orientation. In order to understand what historians do one should start with this fundamental and general function.</p>
                     <p>Human life has its very specific time order. Nietzsche has described it at the beginning of his “Second Untimely Meditation:”</p>
                     <p>Consider the herds that are feeding yonder: they know not the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Historical Narration:</title>
                     <subtitle>Foundation, Types, Reason</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is historical narration? Most historians will feel bored when they hear this question. They will probably think: ‘Leave this matter to the people in the literature and philosophy departments’, but in fact this question impacts on the fundamentals of their own work and brings philosophy and linguistics much nearer than usual to historical studies.</p>
                     <p>Hayden White, with elaborate sagacity, labored to convince historians of this fact when he treated “the historical work as what it most manifestly is,” that is to say, “a verbal structure in the form of a narrative prose discourse.” But since he explicated this discourse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Narrative Competence:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ontogeny of Historical and Moral Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ancient castle of Col is located in the Highlands of Scotland. It is the ancestral residence of the chiefs of the Maclean clan and is still in the possession of a member of the Maclean family, who lives in the castle. On the wall is a stone engraved with the following inscription:<italic>“If any man of the clan of Maclonich shall appear before this castle, though he come at midnight, with a man’s head in his hand, he shall find here safety and protection against all.”</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>This text is from an old Highlands treaty concluded upon a highly memorable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Rhetoric and Aesthetics of History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Leopold von Ranke</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Current discussions on the theory of history stress the poetical and rhetorical character of historiography; yet it is precisely this character that is generally neglected in the self-awareness and self-understanding of most professional historians. There is a good deal of postmodernism in the quest for rhetoric and aesthetics in modern historiography because the modernism of historiography is defined by it’s academic or, in a broader sense of the word, its scientific character. The widespread and deeply rooted opinion of academic historians, as well as of postmodernist theorists of history, is that this scientific character stands in opposition to rhetoric and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Narrativity and Objectivity in Historical Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Narrativity” and “objectivity” seem to be contradictory characterizations of historical studies. The category of narrativity brings historical studies close to literature; it discloses the literary character of historiography, and the linguistic procedures and principles which constitute “history” as a meaningful and sensible representation of the past in the cultural practices of historical memory. Objectivity, on the other hand, is a category that discloses a certain kind of historical knowledge, gained through the methodically-ruled procedures of research and that has furnished it with a solid validity jutting over the field of arbitrary meaning.</p>
                     <p>The metahistorical discourse² on the principles of historical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>What is Historical Theory?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theories are statements which are, in a complex way, linked to each other and have a high degree of generalization. Theories undoubtedly play a decisive role in all sciences which claim to be scientific (as, for example, theoretical physics). The scientific nature of knowledge is often closely connected with the nature and scope of its ability to theorise.</p>
                     <p>For historical studies, however, this poses a problem. It is indeed significant that in antiquity, when a type of theoretical knowledge was developed as an element essential to Western culture, it was regarded as impossible to theorise in historical studies. Aristotle expressed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>New History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paradigms of Interpretation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We cannot say that the development of historical studies in the twentieth century has provided a canonically established use of theory in dealing with sources. There have been different procedures in the developing and use of theory in the methodical procedure of interpretation for historical research. “If” and “how” and “what type” of theories should be developed and used were open questions. Different paradigms for historical interpretation were developed according to different concepts of historical studies. In the following pages I want to characterize some of the more important of these disciplinary structures within historical studies of the twentieth century²,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Theoretical Approaches to an Intercultural Comparison of Historiography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most works on historiography have been done within the framework of a national history.² A broader perspective is related to European or Western historiography³, or to the historiography of non-Western cultures. The latter mainly deals with a single country or a single culture such as China⁴ or India.⁵ Comparative studies have been rare so far.⁶ There are a lot of reasons for this but I will only mention two: the difficulty of combining the competences of research in different historical cultures, and the dominance of Western historical thinking in historical studies even in non-Western countries. This dominance draws the academic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Loosening the Order of History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Modernity, Postmodernity, Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical studies as an academic discipline is under discussion, which treats its roots, functions and principles in a way that render them at the same time satisfactory and uncomfortable. The satisfaction may result from the new attention history has got in the realm of the humanities. One of the most dominating issues here is memory and its role in human culture. “Memory” covers the entire field of dealing with the past, thus including the realm of history as a subject matter and as a mode of recalling the past into life of its representation in the cultural framework of human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Historical Thinking as Trauerarbeit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Burckhardt’s Answer to a Question of our Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some years ago the Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities organized a conference at the Warburg Institute on “Memory, History, Narrative: A comparative inquiry into the representation of crisis.” At the end of this conference Saul Friedländer tried to summarize the main issues and the decisive points of view concerning the Western concept of history and the idea of its practical function today. He said that looking back at the catastrophes of the twentieth century one has to raise the question again: “What is the nature of human nature?”</p>
                     <p>It is this question on which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>Historizing Nazi-Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metahistorical Reflections on the Debate Between Friedländer and Broszat</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The debate on the historization of National Socialism has raised substantial theoretical problems that need further elucidation. The thrust of the<italic>Historikerstreit</italic>was largely political, which meant that fundamental questions on the nature of historical knowledge inherent in that dispute went unseen; they were generally not touched upon or figured only on the periphery. But the exchange of letters between Martin Broszat and Saul Friedländer prompted by the formers provocative “plea” was different.⁴ It also addressed political constellations in German historical culture, and National Socialism’s place in German memory. Yet it differed from the historians’ debate in several ways: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>Holocaust-Memory and German Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Holocaust is the most radical experience of crisis in history. It is unique in its genocidal character and its radical negation and destruction of the basic values of modern civilization. As such it negates and destroys even the principles of its historical interpretation.</p>
                     <p>It has often been characterized as a “black hole” of meaning, that dissolves every concept of historical interpretation. It occludes construction of a meaningful narrative connection between the time before and after it. It is a “borderline-experience” of history, which doesn’t allow its integration into a coherent narrative. It makes every attempt to apply comprehensive concepts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fc2.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
