<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hc05</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Anthropologists and Their Traditions across National Borders</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DARNELL</surname>
               <given-names>REGNA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GLEACH</surname>
               <given-names>FREDERIC W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803253360</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803256873</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803256876</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d9nmkj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Volume 8 of the Histories of Anthropology Annual series, the premier series published in the history of the discipline, explores national anthropological traditions in Britain, the United States, and Europe and follows them into postnational contexts. Contributors reassess the major theorists in twentieth-century anthropology, including the work of luminaries such as Franz Boas, Claude Lévi-Strauss, Bronisław Malinowski, A. R. Radcliffe-Brown, and Marshall Sahlins, as well as lesser-known but important anthropological work by Berthold Laufer, A. M. Hocart, Kenelm O. L. Burridge, and Robin Ridington, among others.</p>
         <p>These essays examine myriad themes such as the pedagogical context of the anthropologist as a teller of stories about indigenous storytellers; the colonial context of British anthropological theory and its projects outside the nation-state; the legacies of Claude Lévi-Strauss's structuralism regarding culture- specific patterns; cognitive universals reflected in empirical examples of kinship, myth, language, classificatory systems, and supposed universal mental structures; and the career of Marshall Sahlins and his trajectory from neo-evolutionism and structuralism toward an epistemological skepticism of cross- cultural miscommunication.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDITORS’ INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DARNELL</surname>
                           <given-names>REGNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLEACH</surname>
                           <given-names>FREDERIC W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin by apologizing to our readers for the recent hiatus in publication of our ostensibly annual publication.<italic>Histories of Anthropology Annual</italic>began in the University of Nebraska book division and moved to the journals category aft er it had established reasonable visibility among anthropologists and historians. We discovered, however, that our readers are more inclined to buy single volumes than to subscribe. Thus we are returning to the book division. This has required rethinking and rescheduling, especially to accommodate the peer review process now in place through the Press in addition to the editors’ review. We are confidant that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“China to the Anthropologist”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Franz Boas, Berthold Laufer, and a Road Not Taken in Early American Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KENDALL</surname>
                           <given-names>LAUREL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“I shall place the ethnography and archaeology of this country on an entirely new and solid basis, that I shall conquer China to the anthropologist. China no longer the exclusive domain of travelers and sinologues, both narrow-minded and one-sided in their standpoints and researches, China to all who have anthropological interests” (Laufer to Boas, 12 August 1903, 1903-13, DAA, AMNH). Thus did Berthold Laufer address his mentor, Franz Boas, the founding father of American anthropology, with a euphoric vision of future anthropological researches in China. A century later, Laufer has been eulogized as the premier Sinologist of his generation, best</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A. M. Hocart:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on a Master Ethnologist and His Work</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAUGHLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Arthur Maurice Hocart (1883–1939), better known as A.M. Hocart, was a British sociocultural anthropologist living and working in the same era as A.R. Radcliffe-Brown and Bronislaw Malinowski. Yet despite his extensive ethnographic fieldwork, scientific sophistication, and prolific writings, his legacy is far less known than his more famous contemporaries. Indeed, Thomas O. Beidelman (1972) referred to Hocart as a “neglected master,” and Meyer Fortes (1967) spoke of him as a “neglected pioneer.” An accomplished master he was, being far more scholarly, experienced, and methodologically and theoretically astute in his explanations than the functionalist accounts of either Malinowski or Radcliffe-Brown.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Malinowski and the “Native Question”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAMONT</surname>
                           <given-names>MARK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Europe, social anthropology is a major social science that can now boast thousands of participants. This was not the case in the 1920s and 1930s, when the number of professional, university-trained anthropologists was limited to a few dozen individuals (Goody 1995; Kuper 1983). The subject is not taught in high schools, yet university recruitment remains robust, even in recent decades when government cutbacks threaten even some of the oldest, most established fields in the humanities and social sciences. It would seem, on the surface, that anthropology has something to offer. While the reasons individuals would choose to study anthropology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Radcliffe-Brown and “Applied Anthropology” at Cape Town and Sydney</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMPBELL</surname>
                           <given-names>IAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A. R. Radcliffe-Brown (1881–1955) was one of the founders of modern social anthropology. His published output was not large, but it was influential. His reputation was probably greater through his teaching and personal contacts, for he was a compelling lecturer with an apparently powerful and attractive personality. The extent of his fieldwork is compared unfavorably with that of his contemporary, Bronislaw Malinowski (though Malinowski’s only sustained experience of fieldwork was his enforced stay in the Trobriands). Hence Radcliffe-Brown is known mainly as a theorist, not as an ethnographer, and as an advocate of pure research grounded in the scientific</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“The Department Was in Some Disarray”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Politics of Choosing a Successor to S. F. Nadel, 1957</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>GEOFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MUNRO</surname>
                           <given-names>DOUG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the unexpected and sudden death of S. F. Nadel in January 1956, at the comparatively young age of fifty-two, the Australian National University (ANU) needed to find a new professor of anthropology in the Research School of Pacific Studies (RSPACS).¹ It was keen to find someone of similar international standing and distinction and quickly drew up a list of possible candidates, settling on the British anthropologist Edmund Leach and, in the event of Leach’s refusal, the American anthropologist Douglas Oliver (Gray and Munro 2012). Both were unable to accept the offer; consequently, the ANU decided to delay making an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>An Elegy for a Structuralist Legacy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lévi-Strauss, Cultural Relativism, and the Universal Capacities of the Human Mind</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DARNELL</surname>
                           <given-names>REGNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Structuralism, whatever that term may mean over a decade into the twenty-first century, is overdue for reassessment. The death of Claude Lévi-Strauss in 2009 provides the obligation as well as the opportunity to engage in such an exercise of historical retrospect. Lévi-Strauss moved with characteristic creative aplomb across a remarkable range of potential disciplinary homes, but anthropology remained his home base, the place of comfort from which to discomfit other disciplines. The history of anthropology therefore has a particular claim to the movement he founded and popularized beyond its origins in Saussurean linguistics despite the fact that French structuralism has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Lévi-Strauss’s Approach to Systems of Classification:</title>
                     <subtitle>Categories in Northwest Coast Cultures</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ABRAHAM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUBEL</surname>
                           <given-names>PAULA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lévi-Strauss, in the first paragraph of<italic>The Savage Mind</italic>, refers to Franz Boas’s discussion in the<italic>Introduction to the Handbook of American Indian Languages</italic>. Though many scholars once maintained that native people lacked the capacity for “abstract thought,” Lévi-Strauss agreed with Boas that the systems of classification found in the languages and cultures of “native peoples” were indeed examples of abstract thought.</p>
                     <p>Much of Boas’s<italic>The Mind of Primitive Man</italic>deals with the question of race and its relationship to language and culture and the question of what constitutes “primitiveness.” However, in the latter part of the volume, in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Lévi-Strauss on Theoretical Thought and Universal History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ASCH</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Claude Lévi-Strauss is often accused of paying too little regard for history and human agency. But this is misguided, for as the above quote shows, Lévi-Strauss, notwithstanding the importance he attached to the study of the unconscious mind, clearly felt that history and agency contribute crucially to the way in which we live our lives, for otherwise (and whether or not<italic>we</italic>call a society “hot” or “cold”) he would not have said that Australian Aboriginal society is the result of a “long series of deliberate elaborations and systematic reforms” that would constitute a “planned sociology.” The question, then, is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Historical Massacres and Mythical Totalities:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Marshall Sahlins on Two American Frontiers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RODSETH</surname>
                           <given-names>LARS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical events, as opposed to trends and processes, have always been difficult to capture in a “scientific” frame. Trends and processes can be explained, in principle, by feedback mechanisms such as self-regulating markets and balances of power. Indeed, simple homeostatic devices such as the fantail, even as they made possible the industrial revolution, served as the first modern models of political economy (Wootton 2007:42). Specific events, however, seem to slip the net of scientific explanation. Whether they are truly random or just impossible to predict from a human standpoint, events often defy our best efforts to organize and make sense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Anthropologists as Perpetrators and Perpetuators of Oral Tradition:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Lectures of Kenelm O. L. Burridge and Robin Ridington, Storytellers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLYNN</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDY-LOU</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The discipline of anthropology is abundant with narratives by and about anthropologists, their unique research projects, their academic philosophies, and their theoretical approaches or contributions. I present here an unpublished 1988 student assignment as a conduit for my ideas on the value of oral tradition in the anthropology classroom, the construction of anthropological kinship networks, and the ways in which both anthropology professors and their students have persisted in telling and retelling the histories of anthropology over time. The 1988 paper incorporates some of my audio recorded lectures of Professors Kenelm O.L. Burridge and Robin Ridington at the University of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Book Reviews</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nmkj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
