<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Desire, Dialectic and Otherness</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Essay on Origins: Second Edition</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Desmond</surname>
               <given-names>William</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174647</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902745</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>William Desmond</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf4pb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is a philosophical effort to deal with the problem of otherness, particularly as it has been bequeathed to contemporary thought by the legacy of German idealism, whose most challenging, influential thinker was Hegel.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="284"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the First Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a philosophical effort to deal with the problem of otherness, particularly as it has been bequeathed to contemporary thought by the legacy of German idealism, whose most challenging, influential thinker was Hegel. The problem of otherness is not just a contemporary issue, of course; because of its intimate link with dialectic, it reverberates throughout the entire tradition of philosophy.¹ In the wake of Hegel, many thinkers have come to see the philosophical tradition as invariably favoring sameness over otherness, identity over difference, unity over plurality. Hegel’s significance for Western philosophy in the last century and a half</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Desire, Lack, and the Absorbing God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Man is the active animal, intensely restless and forever questing.¹ Living on the move, no sooner do human beings settle in a place but its limits become manifest to them, and their restlessness reappears within its borders. As marked by desire, their being often sends them bustling over the globe to gain a habitation and a home. As temporal beings, their present slips away into the past, while the future they anticipate shows them not to be selfsame, not to be coincident with themselves. Behind themselves in a past, in front of themselves in a future, in the present, humans</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Desire and Original Selfness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The search for origins is a recurrent theme in the tradition of philosophy. It tends to be approached in terms of either an origin that is other than human, in traditional transcendent metaphysics, or in terms of a source of meaning immanent in selfhood itself, as in modern transcendental philosophies. The search for origins has been criticized recently on both these scores, the first as so-called ontotheology, the second as in essence a nostalgic continuation of the same ontotheology, only now relocated and hidden within transcendental subjectivity (see Introduction). What these criticisms largely amount to is the accusation that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Desire’s Infinitude and Wholeness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Man’s quest for wholeness matches his quest for origins both as an essential human desideratum and as a recurrent philosophical theme. Whereas in the last chapter we addressed the question of what it means to be a self, in this chapter we will address the question of what it might mean for a self to be whole. In what follows, I want first to consider the desire for wholeness as it gets expressed in terms of either a univocal or an equivocal sense of being. The former tends to yield a sense of wholeness in terms of simple self-identity, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Desire, Transcendence, and Static Eternity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are marked off as other to finite external things in their fixed particularity, since the original power of our being makes us dialectical selves capable of immanent self-differentiation. Our sense of our own difference is inseparable from the fullness of our opening out to being other than ourselves. We must now explore that otherness, not in terms of the difference between the self and external things, but in terms of what transcends the self in its finiteness. This exploration will take up the rest of the book, but my main purpose in this chapter is to look at an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Desire, Knowing, and Otherness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We must now develop in fuller detail the notion of a two-way mediation between desire and otherness. I propose to do this by focusing on the desire to know. This focus is determined by a number of considerations. First, the centrality of reflection on knowledge in philosophy hardly needs to be restated. Focusing on knowledge will allow a certain clarity with respect to the possible relations between self and otherness as explicitly defined by different traditional positions like idealism and realism. Second, our primary stress throughout on human desire, as the thread linking the episodes of our itinerary, does not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Desire, Concreteness, and Being</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may be helpful here to recall the overall purpose of our argument in part 2. First, we should remember that in the self’s quest for immanent wholeness (the focus of part 1) desire inescapably faced toward otherness, and as we saw in chapter 4, it did so not in any casual way, but with the intention of discerning some sense of the absolute or the unconditioned with respect to transcendence. In chapter 4 we considered desire’s relation to otherness and unconditional transcendence in terms of static eternity and the difficulties connected therewith. We considered why we need to understand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Desire, Otherness, and Infinitude</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The desire to know is capable of unreserved openness to otherness. It is openness to what is given. But what is given, we now see, cannot be restricted to the contracted concreteness of the particular thing. Thus the four degrees of concreteness previously discussed are modes of appearance of the thing, progressively more complex presentations of its otherness; correlatively, the four modes of identification are increasingly ample acknowledgments of its inherent richness. As the immanent self-articulation of the thing becomes more concretely communicable, so the matching openness of a human being moves from the immediate, through the dialectically self-mediated, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Desire and the Absolute Original</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In parts 1 and 2, we tried to see how desire might pass beyond dialectical self-mediation to the metaxological community of being. I now want to develop the possibilities afforded by the metaxological view to provide some further picture of that limiting otherness, especially as it is disclosed through the sublime as aesthetic infinitude and through agapeic otherness. I will draw on many of the key notions discussed previously—for instance, the contrast between desire as lacking and agapeic goodwill, the sense of overdetermined being of original selfhood, the coexistence in human desire of an exigence for immanent wholeness and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4pb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
