<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.I65N49 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Irony in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Irony</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Deconstruction</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Irony on Occasion: From Schlegel and Kierkegaard to Derrida and de Man</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Newmark</surname>
               <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823240128</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823249398</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5cht3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What is it about irony--as an object of serious philosophical reflection and a literary technique of considerable elasticity--that makes it an occasion for endless critical debate? This book responds to this question by focusing on several key moments in German Romanticism and its afterlife in twentieth-century French thought and writing. It includes chapters on Friedrich Schlegel, Soren Kierkegaard, Friedrich Nietzsche, Thomas Mann, Jean Paulhan, Maurice Blanchot, Jacques Derrida, and Paul de Man. A coda traces the way unresolved tensions inherited from Romanticism resurface in a novelist like J. M. Coetzee. But this book is neither a historical nor a thematic study of irony. To the degree that irony initiates a deflection of meaning, it also entails a divergence from historical and thematic models of understanding. The book therefore aims to respect irony's digressive force by allowing it to emerge from questions that sometimes have little or nothing to do with the ostensible topic of irony. For if irony is the possibility that whatever is being said does not coincide fully with whatever is being meant, then there is no guarantee that the most legitimate approach to the problem would proceed directly to those places where "irony" is named, described, or presumed to reside. Rather than providing a history of irony, then, this book examines particular occasions of ironic disruption. It thus offers an alternative model for conceiving of historical occurrences and their potential for acquiring meaning.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="380"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Irony on Occasion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If it is true that a book can always be traced back to an occasion from which it must have started out, then the initial occasion for writing this book was not exactly irony. The chapter that was written earliest and which therefore stands more or less at its source is entitled “<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>”—an essay that in the first instance ought to be about faith. It may well be, of course, that the book in its entirety is about the unexpected ways in which irony and faith are indissociable. At any rate, the faith that first occasioned the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Friedrich Schlegel and the Myth of Irony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The peculiar status of irony within the literary and philosophical tradition is perhaps best illustrated by the vexing questions that always hover over its founder and chief exemplar, Socrates. Was Socrates a model pedagogue or a seducer and corrupter of innocent youth? Was his method of rigorous ignorance a path leading to negative knowledge or an abyssal spiraling of rhetorical tricks? Was his stubborn insistence on interpersonal questioning and dialogue a form of urbanity or the egotistical undermining of any genuinely sociopolitical form of community? Was his death sentence an unacknowledged confession of moral and intellectual bankruptcy in Greece or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Taking Kierkegaard Apart:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Concept of Irony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic crux of a reading of Kierkegaard remains the same today as it was when he was fi rst being widely read and discussed in Europe during the early twentieth century: how to understand his theory and technique of indirect communication. It is only by neglecting the centrifugal force exerted by this question on his entire<italic>oeuvre</italic>that it is possible to underestimate or misconstrue the importance of Kierkegaard’s place in the current scene of critical intellectual debate. The issue is not so much to historicize the question and then attempt to choose sides between all the different “Kierkegaards”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Modernity Interrupted:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard’s Antigone</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every so often, and driven by a slightly different critical impulse in each case, a new collection of scholarly essays dedicated to the writings of Søren Kierkegaard appears.¹ One can hardly doubt the enduring importance of Kierkegaard for literary, philosophical, and religious study, yet identifying this significance with any genuine precision, much less consensus, has proven to be a task as elusive as it is repetitive. At stake always seems to be the same issue of what, finally, can be learned from Kierkegaard. And, of course, nothing could be more appropriate to the production of disciplinary criticism and scholarship than</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Reading Kierkegaard:</title>
                     <subtitle>To Keep Intact the Secret</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taking another look at the way someone like Sylviane Agacinski reads Kierkegaard would be of considerable interest for a number of reasons. First of all, it helps to disclose the way that major philosophical writers such as Kierkegaard seem to engender in their wake at least two very different, perhaps incompatible, types of intellectual reception. On the one hand, there is the relatively coherent and self-contained body of scholarship around which a given community of academic specialists constitute themselves as both the members and the custodians. In the world of academe, it is easy enough to recognize the contours of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Fear and Trembling:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Who Is Able to Understand Abraham?”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Just how serious was Socrates when he claimed to know nothing? “When Socrates said that he was without knowledge [uvidende],” Kierkegaard writes, summing up his treatment of Socratic irony near the end of his thesis, “he nevertheless did know something, for he knew about his ignorance [Uvidenhed]; on the other hand, however, this knowledge [Viden] was not a knowledge of something.”¹ At stake, as always for Kierkegaard, is therefore the degree to which the negativity of irony—its own nothingness—is serious; is to be, or can be, taken in earnest. And wherever the knowledge in question is one that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Signs of the Times:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nietzsche, Deconstruction, and the Truth of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When it comes to the state of the university, the current situation seems fraught with uncertainties for the future. Today, perhaps more than ever, there is a sense of crisis in and around the academy, especially concerning the humanities. Most recently, of course, the crisis has been cast in predominantly financial terms, but the financial component of the issue goes hand-inhand with a crisis of values that has been with us for at least the past quarter century if not more. The “value” of a degree in the humanities will of course be subject to particularly acute questioning whenever the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Death in Venice:</title>
                     <subtitle>Irony, Detachment, and the Aesthetic State</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It would certainly be ironic, as they say, if it turned out that one of the most celebrated theorists and practitioners of irony in the twentieth century had actually misconstrued what makes irony into such an unruly and troublesome factor within the discourses of literature and philosophy alike. Such may indeed be the case for Thomas Mann, whose critical essays and literary fictions are regularly cited whenever romantic and postromantic irony becomes a topic for serious consideration. For if, in the case of Socrates, Kierkegaard wondered just how serious the Greek thinker could be about irony, since while rightfully maintaining</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Terrible Flowers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jean Paulhan and the Irony of Rhetoric</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How is literature possible? The question is actually the title of an essay written by Maurice Blanchot, which is itself a response to a most enigmatic book by the French editor, critic, writer, and literary theoretician Jean Paulhan, called<italic>Les Fleurs de Tarbes, ou, La Terreur dans les lettres (The Flowers of Tarbes, or, The Terror in Literature</italic>).¹ In what way, exactly, does Paulhan’s<italic>The Flowers of Tarbes</italic>ask about the possibility of literature? Can the question of rhetorical fl owers, that is, the question of whether and how literature is possible, be asked without its having immediate and far-reaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>On Parole:</title>
                     <subtitle>Legacies of Saussure, Blanchot, and Paulhan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nothing could be simpler, or so it might seem, than to know what it means to take someone at their word. But when that someone is a writer, and that writer is named Maurice Blanchot, then the question of his giving us his word, or of our taking him at his word, can become a source of genuine anguish, if not outright despair. “Reading is anguish,” Blanchot wrote, “and this is because any text, however important, or amusing, or interesting it may be (and all the more so that it gives that impression), is empty—at bottom it does not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>“What Is Happening Today in Deconstruction”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all likelihood, bibliographies will one day reveal that none of the proper names, movements, currents, or themes comprising the many strands of French thought in the twentieth century solicited more or more varied attempts at description and definition than<italic>deconstruction</italic>. No doubt, it also produced the most frustration, since it is increasingly clear that in every case such attempts at description and definition fail to achieve their goal in satisfactory fashion. The failure is built in to the extent that, even in French, the very word<italic>déconstruction</italic>already belongs to more than just one language, thus making any effort</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Bewildering:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paul de Man, Poetry, Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is no easy task to determine the proper place of the “political” within the writings of Paul de Man. The difficulties inherent in the question stem not so much from the absence of references to history and politics in his writing—on the contrary; it is a rare text by de Man that does not mention law, politics, economics, social unrest, war, or revolution. The problem arises instead from the way such references can become intelligible only in the context of analyses that are themselves not in the first place either historical or political. What one does not find</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dark Freedom in J. M. Coetzee’s Disgrace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the relationship between freedom and knowledge? Is it possible to be free without knowing it? Alternatively, is there something about knowledge and its conditions of possibility that imposes exacting limits upon the concept and experience of freedom? These are among the questions that emerge from reading J. M. Coetzee’s strangely disturbing novel<italic>Disgrace</italic>.¹ They have to “emerge” from a reading because they are not there at the beginning. Or, rather, the questions are there from the start, but in the unacknowledged and displaced mode of answers, of presupposed “solutions” for problems that no longer seem of direct concern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cht3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
