<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B836.5 .C66 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Benjamin, Walter, 1892–1940</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Constellations of a Contemporary Romanticism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Khalip</surname>
               <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pyle</surname>
               <given-names>Forest</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Guyer</surname>
               <given-names>Sara</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McGrath</surname>
               <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="series-editor">series editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823271030</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823271061</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c99996"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Constellations of a Contemporary Romanticism takes its title and point of departure from Walter Benjamin's concept of the historical constellation, which puts both "contemporary" and "romanticism" in play as period designations and critical paradigms. Featuring fascinating and diverse contributions by an international roster of distinguished scholars working in and out of romanticism--from deconstruction to new historicism, from queer theory to postcolonial studies, from visual culture to biopolitics--this volume makes good on a central tenet of Benjamin's conception of history: These critics "grasp the constellation" into which our "own era has formed with a definite earlier one." Each of these essays approaches romanticism as a decisive and unexpired thought experiment that makes demands on and poses questions for our own time: What is the unlived of a contemporary romanticism? What has romanticism's singular untimeliness bequeathed to futurity? What is romanticism's contemporary "redemption value" for painting and politics, philosophy and film?</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Present Darkness of Romanticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Khalip</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pyle</surname>
                           <given-names>Forest</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his theses “On the Concept of History,” the final text he bequeathed to the future, Walter Benjamin proposed a model of historical thought quite different from a historicism that tells “the sequence of events like the beads of a rosary.”¹ More kairological than chronological, Benjamin’s understanding of history postulates that “the past carries with it a temporal index by which it is referred to redemption.” According to Benjamin, any “document of culture” from any historical epoch may be redeemed in the constellations that crystallize between past and present. “There is,” writes Benjamin, “a secret agreement between past generations and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The History of Missed Opportunities:</title>
                     <subtitle>British Romanticism and the Emergence of the Everyday</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Galperin</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The subtitle of this chapter—“British Romanticism and the Emergence of the Everyday”—could easily be reversed because, quaint as it sounds, this is an essay about periodization and the hot chronology in British literary and cultural production that we continue to call “romantic.” Specifically, it is about a category of experience—the everyday—that comes to light during this interval as a history of missed opportunities, where what the “everyday” might suffice to name or to describe emerges both as something “uncounted” and as a missed opportunity for historical<italic>accounting</italic>, where what has “happened,” as Walter Benjamin notes, is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Pathology of the Future, or the Endless Triumphs of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Edelman</surname>
                           <given-names>Lee</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though my title could be read as referring to the emergence of a pathology<italic>in</italic>the future, it intends, on the contrary, to mark as pathological our relation to the future as such. Naming, that is, not a pathology to come but the pathology that determines our investment in the promise of something that is<italic>always</italic>“to come,” something, to borrow Wordsworth’s phrase, “evermore about to be,” this pathology of the future informs our contemporary versions of romanticism. For our sense of the contemporary as designating what’s happening now, what’s up-to-date (a sense the OED traces only to the middle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Painting Theory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mark Tansey’s Derrida Queries de Man</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Redfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The spectral debut of “literary theory” in elite sectors of the public sphere in the United States and Britain in the late 1970s and early 1980s is a historical and cultural phenomenon that still awaits nonsuperficial historical and cultural analysis.² Perhaps it will always be awaiting it—Jacques Derrida suggests as much in the well-known opening paragraph, reproduced in the epigraph to this chapter, of “Force and Signification” (1963). Derrida’s subsequent paragraph speaks with even sharper prescience to the polemics of subsequent decades:</p>
                     <p>By way of analogy: the fact that universal thought, in all its domains, by all its path-ways</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Here There Is No After (Richter’s History)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Guyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Sara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is contemporary romanticism? What is its time? Its date? These questions—of aesthetics, periodization, legacy, and continuity—are bound up with another question: what does it mean to come after? In some sense the question is one we understand: A comes after B, October follows September. But in some other sense, it is utterly enigmatic, especially when we are talking about something other than a clearly marked point—a place in the alphabet, a calendar—but rather an event whose effects and aftereffects are neither fully known nor fully understood even after we say that it has come to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Goya’s Scarcity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark</surname>
                           <given-names>David L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Recent discussions of the Francisco Jose de Goya y Lucientes’s series or, better,<italic>assemblage</italic>of influential prints that came posthumously to be known as<italic>The Disasters of War</italic>(c. 1810–1820; published 1863) locate the artist’s unsparing vision of wartime degradation in a necropolitical context in which proliferating sovereign power fuses indistinctly with the unrestrained destruction of others and otherness.² The genesis of the assemblage lies in the singular circumstances in which Spain found itself in 1808. As Gonzalo Anes describes it:</p>
                     <p>The king, queen, and heirs were in captivity. There was no government. The people, abandoned by the royal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Tone of Praise</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Bolla</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is prompted by a set of remarks the American philosopher Stanley Cavell makes in the introduction to his 2005 collection of essays titled<italic>Philosophy the Day after Tomorrow</italic>. As my title indicates, I shall be mostly concerned to think with what is, at least to me, the extremely fecund and surprising notion that praise and its voiced or sounded manifestations might constitute an acknowledgment not only that the world is but also that its being is open. In the first section I take some time to explore the ways in which Cavell introduces—even stumbles across—and then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Endymion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Text of Undersong</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jarvis</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A thing of beauty is a joy forever, but it is not always easy to know where to put it in your perhaps quite ugly house.</p>
                     <p>Trying to interpret Keats’s<italic>Endymion</italic>is not unlike finding yourself (supposing<italic>you</italic>, for the moment, to be, for example, a brain-sick shepherd-prince wandering somewhere in early nineteenth-century Arcady or Hampstead) catching sight of a butterfly on whose wings there appears to be inscribed some sort of singular text. You wish to decipher the text; you follow the butterfly through paths, glens, clefts, woods, and so on, until it alights, say, on a fountain near</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dancing in the Dark with Shelley</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Faflak</surname>
                           <given-names>Joel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter entertains film musicals as what Jacques Khalip calls “the romantic remains of a modernity that defines itself in the claims it cannot reflect, and which it cannot also bury.”² John Ridpath wonders, “If films were once likened to the theatre, perhaps the modern movie is closer to the musical.” Video and digital media have turned cinema’s “immobile, attentive, disciplined, receptive” public into a “distracted audience” engaged in “boundless activity.” This shift transforms cinema’s private catharsis into democratic exchange at the same time that it broadcasts desire as pleasure’s same dull round. For J. Hoberman, this “‘cyborg cinema’” turns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Pastoral Stain:</title>
                     <subtitle>Twombly under the Trees</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jacobus</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Adorno—whose account of the lyric owes much to its German Romantic origins—offers a point of entry into the convergence of past and present in a series of pastoral works by the twentieth-century American artist Cy Twombly.² A resident in Rome since the late 1950s, Twombly is best known for his scribbled, written-on canvases and a poetic lexicon that includes Greek bucolic poetry, English Romanticism, and the modernist European lyric. In 1976, he painted and drew a series of pastoral works on paper:<italic>Untitled (Thyrsis’ Lament for Daphnis)</italic>(1976),<italic>Idilli</italic>(inscribed with the words, “<italic>I am Thyrsis of Aetna</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Walter Scott Experience:</title>
                     <subtitle>Living American History after Waverley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goode</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In July 1869, Jefferson Davis, the former president of the Confederate States of America, traveled to Scotland on a tour of sites associated with Walter Scott and Scottish history. Davis’s ambitious itinerary took in Edinburgh, Abbotsford (Scott’s estate), Dryburgh Abbey (the site of Scott’s tomb), the Trossachs (including Rob Roy’s grave), Glasgow, Oban, the Isle of Mull, Fort William, and, finally, Inverness and Culloden. Davis had been an ardent reader of Scott since his boyhood, and much of the tour amounted to a pilgrimage to honor the most beloved author among the planter class in the antebellum American South.¹ But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Free Indirect Filmmaking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jane Austen and the Renditions (On Emma among Its Others)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Balfour</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jane Austen was and is a phenom. One might like to have said Jane Austen’s<italic>writing</italic>was and is that phenom, but in some respects her writing—so brilliant, so exacting—has been displaced in the popular cultural imagination by the proper name that stands in for or is associated with all the writing, the films, the made-for-TV renditions of her novels, spinoffs of many sorts, all of which are caught up in the huge network of more or less institutionalized devotion to her, from “societies” to websites to blogs to conferences where amateurs (in the original and latter-day senses)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Population Aesthetics in Romantic and Post-Romantic Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the Romantic-era debate between William Godwin and Thomas Malthus seemed to have concluded in the 1820s in something of a stalemate, this conversation has been recently been revived, though with a rather peculiar twist. The Romantic-era version of this debate pitted Godwin’s principle of perfectibility against Malthus’s principle of population, with Godwin arguing that social relations could be slowly perfected to the extent that legal and political “institutions” were eliminated and Malthus countering that a key determinant of collective behavior was located in the biological register of “population.” Malthus contended that the register of population was inaccessible to human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Technomagism, Coleridge’s Mariner, and the Sentence Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wang</surname>
                           <given-names>Orrin N. C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter gathers some thoughts I’ve had on the relation of Romanticism to something I’m calling<italic>technomagism</italic>. My intent is first to give an overview of what I mean by that term and its connection to Romanticism, and then move on to the particular example of a moment of technomagism in a passage from Coleridge’s<italic>The Rime of the Ancient Mariner</italic>. The chapter concludes with a speculation on what a Romanticism built on technomagism might mean for our own present collective moment of global environmental precarity.</p>
                     <p>As one might readily guess, technomagism has to do with the relationship between technology,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Willing Suspension of Disbelief, Here, Now</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spivak</surname>
                           <given-names>Gayatri Chakravorty</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two pieces of practical advice. Like Aristotle in the<italic>Poetics</italic>, Coleridge is giving advice on how to sell poetry. And Marx cautions against basing all analysis on people’s sense of things; rather one should investigate what worldly factors produce that sense. One is talking about producing a certain willingness in the readership. The other is saying that willingness is produced by material conditions bigger than the personal will. For Coleridge, the determinant is spiritual. For Marx, social. Let us call this these remote presuppositions of my argument.</p>
                     <p>Nimai Lohar is an illiterate man in his mid-fifties. He sang a song</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99996.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
