<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Lydia Ginzburg's Prose</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reality in Search of Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Van Buskirk</surname>
               <given-names>Emily</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400873777</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400873770</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRESS</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dr36q1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Russian writer Lydia Ginzburg (1902-90) is best known for her<italic>Notes from the Leningrad Blockade</italic>and for influential critical studies, such as<italic>On Psychological Prose</italic>, investigating the problem of literary character in French and Russian novels and memoirs. Yet she viewed her most vital work to be the extensive prose fragments, composed for the desk drawer, in which she analyzed herself and other members of the Russian intelligentsia through seven traumatic decades of Soviet history. In this book, the first full-length English-language study of the writer, Emily Van Buskirk presents Ginzburg as a figure of previously unrecognized innovation and importance in the literary landscape of the twentieth century.</p>
         <p>Based on a decade's work in Ginzburg's archives, the book discusses previously unknown manuscripts and uncovers a wealth of new information about the author's life, focusing on Ginzburg's quest for a new kind of writing adequate to her times. She writes of universal experiences-frustrated love, professional failures, remorse, aging-and explores the modern fragmentation of identity in the context of war, terror, and an oppressive state. Searching for a new concept of the self, and deeming the psychological novel (a beloved academic specialty) inadequate to express this concept, Ginzburg turned to fragmentary narratives that blur the lines between history, autobiography, and fiction.</p>
         <p>This full account of Ginzburg's writing career in many genres and emotional registers enables us not only to rethink the experience of Soviet intellectuals, but to arrive at a new understanding of writing and witnessing during a horrific century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="368"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A NOTE ABOUT SPELLING, TRANSLITERATION, AND ARCHIVAL REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For seven decades, Lydia Ginzburg (1902–90) wrote about the reality of daily life and historical change in Soviet Russia. In fragmentary notes and narratives, she exercised what she saw as the unique possibilities of “in-between” genres (human documents, memoirs, essays, autobiographies) to bring representations of new realms of life and thought into literature. She recorded, with an unmatched degree of insight and lucidity, how her contemporaries shaped their personalities and self-images in response to the Soviet experience. Yet in the English-speaking world, she is still known primarily as a literary scholar (author of the book<italic>On Psychological Prose</italic>, whose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Writing the Self after the Crisis of Individualism:</title>
                     <subtitle>DISTANCING AND MORAL EVALUATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a New Year’s reflection at the beginning of 1932, Lydia Ginzburg wrote a startling self-description: “My sense of myself is that I’m a piece that’s been torn, with its threads still hanging, from the fabric of social reality, which I’ve succeeded in bringing up close to my eyes, a scrap of reality that’s just handy enough for close observation.”¹ In sensing that she’s a random piece of a whole, she signals her departure from the usual posture of autobiographical subjects, who present themselves in their narratives as uniquely deserving of the reader’s attention.² And instead of making a neat</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Poetics of Desk-Drawer Notebooks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At a private gathering sometime in the early 1930s, after Ginzburg had begun experimenting with longer narratives, she read a draft of “The Return Home” (“Vozvrashchenie domoi”)¹ to a group consisting of Anna Akhmatova, Nikolai Punin, Nikolai Oleinikov, Grigory Gukovsky, Boris Engelgardt, and at least six others.² After the reading, she recorded (in an unpublished note) her listeners’ opinions and characterizations of her narrative’s theme, style, and genre.³ Grigory Gukovsky chose to describe the genre of the innovative piece as a “novel” (<italic>roman</italic>) whose material was “human thought” rather than experience. (It was Gukovsky who proceeded to spread the rumor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Marginality in the Mainstream, Lesbian Love in the Third Person</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1925, Ginzburg wrote, for the desk drawer, a critique of André Gide’s famous defense of homosexuality,<italic>Corydon: quatre dialogues socratiques.</italic>The focus of her attack is not so much his overall purpose, but rather one of his main arguments: the claim that homosexuality is an irreproachable way of being since it is “natural,” and present throughout the animal kingdom. With obvious sarcasm, Ginzburg counters that “in essence, all good things are not natural: art is not natural, [. . .] using a fork or a napkin is not natural, [. . .] the steam engine and electric generators are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Passing Characters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her book<italic>On Psychological Prose</italic>, first published in 1971, Ginzburg articulates the realm in which life and literature dynamically interact as we model our personalities: in daily life, people understand themselves and others through “creative constructs,” carrying out the aesthetic work of “selection, correlation, and symbolic interpretation of psychic elements.” The processes through which we compose and project our self-images resemble the creative acts authors perform when designing literary characters or lyric personae. Not only are these processes similar, they are symbiotic, since a personality “shapes itself, both internally and externally, by means of images, many of which have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Transformations of Experience:</title>
                     <subtitle>AROUND AND BEHIND NOTES OF A BLOCKADE PERSON</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Toward the end of the blockade, Ginzburg observed that Leningraders were beginning to form a collective identity of themselves as heroes, and that this process encouraged forgetting. She wrote of how<italic>blokadniki</italic>were “already eliminating a whole series of inner states” from their memories of the worst period, the winter of 1941–42.¹ They were forgetting that “they vacillated, that many of them remained in the city for reasons that were external, coincidental, or personal, that they lived in fear and despair, that for months they were interested only in food, that they were mean, pitiless or indifferent, that they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>SUSTAINING A HUMAN IMAGE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lydia Ginzburg is a writer whose techniques of analysis and ethical evaluation aim to overcome the catastrophic predicament of the “post-individualist self.” This person is fragmented but anti-Romantic, and lacking moral absolutes; he is “immanent,” meaning that he can experience life’s value only empirically, in and through himself. He is crushed and tested by the external circumstances of war and terror, and has no grounds on which to base a hope for a revolutionary transformation that could bring about a more just society. As Ginzburg wrote during the Leningrad Blockade—and just a few years after Stalin’s purges: “when you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr36q1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
