<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">708181</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">F2520.1.A63B366 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apalakiri Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Folklore</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apalakiri Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral tradition</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Brazil</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Xingu River Valley</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnohistory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Brazil</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Xingu River Valley</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Discourse analysis, Narrative</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Brazil</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Xingu River Valley</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Last Cannibals</book-title>
         <subtitle>A South American Oral History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BASSO</surname>
               <given-names>ELLEN B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780292708181</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780292769755</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>AUSTIN</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Texas Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7560/708181"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>An especially comprehensive study of Brazilian Amazonian Indian history, The Last Cannibals is the first attempt to understand, through indigenous discourse, the emergence of Upper Xingú society. Drawing on oral documents recorded directly from the native language, Ellen Basso transcribes and analyzes nine traditional Kalapalo stories to offer important insights into Kalapalo historical knowledge and the performance of historical narratives within their nonliterate society. This engaging book challenges the familiar view of biography as a strictly Western literary form. Of special interest are biographies of powerful warriors whose actions led to the emergence of a more recent social order based on restrained behaviors from an earlier time when people were said to be fierce and violent. From these stories, Basso explores how the Kalapalo remember and understand their past and what specific linguistic, psychological, and ideological materials they employ to construct their historical consciousness. Her book will be important reading in anthropology, folklore, linguistics, and South American studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A GUIDE TO PRONOUNCING KALAPALO WORDS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the more remarkable stories of Native South American ethnic survival is that of the people who live in a region of the country Brazilians call the Alto Xingu (Upper Xingu), centered around the headwaters of the Rio Xingu, a major northward-flowing tributary of the Amazon. Although most likely visited by eighteenth-century<italic>bandeirantes</italic>(adventurers in search of slaves and precious minerals), the scientific exploration of this region was first undertaken in the last two decades of the nineteenth century by the German explorer-scholars Karl von den Steinen and Hermann Meyer (Meyer 1897, 1898, 1900; Steinen 1886, 1894). In 1884,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Language in Storytelling</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kalapalo told me stories from the very first week in Aifa, their settlement. As a novice, my first research goal was to try to learn how to speak to the residents in their own language, and for this purpose I began my work by asking for lists of words for things, using as a translator the single Portuguese-speaking man present in the settlement at that time and the only person who used a Portuguese name. In 1952, Antonio had been taken as a teenager to live in Rio de Janeiro along with his sister Dyaqui, who was being married to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>An Early Experience of Europeans Told by Muluku</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An anthropological understanding of the history of a people without writing, which will necessarily be communicated orally, must be effected both with respect to their particular ways of remembering and understanding events and to how they communicate this understanding and memory within one or another speech genre. Thus, for example, if we are to know how people construct an awareness of historical processes, we must learn why certain events have become memorable, how they are given explanatory meaning, and how they are integrated into earlier life experiences. History has an explanatory or clarifying function which is inherent in its constant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Kambe’s Testimony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1927, searching for the remnants of the lost civilization of Mu, the English explorer Sir Percival Fawcett, his son Jack, and their friend Raleigh Rimell disappeared somewhere in the central Brazilian Upper Xingu Basin. Colonel Fawcett was no ordinary eccentric. An engineer and distinguished member of the Royal Geographic Society with connections to the Court of St. James, his trip was sponsored by none other than the famous writer H. Rider Haggard, author of<italic>The Ring of the Queen of Sheba</italic>and<italic>King Solomon’s Mines</italic>. Fawcett’s first attempt to obtain the permission of the Brazilian authorities was thwarted by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Warriors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the center of certain Kalapalo stories about the past is the remarkable figure of the warrior. The<italic>tafaku oto</italic>, or “bow master,” was a man who had undergone special training from an early age to become a perfectly skilled and deadly marksman. According to Kalapalo, before firearms became prevalent, many boys were trained to be<italic>tafaku oto</italic>. If a parent had dreamed about the sparrow hawk it was felt that the next male child would, if properly prepared, become a<italic>tafaku oto</italic>. Sometimes young boys were selected for patient and dedicated training in order to fight long-standing enemies. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Ahpĩũ’s Story about Wapagepundaka</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first warrior story I ever heard was told during my visit to the Kalapalo in 1967. I was staying in a big house belonging to one of the largest households in Aifa, led by Ugaki, her husband, Maidyuta, and her brother Agakuni and his wife, Kafundzu. Ugaki and Agakuni were the sister and brother of Ahpĩũ, one of two important leaders of Aifa community at the time. He lived in a house directly across the central plaza from theirs. Nearly every day in the dry season, the old leader would visit his relatives in the late afternoon to drink</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Madyuta’s Story about Tapoge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I first heard the story called “Tapoge the Bow Master” from the leader Madyuta, who told it to his wife, Ugaki, and me on a hot dry afternoon in the Kalapalo settlement of Aifa. Madyuta had recently heard this story from his sister’s husband, a Kuikuro man descended from the Tafununu Lake Community mentioned in the narrative. For several years this man had gone during the dry season with his younger relatives to farm beside Tafununu. When he visited the Kalapalo just prior to such a trip, as a gift to his hosts Madyuta’s brother-in-law told the story of Tapoge.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Kudyu’s Story about Tamakafi</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The biography of Tamakafi is that of a bow master who had once been married to Tapoge’s daughter. It is a story whose events took place many years after Tapoge died, and in it, we learn how that warrior died and how his death influenced what happened to his former son-in-law. Taken together, the two stories seem rather like a grim family history.</p>
                     <p>While still a young bow master, Tamakafi was asked by his uncle to guard him during a trip to cut arrow cane. In fact Tamakafi’s uncle (a man named Afiguata) is taking him to this very dangerous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Kudyu’s Story of the Wanderers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no founding narrative of Upper Xingu society, nor should we expect any. Despite a strong conviction of shared values and practices, as well as certain mutual interests, people of the Alto Xingu see these as having been adopted piecemeal, and in some cases (most critically, peaceful behavior and maintaining a diet free of animal flesh) incompletely. Moreover, the idea of “society,” conceived in the abstract and independently of the actual ongoing relationships between people, is foreign to them. Kalapalo stories about ancestors associated particularly with present-day communities are very specific in describing relationships between individuals, the formation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Ausuki Tells of the Trumai People</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the smaller and most fragile communities of the Upper Xingu region is the Trumai. The earliest Trumai communities that we know of (reported by the German explorer Karl von den Steinen during his mid-nineteenth-century trip to the region) were two: one located far to the south in the region of the early Carib settlements, the other found in the northern region to the east of the Rio Culuene. The Trumai suffered considerably during their residence in the north, being attacked by the Suya and continuously intimidated by their neighbors the Kamaiura. Disease substantially reduced their numbers, as did</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Ugaki Tells of Afuseti, a Woman Stolen by Angikogo</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once the Alto Xingu communities recognized that they had come to share common values, they began to develop ways of dealing with outsiders that were peaceful rather than aggressive. This was sometimes even the case in situations where outsiders posed threats to them. In certain stories about events that took place long after the end of cannibalistic blood feuding, the warrior remains an important though more peaceful figure. But a more ominous practice is developing: the killing of known people, usually people living within a community, because of witchcraft accusations. The fear and anger directed formerly against enemies living elsewhere</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Tsangaku Tells of the Dyaguma</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One afternoon in late January 1979, during the height of the rainy season when food was particularly scarce, Tsangaku, one of Kambe’s two elderly surviving wives, began to tell me stories of her father’s settlement, Kanugidyafïtï. Men had repeatedly gone out to fish and had returned with nothing, commenting upon how close the floodwaters had come to the settlement. The young men in Tsangaku’s household went out mainly for the form of demonstrating their affinal duties but without any hope of actually finding something to eat. We were all living off manioc soup and bread, yellow squash, corn, and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>History, Ideology, and the Personal Version of Reality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During my attempts to understand the narratives in this book and what the Kalapalo storytellers were trying to say to me, I found valuable two concepts which tend to be applied to modern and modernizing societies rather than the nonliterate, relatively detached communities in the Alto Xingu. These are “ideology” and “biography.” Having used the terms in a somewhat implicit manner in the early sections of the book, I turn now to more explicit discussion of the relationships between them to explore some of the consequences of recognizing these relationships in oral genres, so as to better understand narrative representations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF STORIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">708181.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GENERAL INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
