<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Writing of the Formless</book-title>
         <subtitle>Jose Lezama Lima and the End of Time</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Matos</surname>
               <given-names>Jaime Rodríguez</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823274079</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823274109</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1f89tmf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this book, Jaime Rodr+¡guez Matos proposes the GÇ£formlessGÇ¥ as a point of departure in thinking through the relationship between politics and time. Thinking through both literary and political writings around the Cuban Revolution, Rodr+¡guez Matos explores the link between abstract symbolic procedures and various political experiments that have sought to give form to a principle of sovereignty based on the category of representation. In doing so, he proposes the formless as the limit of modern and contemporary reflections on the meaning of politics while exploring the philosophical consequences of a formless concept of temporality for the critique of metaphysics._x000D_ Rodr+¡guez Matos takes the writing and thought of Jos+¬ Lezama Lima as the guiding thread in exploring the possibility of a politicity in which time is imagined beyond the disciplining functions it has had throughout the metaphysical traditionGÇöa time of the absence of time, in which the absence of time no longer means eternity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dislocation of form and content: I take my epigraph from a piece in which Brett Levinson reviews the state of the Latinamericanist field in recent years. He emphasizes the extent to which scholarship on Latin America has been fundamentally defined by the need to point to or show phenomena that are most essentially characterized by the lack of graspable form, or formlessness, if by form we understand Western schemata meant to determine universally what is and is not thinkable, and more generally, what can and should be and what falls beneath the dignity of Being. In reference to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Toward the Absence of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2007 Fidel Castro was in seclusion, and no one seemed to know much about the actual state of his health. Since July 2006 his physical condition had become a state secret. The absence of the leader coincided with the reappearance of figures who had been in positions of power during some of the Revolution’s most repressive years. These were people who many thought had disappeared for good from the public sphere. Their return, in the nation’s various media, gave rise to a clamorous and by now well-known exchange of e-mails, some written by victims of these henchmen.¹ The discussion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Sovereignties, Poetic and Otherwise</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent study of the place of the foco , or the theory of the guerrilla, in the unfolding of the Cuban Revolution, Juan Duchesne Winter offers a temporally determined cause for the ultimate failure of Ernesto Che Guevara’s strategy. His first claim is that it is in the narrative of<italic>Pasajes de la guerra revolucionaria</italic>and not in the theoretically inflected<italic>La guerra de guerrillas</italic>that the Argentine gives full body to the theory of the foco. “This is due,” he explains, “to the ability of narrative discourse to display the<italic>space of experience</italic>as the work of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>The (Mixed) Times of Revolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>José Lezama Lima came of age under the sign of neocoloniality.¹ Which meant that his first political experience was politics as farce. The Republic was a pseudorepublic. Everything political took on the hue of the counterfeit. Rather than imagining that this was an accident that could be corrected, that there was a true politics, and that it was a matter of locating and activating it, Lezama’s early orientation shows a young intellectual who assumes the opposite. Politics is always counterfeit. Neocoloniality, a scene in which colonial rule goes under the name of democracy, with all the formal institutions necessary to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Nihilism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Politics as Highest Value</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theological underpinnings of the Cuban Revolution are often confronted as if it were a nationally circumscribed problematic, even as its analysis reproduces dynamics that are perceptible and operative on a much broader scale.¹ Yet something is erased when the national furnishes the only framework to think through this difficult terrain, and it concerns the specific role of politics. This might seem paradoxical, for how could politics be disregarded when it comes to revolution? Politics becomes invisible when the only viable strategic maneuver to dismiss a political position hinges on the accusation that an authority in power is not legitimate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part II</label>
                     <title>Writing of the Formless</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lezama’s theories cannot be reduced to a system of aesthetics in the philosophical sense of the term. Neither can they be reduced to a set of concepts that one would be able to define and use elsewhere. This is because in his theory of the arts there are no transhistorical constants that give sense to the history of forms. Even in a more specific or circumscribed setting, his method of reading rests on the idea that no two styles can be the same and, as an extension, that there are no two ways of putting together the materials that give</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Godard, Lezama, and the End of Time(s)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-Luc Godard’s<italic>Notre musique</italic>(2004) takes place among the ruins of Sarajevo, at the time, the most recent proof that the state of exception is the rule. In the film, the Spanish novelist Juan Goytisolo makes a cameo appearance that could be wrongly seen as disconnected from the rest of the movie as a whole. During his time on screen, Goytisolo makes the claim that in the contemporary world, among the ruins of the civilizing process, there is a need for contemplative poets like Juan José Valente and José Lezama Lima. It is the world that needs this, not the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tmf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
