<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Scarlet Woman and the Red Hand</book-title>
         <subtitle>Evangelical Apocalyptic Belief in the Northern Ireland Troubles</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Searle</surname>
               <given-names>Joshua T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893729</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843250</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Joshua T. Searle</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdx0n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book provides a comprehensive description of how evangelicals in Northern Ireland interpreted the "Troubles" (1966-2007) in the light of how they read the Bible. The rich and diverse landscape of Northern Irish evangelicalism during the "Troubles" is ideally suited to this study of both the light and dark sides of apocalyptic eschatology. Searle demonstrates how the notion of apocalypse shaped evangelical and fundamentalist interpretations of the turbulent events that characterized this dark yet fascinating period in the history of Northern Ireland. The book uses this case study to offer a timely reflection on some of the most pressing issues in contemporary negotiations between culture and religion. Given the current resurgence of religious fundamentalism in the wake of 9/11, together with popular conceptions of a "clash of civilizations" and the so-called War on Terror, this book is not only an engaging academic study; it also resonates with some of the defining cultural issues of our time.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="276"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book examines how evangelicals in Northern Ireland read the Troubles (1966–2007) in the light of how they read the Bible. Notwithstanding its rootedness in the Northern Ireland context, this work is more than yet another addition to the existing articles and monographs that constitute the historiography of the Troubles. By considering the ways in which evangelical readings of the Bible inform their interpretations of society, this work supervenes on issues that reach out beyond this specific field of scholarly debate and makes sustained critical incursions into the much larger academic provinces of critical theory, hermeneutics and biblical studies.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Religion and Apocalyptic in Northern Ireland</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has been claimed that the scholarly effort to explain the relationship between religion and conflict in Northern Ireland is in danger of becoming “research saturated.”¹ Despite the profusion of articles and monographs, however, genuinely new ideas and original insights into the underlying dynamics of religious convictions in Northern Ireland have been rare. The problem is partly attributable to the dominance of social science approaches, many of which are predicated on the dubious methodological premise that religious convictions and the language in which they assumed textual form can be understood through a proper grasp of the social contexts out of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Texts, Contexts, and Cultures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The aim of this chapter is to provide the theoretical grounds for my main hypotheses. The first part will set out the theoretical basis for the notion of the text as an active agent in the interpretive process. The second part also focuses on theory and deals with the conceptual structure of the argument, based on a methodical examination of texts, contexts, and cultures. After introducing general theoretical considerations to these three concepts, this chapter will then elucidate their application and relevance to the case of Northern Ireland evangelicalism during the Troubles. These descriptions shall be complemented by several examples</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Apocalyptic Fear:</title>
                     <subtitle>“In the last days perilous times shall come”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Antichrist, the Man of Sin, the Whore of Babylon, the Great Apostasy, apocalyptic lawlessness, and the Great Tribulation—these are subjects that might seem more at home in a prayer meeting in a fundamentalist evangelical church in East Belfast than on the national airwaves of the BBC. In any case, these apocalyptic topics are certainly not the themes which one would normally associate with Radio 4’s<italic>Desert Island Discs</italic>. Yet in one broadcast in the summer of 1988, these were precisely the issues that dominated the discussion on Radio 4’s flagship program.¹ Whereas most guests would choose classic numbers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Apocalyptic Hope:</title>
                     <subtitle>“And I saw a new heaven and a new earth”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Hope,” according to Richard Landes, “is the key to understanding the apocalyptic mind-set.”¹ Acknowledging the ways in which apocalyptic eschatology can transfigure notions of chaos and crisis into an overarching narrative of directionality, purpose and hope, it is important to consider how apocalyptic-eschatological language shaped the deepest aspirations of evangelicals in Northern Ireland. Just as pervasive as Antichrist, the Whore of Babylon, the False Prophet, and the Great Tribulation in Northern Ireland evangelical discourses were the symbolic representations of apocalyptic-eschatological hope such as the messianic Lamb of God, the New Jerusalem and the new heavens and new earth. Thus the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Apocalyptic Dualism:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The divergent interpretations of the texts of Northern Ireland apocalyptic eschatology and the semantic oscillations between hope and fear exhibited in evangelical hermeneutics substantiate Montrose’s definition of a text as a site of “convergence of various and potentially contradictory cultural discourses.”¹ This chapter examines the nature of these discourses and how apocalyptic-eschatological language was expressed in the rhetoric of Northern Ireland evangelicalism. More specifically, chapter 5 explores the ways in which apocalyptic-eschatological worldviews corresponded to the political convictions of evangelical interpretive communities. The aim is thus to investigate how the political and social rhetoric emanating from these evangelical communities corresponded</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we approach the final stage of our study, it is appropriate to recapitulate the basic aim of the whole project. The task was to consider the ways in which apocalyptic-eschatological language contributed to the formation of evangelical worldviews during the Troubles. Through its comprehensive exploration of this issue, this study has traversed some of the most salient and pressing issues not only of millennial studies and the historiography of the Troubles but also of contemporary hermeneutics and critical theory. Underlying the various strands of the argument has been a unifying intention to initiate a mutually enriching conversation among a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdx0n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
