<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR3017.C68 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shakespeare, William, 1564–1616</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political and social views</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shakespeare, William, 1564–1616</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English drama</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Power (Christian theology) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Power (Social sciences) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Shakespeare and the Dramaturgy of Power</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>COX</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400860012</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400860016</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zv52h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ranging over all the dramatic genres in the Shakespearean canon, this book focuses on plays where medieval drama most clearly illuminates Shakespeare's treatment of political power and social privilege.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1989.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="300"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>POWER AND THEORY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>CENTRALIZED POWER AND CHRISTIAN POLITICAL REALISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>FIFTH CENTURY AND SIXTEENTH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Politically and socially the most momentous change in the Renaissance is the growth of centralized power. Even in countries where this growth was not very successful, as in Italy and Germany, people acted as if it were. Machiavelli’s penetrating analysis of power in action is based on what he saw of Medici control in Florence, even though the Medicis ruled only a small territory and Italy would not become a unified nation for another four centuries. Machiavelli’s realism contrasts with the cultivated neo-Platonic idealism of the Medici court, but both are direct reflections of an emerging political model that emulated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>LIBIDO DOMINANDI AND POTENTIA HUMILITATIS:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MEDIEVAL DRAMATURGY OF POWER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When one thinks of medieval attempts to stage political power, the first image that comes to mind is the ranting Herod, and it is instructive to realize that Shakespeare’s few overt references to medieval drama include two allusions to this character. True, Shakespeare’s portraits of tyranny far surpass their medieval forbear in complexity and psychological subtlety, and both his allusions to Herod are derisive—one in Hamlet’s advice to the players, the other in Mistress Page’s characterization of Falstaff’s rhetoric. Nonetheless, Herod’s impressive theatricality is what both allusions register, and if Shakespeare saw the Coventry mystery plays—as he could</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>TUDOR POWER AND THE NEW FASHION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Francis Meres assessed English literature in 1598, he did so consistently in terms of the Greek and Latin classics, making in the process what has come to be an often quoted comment about Shakespeare: “As Plautus and Seneca are accounted the best for comedy and tragedy among the Latins, so Shakespeare among the English is the most excellent in both kinds for the stage.”¹ This passage has drawn attention chiefly because Meres follows it with a list of the plays he knew by Shakespeare—a list that has become a benchmark in efforts to establish the early canon and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>DECONSTRUCTIVE COMEDY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shakespeare’s response to the Tudor separation of styles is deeply ambivalent. On one hand, as his career ripened, he perfected what Marlowe had begun, producing a supple and evocative blank verse after a remarkably short time and creating a decorous stratification of style that mirrors the social standing of its speakers, with particularly brilliant effect in<italic>Midsummer Night’s Dream</italic>. The only play Shakespeare wrote that contains no audibly distinguishable low-life characters at all is<italic>Troilus and Cressida</italic>, which is his purest expression of satire in the innovative humanist manner. Thersites rails in prose in that play, but for all his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>INVENTING SECULAR HISTORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE HENRY VI PLAYS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Elizabethan playwrights turned to their own history, they had no classical models to guide them and therefore no ascribed social expectations to meet in shaping their material. If Shakespeare was the first in this field, as he may well have been, he had to find a pattern of his own. The anonymous popular play,<italic>The Famous Victories of Henry V</italic>, may have preceded the<italic>Henry VI</italic>plays, but if it did, Shakespeare eschewed it as a model, though he learned some important things from it, which he put to use when he wrote his own series of plays about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>THE ELIZABETHAN HAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shakespeare did not abandon his critical interest in Elizabethan power when he dramatized the reigns of the three kings preceding Henry VI; if anything, he made it clearer. The topicality of one these plays,<italic>Richard II</italic>, seems to have been recognized at once, not only by the censor, who prudently refused to permit publication of the deposition scene, but by the followers of the earl of Essex, who daringly commissioned a revival of the play on the eve of Essex’s rebellion, and by the queen herself, who ominously claimed to know that she “was” Richard II.¹ This is not to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>POWER AND ARCHAIC DRAMATURGY IN ALL’S WELL THAT ENDS WELL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two comedies that Shakespeare wrote after<italic>Henry V</italic>show the clear impression of what he had done in the history plays. These two are<italic>All’s Well That Ends Well</italic>and<italic>Measure for Measure</italic>, both of which have been recognized as “problem plays” since F. S. Boas called them that in the late nineteenth century.¹ To a large extent, their problems can be understood as an experiment in the dramaturgy of power. On one hand, Shakespeare more explicitly—one is tempted to say, more confidently—recalls the traditions of popular medieval religious drama in these two plays than he had done</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>STYLE, GOODNESS, AND POWER IN MEASURE FOR MEASURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of<italic>Measure for Measure</italic>has long been recognized as an allusion to the eschatalogical discourse of the Gospels, and its application to Angelo is clear: “Judge not, that ye be not judged. For with what judgement ye judge, ye shall be judged, and with what measure ye mette it shall be measured to you again” (Matt. 7:1–2; cf. Mark 4:24 and Luke 6:36–38). In<italic>Measure for Measure</italic>, the duke echoes Jesus’ idea when he meditates gnomically on Angelo’s hypocrisy: “Shame to him whose cruel striking / Kills for faults of his own liking” (3.2.260–61). Angelo</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>TRAGEDY:</title>
                     <subtitle>NOBLE WEAKNESS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Apart from the history plays, for which no classical dramatic precedent existed, the young Shakespeare consistently turned to Roman drama for what he seemed to regard as acceptable models. In comedy, as Francis Meres noted, Shakespeare imitated Plautus, and in what was thought of as the much more demanding form of tragedy, he imitated Seneca.¹ To be sure, the influence of Seneca has been exaggerated, and few would venture to discuss it any longer as J. W. Cunliffe did in the late nineteenth century—as a tissue of quotations and motifs transplanted directly from Senecan tragedy into<italic>Titus Andronicus, Richard</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>RULING TASTE AND THE LATE PLAYS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the plays that follow the tragedies and conclude Shakespeare’s career seem to belong to a different world from the tragedies, the differences do not eradicate some fundamental social continuities. The romances still observe Renaissance social decorum, bestowing the most serious roles on the social elite and depicting them in greater numbers than their inferiors, in defiance of Jacobean social reality. In contrast to the tragedies, redemptive symbols in the late plays are vindicated, and hard won self-knowledge is cherished by cosmic hope. Yet the spiritually ennobling process we witness in the romances is largely confined to the upper classes,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>POWER AND ART</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The difference between Shakespeare’s early romantic comedies and his late romances can be understood, to a very considerable extent, as a difference in the ruling taste. The static dramaturgy and rhetorical virtuosity of<italic>Love’s Labors Lost</italic>are a response to the fashion created by John Lyly, whose linguistic preciosity, in turn, sums up the Tudor endorsement of literacy as an innovative sign of social privilege. Evidence of a similar preoccupation with language appears in the mature romantic comedies as well, particularly<italic>As You Like It and Much Ado about Nothing</italic>. The spectacular dramaturgy of the romances, on the other hand,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS FREQUENTLY CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv52h.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
