<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1995.9.C35L68 1990</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholics in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Italian Americans in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Irish Americans in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnicity</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ford, John, 1894–1973</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Capra, Frank, 1897–</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Coppola, Francis Ford, 1939–</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Scorsese, Martin</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Motion pictures producers and directors</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Italian Irish Filmmakers</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lourdeaux</surname>
               <given-names>Lee</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780877226970</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781439903551</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1990</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Temple University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt14bsx1s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"This penetrating study examines how these filmmakers confronted their cultural heritage and used it as a counterpoint to their depiction of mainstream America." --American Cinematographer In this unique film history, Lee Lourdeaux traces the impact of Irish and Italian cultures on four major American directors and their work. Defining the core values and tensions within each culture, and especially focusing on the influence of American Catholicism, he presents John Ford, Frank Capra, Francis Coppola, and Martin Scorsese as ethnic Americans and film artists. Lourdeaux shows each filmmaker on set with writers and actors, learning to bypass stereotypes in order to develop a shrewd reciprocal assimilation between his ethnic background and Anglo America. Beginning with D. W. Griffith's depiction of Irish and Italian immigrants, the author discusses Hollywood's stereotypical portrayals of ethnic priests, cops, politicians, and gangsters, as well as their surface acculturation in the movies of the 1920s. By the decade's end, John Ford was using all-American stories to embody the basic myths and tensions of Irish-American life. In his later westerns and foreign films, he tried to understand both Irish political strife and the key figures of Irish liturgy. Frank Capra pitted Italian family values against the Anglo success ethic, turning out social comedies about oppressed little people. Several decades later, Martin Scorsese and Francis Coppola were highly critical of their religio-ethnic heritage, though they gradually discovered that to outline its weaknesses, like the blind pursuit of success, was to fashion a critical mirror of mainstream America. Lourdeaux discusses a number of recent films by Coppola and by Scorsese that have not yet been analyzed in any book. And, in the chapter on Scorsese, a personal interview with the director reveals how his ethnic childhood shaped his work in film. Examining the conflicts within American culture, Lourdeaux shows how the filmmakers themselves had to confront the self-destructive aspects of their ethnic background, not only to accommodate WASP audiences but to better understand their own heritage. He also observes that ethnicity is a strong draw at the box office, as in The Godfather, because it creates a sense of the Other who can both be admired and at the same time ridiculed. Illustrated with scenes of the movies discussed, this fascinating film history tells how four of America's most famous filmmakers assimilated their ethnic backgrounds on set and on screen. "Mr. Lourdeaux walks a tricky path in analyzing the films of each [director]: avoiding the trap of excessively detailing their lives and many films, while steering clear of ethnic stereotyping. Those interested in ethnic influences on outstanding persons or in the production of films by four of the best will find the book enjoyable." --The Baltimore Sun "This is an invaluable book because it arouses critical awareness of the ethnicity underlying many Hollywood movies that might otherwise appear merely to represent American archetypes." --Journal of American Studies "A valuable addition to the literature on ethnic identity in film. The insights Lourdeaux offers into major figures like Griffith, Ford, Capra, Coppola, and Scorsese contribute significantly to our understanding of their films." --Virginia Wright Wexman, University of Illinois at Chicago "For a number of years now, church historians have been giving us an account of American Catholicism that is much richer and more varied than the older institutional accounts of the Catholic Church ever let on. In this comprehensive and insightful study, Lee Lourdeaux shows us how much the ethnic movies of directors like Ford and Capra, Coppola and Scorsese have to teach us as well about Irish- and Italian-Catholic mores and instincts." --John B. Breslin, S.J., Director "A wonderfully sensitive, intelligent study of the complex issue of how the Catholic imagination works in the creative personalities of those raised in the Catholic heritage." --Andrew M. Greeley</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Design of the Book</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book groups one Irish- and three Italian-American filmmakers together with D. W. Griffith in order to trace the gradual uphill path of two ethnic cultures in American film. The path was built in three stages.</p>
                     <p>In the 191Os, D. W. Griffith used Irish and Italian characters to touch the fears and address the needs of Anglo-American moviegoers: He probed nativist fears in scenes of ethnic violence, and he responded to Anglo needs with subtly distinctive Irish and Italian values. In the 1920s, a second stage commenced with the release of several hundred mainstream films featuring stereotypical ethnics and supposedly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Irish and Italian Immigrants and the Movies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1900s when the American film industry was just getting on its feet, several million Irish and Italians immigrated to America looking for prosperity. They had fled the grinding poverty of Kilkenny and Catania, endured terrible hardships at sea, and then signed up for twelve-hour shifts in American factories. But at least they could feed a large family and gradually build up some savings. Nothing in their ethnic values or their religion prevented them from subscribing to the country’s Anglo-Protestant ethic of hard work, private ownership, and success.</p>
                     <p>Of course, the Irish and Italians also brought with them</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Irish and Italian Immigrant Stereotypes in the 1920s</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1920s, Griffith’s experiments with Catholic priests and nuns were quickly forgotten. Filmmakers mostly believed that Irish and Italian ethnics on screen had to suit mainstream melodrama. From the kindly Irish cop to the scolding Irish widow, from the Italian criminal to the Neapolitan hurdy-gurdy man, ethnic filmic stereotypes reflected not so much immigrant neighborhoods as the fears and desires of WASP audiences.</p>
                     <p>Still, the closer movies got to Irish and Italian cultures, the more likely they were to capture brief moments of ethnic reality; the realistic tendency in American cinema was never entirely absent. The filmic Irish son,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>John Ford and the Landscapes of Irish America</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>A Short History of the Movies,</italic>Gerald Mast begins his discussion of John Ford’s work with a shrewd cultural observation.</p>
                     <p>[Ford] is the spiritual descendant of D. W. Griffith. Like Griffith, Ford’s values are traditional and sentimental: the pure woman, the home, the family, law, decency, democracy. Like Griffith—and like the two other important Roman Catholic directors of the studio era, Frank Capra and Leo McCarey—Ford was a populist who praised the little people and the institutions that protected the little people while he damned those who selfishly twisted the system to grab money and power. (1981,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Frank Capra and His Italian Vision of America</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Frank Capra Frank Capra hails from the same social tradition in American film as D. W. Griffith and John Ford. Like them, he explored issues of family, law, decency, and democracy. Yet, Capra’s distinctive ethnic background also made a difference. Though as much a social moralist as Griffith, Capra brought to his characters an Italian sense of gentle compassion; his familial concern for others was an ethnic world apart from Griffith’s Anglo view of greedy human nature. As for a resemblance to Ford’s work, Capra’s films often relied on communal values and family scenes. But whereas Ford wrestled with age-old</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Francis Coppola and Ethnic Double Vision</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a child, Francis Coppola often changed schools to keep pace with his father’s musical career. Growing up in various suburbs, he experienced ethnicity not as a way of life on the streets but as a way of relating within a middle-class family. Coppola the filmmaker constantly mirrors both this close-up familial vision of the self and anger towards the symbolic absent father. Although this conflicted familial vision might seem to negate the social values of John Ford and Frank Capra, Coppola does assert similar themes of family and home, law and decency and democracy in seemingly self-contradictory narratives: In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Martin Scorsese in Little Italy and Greater Manhattan</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Martin Scorsese spent much of his childhood in bed with pleurisy, wishing he could play in the streets. When he did get outside, he immersed himself in Little Italy—in an insular, often self-destructive world. Years later, as a young filmmaker, Scorsese translated this world into film with religious-like devotion. Typically, he pictured an intelligent and morally sensitive young man who, in one violent moment, purges his Italian familial community. After thoroughly mining his ethnic boyhood, Scorsese turned to greater Manhattan where he envisioned non-Italian men either confronting or satirizing a WASP society based, not on the family, but on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsx1s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
