<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4v0cc</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN3491.K67 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Values in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and morals</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ethos and Narrative Interpretation</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Negotiation of Values in Fiction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ALTES</surname>
               <given-names>LIESBETH KORTHALS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">SERIES EDITORS</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Matz</surname>
               <given-names>Jesse E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Herman</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803248366</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803255593</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803255594</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d9nm18"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Ethos and Narrative Interpretation</italic>examines the fruitfulness of the concept of ethos for the theory and analysis of literary narrative. The notion of ethos refers to the broadly persuasive effects of the image one may have of a speaker's psychology, world view, and emotional or ethical stance. How and why do readers attribute an ethos (of, for example, sincerity, reliability, authority, or irony) to literary characters, narrators, and even to authors? Are there particular conditions under which it is more appropriate for interpreters to attribute an ethos to authors, rather than to narrators? In the answer Liesbeth Korthals Altes proposes to such questions, ethos attributions are deeply implicated in the process of interpreting and evaluating narrative texts.</p>
         <p>Demonstrating the extent to which ethos attributions, and hence, interpretive acts, play a tacit role in many methods of narratological analysis, Korthals Altes also questions the agenda and epistemological status of various narratologies, both classical and post-classical. Her approach, rooted in a broad understanding of the role and circulation of narrative art in culture, rehabilitates interpretation, both as a tool and as an object of investigation in narrative studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Why Ethos?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Houellebecq’s work and persona provide for a book like mine almost too good a case.¹ Let me explain what I mean through some brief comments on<italic>Atomised</italic>, the author’s breakthrough novel, and its reception.²<italic>Atomised</italic>tells the story of two half brothers, Bruno and Michel, left to the care of their grandparents by their mother, who went off to discover the thrills and deceptions of self-actualization, spurred by the spirit of May 1968 in France. While Bruno is obsessed with sex, which brings him more solitary suffering than pleasure, Michel, just as lonely and desperate, withdraws into the realm of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 1. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of how and why readers would attribute an ethos to literary characters, narrators, or authors is part of the more general issue of how people make meaning from and with texts. Within the humanities, such issues are traditionally the province of hermeneutics, which encompasses the theory, the method (or the “art”), and the practice of interpreting texts. Alternately, interpretations and their underlying processes are studied from the perspective of literary and aesthetic phenomenology, the sociology of literature, discourse analysis, the reception history of literary works (<italic>Wirkungsgeschichte</italic>), or empirical research on actual readers’ responses. Current literary and narrative studies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Literary Interpretation, Ethos Attributions, and the Negotiation of Values in Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following chapter brings together insights from different theoretical frameworks. My intention is not, however, to suggest that such an eclectic juxtaposition amounts to a theory. My aim is, rather, to point out between these quite different frameworks transversal echoes that shed fresh light on narrative, interpretation, and in particular, ethos attributions. While this chapter’s wide-angle perspective seems to lead us away from the more concrete issue of ethos attribution in the context of literary narratives, it actually speaks to the broader relevance of my study, explaining why it is important to debate the authenticity of James Frey’s narrator or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Ethos as a Social Construction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Authorial Posturing, Conceptions of Literature, and Value Regimes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who or what determines the credit granted to Houellebecq’s work and to himself, as a writer? Is it appropriate to ask about the sincerity or authority of his novel’s denunciation of the rotten state of Western culture? What clues would we have to answer this question, or does trust come before the clues? What is the role in such an ethos attribution of clues derived from an author’s public image? Drawing on a combination of approaches and models, this chapter engages with the social fabrication of meaning and the literary value of narratives and with the role of authorial ethos</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 2. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The controversy surrounding frey’s<italic>A Million Little Pieces</italic>, sparked by his passing off as factually correct and honest a memoir that rather creatively invented its truth, raises some central questions. What might the consequences be of framing a work as fiction, or rather as (to some extent) factual, and of experiencing our reading of such a novel as a communication with a fictional character, or rather with a narrator, or even an author? In what respect would our ethos attribution change? What made readers expect Frey to be authentic and truthful in his narration of his character’s tribulations? Can and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Narratology between Hermeneutics and Cognitive Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As has been amply observed, the current proliferation of narratologies did not exactly increase disciplinary consensus on terms and procedures. Concepts that involve ethos attribution, such as those of the implied author or the (un)reliability of narrators, play a central role in rhetorical, ethical, and other forms of critically engaged narratologies, yet there is not much agreement about even these core concepts. This should not come as a surprise, since such concepts bring into the open fundamental divergences of opinion and uncertainties about what narratology is or should be.¹ The appeal to cognitive sciences has not really solved this problem,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Key Concepts Revised:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative and Communication, Embeddedness, Intentionality, Fictionality, and Reading Strategies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Should the debunkers of Frey’s “fraud” have done their narratological homework better? Would any of the current branches of narratology, each of which claims to analyze how we make meaning from narrative texts, have helped explain the bewilderment that for some readers, like Oprah, followed from Frey’s exposure? Perhaps, to the extent that narratologies offer heuristic procedures and concepts to tease out stances conveyed in narratives. Not really, or not yet, because narratology, though concentrating on textual features, insufficiently takes into account the conventions through which these features are invested with narrative functionality and meaning.</p>
                     <p>The following chapter tries to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Whose Ethos?</title>
                     <subtitle>Characters, Narrators, Authors, and Unadopted Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dance for me.</p>
                     <p>They’ve been together for about six months, and so one night he says, Come on, dance for me, and in the bedroom he puts on a cd, the Artie Shaw arrangement for<italic>The Man I Love</italic>with Roy Eldridge playing trumpet. Dance for me, he says, loosening the arms that are tight around her and pointing toward the floor at the foot of the bed. And so, undismayed, she gets up from where she’d been smelling that smell, the smell that is Coleman unclothed, that smell of sun-baked skin … and, with him keeping an eagle eye</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Generic Framing and Authorial Ethos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I would like to spell out the interconnection between generic framing and ethos attributions in more concrete terms. I shall concentrate on two cases, François Bon’s<italic>Daewoo</italic>, as an example of engagé documentary fiction, and Christine Angot’s<italic>Sujet Angot</italic>, which many would classify as autofiction. Both<italic>writing the social and writing the self</italic>raise particular expectations regarding the rapport between (real) author and narrative voices and about their ethos: in the case of<italic>Daewoo</italic>, about the narrator’s and author’s trustworthiness and authorization as a spokesman, in Angot’s case, about the authenticity of the displayed self-reflection. It is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Sincerity and Other Ironies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The epigraph sets the course for this chapter.¹ It features in a short essay on “Irony and Its Malcontents,” part of the appendix added by Eggers to the paperback edition of his first book and bestseller,<italic>A Heartbreaking Work of Staggering Genius</italic>(2001; from now on I will adopt the author’s helpful acronym<italic>ahwosg</italic>for his title). In this book Eggers tells in some five hundred pages the story of an adolescent who loses in a short time both parents, takes upon himself the education of his younger brother, and explores adult life. The cover indicates that the book is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Narrative, Ethos, and Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The notion of ethos has been characterized by Ruth Amossy as a crossroads at which different critical approaches meet. I hope this book has highlighted the fruitfulness of making narratology encounter some perspectives focused on the social construction and negotiations of meanings and values.</p>
                     <p>My own privileged image for readers’ ethos attributions and for their engagement with narrative more generally is that of the kaleidoscope. The kaleidoscope stands for viewing from a certain angle, under a certain aspect, and for reframing a scene or a mental representation with the wonder of seeing configurations change before our own eyes.</p>
                     <p>Among the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nm18.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>326</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
