<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Trouble with Community</book-title>
         <subtitle>Anthropological Reflections on Movement, Identity and Collectivity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Amit</surname>
               <given-names>Vered</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rapport</surname>
               <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors:</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Eriksen</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas Hylland</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gardner</surname>
               <given-names>Katy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mitchell</surname>
               <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745317465</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783715299</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LONDON; STERLING, VIRGINIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2002</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Vered Amit</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Nigel Rapport</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18mvnx3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>'Community' is one of social science's longest-standing concepts. The assumption, of much social science, has been that it is in communities -- and to communities -- that human individuals, as social and cultural beings, belong. Communities are said to embody that interactive environment from which individuals' identities and senses of self derive, and in which they continue to dwell. The trouble with 'community' is that this is not necessarily so; the personal social networks of individuals' actual experience crosscut collective categories, situations and institutions. Communities can prove unviable or imprisoning; the reality of community life and identity can often be very different from the ideology and the ideal. In this provocative new book, anthropologists Vered Amit and Nigel Rapport draw on their various ethnographic experiences to reappraise the concept and the reality of 'community', in the light of globalization, religious fundamentalism, identity politics, and renascent localisms. How might anthropology better apprehend social identities which are intrinsically plural, transgressive and ironic? What has anthropology to say about the way in which civil society might hope to accommodate the on-going construction and the rightful expression of such migrant identities? Nigel Rapport and Vered Amit give their own answers to these questions before entering into dialogue to assess each other's positions. Nigel Rapport is Professor of Anthropological and Philosophical Studies at the University of St. Andrews. He is author of Transcendent Individual (1997). Vered Amit is an Associate Professor at Concordia University in Montreal. She is the editor of Realizing Community (2002).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PROLOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE BOOK’S QUESTIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a dialogue between two anthropologists; it concerns<italic>the conceptualization, the ideology and the practice of community in the contemporary world</italic>. All three of these dimensions of community involve a tension between efforts to fix social and political relations in communal frames and the considerable pressures toward individuation and fragmentation which regularly undo these efforts, but may also be constrained by them. The book offers a review and a reassessment of community as a political, legal, theoretical and ethnographic concept within anthropology.</p>
                     <p>As the new century begins, politico-economic restructuring continues further to embed local economies, economic networks and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>ANTHROPOLOGY AND COMMUNITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>SOME OPENING NOTES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like their counterparts in sister disciplines, many anthropologists have noted the ‘slipperiness’ of the notion of community, arguing that it is too vague, too variable in its applications and definitions to be of much utility as an analytical tool (Bauman, 1996: 14; Cohen, 2002: 165). But the very features that tend to produce this ambiguity also help to ensure the persistence of a notion of community both within scholarly literature as well as in popular vernaculars. Like symbols (Cohen, 1985), key lexical terms such as<italic>community, nation, culture</italic>persist in usage because they evoke a thick assortment of meanings, presumptions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>EMBRACING DISJUNCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At an anthropology conference not too long ago, I presented a paper presenting some material from an ongoing research project that focuses on the lives of travelling consultants.¹ The people I had interviewed were part of a growing global army of professionals whose work involves frequent travel across large distances to a succession of distant clients. A number of these people had explicitly structured their career paths to allow for regular travel, this even when other less ambulant work opportunities were available. Thus for Margaret,² a consultant specializing in urban development and economics, a career involving travel had been a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE TROUBLE WITH COMMUNITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most common appearance of community within the social sciences, and especially the anthropological literature, has probably been in its most taken-for-granted and unexamined form as a unit of analysis, the location rather than the object of research. But community has also featured as a long-standing vehicle for a broader scholarly interrogation of the dialectic between historical social transformations and social cohesion, and as such was a focus in scholarship as varied as that of Tönnies, Durkheim and Weber writing at the turn of the twentieth century (Chorney, 1990), the ‘Chicago School’ urbanists of the first half of the twentieth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES TO PART I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES TO PART I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREAMBLE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An incident at random: a review by John Gray in the<italic>Times Literary Supplement</italic>of a new book on the notion of trust (Adam Seligman,<italic>The Problem of Trust</italic>, 1997) ponders the possibility of ‘a dialectical turn in the ethical life of modern individuality’ wherein people no longer believe they are responsible to themselves as individuals (1998: 6). Personal responsibility as a public ideology, Gray expounds (<italic>après</italic>Seligman), grew over the centuries in the West as traditional social roles became less constraining and the authority of social groups diminished. But now, it seems (somewhat ironically), even the authority of an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>A THEORY OF MOVEMENT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his discussion on the best possible relationship between science and non-science (in which he included religion and the arts), Friedrich Nietzsche decided on the image of human beings having ‘a double brain’: a brain with two chambers lying next to one another, as it were, separable and self-contained, and experiencing different things without confusion (1994: 154). An experience of both science and non-science was necessary for human health, Nietzsche deemed, but at the same time the two had to be kept apart. Non-science inspired and was the source of human strength, while science was the source of truth, direction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>INCOMMENSURABILITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>POLITICS OR LAW?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are at least two potential pitfalls in this project, pitfalls of hoary longevity: the attempt to move from ‘is’ to ‘ought’, from science to morality; and the attempt to move to morality from moralities. At the least, much wisdom would lead one to suspect that an account of a relationship between science and morality which is clearer and firmer than the ambiguous and uneasy one which Gellner finds presently to characterize liberal society would have to take the form of a continuing negotiation of plural and partial compromises rather than anything more singular or statutory. It would be an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>EDUCATING FOR LIBERAL DEMOCRACY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Richard Rorty is under no illusions concerning the revolutionary change in sensibility which procedural justice and substantive irony, as the public traits of a civil society, amounts to. If the shift from religiosity to secularism has proceeded over a number of centuries, is still ongoing and is periodically beset by reactionary counter-reformations, then the shift to postmodern bourgeois liberalism, as a global form of polity, might be equally gradual. For the paradox of ‘getting rid of God and of grammar’ (Nietzsche) while keeping as sacrosanct a method of rationally asserting and adjudicating their (good) riddance – of believing liberal democracy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>THE IRONIZATION OF LIBERAL DEMOCRACY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nietzsche described a ‘revaluation of all values’ as his formula for humankind’s supreme ‘coming-to-itself’. The cognitive act which he called for was an ironic one; the human quality he was calling upon, and raising into a supreme value itself, was irony.</p>
                     <p>Besides its literary meaning, of certain figures of speech (antiphrasis, litotes, meiosis)where there is an inconsistency or contradiction between what is said and what is meant or apparent, irony can be understood as compassing a certain cognitive detachment, recognizing a certain displacement; indeed, it paves a royal road to appreciating displacement as an infinite regress. Irony may be defined</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>HUMAN RIGHTS AND LIBERAL DEMOCRACY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the individual who ironically resists the temptation to cherish particular values, beliefs and desires over and above their continuing revaluation is existentially free, then, as Kateb averred, he or she can still be greatly helped by certain legal-constitutional arrangements, by the procedures of a liberal democracy, which recognize and champion that free ironism. More specifically, the exercise of ironism benefits from the legalism of ‘human rights’: laws which ‘allow for the free exercise of choice as to [the individual’s] involvements and protect against unreflective, herd solidarity’ (Phillips, 1993: 191).</p>
                     <p>Human rights, in the past fifty years, has become ‘one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>UNIVERSALISM AND RELATIVISM IN THE GLOBAL ECUMENE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ernest Gellner spoke of the ‘well-matured political systems’ of the liberal West (1995b: 9), as we have heard, where efficacious scientific practice and knowledge sat alongside cultural faith and spectacle (however ambiguously). In best effecting the satisfaction of human needs and of liberating humanity from material want, in proceeding towards ‘the goal of human liberation’ as such, it was not only true to say that some choices in human world-view and behaviour were better than others, but also that one choice was pre-eminent. This was the liberal West: the meaning-system which had developed and accommodated itself socio-culturally to the power</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>EXISTENTIAL ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What may be drawn from the Salman Rushdie affair, and from Rushdie’s own words, in the context of this essay so as to take the argument forward? Regarding the partiality of meaning which Rushdie describes, I have written elsewhere about the randomness of the creative process and the freedom or arbitrariness with which the imagination is wont to select those construed items from which meaningful worlds are constituted (2001; also cf. Brodsky, 1988: G2). But Rushdie’s words do not only give on to literary concerns; I would read implications in them which are also<italic>realpolitische</italic>, practical and prescriptive.</p>
                     <p>‘Those who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>EXISTENTIAL POLITICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If individual consciousness and agency is seen as responsible for creating and maintaining the diversity of cultural worlds, then anthropologically to ‘decolonize’ the individual human subject also entails the anthropologist proclaiming the value of the former as a prerequisite of the latter. It becomes an anthropological duty to explain that individuals make communities and create traditions, likewise to champion those social environments in which such individuality is recognized and respected, and to declaim against those which bury individual worth under a weight of so-called traditional or revelational or institutional knowledge and practice. Anthropology, in other words, becomes, at least in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES TO PART II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES TO PART II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>VERED AMIT RESPONDS TO NIGEL RAPPORT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Part II, Nigel Rapport provides us with an impassioned and articulate vision that is thoroughly humanist. He argues for an existential politics that can reach beyond the brutal and banal contrivances of categorical identities to individual consciousness, agency and responsibility. Making an analogy with the capacity of scientific knowledge to reach beyond any one culture and transform the universal human condition, Rapport, citing Ernest Gellner, posits the possibility of a moral arrangement which could also achieve globalism. Arguing for the possibilities offered by liberal democratic and human rights discourses, Rapport offers a vision in which it is the dignity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>NIGEL RAPPORT RESPONDS TO VERED AMIT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How is ‘culture’, that abstract explanatory notion of causation and control by which anthropologists have put so much store – that ‘set of control mechanisms ... for the governing of behaviour ... by whose agency the breadth and indeterminateness of [man’s] inherent capacities are reduced to the narrowness and specificity of his actual accomplishments’ (Geertz, 1973: 44–5)–to be properly ‘seen’ or made concrete? In Part I of the book Vered Amit begins by arguing that, as with ‘place’, portrayals of ‘community’ and ‘collectivity’ no longer convince as metaphors. And yet, while having finally given up on the fixity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES TO PART III</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mvnx3.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
