<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmd6g</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Undoing Art</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Caws</surname>
               <given-names>Mary Ann</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Delville</surname>
               <given-names>Michel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9788822900722</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9788822909084</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Quodlibet</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Macerata</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Quodlibet srl</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1vxm83d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What do Stéphane Mallarmé, Antonin Artaud, Meret Oppenheim, Asger Jorn, Yoko Ono, Tom Phillips and Martin Arnold have in common? Whereas a wealth of critics have diagnosed contemporary art’s preoccupations with madness, depression and self-abuse as well as its tendency to cultivate an (anti-)aesthetics of the negative, the excremental and the abject (say, from the Vienna Action Group to Serrano, McCarthy or Delvoye), much less attention has been paid to how modern and contemporary artists and public have thrived on the destruction, disfiguration and obliteration of work by the artists and/or by that of others. From Artaud’s «terminal» notebooks to the recent upsurge in «erasure poetics», the history of «undoing» art deserves to be recounted in a positive mode and rescued from popular narratives of the decline and death of the avant-garde.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="96"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acts of Undoing and How We Care</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: What best undoes something to make it something else? Undoing to do better? Here’s a model case: Mallarmé striking out every other word from his sentences to make the prose unjournalistic, enigmatic, to make it the poetry of a sentence.</p>
                     <p>Acts of undoing can be drama in style, without any apparent reason. Or they can be quite simply, in very low key indeed, the refusal to accept or answer to one’s own name, a pseudonym. And then there is the high style: the poet Pierre Reverdy, contemporary with Max Jacob and Guillaume Apollinaire, to mark - apparently - his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Not Doing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Of more interest, perhaps are two other kinds of cases. One is the not doing what one has been asked to do, or what one has indeed promised to do, so that the act itself perseveres, along with its undoing. Here I am thinking of Rainer Maria Rilke, asked, invited, to edit the letters and journal entries of the great German painter Paula Modersohn-Becker, and refusing, alleging that it would do her reputation no good:</p>
                     <p>For even at the moment that the greatest images of her comes alive within me, how in that very moment am I to bring</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Disownings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Ken Russell, working with Derek Jarman, disowns his film with Nureyev; years before, Antonin Artaud, angry with the way in which his film<italic>La Coquille et le clergyman (The Shell and the Clergyman)</italic>had been directed by Germaine Dulac, disowned it as a badly-interpreted product of his mind. Of course group disownings go even further: Artaud, and then later Salvador Dalí were disowned, as was even the best surrealist poet of them all, Robert Desnos, by the surrealist group. Group disownings remain celebrated, exclusions, just as celebrated as are inclusions.</p>
                     <p>We would be hard put to it to figure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Refusals</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Sadly, the Whitney Museum has just turned down, for the public plaza in front of its new building, Charles Ray’s statue of<italic>Huck and Jim</italic>, remembering<italic>Huck Finn</italic>. «The runaway slave, Jim, is nine feet tall, in the prime of life», as Calvin Tomkins puts it in his article «Meaning Machines: The Sculptures of Charles Ray»³. Jim is reaching out with his right hand protectively over Huck’s body, as the fourteen-year old bends over and scoops out something below him. It relates to the story in which they are looking at the stars, Huck is saying they were always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Obliterations and Deviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: And then, of course, there are acts of disowning, refusal and obliteration perpetrated by artists upon the works of other artists. Among these, the success story of erasure poetics deserves our attention, if only because it has been ignored or relegated to the margins of literary and art history. Erasurism is rooted as much in contemporary philosophy’s deconstructionist turn as in Duchampian found objects and Situationist détournements, of which many of the examples examined below constitute both an extension and a critique. Recent and current developments in erasure art are closely associated with visual artists and writers (many of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Erasurism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: Paul Ricoeur memorably identified Marx, Nietzsche and Freud as the father-founders of a «school of suspicion»<sup>10</sup>which urges readers, critics and artists to unveil the strategies by which art conceals its own constructedness and disguises its ideological complicity with dominant structures of power. Should erasure art be considered as a casualty of the «terminal case of irony» in which the humanities find themselves at the present time, driven as they are by an «uncontrollable urge to put everything in scare quotes»<sup>11</sup>? Even though erasurism does not necessarily set out to destroy the artwork per se (and thus can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pseudonyms and De/Retitlings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Among the varied coverups, the art of the pseudonym works a kind of subterfuge. Blaise Pascal wrote as five different persons, depending what he was writing: mathematics, imagined letters, and so on, and the major othering writer is without any doubt Fernando Pessoa, who had at least seventy-five other characters, known as «heteronyms»: among them Alberto Caeiro, and Ricardo Reis, each of which had a different character, history, and style.</p>
                     <p>As for an amusing material coverup, try the cover of Frederic Tuten’s autobiography, which is over­pictured by a gigantic Roy Lichtenstein cheese: obviously, the Big Cheese whose writing lurks.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canceling (out)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: Whether we are dealing with textual or be-yond-textual subterfuges, Mallarmé appears as the presiding consciousness of a constellation of poeticians of the blank exploring the alternance of absence in presence and for whom the spaces and silences between words matter at least as much as words themselves or the things they designate. Mallarmé’s poetry is geared towards the creation of paradoxical objects which cancel themselves as soon as they are named (one is reminded of his «absent tomb», his «flights which have not fled» and the «abolished bauble of sonorous uselessness» of his aptly de-titled «Sonnet allégorique de lui-même»<sup>13</sup>).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rubouts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: And speaking of self-erasures, «self-kleptomania, the normal state of man is Dada»<sup>23</sup>. What could be more deliciously Dada than the self-interest of self-stealing: why of course, from whom else could one steal so generously? And in any case, self-proclamation as the rubbing out of the self («we are all presidents of Dada» says the Papa-Dada, Tristan Tzara, who proclaims the manifesto as a non-manifesto: «In principle, I am against manifestoes, as I am also against principles»)<sup>24</sup>. Of course, and this is always the Dada point: you state something to unstate it, you state the self as delighting in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Clinamen</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: Walker’s installation is about how art seeks to remediate history’s tragic flaws by revisiting some of its cardinal sins and canonical objects. Likewise, the canonical status enjoyed by Mallarmé and Proust looms large in Broodthaers’s and Bennequin’s erasure experiments. Like Broodthaers’s «IMAGE»,<italic>Ommage</italic>suggests that such acts of undoing - whether affectionate, ironic or both - often originate in an attempt to deal with the pressure of influence. In<italic>The Anxiety of Influence</italic>, Harold Bloom famously argued that poets since Milton have sought to escape from their predecessors’ haunting importance. In view of the examples seen so far the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: The poems in<italic>RADI OS</italic>result from the complete deletion of the «unwanted» words, leaving no trace of the original text except for the layout of the page (the surviving words still appear where they belong in Milton’s poem). Other erasure poets have opted for a format which allows the reader total or partial access to the original work. Jen Bervin’s<italic>Nets</italic>, a rewriting of Shakespeare’s<italic>Sonnets</italic>, relegates Shakespeare’s poems to a faded background text «upon which» the selected words appear in bold ink. Unlike Johnson’s, Bervin’s «reduction» does not stress the elemental and the natural but, rather, tends</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Slashes and Burnings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: As for harmings and undoings of the other, Antonin Artaud really took the cookie. In his celebrated spell-castings, he outdid every performative act in his visual leavings, with the destruction of multiple readable traces. When we read Stephen Barber’s remarkable<italic>Antonin Artaud: Terminal Curses: The Notebooks 1945-1948</italic>, we see how obsession never had it so good. Terminal. Absolutely terminal. We call this apocalyptic erasure, conflagration, tearing up, a destruction willed by a genius of a madman. Artaud-le-Momo, that other, the late other of Antonin Artaud the actor, whose face as the priest holding up the bible for that other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Performative Undoings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: So when the undoing is built into the work of art, is it not still art? Think of the slashes of Fontana into his canvasses, think of Serrano’s «Piss Christ» with the scandal of the title and the figuration, even simply imagined, built right in. Yes, I would say, it is art. Some of the most spectacular spectacles of undoing in recent times are the work of Jay Critchley, both in his home performances, at 7 Carnes Lane, off Pleasant Street, in Provincetown, Massachusetts, and also all over the town. For example, the demolition of a bathhouse which caused</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Attacks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: October 8, 2012, there was a great deal of excitement about a man who scrawled stuff on a Rothko painting over the weekend at the Tate Modern Museum, and led to someone’s listing previous defacements of works of art. Let me meditate first on the idea of defacement: is it not also bestowing a new face on the work of art however celebrated the latter might be? A new face, as in Monument Valley, or Easter Island, something unexpected? Might we not in some moments prefer the unexpected to the ho-hum expected? Not that a Rothko is ever boringly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Redoing as Rethinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: The year 1985 finds another attack on a work of art, and this one on a piece celebrating an exchange between the heavens and a bed. This inadmissible work celebrates an ultimately provocative display of a woman, not just naked but with her delicate slippers tossed to the ground, her ultra-luxurious thick and gold-bordered rug thrown over a bedside table, and the bestowing angel in the heavens: against Rembrandt’s<italic>Danae</italic>a man hurled acid, and destroyed about 30 per cent of the canvas. The conceptual artist Kathleen Gilje in her series of<italic>Restorings</italic>, this one called<italic>Danaë: Restored (after</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>More Cover-Ups, Overpaintings, Blackouts and Cutting-Outs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: An exhaustive list of early 21st century erasurist texts would have to include Stephen Ratcliffe’s<italic>[where late the sweet] BIRDS SANG</italic>(another text cut out of Shakespeare’s<italic>Sonnets</italic>), Mary Ruefle’s correction fluid covered<italic>A Little White Shadow</italic>(based on a late, anonymous 19th century manual published «for the Benefit of a Summer Home for Working Girls»), Austin Kleon’s self-explanatory<italic>Newspaper Blackout</italic>, Janet Holmes’s further reduction of Emily Dickinson’s already elliptical verse in<italic>The ms of my kin</italic>, David Dodd Lee’s Ashbery-erasing<italic>Skybooths in the Breath Somewhere</italic>, Srikanth Reddy’s<italic>Voyager</italic>(an erasure of Kurt Waldheim’s memoirs), my own truncated Carrollian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Turnarounds</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: What a wonderful turnaround, fooling everyone in sight, because that is exactly where it isn’t, in sight! In the Florence Griswold Museum, in Lyme, Connecticut, there is a painting you might know about, but no way can you see it unless you ask. Robert Fullonton’s painting in the dining room? Oh, well, it is on the back of another panel, because the Lyme Colony artists flipped over his panel when he left and didn’t pay his room and board. It sounds grand, but I didn’t see it: it is, evidently, a «Rocky Seacoast», with dabs of green paint for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ex-humings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: Despite the exponential popularity of erasure techniques amongst contemporary experimental artists, the most important and successful avatar of overpainting erasurism to this day remains Tom Phillips’s ongoing<italic>A Humument: A Treated Victorian Novel</italic>(1966-). By «ex-huming» the corpse of an obscure late 19<sup>th</sup>century novel (W.H. Mallock’s now forgotten three-decker<italic>A Human Document</italic>[1892])<italic>A Humument</italic>eludes Bloom’s logic of influence and constitutes a singular case of a rewriting whose achievements clearly outdo those of its (non-canonical) predecessor. For Phillips erasure is as much about covering and adding as it is about canceling and subtracting: the book is filled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Oubapian and Filmic Undoings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: One of the most interesting and innovative successors to Phillips’s<italic>A Humument</italic>, Jochen Gerner’s oubapian blackout<italic>TNT en amérique</italic>(2002), obliterates the pages of Hergé’s 1932<italic>Tintin en amérique</italic>with black ink, substituting pictograms and isolated one-word balloons to the original panels. The selected bits of plot and dialogue become the main focus of attention in the absence of a visible whole by which to contextualize them. On a superficial level, Gerner’s reduction of «TIN-TIN» to «TNT» would seem to evoke the exploded quality of the layout although the words preserved from Hergé’s version are reinscribed in their original</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>RE-doings and Doing Both:</title>
                     <subtitle>Foamy Stuff</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: So here is also what amuses me: think of molecular, what do you call it? molecular magic? that Ferran Adrià led the world in doing, like you make a thing with FOAM and here are the elements all drowned in the magic, and people gasp WOW and is that art or undoing the original elements or both? I think both.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>And How About Meta-Stuff?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: «Katz, a détournement of Maus, has opened to a new interpretation of Art Spiegelman’s work, basically by changing every animal-faced character into a cat-faced one. Then, as Spiegelman published MetaMaus, METAKATZ was realised as a collective essai about copyright and his exceptions, like detournement, collage and sampling»<sup>58</sup>.</p>
                     <p>In a sense, parody undoes art by taking the mickey out of it. So when the publishing house Flammarion destroyed the copies of Ilan Manouach’s<italic>Katz</italic>book, the incineration - think Savanarola, think chopping of the heads of statues during various revolutions, think Fahrenheit 451 (check), this undoing on purpose is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Van Gogh, according to the astounding exhibition in the Metropolitan Museum in New York, knew that the red lake pigment he was using for his still lifes - such as in the irises and the roses he gathered in bunches from the garden in St. Remy to paint, three months before his suicide - might fade. He took that risk because he wanted to see how the purple (blue and red, of course) of the irises would look against the yellow of the sunflowers, and how the pink of the roses (white and red) would look against the verdant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>States of Decay</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: If we are looking for artworks which fore­ground the potential for self-erasure or self-de­struction of the image we have to turn to experimental photography and film. In many ways, Stan Brakhage’s 1963 «Mothlight» bridges the conceptual gap between erasure techniques and (self-) destruction per se. «Mothlight» differs from Brakhage trademark hand painted films in that it incorporates insects wings, petals, leaves and blades of grass pasted upon the strips of celluloid. The director’s account of how «Mothlight» originates in personal suffering deserves to be quoted in full: «Here is a film that I made out of a deep grief.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>More Burnings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In book Twenty-six of Herman Melville’s<italic>Pierre: or, the Ambiguities</italic>, the destruction of a painting figures as the metaphor of a ridding-self of anything former, of past resemblance, to person and to past, and the revivifying of what has been, not irremediably however, lost, leaving only «certain shadowy traces». Two paintings face each other in a gallery, above the heads of the visitors: and mystifyingly, they set the scene for a crisis of non-revelation and future pain. Pierre has destroyed the key to past events, in which his father sired a daughter with a French woman, now present as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Undoings of the Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Human and ritualistic self-destruction works the same way: when you are an artist, and you jump of a bridge into water, it is surely undoing your art. So Robert Schumann trying to drown himself in the Rhine in 1854 before he was taken to an asylum where he stopped composing alto-gether, Paul Celan going off the Pont Mirabeau in Paris - of all bridges, given Apollinaire’s famous poem about its remaining! - and Ghérasim Luca off the same bridge, and then John Berryman in 1972 in Minnesota (see The New York Review of Books, June 4, 2015 for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Undoing the Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: What does madness undo? I have been wondering about suicidal madness, or rather, terminal madness, as in Virginia Woolf, on whom so many of us write and keep writing, and as in Unica Zürn, who - this brilliant artist who jabbed her pencil into her paper as Antonin Artaud jabbed his into his flesh, always on one particular part, to make a point, but finally a fatal one - after being in various mental hospitals, continuing to make her art with the materials brought her by Henri Michaux («the man of Jasmine»), she was released, spent the night with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Self-Undoing Performed</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.D.: David Nebreda’s life and work have pushed the boundaries of undoing (and of abject, stercoral hunger art) to unprecedented extremes.</p>
                     <p>The artist’s emaciated body was born out of a strict vegetarian diet consisting exclusively of small quantities of boiled or raw vegetables. Nebreda’s early artistic career began with a period of total silence which marked his first psychiatric internment at the age of eighteen, a period during which he began to develop his art of the self-portrait, a genre he has been practicing exclusively to this day. Typically, silence and starvation, verbal and alimentary abstinence participate in a movement</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Undoings of the Other</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Madeleine Gide, André Gide’s deservedly angry, disappointed and deeply frustrated wife, given his well-documented and self-documented affection for others, such as Marc Allégret, destroyed his letters, which sent him into major anger. How not, to both reactions? We are talking major jealousy, for major-good reasons.</p>
                     <p>To say nothing, but I’d like to say something, about the woman who so adored him, who so brilliantly translated his work, and who helped him with his English, that is Dorothy Strachey Bussy, the sister of Lytton Strachey. She tore nothing up, set fire to nothing, but spent a good part of her</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Scissoring the Sister</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: Here’s a tale: Florine Stettheimer’s sister Ettie, she of the pseudonym - how delicious it is! - “Henrie Waste,” published two novels under that rather extraordinary name:<italic>Philosophy/An Autobiographical Fragment</italic>, in 1917, and<italic>Love Days</italic>in 1923. She seems to have written her doctoral dissertation for Freiburg University in 1907 on William James’<italic>The Will to Believe</italic>, which was translated into English and published with those two novels and a few short stories.<sup>63</sup>And, to top it off, she also painted, like her famous sister Florine. BUT, and this seems a bit beyond the pale, to understate the case,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Loathing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: So how does your individual loathing undo the art against which it is (and you are) directed? You won’t be alone in our detestation of Jeff Koons, we think, but why? Is it kitsch and we never loved kitsch? Or is it overblownness and we like small? That can’t be it, since we really love large Motherwells and don’t find the massive black ovals overpowering, just persuasive. It is something that is crystallized, well, blown up into the balloons and stuck there, like idiocy itself.</p>
                     <p>But our particular loathing goes nowhere because the Things Sell. So numbers count, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>No Longer Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: A thought-provoking exhibition of artwork deemed, by insurance companies, no longer art, which is the title of the show, documented by John Reed, at the Arthur Ross Architecture Gallery at Columbia University in December of 2012. The first work he saw displayed was a 19<sup>th</sup>century painting of French country life, called<italic>The Harvest (La Moisson)</italic>, by Alexandre Dubuisson. The large gash in its surface meant that it could not be insured, which was the point of the show: thus its title «No Longer Art».</p>
                     <p>Elka Krajewska first had the notion for «No Longer Art» in May of 2009.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Not Even Existing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M.A.C.: «I never say anything», says Artaud (46) and as if to underscore that statement, he uses only school-children’s notebooks to write in, in these last years. He chooses to be infuriating - in writing his<italic>Henchmen and Torturings</italic>of 1947, he says about it:</p>
                     <p>an infuriating book that is absolutely impossible to read that nobody has ever read from end to end, not even its own author, because he doesn’t exist<sup>69</sup>
                     </p>
                     <p>That rather takes care of that.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CREDITS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABSTRACT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIOGRAPHIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm83d.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
