<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN452.B87 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Authors</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Autobiography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Other (Philosophy) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Self in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Identity (Psychology) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Death in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Baudelaire, Charles, 1821–1867</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712–1778</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">De Quincey, Thomas, 1785–1859</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Wilde, Oscar, 1854–1900</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Regard for the Other: Autothanatography in Rousseau, De Quincey, Baudelaire, and Wilde</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Burt</surname>
               <given-names>E. S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823230907</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246762</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x02w0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Although much has been written on autobiography, the same cannot be said of autothanatography, the writing of one's death. This study starts from the deconstructive premise that autobiography is aporetic, not or not only a matter of a subject strategizing with language to produce an exemplary identity but a matter also of its responding to an exorbitant call to write its death. The I-dominated representations of particular others and of the privileged other to whom a work is addressed, must therefore be set against an alterity plaguing the I from within or shadowing it from without. This alterity makes itself known in writing as the potential of the text to carry messages that remain secret to the confessing subject. Anticipation of the potential for the confessional text to say what Augustine calls the secret I do not know,the secret of death, engages the autothanatographical subject in a dynamic, inventive, and open-ended process of identification. The subject presented in these texts is not one that has already evolved an interior life that it seeks to reveal to others, but one that speaks to us as still in process. Through its exorbitant response, it gives intimations of an interiority and an ethical existence to come. Baudelaire emerges as a central figure for this understanding of autobiography as autothanatography through his critique of the narcissism of a certain Rousseau, his translation of De Quincey's confessions, with their vertiginously ungrounded subject-in-construction, his artistic practice of self-conscious, thorough-going doubleness, and his service to Wilde as model for an aporetic secrecy. The author discusses the interruption of narrative that must be central to the writing of one's death and addresses the I's dealings with the aporias of such structuring principles as secrecy, Levinasian hospitality, or interiorization as translation. The book makes a strong intervention in the debate over one of the most-read genres of our time.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>A Clutch of Brothers: Alterity and Autothanatography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the numerous studies that have been devoted to autobiography in the past 30 years, surprisingly few take on directly the question of the other. The reason for the surprise is simple enough: One can hardly envision the self without the other against which it is defined or an autobiography that does not involve the other both in its narrative and as the one to whom the “I’’ addresses itself in its act of confessing. In representing itself, the I must not only represent the others encountered in life, but must also address that representation to another. What is more,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Developments in Character:</title>
                     <subtitle>“The Children’s Punishment” and “The Broken Comb”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Reading” is a term that, through overuse, can easily become confused with interpretation. In fact, there is a crucial difference: Reading involves the undoing of interpretative figures; because it is not an operation opposed to the understanding but rather a precondition for it, it allows us to question whether the synthetic moves of the understanding can close off a text. It leads away from meaning to such problems as the text’s constitution and meaning generation. Unlike interpretation, which implies a development over the course of a narrative toward a single figure reconciling all its diverse moments, reading states the logic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Regard for the Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Embarrassment in the Quatrième promenade</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One difference between shame and embarrassment in Rousseau can be stated quite simply. Shame is a passion productive of discourse. The confessing done under its aegis seems marvelously able to serve as an action of which to be ashamed, and so to provoke more confession. Embarrassment, on the other hand, is tonguetied, an anacoluthon in the grammar of feelings. Where, under influence of timidity, Rousseau manages to blurt something out nonetheless, the effect is not to end the silence but most often to prolong it, rendering the hapless speaker even more incapable of timely speech. The blurted phrase is less</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Shape before the Mirror:</title>
                     <subtitle>Autobiography and the Dandy in Baudelaire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Baudelaire’s work is far from self-evidently autobiographical.<italic>Les Fleurs du mal</italic>, for instance, cannot be easily compared with a self-declared poetic autobiography like Victor Hugo’s<italic>Contemplations</italic>, whose poems are of decidedly personal inspiration, bear dates that attach them to experience, and lay out a plausible narrative of poetic development. In contrast, Baudelaire’s undated poems appear impersonal and, in their emblematic character, untethered to experience. Although the poet does give the collection the status of an expressive work in one letter to Ancelle: “Do I have to tell you, you who have guessed it no more than the others, that in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Hospitality in Autobiography:</title>
                     <subtitle>Levinas chez De Quincey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What would a Levinasian autobiography look like? Is such a thing imaginable? The question is directed in the first instance at autobiography, as a question concerning its ability to go beyond the representation of the subject to write the encounter with the absolutely other for which Levinas’s ethical philosophy calls. But it is also, in the second instance, a question for Levinas, concerning the potential of autobiography to represent an alterity perhaps not fully accounted for by his philosophy. This double question presides over the reflection that follows.</p>
                     <p>Certainly, the notion of Levinasian self-writing is, at first blush, unpromising. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Eating with the Other in Les Paradis artificiels</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critics of autobiography who have cut their teeth on Rousseau’s<italic>Confessions</italic>cannot help but be sensible to numerous differences when they begin reading De Quincey and Baudelaire. One of those differences, at first little more than a direction given a motif, is indicative of a shift in the strategies for responding to the other in Modernist texts, among whom—against the usual tendency to group him with the Romantics—I am counting De Quincey as an early prototype. Through its connection to aesthetics, this motif can let us consider what the Modernist autobiographer, writing in the wake of the<italic>Rêveries</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Secrets Can Be Murder:</title>
                     <subtitle>How to Write the Secret in De Profundis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>De Profundis</italic>, Wilde’s autobiographical letter, is motivated by a double silence, and with it, a double secret and a double responsibility that say much about Wilde’s concept of the I in its relation to the other. As we shall see, these two silences, which bring us into the arena of autobiography yet also bar entrance to it because muteness threatens to make confession problematic, are divided over whether that relation is under the aegis of conditional or unconditional laws, repeating the same division found in the discussion of hospitality in De Quincey. There, I discussed the two cases in isolation;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x02w0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
