<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">AZ186.M35 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanities</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanities</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Learning and scholarship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Communication in learning and scholarship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Technological innovations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Digital media</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Internet</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Globalization</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social change</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Education</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A New Republic of Letters</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McGann</surname>
               <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674728691</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780674369245</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jerome McGann</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt6wpnfx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Jerome McGann's manifesto argues that the history of texts and how they are preserved and accessed for interpretation are the overriding subjects of humanist study in the digital age. Theory and philosophy no longer suffice as an intellectual framework. But philology--out of fashion for decades--models these concerns with surprising fidelity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Here is surely a truth now universally acknowledged: that the whole of our cultural inheritance has to be recurated and reedited in digital forms and institutional structures. But as the technology of cultural memory shifts from bibliographical to digital machines, a difficult question arises: what do we do with the books? This is a problem for society at large and many people are working at it, none more assiduously than certain expert persons, often technicians. Highly skilled and motivated as they are, book history and the complex machineries of books fall outside their professional expertise. Humanist scholars, the long-recognized monitors</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Why Textual Scholarship Matters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why does textual scholarship matter? Most students of literature and culture who worked in the twentieth century would have thought that a highly specialized question, and many still do. But a hundred years ago the question would hardly have been posed at all. Until the early decades of the twentieth century what we now call literary and cultural studies was called philology, and all its interpretive procedures were clearly understood to be grounded in textual scholarship. But twentieth-century textual studies shifted their center from philology to hermeneutics, that subset of philological inquiry focused on the specifically literary interpretation of culture.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“The Inorganic Organization of Memory”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let’s try to imagine philology as the ground of literary and cultural studies. Philology, not philosophy, because philology’s horizon is not a history of ideas but an institutional and programmatic history. And not philology as Wilamowitz presented it to Nietz sche, or as post-Nietzscheans expelled it from humane studies, but Philology in a New Key—a new arrangement of that canonical discipline so neglected after the nineteenth century.¹ Those huddled, dryasdust positivists are yearning to be free.</p>
                     <p>An imaginative recovery of philological method means revisiting some salient moments in our recent institutional history. I begin by telling two stories. One</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>History, Philosophy, Philology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Just about a hundred years before Lyotard and the Paris VIII philosophy department tried to reform both the theory and practice of humanities education and knowledge research, a famous controversy broke out in Germany around the same issues. The publication of Nietzsche’s<italic>The Birth of Tragedy</italic>(1872) provoked Ulrich von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff to a sharp attack—at once witty, trenchant, and ad hominem. Nearly everyone agrees that Wilamowitz largely swept the field. In a confident if nasty peroration, he called for Nietzsche’s resignation as professor of philology at the University of Basel. Six years later Nietzsche did just that, shaking dryasdust</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Documented World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>the need for roots</italic>, Simone Weil criticizes historical thinking and its search for documentary foundations. “There are holes in documents,” Weil points out, so that when we read them we want to ensure that “unfounded hypotheses be present to the mind.” Reading documents requires “reading between the lines, to transport oneself fully, with complete self-forgetfulness, into the events evoked there…. The so-called historical mind does not pass through the paper to flesh and blood; it consists of a subordination of thought to the document.”¹</p>
                     <p>Weil always saw reading as a spiritual emergency. Readings which “pass through the paper to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Marking Texts in Many Dimensions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although “text” has been a “Keyword” in clerical and even popular discourse for well over fifty years, it did not find a place in Raymond Williams’s important book<italic>Keywords</italic>(1976). This strange omission may perhaps be explained by the word’s cultural ubiquity and power. In that lexicon of modernity Williams called the “Vocabulary of Culture and Society,” “text” has been the “one word to rule them all.” Indeed, the word “text” became so shape-shifting and meaning-malleable that we should probably label it with Tolkien’s full rubrication: “text” has been, and still is, the “one word to rule them all and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Digital Tools and the Emergence of the Social Text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like another important edition of our time, Hans Gabler’s<italic>Ulysses</italic>, J. C. C. Mays’s edition on Coleridge—three volumes, each in two parts—set an inspiring example of scholarly thoroughness and integrity.¹ But the real strength of the work rests ultimately in something else—something quite rare in the scholarly editions of English-speaking authors produced in the last fifty years. Mays is deeply sympathetic to Coleridge’s poetry—not unaware of or reticent to address its failings and limitations, but fronting all the work with what Desmond McCarthy, writing of Coleridge, called “the most delicate sympathy.” “When he writes of it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>What Do Scholars Want?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Sustainability” is a dark but potent word in the field of digital humanities. It signals a broad set of concerns—both technical and institutional—about how to maintain and augment the increasingly large body of digital information that humanists are both creating and using. It is a word with far more than a contemporary pertinence, however. It could (it should) remind us that the traditional problems of philology have scarcely changed at all, and certainly have not gone away.</p>
                     <p>But the problems of the philologue and the digeratus do<italic>look</italic>different, so let’s consider the problem of sustainability in its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Philological Investigations I:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Example of Poe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An acute sense of what Marjorie Perloff called “the poetics of indeterminacy” has marked criticism and scholarship for at least thirty years.¹ Synthetic narratives—historicist, dialectical, psychoanalytic—have seen their truth values turn imaginary, becoming what William Blake in<italic>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</italic>called “poetic tales”: arbitrary constructions, “fictions of lineage,” and order.² With the space of knowledge grown so radically volatile and complex, even “contested,” the teacher’s watchword became “teach the conflicts,” the scholar’s, “explore the contradictions.” So David Reynolds dives “beneath the American Renaissance” to expose the fault lines of F. O. Matthiessen’s famous normative narrative,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Philological Investigations II:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Page from Cooper</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Armitage, the Wanderer in Wordsworth’s<italic>Excursion</italic>, tells “The Story of Margaret,” he takes the scene of a ruined rural cottage for his text.</p>
                     <p>I see around me here</p>
                     <p>Things which you cannot see: we die, my Friend,</p>
                     <p>Nor we alone, but that which each man loved</p>
                     <p>And prized in his peculiar nook of earth</p>
                     <p>Dies with him, or is changed; and very soon</p>
                     <p>Even of the good is no memorial left.</p>
                     <p>(<italic>The Excursion</italic>, Book I, 469–474)</p>
                     <p>The tale recalls a dark passage from the inscrutable Book of God. Because Armitage has read the passage before, he is well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pseudodoxia Academica; or, Literary Studies in a Global Age</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since all the cultural materials discussed in this book are resolutely Occidental, I should perhaps say something about how I’ve tried to engage with the global issues facing anyone interested in these things. For my argument holds that digital technology has realized the idea of a new Library of Alexandria. That institution’s dark reciprocal, however, is the global character of the threat to memory, epitomized in the crisis of our languages. Linguists expect that by the end of this century some half of the 7,000 currently recognized languages will be extinct. In a narrow Western view, those losses occur at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wpnfx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
