<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Translating the English Bible</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Relevance to Deconstruction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Goodwin</surname>
               <given-names>Philip W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173916</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227900383</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Philip W. Goodwin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf395"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In his detailed and thought-provoking work, Philip Goodwin conducts a thorough analysis of the challenges facing the Biblical translator, with particular focus on the problematic dominance of the King James Version of the Bible in our imaginations – a dominance which has had a deleterious effect upon the accuracy and originality of the translator's work. Goodwin considers the first two chapters of the Lukan narratives in depth, comparing and contrasting a breadth of widely disparate translations and drawing on a rich body of Biblical scholarship to support his thesis. A wide-ranging discussion of other linguistic issues is also conducted, touching on such vital matters as incorporating the contextual implications of the original text, and the attempt to challenge the reader's pre-existing encyclopaedic knowledge. Goodwin evolves a fresh and comprehensive answer to the difficulties of the translator's task, and concludes by providing his own original and charming translation of the first two chapters of Luke's Gospel. 'Translating the English Bible' provides a fascinating insight into the processes of translation and will interest anyone seeking accuracy and fidelity to the Scriptural message. It will also enlighten readers seeking a challenging translation of Luke that casts off the shackles of the 'Holy Marriage' tradition of Biblical translation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goodwin</surname>
                           <given-names>Phil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Note to the reader</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>The Holy Marriage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘The main thrust of what I want to say is that translating the Bible is an art that we seem to have lost, for mysterious reasons.’ So said David Daniell, the distinguished Tyndale scholar, at a conference in London in February 1995. There has been, to my knowledge, no decisive answer offered to the question implied by his statement. Daniell himself points out some of the central paradoxes of this situation. The ‘we’ of his statement refers, of course, to the community of English-speakers, a language which ‘has never been in better shape … It is healthier than ever before,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Challenging the Holy Marriage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Relevance Theory and translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Relevance Theory is a development of communication theory springing from Paul Grice’s notion that there must be a ‘Co-operative Principle’ at work in conversation. This principle underwrites Maxims of Conversation underlying our ability to communicate. One of these, the so-called Maxim of Relation, simply specifies this: Be Relevant. Grice observed that speakers in conversation seem to observe this maxim, both in speaking and in interpreting, and that it is this ‘unspoken agreement’ which allows communication to take place, despite the indeterminacy of reference which is characteristic of language. Two linguists, Dan Sperber and Deirdre Wilson picked up this ball in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Start as you mean to go on?</title>
                     <subtitle>Syntax in Luke 1.1-4</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen in the previous chapter that a Relevance based theory of translation (which we christened<italic>RTT</italic>) presents a number of attractions in forming a broadly based account for a phenomenon which plays an enormously significant role in human behaviour and culture yet has notoriously defied rigorous analysis. The attractions on which we focussed centred on the simplicity of the account, its integration with communication theory as a whole and with other aspects of human behaviour, and its potential for effecting an intellectual rapprochement with other quite different approaches to the problems of human communication, approaches which are far</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>When is a priest not a priest?</title>
                     <subtitle>The semantics of ἱɛρɛύϛ in Luke 1</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Chapter Three we considered the Preface to Luke’s gospel, and found that it was a certain combination of syntactical features, rather than the semantics of the piece, which gave it its relevance. This, of course, is not the universal or perhaps even the normal state of affairs: on the contrary, the semantic properties of a text are normally very important in how it achieves relevance. Although part of the agenda of the present work is to challenge the assumption that semantics are always and everywhere the ‘trump card’ in interpreting a text, it has to be acknowledged that they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Still looking for clues</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We saw in Chapter Two that in his exposition of a Relevance Theory of Translation, Gutt introduces the idea of ‘communicative clues’ and ‘direct translation’ at a crucial point in his argument.¹ A communicative clue is a feature of an utterance or a text which guides the hearer or reader to how the communicator intends it to achieve relevance. Gutt proposes eight kinds of communicative clue, and suggests that what he names direct translation ‘calls for the preservation of all communicative clues … [B]y preserving all the communicative clues of the original, such translation would it make it possible for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Repetitive texture and four kinds of literalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We ended the last chapter with the potentially disruptive finding that<italic>any</italic>feature of a text may be a communicative clue, and may indeed turn out to be the most important clue to how a given text achieves relevance for a particular reader. As we have seen repeatedly, there is a longstanding practice in biblical translation of attending to only some of the clues to relevance, and this arises because the translator’s mind is clouded by the idea of ‘equivalence’. Because she or he thinks that her task is to produce a target text which is somehow equivalent (however that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Final remarks:</title>
                     <subtitle>The experimental translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The translation which follows, in the Appendix, is not (far from it!) the Perfect Translation, but an Experimental Translation, of the first two chapters of Luke’s gospel, as it appears in the main text of Nestle-Aland 27<sup>th</sup>edition.</p>
                     <p>‘Experimental’ means just that – it is an experiment to see whether and to what extent a ‘perfect’ translation of any text is possible, if perfection is defined as above – as that which permits both construction of the relevant interpretation, and its deconstruction. In terms of the concepts used in Chapter Two, it aims above all to provide ‘outstanding value’ to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Experimental Translation of Luke 1–2</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf395.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
