<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BH39.T93 1990</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Art, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Twentieth Century Theories of Art</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>THOMPSON</surname>
               <given-names>JAMES M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1990</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780886291112</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773596054</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773596054</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1990</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Carleton University Press Inc.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cd0kz3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Description not available.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although it is not always recognized, art is produced and enjoyed and even defined against a background of theories and ideas. Oversimplifying greatly, up to the 18th century theories of art were largely developments of and reactions to elements in Greek thought. The 18th and 19th centuries saw a tremendous development of new thinking about art. The 20th century has been even more prolific in production of new approaches. Some are developments of earlier themes but on the whole they can be studied independently. At the same time one can discern a good deal of interrelation between those 20th century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Expression Theory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Art and Feeling</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Expression Theory is one of the distinctively modern approaches to art. “Art is the expression of emotion.” Of course earlier writers said a good deal about art and emotion. Plato described art as the feeding and watering of the passions. In the third century the Peri-Hypsous stressed the importance of vehement emotions in the literary work. Renaissance artists were much concerned with the faithful rendering of feeling states in the portrayal of their subjects. Eighteenth century artists and theorists had much to say about the sublime, the feeling of delicious terror. Hegel emphasized the insight art gives into the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Formalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though formalism reached its full flowering in the 20th century, there are vigorous statements of formalist themes in the 19th century and its roots go back to the 18th century. To trace the origins of 20th century versions is by no means an easy task. In part formalist theories emerge as protests against other theories, partic:ularly those emphasizing emotion and biographical criticism on the one hand and those which emphasize general rules and classical traditions on the other. Partly also they emerge in response to the challenge of developing critical methods adequate to late 19th and 20th century art forms.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Psychological Approach</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the case of the psychological approach it becomes even more immediately obvious that in fact the title refers not to a single theory but a number of approaches emerging from different psychological theories. Our selections introduce psycho-analytical and gestalt theories.</p>
                     <p>It has been said that with the possible exception of Einstein no one has had more influence than Freud on the 20th century. It is not surprising, therefore, that Freudian approaches to art have been popular. Since a general acquaintance with Freudian theory can be assumed only a very brief introduction will be given.</p>
                     <p>According to Freud much that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Sociological Approach</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any approach to art is sociological which solves the familiar problems of description, interpretation and evaluation by setting the artwork in the context of the society in which it was produced. Nowadays sociological approaches tend either to be committed to or influenced by Marxist views. I use the plural deliberately since there is not a single commonly accepted Marxist approach to a theory of art and art criticism.</p>
                     <p>One reason for the variety of approaches in this case is the fact that Marx himself did not develop a theory of art, nor did Engels. Marx obviously was well acquainted with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Semiotics and Structuralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even more than in the case of the other sections it must be stressed that the selections presented constitute nothing more than an introduction. The double-barrelled title already suggests an embarrassment: are we dealing with one movement or two? In fact semiotics (or semiology, the term often preferred in Europe), let alone structuralism, is used to cover a considerable variety of positions. In the case of movements such as the expression theory and formalism the approaches in their alternative versions have already been pretty thoroughly worked out. Here we are dealing with a dynamic movement (or movements?) which has not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Existentialism and Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary existentialism is typically a combination of two backgrounds, classical 19th century existentialis1l1 and phenomenological techniques. Though existentialist themes are to be found in Greek thought and in the Bible, the two most influential modem proponents are Kierkegaard (1813-1855) and Nietzsche (1844-1900). In Kierkegaard basic themes include: emphasis on the individual in his concrete particularity as contrasted with the individual conceived as part of a system; general antipathy to systems and rules; emphasis on commitment and choice as essential for real existence: emphasis on freedom as realized in the choices by the individual who in choosing makes himself; despair/dread in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Poststructuralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is not clear where semiotics/structuralism ended and poststructuralism began. Indeed it is not clear whether we are dealing with a new movement or new developments in semiotics/structuralism. But it is certain that since the mid-sixties a number of French writers, while still drawing on Saussure, have developed this tradition in novel ways: in Roland Barthes’ writing the shift is evident between<italic>Elements of Semiology</italic>and<italic>S</italic>/Z. Though there are similarities amongst poststructuralists there are also very distinctive differences. Consequently it seems more profitable to describe the theorists who have been most influential than to attempt an encompassing definition. Since</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kz3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Analytical/Linguistic Approach</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the English-speaking world, roughly from the 1950s to the 1970s, academic discussion of art and theory was dominated by this approach. The origin is largely in the work of English philosophers who became prominent in the forties and fifties and whose approach has been variously described as linguistic philosophy, philosophical analysis and philosophy of language. The name most prominent is that of Ludwig Wittgenstein (1889- 1951). His<italic>Philosophical Investigations</italic>was published in 1954 though his views had become widely known during the forties through the writings of other philosophers. Other seminal influences come from John Austin, Gilbert Ryle and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
