<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h097q</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8507.A67Z848 2001</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Davies, Robertson, 1913-1995</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Robertson Davies</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Mingling of Contrarieties</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>La Bossière</surname>
               <given-names>Camille R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Morra</surname>
               <given-names>Linda M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616865</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616862</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Ont. Canada</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpdzq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This collection of essays on the writing of Robertson Davies addresses the basic problems in reading his work by looking at the topics of doubling, disguise, irony, paradox, and dwelling in "gaps" or spaces "in between." The essays present new insights on a broad range of topics in Davies' oeuvre and represent one of the first major discussions devoted to Davies' work since his death in 1995.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Davies Tristram-gistus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LA BOSSIÈRE</surname>
                           <given-names>CAMILLE R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once upon a time, in 1949, Robertson Davies revisited the time of his youth to recall of his first reading in Aldous Huxley that it lifted him into “the sunshine world of high comedy” and cast over his life “a summer glory... which no conceivable winter could dispel” (Enthusiasms 230). The book was Antic Hay (1923), taken up at the suggestion of a lad of his own age who aspired to priesthood in the Church of England. “Enthralled” by the “wonderfully amusing people,” “easy scholarship,” and “witty pedantry” he met with in that novel, the teenaged Davies immediately “knew that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Concert of His Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Perspectives on the Masks of Robertson Davies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PETERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is the spring of 1985 and Robertson Davies is writing to his old friend Gordon Roper about an exhausting publicity trip he has just undergone to promote<italic>What’s Bred in the Bone</italic>. He writes from Windover, his well-appointed rural retreat in the Caledon Hills north of Toronto, where above his desk hangs Yousuf Karsh’s photographic portrait of Carl Jung. Having complained to Roper about how shabbily he had been treated while giving readings at New York University and the National Library of Canada, he launches into an amusing story about his experiences at the National Library prior to his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“A Hint of the Basic Brimstone”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Humour of Robertson Davies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BALISCH</surname>
                           <given-names>FAITH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The comic mode is inseparable from Robertson Davies’ way of viewing the world; it is the illuminating medium, that “light that plays on the writer’s mind, in which all aspects of his work live and take their being.”¹ Nevertheless, amidst the considerable body of criticism of his writing, one finds little or no examination of his humour.² In his interviews, essays, speeches, plays, and works of fiction, Davies repeatedly reiterates his belief that humour is not incompatible with serious purpose, and that comedy “does not mean simply making people laugh. It is not the art of the stand-up comedian, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Undermining Comedy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shadows of Determinism in the Salterton Novels</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CREELMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Robertson Davies’ Salterton Trilogy has long played a poor second cousin to the more accomplished and widely studied Deptford novels. But if the first trilogy has garnered less attention than his subsequent fiction, the critics who have examined<italic>Tempest-Tost</italic>(1951),<italic>Leaven of Malice</italic>(1954), and<italic>A Mixture of Frailties</italic>(1958) have spoken with a perhaps surprisingly unified voice. Since Elspeth Buitenhuis explored the transformations of The Salterton Trilogy’s main protagonists, commentators have agreed that, in his early novels, Davies develops increasingly careful explorations of the individual’s emerging identity. John Mills summarises a commonality of critical opinion when he asserts that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Magic in the Web:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robertson Davies and Shamanstvo</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PETTIGREW</surname>
                           <given-names>TODD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Robertson Davies published books in seven different decades, books ranging from literary criticism to popular journalism to drama, and, perhaps most importantly, to novels. My edition of<italic>Happy Alchemy</italic>advertises thirty-two books by Davies-and that list does not seem to include all the plays. The task of coming to terms with the whole of Davies’ oeuvre is a daunting one.</p>
                     <p>To complicate matters, scholarly opinion about Davies’ work, perhaps inevitably, is more complicated and varied than the work itself. Criticism about Davies seems to include hyperbolic praise and openly hostile attacks in equal measure. John Irving has called him “the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Leaven of Wine and Spirits in the Fiction of Robertson Davies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STICK</surname>
                           <given-names>K.P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Visited a friend this evening who had procured a bottle of a very special tonic called<italic>Noilly Prat</italic>; in the interest of temperance, we experimented to see how much of the tonic it was necessary to put with a jigger of gin in order to kill the horrid taste. After several tries we got the measurements exactly right.” So says Samuel Marchbanks in his<italic>Diary</italic>.¹ Whether Davies himself liked martinis is of no concern here. My subject is his fondness for literary references to alcohol; they are as readily evident in his Marchbanksian ventures as in all of his novels</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Metadrama and Melodrama:</title>
                     <subtitle>Postmodern Elements in the Plays of Robertson Davies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHERLOW</surname>
                           <given-names>LOIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Robertson Davies’ first play,<italic>Three Gypsies</italic>, a romantic comedy set in Wales, was written during Davies’ final year at Oxford (1937-1938), just before his brief first career as a theatre professional.¹ Davies did not apply himself seriously, however, to becoming a playwright until 1944, when he could foresee a post-war resumption of theatrical activity both in Europe and Canada. He developed his craft in what he himself later called “the primitive era of Canadian theatre.”² In the 1940s and early 1950s in Canada, opportunities for professional production of new plays were almost non-existent; the only critics available to assess and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Where There’s a Will, There Are Always Two Ways”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Doubling in World of Wonders</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVERBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>MARK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>World of Wonders</italic>there are, as Magnus Eisengrim says, “double words for everything.”¹ Like many of Davies’ texts, World of<italic>Wonders</italic>is an intricate structure of dialogue and duality wherein Davies continually creates situations, images, and narrative structures that are doubled. Not only are they doubled, but this doubling is done in a duplicitous way. Like Eisengrim himself, who is named after that cunning animal the wolf, Doubles are often there to trick us. I intend to examine this doubling in two ways: in terms of narrative content and narrative structure. In the content phase, I will focus on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Authentic Forgeries:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hermeneutics, Artifice, and Authenticity in Robertson Davies’ What’s Bred in the Bone</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALLETT</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Simon Darcourt calls Francis Cornish a “true son of Hermes” early in<italic>What’s Bred in the Bone</italic>, he provides a hermeneutic “skeleton key” both to meaning in the novel and to a comprehension of Davies’ sense of self as moral fictionist.¹ The figure of Hermes organizes and gives meaning to the novel’s many uses of artifice and invention, even as the hermeneutic notion of “horizon(s) of expectation” enables a recognition of the didactic component of Davies’ fiction. Reference to devices such as retouched photos, player pianos, stories and lies that characters tell each other, and, especially, art restoration help</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Myth and Magic of a Textual and/or a Metaphorical Reading of The Deptford Trilogy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHORNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>TATJANA TAKSEVA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an interview with Michael Hulse in 1986, Robertson Davies responded at length to a question concerning the structure and themes of his novels and concluded by saying:</p>
                     <p>You have to think about readers. This is where I get in trouble with some of my academic critics. I am interested in having as many readers as possible, reaching as wide an audience as possible.... My books are not novels in the sense of being artistic constructs formed on something which reaches back to a French origin, or Henry James, or something. They’re romances. I just write romances, and when you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Converting the Clerisy”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Quest/ioning, Contradictions, and Ethics in The Cornish Triptych</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COLE</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREA C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Lyre of Orpheus</italic>, academic Penny Raven (a professor of Comparative Literature) comments on the significance of a piece of literature for an understanding of the project that the Cornish Foundation has undertaken:</p>
                     <p>You see, there’s a very great poem by Lewis Carroll about the Hunting of the Snark; a lot of crazy creatures set off, they know not whither, in search of they know not what.... It’s just about a crazy voyage that somehow, in an unfathomable way, makes a kind of eerie sense.¹</p>
                     <p>Canadians can be great seekers, or questers, for identity. The quest for identity is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Medical Consultation” for Murther and Walking Spirits and The Cunning Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>RICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRIGG</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is not an academic paper but a story with academic interest. It is the story of a book collector who particularly collected the books of Robertson Davies and who contacted him to ask if he would sign some books. From this grew an acquaintance of eight years and from that acquaintance came a correspondence in which that highly encyclopaedic among modern writers began to ask the book collector, who happened to be a physician-my physician, in fact-if he could provide answers to some unusual medical questions.</p>
                     <p>In what follows, Dr. Rick Davis shall read from his own letter to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdzq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
