<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vbx</collection-id>
      <volume>18</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Thresholds of Meaning</book-title>
         <subtitle>Passage, Ritual and Liminality in Contemporary French Narrative</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DUFFY</surname>
               <given-names>JEAN H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846316661</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846316791</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jean H. Duffy</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vjnd2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Thresholds of Meaning examines contemporary French narrative and explores two related issues: the centrality within recent French fiction and autofiction of the themes of passage, ritual and liminality; and the thematic continuity which links this work with its literary ancestors of the 1960s and 1970s. Through the close analysis of novels and récits by Pierre Bergounioux, François Bon, Marie Darrieussecq, Hélène Lenoir, Laurent Mauvignier and Jean Rouaud, Duffy demonstrates the ways in which contemporary narrative, while capitalising on the formal lessons of the nouveau roman and drawing upon a shared repertoire of motifs and themes, engages with the complex processes by which meaning is produced in the referential world and, in particular, with the rituals and codes that social man brings into play in order to negotiate the various stages of the human life-cycle. By the application of concepts and models derived from ritual theory and from visual analysis, Thresholds of Meaning situates itself at the intersection of the developing field of literature and anthropology studies and research into word and image.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="364"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the last thirty years or so, critics and cultural commentators in France and elsewhere have regularly – often with irritation, sometimes with gloomy defeatism and occasionally with a touch of<italic>Schadenfreude</italic>– drawn attention to what they believe to be the current ‘crisis’ or even decline of the French novel. These comments are, of course, part of a much more general context in which France has seen its cultural influence in the world undermined by among other factors: competition from the New York and London art markets, the impact of American cinema on French box-office receipts, the popularity of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>At death’s door:</title>
                     <subtitle>illness, ritual and liminality in Darrieussecq, Lenoir, and Mauvignier</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years the concepts of rite of passage and, in particular, of liminality have figured prominently in medical and medical-related research, providing useful ways of analysing a range of experiences of illness and disability. With the expansion of the medical humanities and the development of ‘narrative medicine’, medical practitioners have looked to other disciplines – literary analysis, philosophy, history and anthropology – for models and metaphors by which to express the experiences of patients, carers and clinicians. The attraction of the notion of rite of passage is obvious, offering a versatile means of expressing a range of phenomena including:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Suicide and saving face in Bon, Mauvignier and Bergounioux</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among acts by individuals that challenge social and religious norms, suicide ranks among the most transgressive. The part played by religion and, in particular, Christianity in the stigmatisation of the act of self-destruction and the individual who kills or attempts to kill himself/herself has, of course, been rehearsed on countless occasions. As Georges Minois points out in his overview of the history of suicide, the early Christian Church seemed to give out mixed messages on the question: the earthly life is a vale of tears and the Christian should aspire to death so that he/she can be united with God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Commemoration, monument and identity in Bergounioux, Darrieussecq and Rouaud</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the last thirty years, memory and commemoration studies have become one of the fastest developing interdisciplinary fields in the humanities, attracting the attention of, among others, historians, anthropologists, sociologists, literary critics and art-historians. This growth and the dizzying array of publications produced not only reflect what has been variously described as a memory boom, a memory industry, an addiction to memory and, perhaps most graphically, an ‘immersion in memory and its sites [that] may at times have the quality of junk-Proustian<italic>Schwärmerei</italic>’ (LaCapra, 1998, 8).¹ They also attest to the dynamic, if at times confusing and confused, dialogues taking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Retouching the past:</title>
                     <subtitle>family photographs and documents in Rouaud, Bon and Lenoir</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first hundred and twenty years following photography’s invention, analysis of the new medium was dominated by discussion of three central issues: its relationship with art and its impact on and implications for painting; the photograph’s status as objective trace and its potential as a means of recording and, indeed, knowing the world; the technological advances that constantly refined the camera’s capacity to replicate reality and democratised access to photographic practice. With the exception of a few sceptical voices, for most commentators, the documentary, indexical status of photography was a given. If Dadaist and Surrealist experimentation – the photomontages,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Writing passage and the passage to writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From its outset, this book set itself a critical agenda that deflected attention away from the reflexive and metafictional aspects of the selected texts in favour of a reading that would highlight their thematic range and density and provide some measure of the complexity of their engagement with the ‘real’ and with the social, religious and cultural structures by which man tries to make sense of reality. Foremost on this agenda and central to the inquiry conducted in the intervening pages have been the following priorities: the provision of a selective survey of late twentieth and early twenty-first century fiction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>302</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjnd2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>348</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
