<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm6v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cinematography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Moving Images</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Edison to the Webcam</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Fullerton</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Widding</surname>
               <given-names>Astrid Söderbergh</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781864620542</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780861969173</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0861969170</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>John Libbey Publishing</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Libbey Publishing Ltd.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bmzn7v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In 1888, Thomas Edison announced that he was experimenting on "an instrument which does for the eye what the phonograph does for the ear, which is the recording and reproduction of things in motion." Just as Edison's investigations were framed in terms of the known technologies of the phonograph and the microscope, the essays in this collection address the contexts of innovation and reception that have framed the development of moving images in the last 100 years. Three concerns are of particular interest: the contexts of innovation and reception for moving image technologies; the role of the observer, whose vision and cognitive processes define some of the limits of inquiry and epistemological insight; and the role of new media, which, engaging with the domestic sphere as cultural interface, are transforming our understanding of public and private spheres.</p>
         <p>The 17 previously unpublished essays in Moving Images represent the best of current research in the history of this field. They make a timely and stimulating contribution to debates concerning the impact of new media on the history of cinema.</p>
         <p>Contributors include: William Boddy, Carlos Bustamante, Warren Buckland, Valeria Camporesi, Bent Fausing, Oliver Gaycken, Alison Griffiths, Christopher Hales, Jan Holmberg, Solveig Jülich, Frank Kessler, Jay Moman, Sheila C. Murphy, Pelle Snickars, Paul C. Spehr, Björn Thuresson, and Åke Walldius.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Olsson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M<italic>oving Images:</italic>From Edison to the Webcam is the outcome of a conference held in the Department of Cinema Studies at Stockholm University from 6–9 December 1998. Organised in association with the Institute for Futures Studies, the conference showcased thirteen keynote addresses and almost sixty papers covering aspects as diverse as intermediality, indexicality, prosthesis, film and stage, screen practices and reception studies, documentary, film, history, memory, filmand changes in the modes of subjectivity, and transformations in the public and private spheres.</p>
                     <p>With receptions at City Hall and at The Technical Museum, and with a demonstration of a virtual environment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fullerton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Widding</surname>
                           <given-names>Astrid Söderbergh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fullerton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Widding</surname>
                           <given-names>Astrid Söderbergh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 17 October 1888, Thomas Alva Edison filed a caveat in which he announced that he was ‘experimenting upon an instrument which does for the Eye what the phonograph does for the Ear, which is the recording and reproduction of things in motion, and in such a form as to be Cheap, practical and convenient’. Just as work on the development of the instrument to which Edison referred, a precursor of the Kinetoscope, instances an apparatus that was framed in terms of the known technologies of the phonograph and the microscope, the essays in this collection variously address the contexts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Unaltered to Date:</title>
                     <subtitle>Developing 35mm Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spehr</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Thomas Edison introduced his Kinetoscope in April 1894, it used a film that is almost identical with the 35mm film used today – the same width and with four similar perforations on each side of the image. W. K. L. Dickson’s abridged account is accurate except for the date, which he exaggerated in his eagerness to reinforce Edison’s claim that his invention preceded all competitors. At the end of 1891 and the beginning of 1892 Dickson made the changes which resulted in a film 35mm wide.</p>
                     <p>Dickson’s pride was justified because it was, arguably, Edison’s – and Dickson’s – major contribution to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Seeing Seeing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hermann von Helmholtz and the Invention of the Ophthalmoscope</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaycken</surname>
                           <given-names>Oliver</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1850, Hermann von Helmholtz published a short treatise entitled<italic>Description of an Ophthalmoscope</italic>. Near its beginning, he describes his objective in the following words: ‘The present treatise contains the description of an optical instrument by which it is possible to see and recognize exactly in the living eye the retina itself and the images of luminous objects which are cast upon it.’² Helmholtz’s invention frequently is described as an event of foundational importance in the field of ophthalmology, an event that, indeed, creates that field in its modern sense.³ While such claims are not exaggerated, the ophthalmoscope nonetheless should</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Fairies and Technologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kessler</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Georges Méliès published his<italic>causerie</italic>on ‘Les vues cinématographiques’ in1907, he told his famous anecdote about how he discovered the so-called ‘ substitution stoptrick’ as a result of a jam in his camera. Putting this effect to creative use, he consequently filmed a couple of metamorphoses changing men into women, as well as a number of other pictures where people suddenly vanished or appeared. ‘It’s thanks to this simple trick’, Méliès observed, ‘that I made the first<italic>féeries: Le Manoir du Diable, Le Diable au couvent, Cendrillon, etc</italic>.’¹ According to Méliès, the origin of cinematographic<italic>féeries</italic>is thus directly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Seeing in the Dark:</title>
                     <subtitle>Early X-ray Imaging and Cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jülich</surname>
                           <given-names>Solveig</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The phenomenon of temporary blindness to dim light after exposure to intense illumination is an experience we have come to accept as, in one way or another, common to all people. Yet, despite the familiarity and apparent simplicity of dark adaption, physiologists of vision have shown it to be a highly complex affair. And what is more interesting, the uses and meanings of scotopic vision are so rich that it could well be said to have a cultural history of its own. This paper focuses on dark adaption as a site for early X-ray imaging and cinema.</p>
                     <p>Both the science</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Bolex Motion Picture Camera</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bustamante</surname>
                           <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Paillard-Bolex H16 camera played a central role in the work of many avant-garde filmmakers from the 1940s through to the 1970s because of its precision and light weight, robustness and range of facilities,¹ and the high quality of its optics – especially the zoom lenses – and its simple operation, which made possible an infinite combination of creative cinematographic choices. The Bolex H16 is probably<italic>the</italic>camera which most influenced a generation of experimental and documentary/ethnographic filmmakers. Leafing through old issues of<italic>Film Culture</italic>, I note that the camera was also an important prop, a kind of status symbol, included in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sore Society:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dissolution of the Image and the Assimilation of the Trauma</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fausing</surname>
                           <given-names>Bent</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why digital images? In the following discussion, the new media are regarded as a turning point in representation. The symbols and self-esteem in the public sphere show us a house divided in itself, and this plays a role in creating media and in constructing new images that are detached from referential and representational bonds. The<italic>public</italic>has difficulties in approaching the<italic>private</italic>with explanations and images. There is a tendency that expression goes in the reverse direction, from the private sphere to the public media. The point at which you live clearly expresses that you are made of flesh and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Closing In:</title>
                     <subtitle>Telescopes, Early Cinema, and the Technological Conditions of De-distancing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holmberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Figure 1 shows an illustration from Jules Verne’s short story ‘Un Drame dans les airs’ (1874). Although this example is rather obscure, air balloons like this one are a common means of transportation throughout Verne’s œuvre, from his first novel,<italic>Cinq Semaines en ballon</italic>(1863) to<italic>Maître du monde</italic>(1904). This is hardly a coincidence. Although perhaps not often acknowledged as such, the air balloon too is a quintessentially<italic>modern</italic>vehicle, if not as emblematic as, say, the train. Nevertheless, balloons promised to change the perception of the world, and hence fit nicely into Verne’s project whose ambition, in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘We Partake, as it Were, of His Life’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Status of the Visual in Early Ethnographic Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffiths</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her speech as outgoing president of the American Anthropological Association in 1960, pioneering visual anthropologist Margaret Mead urged her colleagues to make greater use of the technologies of the still camera, audio tape recorder and motion picture camera. According to some observers, the reaction among Mead’s professional audience was decidedly mixed. Her appeals were greeted with ‘restless stirrings and angry murmurs … as these notebook-oriented scholars expressed their irritation at this revolutionary suggestion.’¹ In some respects, it is hardly surprising that Mead’s colleagues balked at the idea of using tape recorders and motion picture cameras in the field; beyond</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Architectonics of Seeing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Architecture as Moving Images</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Snickars</surname>
                           <given-names>Pelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sergei Eisenstein seems to have believed that one of the ancestors of cinema was architecture. The ancient Greeks, he writes, ‘have left us the most perfect examples of shot design … Acropolis of Athens could just as well be called the … most ancient [of] films’.² Eisenstein’s thoughts can be found in ‘Montage and Architecture’, an essay written towards the end of the 1930s. For the soviet filmmaker the buildings on the Acropolis were first and foremost a montage of carefully enframed spatial views. The Parthenon, for example, faces the spectator obliquely, he notes, just like a calculated shot, thus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Submerged Landscapes of the Postmodern Body:</title>
                     <subtitle>Surface, Text, Commodity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moman</surname>
                           <given-names>Jay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1990s it seems that no anthology of cultural theory is complete without a contribution to the increasingly pervasive discourses on the body. Emerging theories attempt to manage Arthur and Marilouise Kroker’s ‘crisis of the body’ by sketching out a map to navigate a world marked by genetic testing, retinal and thumbprint identification, cybersex, and other technological and increasingly digital bodily formations.¹ As I aim to show, this is a map written both<italic>about</italic>and<italic>upon</italic>the body in order to regulate the myriad technological systems which dis-/configure it.</p>
                     <p>According to various sources, the genesis of the discursive body</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Weather Porn and the Battle for Eyeballs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Promoting Digital Television in the USA and UK</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boddy</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the form of lavish ad campaigns, front-page news stories, and overheated techno-punditry, the end of the 1990s marked the culmination of a long technological, policy-making and marketing campaign waged by a diverse set of private interests to bring digital television into American and British homes. Charting digital television’s distinct fortunes in the United States and Great Britain can illuminate some of the most persistent and difficult issues in media historiography, including sorting out the determinations of national culture, market structures, and ideological valence in technological innovation. The current transition from analogue to digital standards for electronically stored and transmitted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Stereotyping a Competitor:</title>
                     <subtitle>Images of Television in Spanish Cinema in the 1960s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Camporesi</surname>
                           <given-names>Valeria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An image may comprise a number of rather different things. Of the various mental, visual and physical objects with which it may be identified, I am concerned in this essay with a rather practical definition. My principal concern is with the cinematographic representation of television, both in image and sound.</p>
                     <p>If the question of the interrelationship of the cinematographic image to its signified cannot be avoided, the prime purpose of this study is not to establish whether there is a ‘discrepancy between facts and representations’.¹ My aim will be to analyse the ways in which an historical process, in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Video Pleasure and Narrative Cinema:</title>
                     <subtitle>Luc Besson’s The Fifth Element and Video Game Logic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buckland</surname>
                           <given-names>Warren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jerome Bruner reminds us that narrative is not a contingent, optional dimension of society, but is an essential, ecologically necessary structure with which individuals make sense of social complexity.² We do not need to subscribe to ontological structuralism – which argues that narrative is a timeless structure that transcends society – to accept this level-headed reminder. In the process of structuring social experience, narrative necessarily reinvents itself in each epoch, offering an historically specific experience. Fredric Jameson’s analysis of the novels of Balzac and Conrad is exemplary in this respect. Jameson identifies in the narrative narrative</p>
                     <p>of Lord<italic>Jim</italic>the emergence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Space and Character Representation in Interactive Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thuresson</surname>
                           <given-names>Björn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a broad sense, I want to bridge the gap between traditional narratives and the new expectations of a high level of interactivity, and the call for hypermedia structured material. I’m trying to bring some of the experiences from cinema, radio and television to the production of material which is to be viewed on a computer screen. The leading questions are embarrassingly simple:</p>
                     <p>– How does an interactive narrative (I’m deliberately using the term ‘narrative’ instead of ‘fiction’) work and function?¹ What does it look like? How do you construct it?</p>
                     <p>– How does it affect the use of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lurking and Looking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Webcams and the Construction of Cybervisuality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Murphy</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheila C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 1990s has been a decade in which communications technologies and moving image technologies have converged inmultiple ways, producing new cultural ‘extensions’ (and fragmentations) of the human body and of subjectivity. I am particularly interested in the new mode of cultural engagement enacted by Internet users who extend their visual access to the public sphere by connecting to Internet webcamsites and becoming part of the always only partially knowable subculture of webcams (Fig. 1). Briefly, webcams, also known as SpyCams, are Internet websites that contain views of a wide range of vistas produced by connecting a video camera to a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Visual Diaries:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revival of a Documentary Form in Digital Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walldius</surname>
                           <given-names>Åke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Abroad spectrum of digital techniques is revitalising formal innovation as the technology of moving images enters its second century of development. Established narrational forms are being revised according to new expressive opportunities. The screen writers of Hollywood movies and computer games apply new technology to let us experience new exotic vistas and new zones of intimate personal virtuality.</p>
                     <p>Our daily lives are influenced by digitalisation as well. The way we write letters is gradually changing. The ways in which we take notes and pictures are changing too. It is the accommodation of one of these more prosaic forms of communication,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Interactive Filmmaker’s Challenge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hales</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The earliest cinema of Méliès and Lumière has more than once been likened to the current state-of-the-art interactive ‘new media’, and more specifically to non-linear interactive movies. Implicit in this observation is the fact that the sophistication of interactive movie language is awaiting the passage of time and the development of technology before it matures. It has been frequently noted that computers are still waiting for the first great visionary genius to take us into a new dimension.</p>
                     <p>This essay demonstrates how computer technologies can now offer completely new interactive movie paradigms and structures; that the expectations of the audience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzn7v.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
