<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8btr</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B829.5 .G37 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aristotle</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Persuasion (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Heidegger, Martin, 1889–1976</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Arendt, Hannah, 1906-1975</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judgment</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Persuasion, Reflection, Judgment</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ancillae Vitae</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Vitae</surname>
               <given-names>Ancillae</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gasché</surname>
               <given-names>Rodolphe</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253025531</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253025852</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253025850</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Rodolphe Gasché</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005wvb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>As one of the most respected voices of Continental philosophy today, Rodolphe Gasché pulls together Aristotle's conception of rhetoric, Martin Heidegger's debate with theory, and Hannah Arendt's conception of judgment in a single work on the centrality of these themes as fundamental to human flourishing in public and political life. Gasché's readings address the distinctively human space of the public square and the actions that occur there, and his valorization of persuasion, reflection, and judgment reveals new insight into how the philosophical tradition distinguishes thinking from other faculties of the human mind.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Each of the three sections of this book—on persuasion in Aristotle, reflection (<italic>Besinnung</italic>) in Martin Heidegger, and judgment in Hannah Arendt—comes with its own introduction. Each section can, thus, be read on its own and without regard for the order in which it is presented. Yet, apart from the fact that the order in which these studies follow one another is chronological, the essays, though they do not explicitly build upon or derive from one another, are interrelated in many ways and, ultimately, pursue one question, one major concern. These prefatory remarks, which I keep to a minimum,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN ARISTOTLE SCHOLARSHIP, the Stagirite’s treatise on rhetoric has undergone a peculiar treatment. Not only is it one of the philosopher’s most neglected works, but this neglect has also taken peculiar forms. When it is taken seriously at all, the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>is considered only after all the other works of the philosopher have been dealt with. Commentators’ uneasiness with the work has been so great that the place usually reserved for it is, once respect has been paid to all of Aristotle’s great works, at the end of their commentaries, in the shape of an acknowledgment, an endnote, as it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A TRUTH RESEMBLING TRUTH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WHEREAS IN THE<italic>TOPICS</italic>, which is closely associated with the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>, Aristotle clearly names his addressee, namely, students of philosophy, he does not specify for whom the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>is intended.¹ This alone is reason enough not to call this work a technical handbook for rhetoricians, as it has been, and still is by most of the commentators. I do not deny that the Rhetoric also contains advice for students about public speaking; it certainly does so. But right from the beginning, Aristotle takes issue with previous compilers of “arts” of rhetoric who have, as he argues, “provided us with only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>NECESSITY OR PROBABILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AFTER HAVING TAKEN issue with the previous compilers of “arts” of rhetoric, and criticized them for having dealt only with things exterior to such an art, Aristotle sets out in chapter 2 of Book I of his treatise to make a new beginning and does so by offering the following definition of what constitutes rhetoric. Rhetoric as an art of<italic>logos</italic>, he writes, is “the faculty of discovering the possible means of persuasion [<italic>theoresai to endechomenon pithanon</italic>] in reference to any subject whatsoever” (15). It is, according to the more literal translation of Kennedy, the “ability, in each [particular] case</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>LOGOS, TOPOS, STOIKHEION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AT THE END OF CHAPTER 2 of Book I of the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>, Aristotle makes a distinction between elements and propositions,<italic>stoikheia</italic>and<italic>protaseis</italic>. From the context it is clear that this distinction primarily concerns the genres of rhetoric—the deliberative, judicial, and epideictic kinds of oratory—which are the subject matter of the following chapter. Indeed, having just discussed the<italic>koinoi</italic>, or “universal topics,” Aristotle, in his conclusion to chapter 2, writes that, before continuing with a discussion of the specific topics, it will be necessary to “ascertain the different kinds of Rhetoric, so that, having determined their number, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IF SOMETHING LIKE thought were possible, that is, if thought would indeed come to pass in philosophical reflection (<italic>Besinnung</italic>), in an inquiry that is entirely directed toward making thought occur, then for such thought, Heidegger submits in<italic>Besinnung</italic>, “it would not be essential whether it succeeds in making an observation about something hitherto unknown, [and] whether something conducive to ‘life’ can be determined.”¹ By contrast, what is essential to thought, as Heidegger understands it, is exclusively whether within it Being itself has come properly into its own (<italic>sich er-eignet</italic>) and, in the same stroke, has thus abysmally unsettled metaphysical, that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>BREAKING WITH THE PRIMACY OF THE THEORETICAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>NOTWITHSTANDING HEIDEGGER’S regular references to theory and the theoretical, both his criticism of the theoretical attitude in<italic>Being and Time</italic>and his rehabilitation of<italic>theoria</italic>in some of his later work do not, at first sight, seem to be a sign that the issue of theory and the theoretical are a major concern in Heidegger’s work. This impression, however, is deceptive. Indeed, even a cursory glance at his first lecture course from the<italic>Kriegsnotsemester</italic>1919 in Freiburg—a lecture course entitled “Die Idee der Philosophie und das Welt-anschaungsproblem” in which the question of the theoretical is the central theme—shows</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE GENESIS OF THE THEORETICAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated from German by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Collins</surname>
                           <given-names>David B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN HEIDEGGER’S EARLY Freiburg lecture series from the summer semester of 1923,<italic>Ontology: The Hermeneutics of Facticity</italic>, there is the following parenthetical remark: “(The genesis of the theoretical, what is prior here: ‘curiosity.’)”¹ This problem of the genesis of the theoretical will be investigated in the following with special consideration of the role that it plays in<italic>Being and Time</italic>(1927). First of all, however, it may be appropriate to pose again the question of the importance of the subject of “theory” to Heidegger’s thinking in general. At first glance it might appear as if his critical encounter with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>BEYOND THEORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THEORIA, OR WATCHING OVER WHAT IS STILL TO COME</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AT FIRST SIGHT, THE LECTURE from 1953 on “Science and Reflection” is above all concerned with the modern sciences.¹ As “the theory of the real,” they have shaped our sense of reality. But if this state of affairs requires a reflection, or rather a<italic>Besinnung</italic>, it is because something is already at work in the sciences, which, in spite of what I will call the “un-world” to which they have given rise, announces a new age of the world: an age that, in distinction from the sciences’ planetary expansion, would be one of the “world” itself.² It is in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN A LETTER from 1955, Hannah Arendt confides to Karl Jaspers that she intends to call a planned “book on political theories, ‘Amor Mundi.’”¹ Several scholars, among them Elisabeth Young-Bruehl, have held that this book is none other than<italic>The Human Condition</italic>.² Indeed, it was the first book to be published in the aftermath of the letter to Jaspers.³ As Ursula Ludz has convincingly pointed out, however, when Arendt spoke to Jaspers about the title in question, neither<italic>The Human Condition</italic>nor her<italic>Introduction into Politics</italic>were in progress at the time. Ludz, therefore, writes: “With ‘the book on political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>THE SPACE OF APPEARANCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>HANNAH ARENDT’S REFLECTIONS on judgment, which she qualifies as the most political of all of the human being’s faculties, are intimately tied to a debate over Kant’s philosophy that spans almost two decades. Central to this debate is the Kantian distinction between determinant (i.e., cognitive) judgment and reflective (i.e., aesthetic or teleological) judgment. Arendt’s own conception of judgment originates largely from her interest in and her commentaries on Kant’s elaboration of the judgment of taste in the<italic>Critique of the Power of Judgment</italic>.</p>
                     <p>As the entries of August 1957 in<italic>Denktagebuch</italic>demonstrate, Arendt construes the difference between the two types</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>THE WIND OF THOUGHT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE CONCERN WITH the power of judgment arises in Hannah Arendt’s work in response to critical events in modernity. As a result of the impotence of familiar standards and categories to provide answers and orientation, this power has become undone. It is a question not only of the impotence of the common standards regarding certain events of modernity but also of the fact that these events have been so terrifying that they have altogether destroyed all our habitual categories of thought and standards of judgment. Yet, as Arendt remarks in 1953 in “Understanding and Politics (The Difficulties of Understanding),” that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>A SENSE OF THE WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FROM WHAT WE have seen so far, Arendt’s theory of judgment sketches out a novel conception of a kind of mental activity that she holds Kant to have unwittingly discovered when he came across the judgment of taste. This kind of judgment, which lies behind the reflective judgment of taste and is not identical with it, concerns appearances. What Arendt calls appearances can be retraced to Kant’s transcendental aesthetics, in which he elaborated on the a priori forms constitutive of phenomena of nature that are to be subsequently subsumed by the determinant judgment under the discursive conditions of cognition, that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wvb.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
