<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ms2k</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.S52G45 1997</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Gender identity in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Gender and Narrativity</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RUTLAND</surname>
               <given-names>BARRY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780886292980</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773584310</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Individual Authors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt80x53"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>It is impossible to imagine a community that is not divided into at least two gender groups. It is equally impossible to imagine a community that does not tell or enact stories. The relationship between these universal aspects of human culture is the mainspring of Gender and Narrativity. From Genesis to Freud, the Western narrative tradition tells the same old story of masculine dominance/feminine subservience as a matter of divine will or natural truth. Here, nine Canadian scholars challenge and interpret this tradition, in effect "re-telling" the story of gender, and themselves intervening in the narrative process. Critical readings from a wide range of literary texts - medieval and modern, European and Canadian - replace abstract theory in these studies, while sociology, anthropology, psychoanalysis, deconstruction and new history are the axes of discussion. This book exemplifies the current range and diversity of Canadian critical writing.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="268"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rutland</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>TELLING DIFFERENCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rutland</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gender is a fundamental constitutive category of culture, narrative is a basic cultural practice. It is impossible to conceive of a human community that is not<italic>ab initio</italic>divided into two (at least) gender groups; it is equally impossible to imagine a human community that does not tell/enact stories. What is the relationship between the category and the practice? The nine essays that follow broach this question in terms of current theories of meaning and text.</p>
                     <p>Gender is a secondary formation grounded in biological reproductive sex but distinct from it, as a building is distinct from and heterogenous to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>TOWARD AN EPISTEMOLOGY OF GENDER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Verdon</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That higher life forms exist in the two physical categories of female and male is universally self-evident and is not of itself a problem. Beyond this basic understanding, however, the two sexes become associated with a vast panorama of cultural phenomena, including categorical ascriptions of social roles, behavioural expectations, and personality characteristics. How does the simple, incontrovertible, and universal fact of biological dimorphism generate the staggering complexity of cultural, social, and psychological dynamics of the human condition? It is the translation of the biological into social/cultural experience that is the heart of an epistemology of gender. An elaboration of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>READING THE FEMININE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Richard</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discourse—all discourse—has forever been the object of surveillance. History is there to remind us that political or religious thought has never been totally free. And of course, esthetic discourses of all kinds (paintings, books, plays) have always been prey to censorship. Tintoretto, Molière, Voltaire, Rousseau, etc., all had dealings with the thought police of their day.¹ In the last ten years or so, the age-old practice of policing opinions has acquired a new name: political correctness, offspring of the American liberal left of the 1980s. For the purposes of this paper, I will single out two discourses that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>SEX, LIES, AND PHOTOGRAPHY:</title>
                     <subtitle>READING DETECTIVE FICTION AS PSYCHOANALYSIS IN TIMOTHY FINDLEY’S THE TELLING OF LIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gabriel</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though Timothy Findley’s<italic>The Telling of Lies</italic>(1986) announces itself as a “mystery,” the preferred British term for detective fiction, it subverts as well as continues many of the classic characteristics of the genre. Following the established conventions of its predecessors, from Poe’s “Murders in the Rue Morgue” onward, it employs a sleuth outside the regulatory powers of the state, in pursuit of a murderer whose motive and means are out of the ordinary. There is a body, a setting which unites all the suspects under one roof, and an Aristotelian structure of<italic>peripeteia</italic>(Porter 1983, 331). Like all detective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>F(R)ICTIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>FEMINISTS RE/WRITING NARRATIVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godard</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The border/play characteristic of contemporary women’s parodic re/- writing of fictional genres reveals engagement with narrative as a critical strategy designed to expose the positioning of woman as<italic>silent other</italic>, on whose mutilated body narrative is constructed in dominant (patriarchal) discourse, and to posit alternate positionings for women as subjects producing themselves in/by language. What feminist theory has shown is that strategies of writing and reading are forms of cultural resistance. They work to turn dominant discourses inside out and challenge theory in its own terms, the terms of a semiotic space constructed in language. They do so by unfixing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE (W)RITE OF PASSAGE:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM CHILDHOOD TO WOMANHOOD IN LUCY MAUD MONTGOMERY’S EMILY NOVELS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Woods</surname>
                           <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The second volume of a series, especially if it deals with a very young girl, is the hardest for me to write—because the public and the publisher won’t allow me to write of a young girl as she really is. One can write of children as they always are; so my books of children are always good; but when you come to write of the “miss” you have to depict a sweet, insipid young thing—really a child grown older—to whom the basic realities of life and reactions to them are quite unknown.<italic>Love</italic>must scarcely be hinted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>WRITING TOWARD ABSENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>FRANCES GREGG’S THE MYSTIC LEEWAY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Ben</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me start with cautionary words from Frances Gregg: “So far, in all my life I have met no single Man—though I have done my best to make one of Oliver Marlow [her son]—nor has any man encouraged me, or indeed been willing for me, to be a Woman. Mumbo-jumbo, superstitions, muddled mythologies, have been my fate among these artists and prelates and magicians, these escapists from life—from Life!” (1995, 61).</p>
                     <p>My title attempts to account for Frances Gregg’s title.<italic>The Mystic Leeway</italic>is a writing toward absence.¹ Leeway itself is a metaphor for absence, absence from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>PARSIFAL AND SEMIOTIC STRUCTURALISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Prattis</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Iain</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The legend of Parsifal and the quest for the Holy Grail has been one of my favorite stories since boyhood. The many versions I have encountered have never failed to fascinate and ignite the imagination. The long acquaintance with the story and the personal cultural tendrils that take me into the Celtic world are sufficient (though perhaps not necessary) to recognize an adequate treatment of the material when it is presented. Such a recognition was not forthcoming in my reading of Lévi-Strauss’s discourse on the myth (1985, 219-34). But my respect for Lévi-Strauss’s immense contribution to scholarship remains constant. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>ANDROGYNOUS REALISM IN HEINRICH VON KLEIST’S “DIE HEILIGE CÄCILIE ODER DIE GEWALT DER MUSIK (EINE LEGENDE)”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bohm</surname>
                           <given-names>Arnd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Relatively neglected by critics in comparison to others of his works, Kleist’s story with the elaborate tripartite title, which can be approximately translated into English as “Saint Cecilia, or the Power of Music (A Legend),” has begun to attract increasing attention. To some extent, this is due to the fact that the other works have been examined and reexamined with such exhausting intensity that a turn to lesser-known texts is inevitable. But it is also the case that, among Kleist’s puzzling prose, this story stands out for its strangeness. What is it about? What is its “message”? In this case,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>CLOUGH, CLAUDE, ARNOLD, AND MARGUERITE:</title>
                     <subtitle>MALE HETEROPHOBIA IN VICTORIAN POETRY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rutland</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The poems that Matthew Arnold addressed to Arthur Hugh Clough in life and death, most notably “The Scholar Gipsy” and “Thyrsis,” make these poets the<italic>dioscuri</italic>of nineteenth century English literature, as securely twinned as Castor and Pollux. There is, of course, a conventionally acknowledged difference: Arnold is major-canonical, while Clough, until recently at least, has been regarded as minor, generally no more than a footnote to his younger friend.¹ In 1849, the year of the composition of the majority of Arnold’s “Switzerland” lyrics and Clough’s epistolary novel in verse,<italic>Amours de Voyage</italic>, they were pretty much on a footing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x53.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
