<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442686731</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HM554.F53 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War and society</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War in mass media</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Fighting Words and Images</book-title>
         <subtitle>: Representing War Across the Disciplines</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BARABAN</surname>
               <given-names>ELENA V.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JAEGER</surname>
               <given-names>STEPHAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MULLER</surname>
               <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442641235</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442686731</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442686731"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This collection creatively and insightfully explains the nature, origins, dynamics, structure, and impact of a wide variety of war representations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representing War across the Disciplines</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARABAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ELENA V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JAEGER</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MULLER</surname>
                           <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Julius van der Merwe fraudulently enlisted with the South African Air Force (SAAF) at the age of fourteen. From July 1942 until the end of the Second World War, he operated the tail guns of a B-26 Marauder.¹ Part of the Desert Air Force and later the Balkan Air Force, both under British command, the SAAF and van der Merwe along with it fought in North Africa, Italy, and Yugoslavia. Upon cessation of hostilities, van der Merwe stayed in northern Italy in order to assist with troop demobilization, the grunt work of getting tens of thousands of men and their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[SECTION ONE: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The three chapters gathered together in this section address the silences arising from, and complicating, the representation of war. Each of them considers silence not so much as an absence as it does as a technique for indirectly evoking war, a large and multifaceted phenomenon whose complexity resists comprehensive articulation at nearly every turn. Jay Winter, Kate McLoughlin, and Brad Prager all work to show how silences about war may be deployed to animate an understanding of warʹs representational elusiveness. Each author, however, locates this elusiveness in different representational domains: Winter in commemorations of war organized around the construction of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Representations of War and the Social Construction of Silence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WINTER</surname>
                           <given-names>JAY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The wrenching experience of war has occasioned commemorative practices of many kinds all over the world. Every one of them is framed by representations of war. Some are heroic, some filled with tragedy, some triumphalist, some angry, some resigned. Every one of them is incomplete, in that the visceral experience of combat, what Tolstoy called ʹthe actual killing,ʹ the smell of it, the taste of it, is irreproduceable. This stark and unavoidable fact means that all commemoration is metaphoric, or metonymic, or in some sense at a considerable remove from the subject – war – and its bloody remains. Many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Not Writing about War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCLOUGHLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>KATE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The reasons not to write about war are myriad and compelling. They fall into two overlapping categories: war cannot be written about and war should not be written about. For a start, war cannot be written about because the logistical difficulties of doing so are insuperable (the sheer scale of armed conflict is prohibitive). This makes a synoptic view practically and politically problematic to obtain. Then there is a premium on first-hand experience (or ʹcombat gnosticismʹ)¹ that undermines the validity of non-combatant representations. Combatant representations are themselves suspect as they may lack the necessary distance and detachment; censorship and self-censorship</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Occupation as the Face of War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Concealing Violence in the Diary A Woman in Berlin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PRAGER</surname>
                           <given-names>BRAD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Representations of war are determined not only by the ages in which they appear, but also by the boundaries understood to define war. The idea, for example, that it is not battle but war itself that leaves behind scars presumes that war has both a beginning and an end, or that we can differentiate between the event and its traces. War is, however, an extended process, one that can hardly be isolated or made wholly distinct from peace. The vagueness of the concept suggests that much remains unknown about its limits. For this reason, detailed depictions of occupation are of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[SECTION TWO: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though relevant to any representation, perspective is a particularly important theoretical issue in war representations. At first glance this is readily apparent, since every struggle, military or otherwise, involves at least two antagonists, and representations of conflict usually emphasize the concerns of only one of them. At the same time, there are numerous journalistic and academic accounts of war that aim for a birdʹs-eye view. For example, a historian sifting through historical sources must deal with many different perspectives, all in some way unreliable since they are written from limited – and often during times of war strategically manipulated –</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Historiographical Simulations of War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JAEGER</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The numerous narrative techniques available to represent war and violence must allow for the expression of an immense range of perspectives. It spans from the survey perspective of the historian to the personal experiences of participants in the war such as soldiers or civilians, from first-hand experiences to considering the impact on future generations. Representations oscillate between distance and proximity, between critical summary or analysis and personal experience. For historiography in its narrower meaning as historical writing within the scholarly field of history, representing war seems particularly difficult since historiography is traditionally seen as a secondary narrative discourse, one in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Aestheticization of Suffering on Television</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHOULIARAKI</surname>
                           <given-names>LILIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The broadcast of Iraq War footage on Western televisions from March to April 2003 was a paradoxical event. It was the most transparent war footage ever but at the same time it was also condemned as the most manipulative. It was transparent in its first-time use of embedded journalists and in the concentration of an international pool of reporting journalists in Baghdad itself. It was manipulative in that this unprecedented proliferation of information and imagery intensified the processes of news regulation and censorship, opening the footage to criticism of a heavy bias in favour of the coalition troops. But, one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Slotting War Narratives into Cultureʹs Ready-Made</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOSCILO</surname>
                           <given-names>HELENA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Friedrich Nietzscheʹs famous lapidary dictum ʹThere are no facts, only interpretationsʹ summarizes his vastly influential assertion that if an objective reality exists, the perspectival nature of human cognition renders that reality inaccessible. War, according to Lev Tolstoyʹs<italic>War and Peace</italic>(1869), reveals that incapacity as deriving at least partly from the two extremes of proximity and remoteness: both Nikolai Rostovoʹs complete submersion in the immediacy of battle and Napoleonʹs distant, hence more abstract, viewpoint hamper their powers of perception. The two radically contrasting subject/ive positions are equally disabling for, in the complex, chaotic circumstances of war no such vantage point</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[SECTION THREE: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The three chapters that make up this section address questions of identity from perspectives rooted in the disciplines of literary studies, anthropology, and classics, which themselves are simultaneously inflected by ideas drawn from such other domains as history, philosophy, political studies, and sociology. Each considers not so much the frequently discussed ways in which our identities are subject to alteration under conditions of war, but rather the processes whereby identities become mobilized in warʹs many different representational contexts, including commemorative rites and monuments, in order to produce, respectively, political resistance (Jennifer James), social solidarity (Serguei Oushakine), and civic virtue (James</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Blessed Are the Warmakers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Martin Luther King, Vietnam, and the Black Prophetic Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JAMES</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIFER C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 4 April 1967, at Riverside Church in New York City, Martin Luther King delivered his first public indictment of the Vietnam War. Standing before the Clergy and Laity Concerned about the Vietnam War, he praised fellow religious leaders for having the courage to ʹmove beyond the prophesying of smooth patriotismʹ to speak from the transcendent ʹmandates of conscience.ʹ¹ At the same time, he rebuked those in the civil rights movement who characterized his anti-war activism as a distraction from his primary mission: ʹ[T]hough I often understand the source of their concern, I am nevertheless greatly saddened, for such questions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Exchange of Sacrifices:</title>
                     <subtitle>Symbolizing an Unpopular War in Post-Soviet Russia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OUSHAKINE</surname>
                           <given-names>SERGUEI ALEX.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Chechen war became one of the most vivid representations of the political and social chaos that followed the collapse of the Soviet Union. To a large degree, the war was an unexpected outcome of the fight for independence that had started in Chechnya in the early 1990s. At the time, Boris Yeltsinʹs government was capable of neither negotiating with the pro-independence forces in Chechnya nor suppressing them. Apparently misinformed by his advisors about the possibility of defeating heavily armed Chechen rebels, in December 1994 Yeltsin began a military campaign aimed at ʹrestoring the constitutional orderʹ in Chechnya (see figure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Identity and the Representation of War in Ancient Rome</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHLUP</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In ancient Rome the historianʹs reputation rested on his ability to balance the narrative of events at Rome (<italic>domi</italic>) and those elsewhere (<italic>militae</italic>).¹ Of the latter wars were particularly worthy of narration. They necessitated the writing down of Roman history with a special focus on short but intense wars of Romeʹs early period in which she fought for survival against other Italian city states (ca 750–300 BCE); wars fought over several years or decades against rival nations as she established and expanded her empire; and civil wars.</p>
                     <p>While the omnipresence of war in Roman culture is readily acknowledged in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[SECTION FOUR: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The redrawing of state borders, the dissolution of empires, and the emergence of new states; the decline of some political and social groups and the rise of others; the depopulation of whole regions and economic collapse; the adjustment of legal systems and attempts at international cooperation in preventing future wars – these are only a few of warʹs many aftermaths. Historians, political scientists, philosophers, sociologists, psychologists, environmentalists, and scholars representing a number of other academic fields have written thousands of volumes on the dramatic changes wars bring to geopolitical and political arrangements as well as to different countriesʹ ideological, legal,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Battle of Stalingrad in Soviet Films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARABAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ELENA V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Battle of Stalingrad claimed the lives of more than one million people. In September–October 1942 a newly arrived Soviet private had little chance of living longer than twenty-four hours on the battlefield. In January 1943 German soldiers died by the hundreds every hour. The scope of events, their military, political, and ideological significance as well as their emotional intensity – the struggle of the Russians to achieve the unthinkable in the first part of the battle and the struggle of the Germans ʹto cope with the unthinkableʹ¹ in its second part – account for the unending flow of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Monsters in America:</title>
                     <subtitle>The First World War and the Cultural Production of Horror</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LUBIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Monsters, madmen, and ghouls have always stalked the American imagination. Between the Revolution and the Civil War, headless horsemen, murdering apes, killer sharks, giant white whales, pillaging barbarians, and other evil avatars inhabited the fiction of Washington Irving, Edgar Allen Poe, Nathaniel Hawthorne, and Herman Melville as well as the art of John Singleton Copley, Benjamin West, and Thomas Cole. After the Civil War, the presence of such grotesque and aberrant figures diminished. Beholden to evolutionary science, naturalism had little use for the supernatural. In the opening years of the twentieth century, the publicʹs faith in technology, progress, and rational</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>ʹRuins:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ruin of Ruinsʹ – Photography in the ʹRed Zoneʹ and the Aftermath of the Great War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAKER</surname>
                           <given-names>SIMON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The period between the conclusion of hostilities on the Western Front in 1918 and the start of the Second World War twenty years later is one within which several cultural trajectories comprising the subjects of this essay overlap: the reconstruction of the built environment in north-eastern France (the devastated areas known as the ʹRed Zonesʹ); the development and popularization of modernist and avant-garde photography in Europe; and the development and cultural assimilation of the work of Sigmund Freud, both in avant-garde literary and artistic circles and more widely in popular cultural forms such as ʹpulpʹ fiction. These three very different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686731.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
