<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Philokalia and the Inner Life</book-title>
         <subtitle>On Passions and Prayer</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cook</surname>
               <given-names>Christopher C.H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173428</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227900055</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Christopher Cook</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf4m9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Philokalia was published in Venice in 1782. It is an anthology of patristic writings from the Eastern Church, spanning the 4th to the 15th Centuries, which has been the subsequent focus of a significant revival in Orthodox spirituality. It presents an understanding of psychopathology and mental life which is significantly different to that usually encountered in western Christianity. It also presents accounts of both mental well-being and the pathologies of the mind or soul that are radically different to contemporary secular accounts and yet also find remarkable points of similarity with contemporary psychotherapeutic approaches, such as cognitive therapy. The book provides an introduction to the history of the Philokalia and the philosophical, anthropological and theological influences that contributed to its information. It presents a critical account of the pathologies of the soul, the remedies for these pathologies, and the therapeutic goals as portrayed by the authors of the Philokalia. It then offers a critical engagement of this material with a contemporary understanding of psychotherapy. Finally, it raises important questions about the relationship between thoughts and prayer.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="401"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Names &amp; Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thoughts, like sheep, given the chance, are prone to wander aimlessly. Sheep follow one another, without any necessary sense of direction or purpose. They are often found gathered together in flocks, but each individual creature presents its own image of vulnerability and individuality. They get lost, and become sick or lame or hungry. But they can also be shepherded, thus gaining direction, and may be cared for, fed, and protected. A good shepherd will search out the lost, feed the hungry and care for the sick.</p>
                     <p>Such an image, particularly for those familiar with rural life, offers countless metaphorical and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Influences and Foundations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Explorations of the inner world of human beings might reasonably be expected to be dependent upon the outer world in which they live: its culture, its history, traditions, assumptions, language and beliefs. Such things influence the way in which we perceive ourselves and thus, at least potentially, the way in which we think. If we are to understand properly what the authors and compilers of the<italic>Philokalia</italic>had to say about the inner life it would therefore seem to be important to consider the nature of their outer world, and especially its anthropological assumptions and beliefs. However, this immediately presents</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Passions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The passions (τὰ πάθη) represent a central concept in the psychology of the<italic>Philokalia</italic>and yet, with only one or two exceptions, its authors do not generally seem to consider that this concept requires definition. The definition helpfully provided by the editors of the English translation emphasises the passivity of that which is experienced by the soul.¹ However, for the present purpose, there is much more that needs to be said about the way in which the concept has been developed, employed and implicitly defined by the authors themselves.</p>
                     <p>Before proceeding to consider the way in which the concept is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Remedies for the Passions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the passions are “hostile pleasures”, which threaten to enslave and debilitate human beings, then what remedies might be found to address them?</p>
                     <p>There is no doubt that remedies for the passions are on offer in the classical tradition, in the teachings of Evagrios and the Desert Fathers, and in the<italic>Philokalia</italic>. However, before moving on to consider these remedies, and to assess their efficacy, it may be well to consider briefly what is being suggested by the idea of a “remedy”, or at least what might be implied in the use of that word in the present context.</p>
                     <p>A</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Mental Well-Being</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the<italic>Philokalia</italic>provides a pharmacopoeia of remedies for the passions, then a little more needs to be said about the goal of the programme of treatment in support of which they are applied. Or, to put things a little differently, what does it mean to be a healthy and flourishing human being? In particular, what understanding of mental well-being does the<italic>Philokalia</italic>convey?</p>
                     <p>As in previous chapters, it will be helpful first to consider what the traditions of understanding were in the classical world and amongst the Desert Fathers, especially Evagrios. However, at this point some complicating problems of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Psychotherapy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the<italic>Philokalia</italic>offers a diagnosis of the pathology of the human soul, a pharmacopoeia of remedies for the passions, and a vision of what a healthy and flourishing human-being (soul and body) can aspire to, then it begins to sound as though the<italic>Philokalia</italic>is really all about the health and therapy of the soul or psyche (ѱυχή). Furthermore, some of the subjects tackled by the<italic>Philokalia</italic>sound very similar to the concerns of psychological medicine: Evagrios seems to be very aware of unconscious processes, acedia bears a marked apparent resemblance to depression, the ensnaring hostile pleasures of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>On Thoughts and Prayer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the<italic>Philokalia</italic>is concerned with mental well-being, or with the proper ordering of the inner life of thoughts, then its only understanding of this is in the context of prayer. It is concerned primarily with prayer, yet it insists that prayer may only be properly understood and practised if attention is given first to the world of thoughts. This understanding of an inextricable relationship between thoughts and prayer runs all the way through the<italic>Philokalia</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Whilst the<italic>Philokalia</italic>has come down to us through the Eastern Church, and though its origins are in Classical and early Christian thought, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Being a shepherd, I am told, is not as romantic as it may sound. It is hard work. It requires perseverance in all weathers. It requires patience. Similarly, the process of “shepherding thoughts” that is described in the<italic>Philokalia</italic>is not for the faint hearted. It requires a self emptying that imitates that of Christ, it requires discipline, it requires watchfulness and patience. Above all, it requires perseverance in prayer. Just as sheep require pasture and protection every day, so do thoughts. [Theognostos] employs an image of the intellect as a sheep dog that has to keep watch lest the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Constituent works of the Greek Philokalia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Authors of the works included in the Greek Philokalia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4m9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
