<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B2430.R554P36 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ricoeur, Paul</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Passion for the Possible: Thinking with Paul Ricoeur</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>TREANOR</surname>
               <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VENEMA</surname>
               <given-names>HENRY ISAAC</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823232925</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823249183</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5chgx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Paul Ricoeur's entire philosophical project narrates a passion for the possibleexpressed in the hope that in spite of death, closure, and sedimentation, life is opened by superabundance, by how the world gives us much more than is possible. Ricoeur's philosophical anthropology is a phenomenology of human capacity, which gives onto the groundless ground of human being, namely, God. Thus the story of the capable man, beginning with original goodness held captive by a servile will and ending with the possibility of liberation and regeneration of the heart, underpins his passion for the more than possible. The essays in this volume trace the fluid movement between phenomenological and religious descriptions of the capable self that emerges across Ricoeur's oeuvre and establish points of connection for future developments that might draw inspiration from this body of thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>How Much More Than the Possible?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TREANOR</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VENEMA</surname>
                           <given-names>HENRY ISAAC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The death of Paul Ricoeur brings to a close the brilliant career of one of the best and most important philosophers of the twentieth century. His books and essays have informed and inspired untold numbers of scholars, teachers, and intellectuals around the world, and will continue to do so for generations to come. As Ricoeur wrote, however, in memory of Emmanuel Mounier,</p>
                     <p>One of the cruelties of death is to alter profoundly the meaning of a literary work in progress. Not only does the work no longer involve a continuation since it is finished in every sense of the word,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Asserting Personal Capacities and Pleading for Mutual Recognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RICOEUR</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prize with which I have been honored by the John W. Kluge Center at the Library of Congress, and for which I extend my sincere thanks, is motivated by the humanism attributed to my life’s work by these generous benefactors. The reflections that follow are devoted to examining some of the bases of this humanism.</p>
                     <p>My title is twofold: it designates, on the one hand, the capacities that a human agent attributes to himself and, on the other, the recourse to others required to give to this personal certainty a social status. The stakes shared by both poles of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious Belief:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Difficult Path of the Religious</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RICOEUR</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In agreeing to this title for my address to this prestigious group of conferences for 2000, I chose to add to it a more problematic subtitle: “the difficult path of the religious.” I propose, under the aegis of this heading, to transform certain objections and accusations addressed to believers into intimate difficulties for their belief itself. It is in particular the threats of intolerance and violence contained in religious belief that I want to confront, by calling upon the resources of self-criticism that the intelligence inherent in such belief is able to mobilize.</p>
                     <p>To begin, I would like to answer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Remembering Paul Ricoeur</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PELLAUER</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early on he said, “The word is my kingdom and I am not ashamed of it.”¹ In a later book,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, he cited this from Vladimir Jankéloevitch as an epigram: “He who has been, from then on cannot not have been: henceforth this mysterious and profoundly obscure fact of having been is his viaticum for all eternity.”²</p>
                     <p>It is almost eighteen months now since Ricoeur’s death. I believe he would have agreed that as the work of mourning progresses, the balance shifts between what at first is an almost overwhelming sense of grief and an accompanying sense of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Capable Man, Capable God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEARNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For some thirty years I had the honor of conducting a dialogue with Paul Ricoeur on the subject of the “possible.” This dialogue extended from our initial exchanges during Ricoeur’s seminars at the Center for Phenomenology and Hermeneutics on Avenue Parmentier in Paris, some of which (like “Myth as the Bearer of Possible Worlds”) were published in the late 1970s, to my doctoral thesis under Ricoeur’s generous supervision,<italic>Poétique du possible</italic>(defended in 1980 and published in 1984), and finally to my more recent reflections on the eschatology of<italic>posse</italic>in<italic>The God Who May Be</italic>(2003) and<italic>After God</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Source of Ricoeur’s Double Allegiance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VENEMA</surname>
                           <given-names>HENRY ISAAC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the abiding features of Paul Ricoeur’s long and productive career has been his “double allegiance” to philosophical and religious thought. Ricoeur tells us that he has “always moved back and forth between . . . a Biblical pole and a rational and critical pole, a duality that, finally, has lasted through my entire life . . . a continuous negotiation with a wellestablished bi-polarity . . . [a] sort of controlled schizophrenia . . . a double allegiance to which, ultimately I remained faithful.”¹ This duality is paramount for Ricoeur and constitutes a relation of mutual distance and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Golden Rule and Forgiveness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIASSE</surname>
                           <given-names>GAËLLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As is well known, Ricoeur seeks to counter the egological tendencies of philosophies of the subject. With the emphasis he puts on the role of the other, in ethics he belongs to the group of thinkers concerned with otherness within the sphere of ethical thought. But at the same time, he also takes into consideration the excessive weight that this other places on the self. Raising doubts about Emmanuel Levinas’s philosophy, while maintaining his admiration of the latter’s hyperboles, Ricoeur wishes to underline the definitive aspect of receptivity when encountering the other.¹ There is no “you” without an “I” who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Toward Which Recognition?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GREISCH</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last book that Paul Ricoeur published in his life bears the beautiful title<italic>The Course of Recognition</italic>.¹ I do not know whether it has already been translated into German, or if it has been, under what title. In my view, the translation that would best do justice to the work of thought to which Ricoeur invites his readers would be<italic>Unterwegs zum Anerkennen</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Since the philosopher’s death, this title takes on new connotations that transform the task of reading and appropriating his work into a “course of recognition,” with its own risks and dangers, which each reader will carry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Paul Ricoeur and Development Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAPLAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What do Paul Ricoeur and Amartya Sen have to do with one another? On the surface, not much. Ricoeur is a French hermeneutic philosopher and theologian; Sen is a Nobel Prize–winning Indian economist. Ricoeur researches such topics as subjectivity, imagination, and memory; Sen, poverty, development, and famine. But beneath their surface differences lies a fundamental similarity in their respective projects. Both take the notion of human capability as the central descriptive and normative feature of human existence. For Ricoeur, the capable human being (<italic>l’homme capable</italic>) is the ultimate subject of philosophical analysis. For Sen, the right to capabilities forms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Narrative Matters among the Mlabri:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interpretive Anthropology in International Development</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HERDA</surname>
                           <given-names>ELLEN A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most persuasive moment of Paul Ricoeur’s work for the development anthropologist is his idea of narrative imagination. This concept, applied to the development act of working together with the other who faces marginalization, fear, famine, and isolation, provides a medium for both the anthropologist and the local to emplot history and fiction into a social reality that brings each to a new place. Far from static, this new place is an emerging plot that enables movement from shame and hunger to selfsustainability on the part of the local, and movement from the confinement of Western individualism to an ontological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Place of Remembrance:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Paul Ricoeur’s Theory of Collective Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARASH</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY ANDREW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme of collective memory, conceived as a source of social cohesion, has come to assume a unique importance in the heterogeneous context of our contemporary societies. The public function of collective memory, in the form of commemorations or museums, as in the evocation of traumatic memories shared by entire social groups, has become a topic of lively debate in a large number of theoretical areas, ranging from cognitive science to sociology, political theory, history, and other disciplines of social inquiry. It is the singular achievement of the recent work of Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting,</italic>to take a wide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Refiguring Virtue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLUNDELL</surname>
                           <given-names>BOYD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By Paul Ricoeur’s own account, the dynamic of detour and return is the central motif of his philosophy. As he said to Charles Reagan: “Detour/return is the rhythm of my philosophical respiration.”¹ The pattern is so pervasive that it shaped the trajectory of his entire career: a philosophy of the will that<italic>detours</italic>through analyses of sign, symbol, metaphor, and narrative,<italic>returning</italic>to a richer account of personal identity in his hermeneutics of the self.² But Ricoeur’s endlessly dialogical mode of thinking not only leads him to take many detours; it also makes his work suitable to be used as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Emplotting Virtue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative and the Good Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TREANOR</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul Ricoeur’s work remains lamentably underappreciated a few years after this death. Several factors contribute to the relative neglect of his thought. First, Ricoeur is fastidious to a fault in acknowledging his intellectual debts, which can, deceptively, make his thought appear derivative. Second, the pattern of “detour and return” that characterizes his thinking can make it difficult to keep up with him. Following Ricoeur takes one through the diverse fields of existentialism, structuralism, psychoanalysis, and analytic philosophy, to name only a few of his better-known detours. How many philosophers read both Derrida and Parfit? Heidegger and Searle? Nevertheless, those willing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preserving the Eidetic Moment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on the Work of Paul Ricoeur</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RASMUSSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My original encounter with the person and the work of Paul Ricoeur began with an attempt to appropriate his thought for the retrieval of the symbolic. This led to a concern with what I called<italic>mythic-symbolic</italic>language correlated with anthropological considerations about the nature of the human, subjectivity, the self—stemming from his<italic>Philosophy of the Will</italic>. At that time I had been meeting once a week with the Romanian phenomenologist of religion Mircea Eliade to discuss his work in general, which I wanted to write about. I had told Eliade that I was not particularly interested in his classes;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chgx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
