<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B4378.D43K54 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kierkegaard, Søren, 1813–1855</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Death</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Kierkegaard and Death</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>STOKES</surname>
               <given-names>PATRICK</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BUBEN</surname>
               <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253356857</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253005342</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253005345</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BLOOMINGTON; INDIANAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz6m3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Few philosophers have devoted such sustained, almost obsessive attention to the topic of death as Søren Kierkegaard. Kierkegaard and Death brings together new work on Kierkegaard's multifaceted discussions of death and provides a thorough guide to the development, in various texts and contexts, of Kierkegaard's ideas concerning death. Essays by an international group of scholars take up essential topics such as dying to the world, living death, immortality, suicide, mortality and subjectivity, death and the meaning of life, remembrance of the dead, and the question of the afterlife. While bringing Kierkegaard's philosophy of death into focus, this volume connects Kierkegaard with important debates in contemporary philosophy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stokes</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buben</surname>
                           <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On Wednesday, July 29, 1835, two days before the first anniversary of his mother’s death, a twenty-two-year-old theology student writes of his experience of standing atop Gilbjerg Hoved, a small cliff just outside the North Zealand coastal town of Gilleleje:</p>
                     <p>This has always been one of my favorite spots. Often, as I stood here on a quiet evening, the sea intoning its song with deep but calm solemnity, my eye catching not a single sail on the vast surface, and only the sea framed the sky and the sky the sea, while on the other hand the busy hum of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Knights and Knaves of the Living Dead:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard’s Use of Living Death as a Metaphor for Despair</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Connell</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the endlessly repeated motifs of the horror genre, none more reliably evokes a shudder than the idea of the undead, of humans doomed to wander between life and death. This response has a variety of deep psychological sources. Our anxiety in the face of our own mortality plays a part, as does a physiological revulsion to decaying bodies. Further, the sense of the living dead as ontologically other evokes in us a sense of numinous dread. Following Mary Douglas, the way such beings transgress the boundary separating life and death renders them both dangerous and impure.¹</p>
                     <p>Given the resonances</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>To Die and Yet Not Die:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard’s Theophany of Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Podmore</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Periissem, nisi periissem</italic>[I would have perished, had I not perished] still is and will be my life motto. This is why I have been able to endure what long since would have killed someone else who was not dead.¹</p>
                     <p>—KIERKEGAARD,<italic>SØREN KIERKEGAARD’S JOURNALS AND PAPERS</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Confessing in this journal entry from 1848 that, without dying willingly, death would have prevailed over him, Kierkegaard discloses how a life of suffering has prevented death from laying its claim to one who was already dead. Kierkegaard’s appropriation of the Latin aphorism further expresses an integral spiritual dialectic at the heart of Lutheran</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Christian Hate:</title>
                     <subtitle>Death, Dying, and Reason in Pascal and Kierkegaard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buben</surname>
                           <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Should Søren Kierkegaard be listed among Christian apologists such as Anselm, Thomas Aquinas, or even Blaise Pascal? Focusing on his connections to Pascal, twentieth-century scholars Denzil G. M. Patrick and José Raimundo Maia Neto claim that Kierkegaard is, in fact, engaged in the same sort of project.¹ Kierkegaard himself seems to lend support to these claims when he states, “I have never broken with Christianity … from the time it was possible to speak of the application of my powers, I had firmly resolved to employ everything to defend it, or in any case to present it in its true</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Suicide and Despair</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mjaaland</surname>
                           <given-names>Marius Timmann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Sickness unto Death</italic>. Already the title indicates a deep affliction with the problem of suicide, although the book is presented as a treatise on the modern self in despair. Suicide is not mentioned until a later stage of the analysis, when Kierkegaard suddenly breaks into a short discussion of how suicide influences despair. Then he admits, albeit in brackets, that this is what the<italic>entire</italic>investigation is about—in a “more profound” sense. The question of suicide thus seems unavoidable for any reading of<italic>The Sickness unto Death,</italic>but its significance has, so far, hardly been acknowledged or properly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Thinking Death into Every Moment:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Existence-Problem of Dying in Kierkegaard’s Postscript</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Muench</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Doing philosophy may be hazardous to your health, resulting in a condition of “absentmindedness” or distraction in which you forget yourself.¹ In such a case, philosophy becomes an activity that positively interferes with the age-old Socratic task of attending to and caring for the self, and may even have the opposite effect of making people “incompetent to act” (CUP, 1:135/SKS 7, 126). If you are the type of person who is drawn to philosophy and perhaps insufficiently aware of its hazards, then what could be more valuable than a book that seeks to alert you to these dangers, and in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Death and Ethics in Kierkegaard’s Postscript</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Possen</surname>
                           <given-names>David D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the aims of Kierkegaard’s<italic>Concluding Unscientific Postscript</italic>is to recover an “ancient” model of ethics—“the subjective ethics,” or “the socalled subjective ethical” (CUP, 1:144–47/SKS 7, 134–36)—and defend it against the “objective” approach that has become the norm “in modern parlance” (CUP, 1:133/SKS 7, 124–25; trans. modified). Johannes Climacus, the<italic>Postscript</italic>’s pseudonymous author, expresses the difference between ancient/subjective ethics and modern/objective ethics as follows.<italic>Modern</italic>ethics, he quips, answers the question fundamental to all ethical inquiry—the question “What am I to do?” (CUP, 1:133/SKS 7, 125)—with “the modern slogan … ‘What the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>The Intimate Agency of Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mooney</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Midway through his fluid meditations in<italic>Moby Dick,</italic>Melville presents us with a particularly hair-raising incident. A fourteenth-century British commander has conquered a French town and demands his fair tribute in victory. He asks for six citizens to step forward to be hanged. The mayor and five others advance with halters around their necks. This fright snaps us alert—not just to cruelty, but to our mortality. And within a page, Melville assures us that a philosopher, sitting by the fire contemplating death, can be as aware, afraid, and deeply cognizant of death as anyone mounting a gallows. We all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>A Critical Perspective on Kierkegaard’s “At a Graveside”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marino</surname>
                           <given-names>Gordon D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This short chapter is faceted to one text—Kierkegaard’s “At a Graveside.” While Kierkegaard’s thoughts on death spill across his corpus, I believe that this nonpseudonymous discourse, published in 1845, is his most straightforward and sustained reflection on what might be termed Kierkegaard’s account of “Being-towards-death.” Drawing a comparison with Tolstoy, I submit that for all the epiphanies in these pellucid pages, there is something lacking. There are other lessons to be drawn.</p>
                     <p>Kierkegaard and his pseudonyms stress that thinkers who fail to express their words in their actions do not really understand what they are spouting. Over and over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Life-Narrative and Death as the End of Freedom:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard on Anticipatory Resoluteness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davenport</surname>
                           <given-names>John J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In three recent articles, John Lippitt has raised important questions about the notions that human selves have a “narrative” structure and that the natural development of our capacity for robust selves (including autonomy and ethical maturity) involves achieving “narrative unity” in the stories that we are.¹ His questions intersect with other critiques of narrative models raised in the wider and growing literature on this topic in the past decade. Lippitt forces us to reconsider claims that Anthony Rudd, I, and others made in<italic>Kierkegaard After MacIntyre</italic>that MacIntyre’s famous account of narrative unity as part of the telos of human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Heidegger and Kierkegaard on Death:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Existentiell and the Existential</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Guignon</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The jury is still out on the nature and extent of Kierkegaard’s influence on the early Heidegger, including his magnum opus<italic>Being and Time</italic>(1927) as well as his lectures and writings prior to that work. In the “Foreword” to the 1972 edition of his “Early Writings” in German, Heidegger speaks of those “exciting years between 1910 and 1914” when, together with the work of Nietzsche and Dostoevsky, he read translations of the writings of Kierkegaard.¹ However, it is not evident how much of Kierkegaard seeped into Heidegger’s thought or precisely which texts influenced his own. Theodore Kisiel suggests that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Kierkegaard, Levinas, Derrida:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Death of the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Llevadot</surname>
                           <given-names>Laura</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“A free man thinks of nothing less than of death”¹ according to proposition 47 of Spinoza’s<italic>Ethics,</italic>in which death is portrayed as a saddening thought, one which, moreover, depletes our potential to work and to think. The refusal to think about death, and specifically its association with sadness and pain for those left behind, is a constant theme in the history of philosophy. The image of Socrates presented in<italic>Phaedo,</italic>happy to accept his own death, is emblematic of the philosopher who has learned how to die. Xanthippe, his wife, is expelled from this scene in which philosophy and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Derrida, Judge William, and Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duckles</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I attempt to take seriously Derrida’s reading of Kierkegaard’s<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>in<italic>The Gift of Death</italic>.¹ In particular, I focus on Derrida’s claim that all universalizing ethical systems involve an evasion of responsibility for one’s actions. As Derrida sees it, this has important connections with mortality, since (following Heidegger)² it is through developing the correct attitude toward my own mortality—and consequently my singularity as this particular individual—that I am able to lead an authentic life. In effect, I take Derrida to be suggesting that pursuing ethical considerations is an attempt to avoid confronting one’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>The Soft Weeping of Desire’s Loss:</title>
                     <subtitle>Recognition, Phenomenality, and the One Who Is Dead in Kierkegaard’s Works of Love</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremy J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the ninth chapter of the second set of deliberations in<italic>Works of Love,</italic>Kierkegaard writes the following words: “I know of no better way to describe true recollection than by this soft weeping that does not burst into sobs at one moment—and soon subsides. No, we are to recollect the dead, weep softly, but weep long” (WL, 348/SKS 9, 342). Much of the work in the chapter you now read is spent setting up the problematic that aims at establishing a relation between grieving and the lack of recognition from those now absent from our experience of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Duties to the Dead?</title>
                     <subtitle>Earnest Imagination and Remembrance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stokes</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Perhaps nothing in Kierkegaard’s writings has proven quite as polarizing as<italic>Works of Love</italic>. The reception of this work has been characterized by perennial charges that it articulates an inhuman, acosmic, inward-looking vision of ethical life. These criticisms famously begin with Adorno, who claims that Kierkegaard’s concern to avoid “preferential” love in all forms leads to an “object-less” love in which the other is reduced to a mere “stumbling block.”¹ The result is an ethic whose “content is oppression: the oppression of the drive which is not to be fulfilled and the oppression of the mind which is not allowed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Kierkegaard’s Understanding of the Afterlife</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marks</surname>
                           <given-names>Tamara Monet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kierkegaard believed that he would experience a postmortem existence. Direct evidence for his belief may be found in his personal, pseudonymous, and signed writings. At the age of thirty-two, Kierkegaard wrote detailed instructions for the repair of his family’s burial site. Among his plans one finds lines from a hymn Brorson penned for his own tombstone. The content of the hymn suggests, among other things, that the afterlife puts an end to struggle in this life. The lines read:</p>
                     <p>In yet a little while</p>
                     <p>I shall have won;</p>
                     <p>Then the whole fight</p>
                     <p>Will at once be done.</p>
                     <p>Then I may</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz6m3.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
