<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g541</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>François Laruelle’s Philosophies of Difference</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Critical Introduction and Guide</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GANGLE</surname>
               <given-names>ROCCO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748668120</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748668144</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748668144</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Rocco Gangle</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b3gr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Everything you need to understand both Laruelle's critique of difference and his project of non-philosophyGBS_insertPreviewButtonPopup (['ISBN:9780748668120','ISBN:9780748668144','ISBN:9780748668137','ISBN:9780748668151']);</p>
         <p>Gilles Deleuze described Laruelle's thought as 'one of the most interesting undertakings of contemporary philosophy'. Now, Rocco Gangle - who translated Laruelle's philosophy into English - takes you through Laruelle's trailblazing book<italic>Philosophies of Difference</italic>, helping you to understand both Laruelle's critique of Difference and his project of non-philosophy, which has become one of the most intriguing avenues in contemporary thought. He explains the context within which Laruelle's thought developed and takes you through the challenging argument and conceptual scaffolding of 'Philosophies of Difference'.</p>
         <p>Key Feature</p>
         <p>Critiques philosophical Difference as a whole and the 3 specific models treated by Laruelle: Nietzsche-Deleuze, Heidegger and DerridaSituates Philosophies of Difference within the rest of Laruelle's work and contemporary European thoughtExplains the key shift from philosophy to non-philosophy which makes Laruelle so intriguing to philosophers todayShows how Laruelle impacted on the work of Deleuze and Badiou and the Speculative Realism movement</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Situating Philosophies of Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What has philosophy done for you lately? Has it challenged you? Has it saved you? Has it become an instrument in your hands for challenging and saving others? Or has it used you merely to propagate itself? Has it tricked you? In this dance or friendship or war between you and philosophy, who leads and who follows? Are you philosophy’s subject or its object, its mirror or its image? Are you Master or Slave here; maker, tool or half-finished product? To be sure, such images and relations are just metaphors and not concepts, yet we cannot help but ask what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The critique of Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Philosophies of Difference</italic>engages the philosophies of Nietzsche, Heidegger, Derrida and Deleuze in order to mark a distinction between philosophical thinking (which perhaps in the work of these thinkers is pushed in some sense to its limit) and a new, more general mode of thinking which will be called non-philosophy. Laruelle’s text itself bridges the diff erence both methodologically and thematically between these two kinds of thought; it is at once philosophical<italic>and</italic>non-philosophical. Keeping in mind that non-philosophy is not meant to be a negation but rather a generalisation of philosophy, we should understand this ‘at once’ as in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Nietzsche-Deleuzean model of Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>Idealism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the history of modern philosophy, after the systems of Kant and Hegel – systems respectively of the immanent critique and the apotheosis of Reason – the non-rationalist image of philosophy as anti-system or immanently creative Difference is born with Nietzsche. As the first of the three models of Difference analysed by Laruelle, Nietzschean Difference may be considered in an important sense as the base or standard model for the analysis overall.¹ Nietzschean Difference represents, from this point of view, the more general philosophical platform upon which the other, more specialised models of Difference will be constructed. Historically, it is with Nietzsche</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Heideggerean model of Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>Finitude</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If for Laruelle Nietzsche establishes the standard model of philosophy as Difference, Heidegger marks the full taking-stock of Difference in relation to the Western tradition as such and draws out the consequences of its immanent critique as the culmination of metaphysics. Whereas Laruelle characterises the Nietzschean model of Difference as one of ‘Idealism’, he designates the Heideggerean model as that of ‘Finitude’. Laruelle’s reading of Heidegger follows the late Heidegger in treating the thought of the ontological difference of Being and beings as still determined and thus relatively constrained by the history of metaphysics. Thus for the late Heidegger, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Derridean model of Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>Differance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Laruelle opens his chapter on Derrida with a quintessentially Nietzschean image, that of the tightrope-walker. Derrida is characterised by Laruelle as being perhaps the most trenchant critic of the Western decision for logocentrism and metaphysics, while nonetheless reinstating that decision despite himself, being unable ‘to take the final step’:</p>
                     <p>Derrida is the thinker who carries philosophical decision to the limit of aporetic dislocation pure and simple and who yet, through<italic>the virtuosity of the endangered tightrope-walker</italic>, undertakes to seize decision again one last time and to maintain its possibility and truth, refusing to take the final step.¹</p>
                     <p>Laruelle appears here</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>From Difference to vision-in-One</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We noted early in our opening chapter that in<italic>Philosophies of Difference</italic>Laruelle aims to mount a ‘critique that would no longer be a complement, a rectification, a deconstruction, a supplement’, the object of this critique being philosophy’s need ‘to think through unifying duality, through the synthesis of contraries, through the One as All or as unity of contraries, through dialectic and difference’.¹ We are now in a position to understand this aim more precisely with respect to the triad of models of Difference represented by Nietzsche-Deleuze, Heidegger and Derrida respectively, as well as the (partially anachronistic) history they compose.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b3gr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
