<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR428.T7A53 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Early modern, 1500–1700</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Translating and interpreting</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">16th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Translating and interpreting</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Early modern, 1500–1700</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">16th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Renaissance</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Translating Investments: Metaphor and the Dynamics of Cultural Change in Tudor-Stuart England</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Anderson</surname>
               <given-names>Judith H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823224210</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246755</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x05b5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The title Translating Investments, a manifold pun, refers to metaphor and clothing, authority and interest, and trading and finance. Translation, Latin translatio, is historically a name for metaphor, and investment, etymologically a reference to clothing, participates both in the complex symbolism of early modern dress and in the cloth trade of the period. In this original and wide-ranging book, Judith Anderson studies the functioning of metaphor as a constructive force within language, religious doctrine and politics, literature, rhetoric, and economics during the reigns of the Tudors and early Stuarts. Invoking a provocative metaphorical concept from Andy Clark's version of cognitive science, she construes metaphor itself as a form of scaffolding fundamental to human culture. A more traditional and controversial conception of such scaffolding is known as sublation-Hegel's Aufhebung, or raising,as the philosophers Jacques Derrida and Paul Ricoeur have understood this term. Metaphor is the agent of raising, or sublation, and sublation is inseparable from the productive life of metaphor, as distinct in its death in code or clich. At the same time, metaphor embodies the sense both of partial loss and of continuity, or preservation, also conveyed by the term Aufhebung. Anderson's study is simultaneously critical and historical. History and the theory are shown to be mutually enlightening, as are a wide variety of early modern texts and their specific cultural contexts. From beginning to end, this study touches the present, engaging questions about language, rhetoric, and reading within post-structuralism and neo-cognitivism. It highlights connections between intellectual problems active in our own culture and those evident in the earlier texts, controversies, and crises Anderson analyzes. In this way, the study is bifocal, like metaphor itself. While Anderson's overarching concern is with metaphor as a creative exchange, a source of code-breaking conceptual power, each of her chapters focuses on a different but related issue and cultural sector. Foci include the basic conditions of linguistic meaning in the early modern period, instantiated by Shakespeare's plays and related to modern theories of metaphor; the role of metaphor in the words of eucharistic institution under Archbishop Cranmer; the play of metaphor and metonymy in the writings of Luther, Zwingli, and Calvin and in John Donne's Devotions; the manipulation of these two tropes in the politics of the controversy over ecclesiastical vestments and in its treatment by John Foxe; the abuse of figuration in the house of Edmund Spenser's Busirane, where catachresis, an extreme form of metaphor, is the trope du jour; the conception of metaphor in the Roman rhetorics and their legacy in the sixteenth century; and the concept of exchange in the economic writing of Gerrard de Malynes, merchant and metaphorist in the reigns of Elizabeth and James. What emerges at the end of this book is a heightened critical sense of the dynamic of metaphor in cultural history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>J.H.A.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Renaissance Metaphor and the Dynamic of Cultural Change:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introductory Road Map</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book studies the functioning of metaphor in Tudor and early Stuart culture. Accordingly, its chapters treat a range of disciplines, including language, religion, rhetoric, politics, literature, and economics. Also and inevitably, it touches the present, raising questions about the position of language and rhetoric within post-structuralism and neo-cognitivism and doing so in a way that highlights the connection between intellectual problems active in our own culture and those manifested in the sixteenth- and seventeenth-century texts, controversies, and crises that I discuss.<italic>Translating Investments</italic>is thus conceived as simultaneously a critical and a historical study.</p>
                     <p>In it, I am recurrently</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Translating Investments:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Metaphoricity of Language, Hamlet, and 2 Henry IV</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, my argument, which is historical in orientation, suggests a way of conceiving language that informs the metaphoricity of Renaissance writings and bears on our reading of them. In doing so, it also addresses contemporary debates about the metaphoricity of language and their application to the early modern period. Ultimately it treats Shakespeare’s use of the word<italic>investment</italic>in<italic>2 Henry IV</italic>and<italic>Hamlet</italic>as telling instances of the linguistic character of early modern metaphor, whose conditions of meaning differ in significant ways from our own. What follows in this chapter is an effort to make history, theory,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Language and History in the Reformation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translating Matter to Metaphor in the Sacrament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What follows further concerns two interlocking interests: the involvement of language in history, history in language, and herein the particular role of language, especially figurative language, in the early reforms of the established church in Tudor England. Still more specifically, my concerns in this chapter will focus on explanations of eucharistic belief during the archbishopric of Thomas Cranmer. As Diarmaid MacCulloch, Cranmer’s recent biographer, has observed, Cranmer’s basic problem ‘‘was how best to convey a metaphorical notion of presence.’’¹ Language and rhetoric, the language art, were at the heart of this problem.</p>
                     <p>Linguistic history is the larger backdrop against which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Donne’s Tropic Awareness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metaphor, Metonymy, and Devotions upon Emergent Occasions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To ask in what ways and to what extent John Donne might have been aware of the dazzling tropes he used would seem a question whose answer is self-evident. Historically, however, this is a real question, and one bearing on faith and ideology. To take an obvious instance, the correspondences invoked so often in Donne’s writing are to us metaphoric fiction, but as extensions of a single, celestial power, hence valid and real parallels, they presumably meant more for Donne and his immediate audience, even in their more skeptical moments. They assume the familiar centered universe organized hierarchically from low</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Vesting Significance and Authority:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Vestiarian Controversy under Cranmer and Its Treatment by Foxe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That a particular outfit or a more general style of clothing should make a ‘‘statement’’ is a familiar enough idea in the twenty-first century. It assumes that clothing, like language, participates in a system of signs, and that plain clothing, such as chinos or blue jeans, can be every bit as much a statement as can a dark suit, a pink dress, or a tuxedo. But when we take clothing to be making a ‘‘statement,’’ rhetorically we are using a metaphor, or possibly a metonymy, or both. Only figuratively does clothing speak and whether it speaks metonymically or metaphorically depends</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Busirane’s Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>The House of Abusive Rhetoric in The Faerie Queene</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the House of Busirane, culmination of the 1590 edition of Spenser’s<italic>Faerie Queene</italic>, should be a ‘‘house’’ in the rhetorical sense—a rhetorical place or topos—came with the surprise of delayed recognition to me, as well as to the audiences with whom I have shared and explored this idea. The delay may testify to our distance from a deliberately, self-consciously rhetorical culture, even as its recognition suggests that this distance is not insurmountable. Erotic reality, a conception tottering on the brink of oxymoron, conspicuously and especially takes rhetorical forms, as it radically does in Busirane’s House, precisely because</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Catachresis and Metaphor:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Be Bold, Be Bold, Be Not Too Bold’’ in the Latin Rhetorical Tradition and Its Renaissance Adaptors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Twice in recent chapters, I have invoked Richard Lanham’s definition of catachresis as a wrenching of metaphor or an extravagant use of it, in any case, as a violent (mis)use of language. Qualifying Lanham’s definition, I have also observed the appreciation of traditional rhetoric for the necessity, and not merely the extravagance, of catachresis in the absence of any other suitable words. Lanham’s definition is a cogent synthesis abstracted from classical and Renaissance sources, and I have annotated it as such, along with reference to Patricia Parker’s provocative analysis of definitions of metaphor and catachresis from classical times to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Exchanging Values:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Economic and Rhetorical World Seen by Gerrard de Malynes, Merchant</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1622, Gerrard de Malynes, self-styled ‘‘Merchant,’’ published his<italic>magnum opus</italic>entitled<italic>Consuetudo, vel Lex Mercatoria, or The Antient Law-Merchant</italic>. While concerned with mercantile law (and nowadays found in law libraries),<italic>Lex Mercatoria</italic>focuses primarily on mercantile custom. It fundamentally engages economic issues, as do Malynes’ earlier writings, on which discussion of his historical significance has focused.<italic>Lex Mercatoria</italic>affords a broader context for these views than do his other writings, however, and it affords ways of looking at them that cast light on the curious fact of his also having composed an allegory about usury and exchange, complete with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x05b5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
