<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">QL87.5 .M68 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dead animals</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pets</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Death</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pets</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Funeral rites and ceremonies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Animal cemeteries</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human-animal relationships</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Biological Sciences</subject>
         <subject>Zoology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mourning Animals</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rituals and Practices Surrounding Animal Death</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DeMello</surname>
               <given-names>Margo</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>Series Editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kalof</surname>
               <given-names>Linda</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781611862126</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609174989</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michigan State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt1c6v89n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>We live more intimately with nonhuman animals than ever before in history. The change in the way we cohabitate with animals can be seen in the way we treat them when they die. There is an almost infinite variety of ways to help us cope with the loss of our nonhuman friends-from burial, cremation, and taxidermy; to wearing or displaying the remains (ashes, fur, or other parts) of our deceased animals in jewelry, tattoos, or other artwork; to counselors who specialize in helping people mourn pets; to classes for veterinarians; to tips to help the surviving animals who are grieving their animal friends; to pet psychics and memorial websites. But the reality is that these practices, and related beliefs about animal souls or animal afterlife, generally only extend, with very few exceptions, to certain kinds of animals-pets. Most animals, in most cultures, are not mourned, and the question of an animal afterlife is not contemplated at all.<italic>Mourning Animals</italic>investigates how we mourn animal deaths, which animals are grievable, and what the implications are for all animals.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>People today, especially in the industrialized and postindustrialized world, live more intimately with nonhuman animals than ever before in history. We share our lives with companion animals in a way that just fifty years ago would have been unheard of. One way to measure this drastic change in our relationships with other animals is to look at the growth of the animal death care industry. According to Brandes, there are over six hundred pet cemeteries in the United States alone, while according to Ambros there are over 900 in Japan.¹ There is even a small but growing movement to allow</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Discarded Property</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOHNSTONE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY SHANNON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xxvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In North Carolina, the state in which I live, every year over one hundred thousand dogs and cats are euthanized because there is no place to put them (North Carolina Department of Health and Human Services). That is almost 300 animals every day, which I find shocking and heartbreaking.</p>
                     <p>Before I began this project, I knew that animal euthanasia was a fact. When I heard the statistics, I naively wanted to believe that those two hundred thousand euthanized dogs and cats were the bad ones—the sick, aggressive, feral, mean dogs and cats that needed to be put down. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxviii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>More than a Bag of Bones:</title>
                     <subtitle>A History of Animal Burials</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COLLIER</surname>
                           <given-names>IVY D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Animal burials have been found throughout the archaeological record dating back to the Neolithic period. The question is, how do we know if those burials are the result of a human–animal bond or if the animals buried are what zooarchaeologists call articulated or associated animal bone groups?</p>
                     <p>There are a great many reasons why animals could be found buried that may have nothing to do with a relationship with a person. For example, animals could be buried after a sacrifice (the animal was killed but was left whole); the animal could have died of natural causes (it may have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mourning the Sacrifice:</title>
                     <subtitle>Behavior and Meaning behind Animal Burials</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORRIS</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The remains of animals, fragments of bone and horn, are often the most common finds recovered from archaeological excavations. The potential of using this material to examine questions of past economics and environment has long been recognized and is viewed by many archaeologists as the primary purpose of animal remains. In part this is due to the paradigm in which zooarchaeology developed and a consequence of practitioners’ concentration on taphonomy and quantification.¹ But the complex intertwined relationships between humans and animals have long been recognized, a good example being Lévi-Strauss’s oft quoted “natural species are chosen, not because they are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Horses, Mourning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interspecies Embodiment, Belonging, and Bereavement in the Past and Present</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ARGENT</surname>
                           <given-names>GALA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some 2400 years ago, people belonging to the Iron Age Pazyryk archaeological culture gathered together to lay their dead to rest in burial mounds in the remote Inner Asian Altai Mountains. At these funerals, they sacrificed elaborately costumed riding horses and carefully buried them alongside the deceased (figure 1). While typical burials of this age present only metal and bone for analysis, here the graves subsequently froze in permafrost, preserving wood, leather, fabric, and often the entire bodies of the humans and horses. These unusual burials thus provide an excellent opportunity for exploring the particular connections between these people and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Issue of Animals’ Souls within the Anglican Debate in the Eighteenth to Nineteenth Centuries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MASSARO</surname>
                           <given-names>ALMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The debate on animal souls and the problem of theodicy with respect to animal suffering, a discussion that has been a feature of European thought since the seventeenth century, became the perfect pillar for those philosophies that were born in the wake of scientific discoveries and that aimed to assert the unreasonableness of Christianity. Such philosophies questioned how a good and almighty God could let innocent animals undergo all the evils they endure daily. One solution was to deny to animals feelings and reason; for instance, Descartes’s theory of the animal-machine suggested that animals were unable to feel pleasure and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hartsdale Pet Cemetery</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARGULIES</surname>
                           <given-names>LIZA WALLIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite living most of my life within a fifteen-minute drive of the country’s oldest pet cemetery, it wasn’t until a brisk late-winter afternoon that I visited there for the first time. I had just said a final goodbye to my bonhomous black lab, Ben, and brought him to the crematory on the grounds of the cemetery. The arrestingly cheerful woman behind the desk invited me to walk around the place while he was being cremated. She said it would take roughly two hours. In the end I would leave with a container of ashes.</p>
                     <p>This is the first example of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>All the World and a Little Bit More:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pet Cemetery Practices and Contemporary Relations between Humans and Their Companion Animals</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PRĘGOWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAŁ PIOTR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Burying companion animals had been practiced by humans as early as 16,500 years BP, as recent archeological findings from the Epipaleolithic cemetery of Uyun al-Hammam suggest.¹ During the Early Neolithic (ca. 8000 BP) the burials of dogs who accompanied hunter-gatherers were already common.² Despite having a significant history, mortuary practices related to companion animals gained social significance not so long ago—in the nineteenth century, following industrialization, urbanization, as well as the rise of the middle class. At that time, purebred dogs ceased to dwell mostly in upper-class estates and became a fixture in the confined spaces of European and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>To All that Fly or Crawl:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Recent History of Mourning for Animals in Korea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VELDKAMP</surname>
                           <given-names>ELMER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In residential neighborhoods in Korea up until the 1980s, dog buyers would roam the area calling out “Sell your dogs, sell your dogs!,” indicating their willingness to pay for privately kept dogs as a source of meat. For many, the divide between pets and nonpets was not a clear-cut line, and the death of dogs, cats, and other animals was not considered something to mourn for.</p>
                     <p>On October 30, 2014, news came out that a seventeen-year–old high school student had taken her own life. In her final communication with other students, she stated that she felt guilty about her</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Freeze-Drying Fido:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Uncanny Aesthetics of Modern Taxidermy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COLVIN</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINA M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two forms of taxidermy predominate in the popular imagination: the type specimen in the natural history museum and the severed-head–style hunting trophy. In the case of the museum specimen, taxidermic animals stand in for their species; single animals serve as representatives of whole populations. In the tradition of the “Father of Modern Taxidermy” Carl Akeley, the aesthetic of the museum specimen minimizes differences between individuals (such as bullet wounds and other surface blemishes) to maximize an animal’s emblematic power; according to Donna Haraway, such taxidermy makes “nature true to type.”¹ In the case of hunting trophies, taxidermic animals represent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Clutching at Straws:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dogs, Death, and Frozen Semen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WANNER</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISSIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One summer morning in 2013, I received a call from a vet who had been assisting me in my research on the ethics of pedigree dog breeding. She asked me to meet her at her canine reproduction clinic because she had been contacted by a client whose three-year–old male dog, Jake, had just been diagnosed with terminal cancer and was not expected to see the end of the summer. The owner had been given the diagnosis the previous day, and the clinic was her first port of call. The vet did not offer any hope of a cure for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>I Remember Everything:</title>
                     <subtitle>Children, Companion Animals, and a Relational Pedagogy of Remembrance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUSSELL</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSHUA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a cool April afternoon in 2012, I sat down to interview six-year–old Oscar at his family’s kitchen counter in their semidetached home in Toronto. I asked Oscar if it was okay to turn on the audio recording device during our conversation. He said yes, and I showed him how to turn it on. He agreed to be in charge of the recorder during the interview, a task that many children seem to enjoy. After waiting for the red recording light to appear, I showed Oscar a piece of paper with a short list of interview guidelines and matters</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Cats and Contradictions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mourning Animal Death in an English Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TIPPER</surname>
                           <given-names>BECKY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We live among nonhuman animals. Even in cities and suburbs, spaces seemingly dominated and shaped by human intent, animals inhabit our homes and gardens (sometimes by invitation and sometimes not); their tracks and trails intersect with ours; their lives touch our own. For more than a year, I researched these ordinary encounters between the species. I focused on a neighborhood in a northern English city, and (following in a tradition of interpretive sociology) I employed an ethnographic approach to explore the ways that people made sense of their everyday engagements with the creatures who shared their neighborhood.¹</p>
                     <p>In the course</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>So Sorry for the Loss of Your Little Friend:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pets’ Grievability in Condolence Cards for Humans Mourning Animals</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>REDMALM</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If a friend of yours loses a beloved companion animal, would you send her or him a condolence card? Previous research suggests that, because of a widespread taboo on the display of grief for companion animals, it is doubtful that you would. The explanations for such a pet grief taboo converge around one main point: a human’s grief for members of other species threatens humans’ anthropocentric worldview.¹ Companion animals have a liminal position as they are regarded both as persons and as property, as subjects and objects, and to mourn such liminal persons would be to transgress the human/animal divide.²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Claire:</title>
                     <subtitle>Last Days</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHLOSSER</surname>
                           <given-names>JULIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Claire came to live with me in 2009. I made the decision to euthanize her on July 5, 2011, because she suffered from osteomyelitis, a painful bone infection. I’ve lived with animals since I was four. In my adult life, I have loved, nursed, and mourned the loss of beloved animal companions. But when I reflect on Claire’s life, I am haunted by questions that I never had to ask when those other animals died. Would she have rather I left her where I met her, living in a cardboard box in a windowless bathroom? Or would she have made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Britain at War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering and Forgetting the Animal Dead of the Second World War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEAN</surname>
                           <given-names>HILDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent decades when contested invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq have resulted in human and nonhuman animal combatant and civilian war dead—and massive demonstrations against such adventures—the British remain obsessed with commemorating the Second World War. The 1939–45 war has remained as a “good” war in public memory. Despite—or perhaps because of—the passing of the years new memorials have been erected to discrete groups of humans previously not specifically commemorated. These include one to firefighters near St. Paul’s Cathedral (which they helped to ensure was not destroyed by fire), one to women in the site</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Now on Exhibit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Our Affection for, Remembrance of, and Tributes to Nonhuman Animals in Museums</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MULLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>CAROLYN MERINO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Virtually every aspect of society—from spam to broken relationships—has been curated in the museum field, and such is the case with mourning and death, albeit few and far between. Just a few thematic institutions exist, like the Museum of Mourning Art at the Arlington Cemetery (no reference to animals, as far as my research indicates) and the Museum of Death in Hollywood, California. The latter has a small gallery dedicated to taxidermy and jarred animal bodies, and the owners’ own potbellied pig, now stuffed, greets visitors as they enter the theater.</p>
                     <p>In terms of mourning and commemoration, more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Another Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KISIEL</surname>
                           <given-names>EMMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of whether or not humans mourn animals is present in all of my photographic work. This theme emerged in my art when I began looking closely at dead animals and making images of roadkill animals, photographing flower and stone memorials I built around their bodies. My recent project, “Another Death,” portrays museum taxidermic animals that have suffered another kind of death after their initial demise. Frozen in time, they are presented either in the throes of death at another creature’s hand or in a limp resting pose, having just passed. Moments like these appear frequently in natural history</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>In the Heart of Every Horse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Combating a History of Equine Exploitation and Slaughter through the Commemoration of an “Average” Thoroughbred Racehorse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCKEE</surname>
                           <given-names>TAMAR V. S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In mid-September 2011, on a breezy day edged with a hint of autumn chill, I took a seat amid a modest collection of bright white folding chairs lined up outside the Hall of Champions complex at the Kentucky Horse Park. People were milling about, enjoying refreshments and chatting to each other before the memorial service began for a Thoroughbred racehorse by the name of Invisible Ink. On display in front of the chairs was a richly colored photograph of the horse, who was bay with a white, heart-shaped “star” on his forehead. Groomed to shine, he wore a fine leather</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Creating Carnivores and Cannibals:</title>
                     <subtitle>Animal Feed and the Regulation of Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHEZ</surname>
                           <given-names>KERIDIANA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the nineteenth century, the dog and the horse were man’s best friends. Sagacious, affectionate, and loyal, dog and horse were represented as faithful and helpful creatures that had played key roles in the development of civilization. Frameworks like the animal protection movement enabled, and encouraged, the development and intensification of these affectionate ties. Yet in spite of these ties, the horse was systematically served up to the dog for dinner.</p>
                     <p>To be deemed killable, as Judith Butler says, entails being deemed not grievable. An unmournable life “is not quite a life; it does not qualify as a life and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mourning the Mundane:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memorializing Road-Killed Animals in North America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MONAHAN</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I forced myself to look. Turned away from approaching traffic, but visible in profile as my car crawled to a stop was the bloodied face of a fawn. The young deer must have been killed a few days ago as skin was still largely intact, but exposed wounds were black with rot. In that time, tens of thousands of drivers and even more passengers would have passed his or her body. How many noticed? How many had time to take note of the species, possible age, and likely circumstances of the killing? And how many felt compelled to mourn the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Unmourned</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRANT</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Beyond Coping:</title>
                     <subtitle>Active Mourning in the Animal Sheltering Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AUSTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JESSICA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Animal shelter employees face each day with the possibility of inhabiting antithetical roles: the caretaker, charged with ensuring the safety and well-being of the wards in their custody; and the executioner, overseer of these same animals’ untimely deaths. With shelter euthanasia estimates reaching three million adoptable animals per year, shelter workers shoulder a considerable burden of grief, resulting in stress and manifesting in depression and even physical complaints, such as sleep disturbance and headaches.¹ While several authors describe coping mechanisms for those whose work involves death, both in general and specifically tailored toward shelter employees, little is written about how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mourning for Animals:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Companion Animal Veterinarian’s Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FAWCETT</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I always wanted to work with animals, but the euthanasia of our fifteen-year-old cat when I was fourteen catalyzed that ambition. My grief and sense of helplessness were overwhelming. I can still feel tears stinging my cheeks as I walked into school knowing that the cat I grew up with was being taken to the vet to be “put to sleep” and I could do nothing to save her.</p>
                     <p>Back then I questioned the judgment of my parents and our veterinarian in the end-of-life decision making. I believed I would have made different decisions.</p>
                     <p>Fast forward twenty years and I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>You’re My Sanctuary:</title>
                     <subtitle>Grief, Vulnerability, and Unexpected Secondary Losses for Animal Advocates Mourning a Companion Animal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PALLOTTA</surname>
                           <given-names>NICOLE R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is now well documented that the loss of a cherished companion animal can be as devastating, if not more so, than the loss of an important human relationship.¹ People can experience profound grief over the loss of a beloved animal.²</p>
                     <p>The societal acceptance of companion animals as legitimate objects of grief has become more widespread alongside other cultural trends that have elevated the status of dogs and cats in society, including the rising number of homes that include one or more companion animals and the shifting definition of those companion animals as family members. These trends have led to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Keeping Ghosts Close:</title>
                     <subtitle>Care and Grief at Sanctuaries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JONES</surname>
                           <given-names>PATTRICE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRUEN</surname>
                           <given-names>LORI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the gentle turkey called Dante began to flail and flap in the grip of a heart attack, VINE Sanctuary’s recently hired bird caregiver Danielle Salino flung herself over him, using her own body to buffer him and others from the frantic spasms of his powerful wings. She whispered to him until the spasms subsided then remained draped over his body.</p>
                     <p>“I can’t take it anymore! I can’t take all this death!” she howled. Two other sanctuary workers, each with years of experience, made eye contact, wondering: How will this go? Danielle gulped, then switched gears and began reciting Dante’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Grieving at a Distance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PRIBAC</surname>
                           <given-names>TEYA BROOKS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is not often that, in the daily inundation of concise and carefully selected wordings accompanying images, jointly aiming at bringing the attention of the current-time ever-distracted and ever-rushing viewer to focus on some important plight or another, a verbal-image combination—an Internet meme—strikes me so powerfully as to remain with me for years, possibly forever. This was the case, however, with the photograph of a calf, removed from the mother far too young and placed in a barren crate with barely enough room to move. The calf is looking directly into the camera with pleadingly confused eyes. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Who Is It Acceptable to Grieve?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCARTHUR</surname>
                           <given-names>JO-ANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We grieve our companion animals when they die. Those with whom we share our homes, even our food and our beds. They are dogs, cats, sometimes rodents and winged creatures, sometimes horses or potbellied pigs.</p>
                     <p>Superficially, we grieve the charismatic megafauna whose numbers are in decline. The majestic, the exotic, and the beautiful, like the elephants in Africa and the polar bears in the north. We admire them from afar. We wring our hands and donate to organizations that support their conservation.</p>
                     <p>But there are other animals in our lives. The invisible, yet ever-present, who die unconsidered and unmourned. They</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c6v89n.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
