<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="nlm">Narration</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="nlm">Physician-Patient Relations</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="nlm">Ethics, Medical</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="nlm">Medical History Taking</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Health Sciences</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Chief Concern of Medicine</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Integration of the Medical Humanities and Narrative Knowledge into Medical Practices</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schleifer</surname>
               <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Vannatta</surname>
               <given-names>Jerry B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="author">with</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Crow</surname>
               <given-names>Sheila</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Vannatta</surname>
               <given-names>Seth</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472118595</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472028863</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ANN ARBOR</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.3157169"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Unlike any existing studies of the medical humanities,<italic>The Chief Concern of Medicine</italic>brings to the examination of medical practices a thorough---and clearly articulated---exposition of the nature of narrative. The book builds on the work of linguistics, semiotics, narratology, and discourse theory and examines numerous literary works and narrative "vignettes" of medical problems, situations, and encounters. Throughout, the book presents usable expositions of the ways storytelling organizes itself to allow physicians and other healthcare workers (and even patients themselves) to be more attentive to and self-conscious about the information---the "narrative knowledge"---of the patient's story.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="456"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Medicine, Narrative, and Schema-Based Understanding</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the past decade, we have been teaching a course on literature and medicine. Our purpose has been to make medical students and physicians more cognizant of the role of narrative in medical practice and to help them develop skills that make narrative knowledge a useful and important part of their engagement with patients. To this end, in class and elsewhere (see Vannatta, Schleifer, and Crow 2005, 2010), we have attempted to arrive at—or at least circumscribe—a working definition of knowledge in the “humanistic sciences” in relation to what we are (with others) calling “narrative knowledge.” Such knowledge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE FUNCTIONAL REALISM OF MEDICINE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While efficacy of training for and utilizing “narrative knowledge” within the practices of medicine— something that Rita Charon has aptly called “ narrative medicine”—has grown and continues to grow in medical education and professional practice (see Charon 2006a for a thorough account), defending its method and aims to the medical establishment remains a difficult task. it seems that the burden of proof of its efficacy and scientific reliability still resides on the shoulders of the practitioners of narrative medicine. Those teaching physiology to first-year medical students seem relatively free of the similar onus of demonstrating in a decisive way</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>MODALITIES OF SCIENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative, Phronesis, and the Skills (Technē) of Medicine</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Near the beginning of the<italic>Nicomachean Ethics,</italic>aristotle describes the nature of practical reason, or<italic>phronesis,</italic>particularly in relation to action rather than theoretical thought. “Since, then,” he writes,</p>
                     <p>the present inquiry does not aim at theoretical knowledge like the others (for we are inquiring not in order to know what virtue is, but in order to become good, since otherwise our inquiry would have been of no use), we must examine the nature of actions, namely how we ought to do them. . . . now, that we must act according to the right rule is a common principle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE CHIEF CONCERN OF MEDICINE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative Knowledge and Schema-Based Practice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we examine the concept and function of “narrative knowledge,” both in general and in the practice of medicine. We focus on narrative knowledge in terms of not only the knowledge that a physician-listener can glean from narrative—knowledge that Rita Charon richly describes in her presentation of part of medical practice she calls<italic>narrative medicine</italic>—but also the knowledge of narrative itself and how a working understanding of the shape and features of narrative can contribute to successful medical practices (which Charon also describes). There is great controversy concerning the nature of narrative, its “salient” features, its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>THE LOGIC OF DIAGNOSIS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Peirce, Literary Narrative, and the History of Present Illness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapters 2 and 3, we examined the practical wisdom of the physician in relation to narrative and, particularly, the chief concern of the narratives patients bring to their physicians. In this chapter, we will continue examining the role of narrative in the practices of medicine, but with particular focus on the ways narrative can contribute to diagnostic skills. Specifically, we will examine the logic of hypothesis formation that Charles Sanders Peirce articulated at the turn of the twentieth century, and we hope to demonstrate that his “logic of abduction,” as he called it, approximates the “practical syllogism” that aristotle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE PATIENT-PHYSICIAN RELATIONSHIP:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Scene of Narration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen, the patient brings to the clinical encounter a story, the history of Present Illness (HPI). As the physician listens and responds to this story, a special kind of relationship begins to develop between the patient and doctor. At its best, it is personal and professional at once. It is often charged with deeply felt emotion on the part of the patient—fear and anxiety, anger, sadness, or a combination of these feelings—and with empathetic and more or less calm attention on the part of the physician. Usually growing out of the event of storytelling and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>THE PATIENT’S STORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Apprehension of Narration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 5, we examined the scene of narration; here, we examine the patient’s narration itself, the narrative knowledge it gives rise to, and the ways that knowledge fails to be apprehended by physicians. As we have already noted, the story a patient brings to the physician is usually among the first and most important pieces of information about that patient that health care workers encounter. These stories—narrated by the patient or, in special cases, by others—present information organized in specific ways that call for specific kinds of listening; that define, to a large extent, the patient-physician relationship;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>DOCTORS LISTENING AND ATTENDING TO PATIENTS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Response and Engagement with Acts of Narration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Listening to patients and the illness story is one of the most important skills (<italic>technē</italic>) a physician uses during a lifetime of practice. Because the patient history is the most important diagnostic information, listening carefully is of enormous importance. Patients commonly complain that their doctor does not listen. But when patients are heard, they report that their doctor was empathetic. Listening carefully helps build rapport, increases diagnostic accuracy, and improves patient satisfaction. If a doctor has a broad and deep enough knowledge base, has the skills to listen carefully to what the patient has to say, and gets the information</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>NARRATIVE AND MEDICINE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Schemas of Narration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout Part 2 of this book, we were concerned with storytelling and narrative—with the patient-physician relationship growing out of the encounter of storytelling, the patient’s narrative itself, and a doctor’s ability in listening to narrative. Many experienced physicians develop types of understanding—<italic>phronesis,</italic>narrative knowledge, and logic of diagnosis—that, in their functional engagements with narrative and reality, are different from and complementary to the biomedical knowledge of scientific explanation. Such engagements with narrative are at the heart of humanistic understanding. This chapter reexamines the importance of narrative in the practice of medicine from the point of view of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>NARRATIVE AND EVERYDAY MEDICAL ETHICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Schemas of Action</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ethical practices—behaviors and relationships that necessarily encompass “good” (versus “bad”) actions—are woven into every aspect of medical practices precisely because health care always is vitally concerned with issues of the nature of well-being (the good life, Aristotle’s<italic>eudaimonia</italic>), the nature of interpersonal care (responsibilities of behavior between people, especially in the face of suffering), the maintenance of health and well-being in the larger community (the public and professional roles of physicians and health care workers), and issues of life and death (measures of crucial values). Moreover, the ethics of attitude and action, like the meanings of narrative, is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>READING THE DEATH OF IVAN ILYCH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Leo Tolstoy’s novella<italic>The Death of Ivan Ilych</italic>is a significant literary text that brings together many of the themes of<italic>The Chief Concern of Medicine.</italic>it is a story that resonates with the experience of health care workers—with the experience of physicians, nurses, and others confronted with suffering and dying—and at the same time provokes powerful feelings about our shared knowledge and, indeed, our shared lives as human beings. in significant ways, Tolstoy’s<italic>The Death of Ivan Ilych</italic>is a modern version, in novelistic prose narrative, of the ancient themes of the pity and terror of suffering</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Nexus of Literature and Medicine; The Interactions of Patient and Physician</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We began this book’s discussion with a philosophical argument that the objects of humanistic understanding obtained through narrative knowledge are real and that this reality is a result of narrative understanding and reflection. This reality is demonstrated in a pragmatic way by attending to the actions that spring from the apprehension of dramatic stories and by the outcomes or consequences resulting from exposure to their literary structure and content. We have demonstrated that the consequences of having studied and reflected on the features of narrative structure, character development and motives, time lines in narrative—in a word, the details and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 1.</title>
                     <subtitle>HUMANITIES AS A DISCIPLINE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 2.</title>
                     <subtitle>CHECKLISTS FOR SKILLS IN LISTENING, INTERVIEWING, AND ACTION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>374</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 3.</title>
                     <subtitle>A COMPILATION OF SCHEMAS FOR MEDICAL PRACTICES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>382</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.3157169.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
