<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.H55 L36 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945), in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Silence in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mimesis in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Realism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Textual Silence</book-title>
         <subtitle>Unreadability and the Holocaust</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LANG</surname>
               <given-names>JESSICA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813589909</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813589947</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813589940</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, Camden, Newark, New Jersey; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jessica Lang</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pwtdjf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>There are thousands of books that represent the Holocaust, but can, and should, the act of reading these works convey the events of genocide to those who did not experience it? In<italic>Textual Silence</italic>, literary scholar Jessica Lang asserts that language itself is a barrier between the author and the reader in Holocaust texts-and that this barrier is not a lack of substance, but a defining characteristic of the genre.Holocaust texts, which encompass works as diverse as memoirs, novels, poems, and diaries, are traditionally characterized by silences the authors place throughout the text, both deliberately and unconsciously. While a reader may have the desire and will to comprehend the Holocaust, the presence of "textual silence" is a force that removes the experience of genocide from the reader's analysis and imaginative recourse. Lang defines silences as omissions that take many forms, including the use of italics and quotation marks, ellipses and blank pages in poetry, and the presence of unreliable narrators in fiction. While this limits the reader's ability to read in any conventional sense, these silences are not flaws. They are instead a critical presence that forces readers to acknowledge how words and meaning can diverge in the face of events as unimaginable as those of the Holocaust.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading Holocaust texts is difficult, nearly impossible in fact.¹ Such a statement seems a contradiction in terms for, once the skills behind reading are mastered, reading becomes almost instinctual or automatic. It is difficult<italic>not</italic>to read when faced with a text—an aspect of reading (and audience) that has long been recognized and assumed, as evidenced by the multitude of public texts all around us. Moreover, given the sheer number of texts that invoke the Holocaust, texts that position the Holocaust as either primary or secondary, the claim that we<italic>cannot</italic>read these works when precisely that task—reading—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>READABILITY AND UNREADABILITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Fractured Dialogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The two opening images of Primo Levi’s<italic>La Tregua—The Truce</italic>(published in the United States as<italic>The Reawakening</italic>), which describes his liberation from Auschwitz and his long journey home, shift between his own act of reading and ours.¹ I use these images here as a means to introduce the concept of readability and unreadability—in contrast to postwar and ongoing discussions around the process of reading itself, including theories that investigate how meaning and interpretation emerge from reading. After Auschwitz was liberated by the Russians, Levi is ill and weak and is hoisted into a cart along with other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>BEFORE, DURING, AND AFTER:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading and the Eyewitness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing in his unpublished diary, Polish Jew Kalman Rotgeber recorded many of his observations from his hiding place on the Aryan side of Warsaw not long after he and his wife escaped from the ghetto, where they had witnessed the deportation of their son. In the earliest pages of his diary, Rotgeber addresses his anticipated reader:</p>
                     <p>The person into whose hands this diary should happen to fall is strongly urged not to discard it, or to destroy it. … In case it is not possible to deliver it to the intended address—one is kindly asked to give it over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>READING TO BELONG:</title>
                     <subtitle>Second-Generation and the Audience of Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The presence and importance of unreadability in the sense of a direct relationship between the reader and the text becomes more intricate and convoluted in writings by second-generation Holocaust authors who often document their quest to discover or write a “readable” narrative of their parents’ wartime experiences.¹ In the absence of this text, second-generation writers bear a more complex relation to even the idea of text than do eyewitnesses or other first-generation writers. Whereas eyewitness authors record their memories or at least try to put fragmented memories together and then read them, authors who identify themselves as “second-generation” writers search</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>THE THIRD GENERATION’S HOLOCAUST:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Story of Time and Place</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Second-generation authors are also readers of inherited memory, recognizing the presence of the unreadable through aligning themselves with their audience.¹ Part of the drive behind second-generation authors wanting to document their relationship with their parents is to read and touch the material presence offered by a text that they have been largely deprived of through a range of destructive and traumatic means. By their own recounting, second-generation memoirists acknowledge the push and pull of two incongruous forces: a desire to read—to handle, to contain—the experience of their eyewitness parents and, at the same time, a desire to understand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>AMERICAN FICTION AND THE ACT OF GENOCIDE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paradoxically, the more time that separates the Holocaust from the present, and so the less available the Holocaust is in terms of eyewitness testimony, the more accessible it becomes to readers and writers of Holocaust fiction and the more it becomes historically normalized.¹ Whereas eyewitness authors overtly acknowledge the impossibility of reading their texts in the truest sense of the word—a consequence of reaching the limits of language and representation—contemporary authors, often in an effort to shorten the distance between themselves and the historical event at hand, create a version of the Holocaust that is increasingly available as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>RECEDING INTO THE DISTANCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Holocaust as Background</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Holocaust fiction written by authors who are themselves distanced from the authority of survivor testimony and its inheritance lead readers to question the very value and meaning of the term “Holocaust literature.”¹ In his defense of Holocaust fiction more generally, Lawrence Langer notes that its significance can be found in “its ability to evoke the atmosphere of monstrous fantasy that strikes any student of the Holocaust, and simultaneously to suggest the exact details of the experience in a way that forces the reader to fuse and reassess the importance of both. The result is exempted from the claims of literal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Fragments of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a value in recognizing the limits of reading, or the unreadable, in Holocaust literature.¹ My argument in support of “unreadability” depends on a conventional and presumptive view of contemporary reading: we read in order to experience, to feel, to understand, to learn from, to empathize with, to imitate, to be inspired by text. Reading at its most powerful is a deeply intuitive moment or series of moments of connection and understanding. It is precisely from this background<italic>as</italic>conventional and presumed that my notion of unreadability in connection with traumatic narratives such as those concentrating on the Holocaust</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwtdjf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
