<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Preaching Must Die!</book-title>
         <subtitle>Troubling Homiletical Theology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Myers</surname>
               <given-names>Jacob D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506411866</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506411873</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7hbc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The real question for homiletics in our increasingly postmodern, post-Christian contexts is not how are we going to prevent preaching from dying, but how are we going to help it die a good death. Preaching was not made to live. At most, preaching is a witness, a sign, a crimson X marking a demolition site. The church has developed sophisticated technologies in modernity to give preaching the semblance of life, belying the truth: preaching was born under a death sentence. It was born to die. Only when preaching embraces its own death is it able to truly live.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Preaching Must Die!</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Homiletics exists to free preaching from theology. Homiletics is neither words about God nor God’s “Word,” if there<italic>is</italic>such a<italic>thing</italic>. Homiletics, like theology, like preaching, can have no life in and of itself. I believe that homiletics’ sole purpose is to help preaching die a good death.</p>
                     <p>Unfortunately, in its quest for academic and ecclesial respectability, homiletics has made a pact with theology: contemporary homiletics presents itself to the world as “theology in the form of sermon preparation.”³ Homiletics has sold its birthright for a bowl of stew. Such is theology’s deviousness. Homiletics has failed to notice that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Before One’s Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Troubling Language</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 2016 film<italic>Arrival</italic>shows how language structures our relationships with others—and what is preaching if not a particular use of language to relate with others around the Absolute Other, God? The film features Dr. Louise Banks, a linguist recruited by the military to attempt to communicate with one of twelve alien spaceships that have recently arrived on earth.</p>
                     <p>In their first encounter, the humans and aliens attempt to communicate orally/aurally. Dr. Banks quickly determines, however, that the aliens are conveying too much information at once for the human ear to decipher. This is a limit of spoken discourse:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Crossing Over to the Other Side:</title>
                     <subtitle>Troubling the Preacher</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few shows engage the intersecting domains of identity and selfhood as poignantly—or as violently—as HBO’s<italic>Game of Thrones</italic>. Nowhere is this confluence seen more clearly than in Arya Stark, who just so happens to be my favorite character in the series. For the uninitiated, Arya is the youngest daughter of Eddard Stark, the Lord of Winterfell.</p>
                     <p>When we first meet Arya, she is doing everything in her power to denounce her social status and expectations of her gender. Arya doesn’t want to be a Lady, which she makes no attempt to conceal through her half-hearted attempts at needlepoint</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Gift of Death:</title>
                     <subtitle>Troubling Scripture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Moana</italic>follows a narrative arc on par with the best Disney films: facing impossible odds, the heroine must deliver her people (and herself) from peril. As the title suggests, this heroine is named Moana, a teenage girl next in line to rule her Pacific island village. When the villagers discover that the island is dying and the fish have left the surrounding waters, Moana ventures into the tempestuous sea in search of a mythical demigod named Maui to save her people.</p>
                     <p>The cosmogony underlying<italic>Moana</italic>is plot critical. Moana’s people believe that there was only ocean before the Mother island</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Giving Up the Ghost:</title>
                     <subtitle>Troubling God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The film<italic>Inception</italic>centers on a man named Cobb, a thief-for-hire who infiltrates the unconscious minds of corporate magnates to extract valuable information. Following a botched assignment, Cobb is forced to accept a seemingly impossible mission:<italic>inception</italic>. Inception is the implantation of an idea into a target’s unconscious, thereby altering the target’s psyche. If he is able to achieve inception, Cobb’s criminal record will be expunged, and he will regain his freedom.</p>
                     <p>Complications ensue when Cobb’s deceased wife, Mal, appears. She begins to haunt his efforts, threatening to unravel his work from within (himself). The nearly impossible task of inception</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Preaching Meets Its Maker, Perchance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even as homiletics lives not for itself, so too its death is not its own. Homiletics must die because preaching must die. That is its lot, its trouble, its troubling—its “mortal coil,” as Hamlet declares. And it is Hamlet who offered the first words of this book. It is he who set us on our course with his famous soliloquy. “To be, or not to be, that is the question.” For homiletics. For preaching.</p>
                     <p>This<italic>coil</italic>of which Hamlet speaks has done some work for us throughout this book. The word enjoys a peculiar etymology, hence its facility for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Scripture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names and Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hbc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
