<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4v0cc</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS374.N285P86 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mass media and literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Writing at the Limit</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Novel in the New Media Ecology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PUNDAY</surname>
               <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803236462</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803240810</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803240813</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d9nr4r"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While some cultural critics are pronouncing the death of the novel, a whole generation of novelists have turned to other media with curiosity rather than fear. These novelists are not simply incorporating references to other media into their work for the sake of verisimilitude, they are also engaging precisely such media as a way of talking about what it means to write and read narrative in a society filled with stories told outside the print medium.</p>
         <p>By examining how some of our best fiction writers have taken up the challenge of film, television, video games, and hypertext, Daniel Punday offers an enlightening look into the current status of such fundamental narrative concepts as character, plot, and setting. He considers well-known postmodernists like Thomas Pynchon and Robert Coover, more-accessible authors like Maxine Hong Kingston and Oscar Hijuelos, and unjustly overlooked writers like Susan Daitch and Kenneth Gangemi, and asks how their works investigate the nature and limits of print as a medium for storytelling.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Writing at the Limit</italic>explores how novelists locate print writing within the contemporary media ecology, and what it really means to be writing at print's media limit.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="376"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Rhetorical Construction of Media Ecologies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Novels written today spill over with references to other media—television, film, music, the Internet. The presence of such alternate media in the novel can be seen as simply a natural reflection of contemporary life. During an average day, most of us spend some time watching television, sending e-mail, reading the newspaper, and listening to the radio. Is it any wonder that these media make their way into the contemporary novel?</p>
                     <p>It’s hard to shake the impression, however, that contemporary writers are doing more than simply adding media to their stories as part of the narrative furniture of contemporary life.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Multimedia Moments Old and New</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Media other than writing have always had a place in the novel, whose history is full of stolen paintings, romances developed during a piano duet, and social faux pas at gala theatrical performances. In the introduction we have already considered (and dismissed) the idea that media appear in the contemporary novel simply as part of the “furniture” of everyday life. It is an inadequate explanation, but it does touch on a truth that we will explore in this chapter: the novel seems to use other media as a tool for storytelling in a pragmatic way that is independent of whatever</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Story, Discourse, and Circulation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contemporary novel uses media other than writing as a way to investigate the strengths and ambiguities that writing provides to the novel. Already we have seen some of the ways that media stories like “Duck Tape,”<italic>The Salt Eaters</italic>, and<italic>Vineland</italic>investigate some of the basic elements of narrative as they appear in writing. In the next chapter we will discuss this in a systematic way and come to some tentative conclusions about what contemporary authors find to be unique about the novel as a written medium. This investigation into the qualities of writing is fundamentally rooted in an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Defining the Vocation of the Novel through Narrative Elements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The general outline of how the contemporary U.S. novel uses media other than writing should now be clear. Once the novel had lost its traditional vocation, any choice by a writer must be evaluated against its rhetorical effectiveness. Novels can use media for a variety of storytelling purposes, and contemporary writers can appeal to other media to reveal the potential and limits of writing. We have seen how many of these novels thematize the circulation of the media object within the story world to explain the cultural meaning of the medium of writing. In the remainder of this book, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Writing Beyond the Media Limit?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contemporary novelists whose works we examined in the previous chapter have approached the limit of what the novel can do. Gangemi’s use of film, Coover’s use of television, or Daitch’s use of comics each contemplated another medium and then turned back to the novel the wiser. It should go without saying that another way to respond to these limits is to leave writing and move on to another medium. Some have done so for purely financial reasons, like William Faulkner’s writing for Hollywood in the 1930s and ’40s, while others have seen in another medium aesthetic possibilities, like William</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Negotiating Public and Private Spaces</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary media novels show us that authors are eager to understand what makes the traditional written novel distinctive among storytelling forms. Their eagerness is heightened by the lack of any consensus about what the novel<italic>should</italic>do today: what is its role within American public life? As I noted in chapter 3, writing, and thus the novel, is especially good at representing the absent, the potential, or the unrealized. By focusing on the absent, writers are able to discuss the community in which the story circulates. More broadly, contemporary media novels point to those elements of the story that are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>Connection through Limits and the Myth of Media Fullness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this book, I have offered an unlikely image of the novel within the contemporary media ecology. We would expect that media would create a sense of connection to social and cultural forms by reaching out to describe larger media systems directly. Instead, what we have seen is that the contemporary media novel emphasizes quite the opposite: the limits of writing. Instead of isolating novelists, characters, and readers, those limits are precisely what allow them to be aware of the world beyond themselves. In emphasizing media limits, these writers are able to embrace an agency that comes from being an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nr4r.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
