<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PE1404 .P574 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching (Higher)</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Academic writing</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Report writing</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Methodology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Points of Departure</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rethinking Student Source Use and Writing Studies Research Methods</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SERVISS</surname>
               <given-names>TRICIA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JAMIESON</surname>
               <given-names>SANDRA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781607326243</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781607326250</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Utah State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Boulder, Colorado</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University Press of Colorado</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xzh15w"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Points of Departure</italic>encourages a return to empirical research about writing, presenting a wealth of transparent, reproducible studies of student sources. The volume shows how to develop methods for coding and characterizing student texts, their choice of source material, and the resources used to teach information literacy. In so doing, the volume advances our understanding of how students actually write.The contributors offer methodologies, techniques, and suggestions for research that move beyond decontextualized guides to grapple with the messiness of research-in-process, as well as design, development, and expansion. Serviss and Jamieson's model of RAD writing studies research is transcontextual and based on hybridized or mixed methods. Among these methods are citation context analysis, research-aloud protocols, textual and genre analysis, surveys, interviews, and focus groups, with an emphasis on process and knowledge as contingent. Chapters report on research projects at different stages and across institution types-from pilot to multi-site, from community college to research university-focusing on the methods and artifacts employed.A rich mosaic of research about research,<italic>Points of Departure</italic>advances knowledge about student writing and serves as a guide for both new and experienced researchers in writing studies.<italic>Contributors</italic>: Crystal Benedicks, Katt Blackwell-Starnes, Lee-Ann Kastman Breuch, Kristi Murray Costello, Anne Diekema, Rebecca Moore Howard, Sandra Jamieson, Elizabeth Kleinfeld, Brian N. Larson, Karen J. Lunsford, M. Whitney Olsen, Tricia Serviss, Janice R. Walker</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Appendices</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lunsford</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Somewhat to my surprise, as I write these words, I realize it has been over a decade since Rich Haswell (2005) published his influential article, “NCTE/CCCC’s Recent War on Scholarship.” Calling on writing scholars to return to conducting empirical studies, Haswell coined a term to encompass both the qualitative and quantitative research needed—“RAD scholarship,” or “replicable, aggregable, and data-driven scholarship.” He also implied an agenda for the discipline: to define areas in which our collective research will make a difference. In the decade since then, writing scholars have responded to his call. As the contributors to this collection argue,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE RISE OF RAD RESEARCH METHODS FOR WRITING STUDIES: Transcontextual Ways Forward</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Serviss</surname>
                           <given-names>Tricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Investment in data-driven research and the writing-education reforms it might allow dominated conversations about research methods and methodology in the first decade of the twenty-first century. Chris Anson argued at the Council of Writing Program Administrators 2006 conference, and in print two years later (Anson 2008), that the field of writing studies needed to attend to data-driven research if we hoped to reach audiences beyond ourselves, referencing what Rich Haswell (2005) calls “RAD,” or “replicable, aggregable, data-driven research.” In addition to speaking to those outside the discipline, such data also challenges some of our own assumptions about student writing, expanding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interchapter 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>WHAT DO WE MEAN BY TRANSCONTEXTUAL RAD RESEARCH?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many researchers in writing studies resist quantitative research because they feel unprepared in statistical methods or lack the time required to learn and then conduct such research. This worry is hardly new, though. It has been repeatedly articulated by those struggling to develop research methods since the earliest days of our national conferences and journals (see Serviss, introduction to this collection). Members of our discipline, particularly WPAs, often employ qualitative or quantitative research, or a combination of the two, in response to local institutional need, but when those local questions are answered, they move on to the next issue. Sometimes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>THE EVOLUTION OF THE CITATION PROJECT:</title>
                     <subtitle>Developing a Pilot Study from Local to Translocal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jamieson</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter provides an antidote to the (necessarily) highly systematized accounts of research processes to which new researchers frequently turn, accounts that in users’ minds too easily become ideals to be achieved and standards by which to measure their work. Books such as Johnny Saldaña’s (2013), Stefan Titscher et al.’s (2000), and John Creswell’s (2014) are invaluable procedural guides for conducting research—and highly recommended—but while they do acknowledge the unruliness of qualitative research, they nevertheless present a linear, cleaned-up version of the process that can leave new researchers at a loss when their own work is stalled. Along</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>REPORTS FROM THE LILAC PROJECT:</title>
                     <subtitle>Designing a Translocal Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackwell-Starnes</surname>
                           <given-names>Katt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walker</surname>
                           <given-names>Janice R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the foreword to<italic>The New Digital Scholar</italic>, Alison J. Head and Michael B. Eisenberg note that “one of the paradoxes of the digital age is that while finding information and answers may be easy, making sense and using all that information is not” (Head and Eisenberg 2013, xi). In that same volume, Barry M. Maid and Barbara J. D’Angelo suggest ways instructors can “think about which pedagogical strategies all of us need to employ in order to develop an [information-literacy]-based curriculum that is relevant in the digital age” (Maid and D’Angelo 2013, 310–11). In this chapter, we discuss</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Points of Departure 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>REPLICATION AND THE NEED TO BUILD ON AND EXPAND LOCAL AND PILOT STUDIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In August 2015, the Open Science Collaboration (OSC) published the results of a project that attempted to replicate the results of one hundred experimental and correlational studies reported in three top-tier psychology journals in a single year (2008). The collaboration warns that there is no single indicator that can describe replication success, but based on the five different indicators they employed, they report that between 53 and 64 percent of the studies they replicated did not produce the same results as the original. They report that their replication studies used materials provided by the original authors and were reviewed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interchapter 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>WHAT DOES DESIGN-BASED RESEARCH OFFER AS A TOOL FOR RAD RESEARCH IN WRITING STUDIES?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the great challenges and opportunities of educational research is rectifying predictions about how learning theoretically works with how learning<italic>actually</italic>works in—and across—different contexts. Those of us who study writing and literacy are uniquely aware of these tensions. In fact, writing studies research traditionally inquires into how beautifully divergent and surprising learning can be in practice. Conversations about writing processes in 1960s writing-pedagogy research embody this tension; theoretical understandings of<italic>typical</italic>processes of developing writers became dangerously calcified into<italic>the</italic>writing process quite quickly. What began as inquiry about how writing happens (Cooper 1986; Emig 1971;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>THE THINGS THEY CARRY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Design-Based Research in Writing-Teacher Education</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Serviss</surname>
                           <given-names>Tricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For writing studies scholars like me who focus on teacher preparation, terms like<italic>teaching practicum</italic>and<italic>graduate-student orientation</italic>stir up deep and pressing disciplinary tensions. We return to the same theoretical and practical questions as we do in the work of professionalizing ourselves as teachers:<italic>How can we best prepare writing teachers, both novice and veteran? When and how should programming support their professionalization? How do we simultaneously prepare them both as emerging writers and writing teachers?</italic>As we embrace digital writing, reading, and research tools even more fully, the cracks in our knowledge and strategies for preparing new writing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>STORIED RESEARCH:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Focus Groups as a Responsive Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benedicks</surname>
                           <given-names>Crystal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The research project I describe in this chapter had two goals: capturing the ways students at a small liberal arts college (SLAC) think about source use and academic honesty, and prompting institutional change in response to these findings. My methodologies therefore had to be flexible enough to be responsive to things we heard from students along the way. Further, those methodologies also combined qualitative and quantitative data to provide a fuller understanding of student source use; I therefore used both qualitative and quantitative data-analysis strategies to prepare the results for faculty and administrators across the disciplines. This chapter is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>TERMS AND PERCEPTIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Surveys to Discover Student Beliefs about Research</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Costello</surname>
                           <given-names>Kristi Murray</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Numerous articles and studies about research papers in first-year writing (FYW) courses appeared in English journals beginning in the 1930s, many calling for abolition of the extended research paper in FYW (Larson 1982; Strickland 2004). These recurrent calls, combined with recent Citation Project findings (Howard, Serviss, and Rodrigue 2010; Jamieson and Howard 2011; The Citation Project 2012) and other works (Nelson 2011) have led some programs to eliminate the “research paper” from their curriculum altogether. Though discussions among FYW faculty at a public university in the State University of New York (SUNY) system echoed the same questions about the validity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Points of Departure 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>DEVELOPING DESIGN-BASED LOCAL AND TRANSLOCAL STUDIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the main assertions embodied in this collection is that we can make real progress toward establishing ethical, productive RAD writing studies research by orienting ourselves in two explicit directions: (1) making renewed commitments to the idea that research projects are<italic>processes</italic>as well as<italic>products</italic>that convey findings and theories and (2) pursuing the idea that research ought to be designed and presented in anticipation of eventual transcontextual—as well as local—utility. Such possibilities for departure are illuminated by Tricia Serviss, Kristi Murry Costello, and Crystal Benedicks in chapters 3, 4, and 5 in part 2. These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interchapter 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>WHAT DOES THRESHOLD-CONCEPT RESEARCH OFFER WRITING STUDIES RAD RESEARCH?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seeking to understand why some students succeed in specific disciplines while others do not, Erik Meyer and Ray Land posited that there are key—or threshold—concepts in every field that must be understood and incorporated into one’s thinking before one can move forward in that field (Meyer and Land 2003). Once these conceptual “thresholds” have been crossed, learners can build on the knowledge made accessible by them and progress to the next threshold, gaining ever-deeper understanding and mastery as they go. Every teacher has experienced the frustration of explaining information or instructions to students who seem to understand in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>RESEARCH AND RHETORICAL PURPOSE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Genre Analysis to Understand Source Use in Technical and Professional Writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Breuch</surname>
                           <given-names>Lee-Ann Kastman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Larson</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we address student research writing in the context of a technical and professional writing course at a large public university. Specifically, we examine how students situate references to previous research in analytical reports. Our study addresses the question,<italic>for what rhetorical purposes do students integrate sources into research reports?</italic>This inquiry was inspired in part by recent work in the Citation Project regarding the ways students integrate sources into research writing. When Howard, Serviss, and Rodrigue (2010) examined eighteen student texts for instances of paraphrases, patchwriting, summary, and direct quotes, their analysis supported the hypothesis that students</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>ASKING THE RIGHT QUESTIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Interviews to Explore Information-Seeking Behavior</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Olsen</surname>
                           <given-names>M. Whitney</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Diekema</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1993, Charles Schroeder wrote, “I am suggesting that an overall understanding of how students learn and where they are in the process can help us meet the needs of the new students who sit in our classrooms” (Schroeder 1993, 26). His suggestion is as true now as it was more than twenty years ago: as teachers, we must understand our ever-changing groups of students in order to help them. Today’s writing students are mired in a conflicting world of computers and pens, smart phones and paper, and digital and physical information. Before writing instructors can ask students to research,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>JUST READ THE ASSIGNMENT:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Course Documents to Analyze Research Pedagogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kleinfeld</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2009, the Metropolitan State University of Denver’s (MSU Denver) English department volunteered to become one of sixteen institutions that contributed first-year composition (FYC) students’ research papers to the Citation Project’s data pool. The preliminary findings of the Citation Project resonated with the composition program’s leadership, and as an emerging Hispanic-serving institution (HSI) with modified open enrollment that attracts many first-generation college students and nontraditional students, we were eager to learn how our students’ writing compared with the writing of students at other institutions.</p>
                     <p>One of the benefits of being a participating institution in the Citation Project study was receiving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Points of Departure 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>USING EXISTING RESEARCH TO THINK BEYOND THE LOCAL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the other research described in this collection, we present the chapters in this section along with their various appendices as part of the evolving research process that informs writing studies, with each serving as a potential point of departure for adaptation or development. As they plan a study or take existing research beyond preliminary, pilot, or local study, researchers can use what these chapters reveal to help them shape and refine questions, generate hypotheses to test, and replicate or revise methods and interpretations. We also hope these adaptations will be developed in ways that allow the studies to become</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>TEACHING HYBRIDITY IN GRADUATE RESEARCH COURSES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Howard</surname>
                           <given-names>Rebecca Moore</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Tanya Rodrigue, Tricia Serviss, Sandra Jamieson, and I began work on the Citation Project, we faced a steep learning curve. None of us had much (if any) specific training in research methods for writing studies, and all of us knew the hermeneutics with which we were familiar were of little use for persuading audiences outside our field. None of our training prepared us for conducting research that would be replicable, aggregable, or data based. All of us thought, though, that such research was valuable for understanding how college students work with source material. Too much had been written about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE AUTHORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh15w.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
