<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1551n5f</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Time and world politics</book-title>
         <subtitle>Thinking the present</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hutchings</surname>
               <given-names>Kimberly</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780719073021</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781847792181</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Kimberly Hutchings</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155jdgf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book offers the first authoritative guide to assumptions about time in theories of contemporary world politics. It demonstrates how predominant theories of the international or global ‘present’ are affected by temporal assumptions, grounded in western political thought, that fundamentally shape what we can and cannot know about world politics today. The first part of the book traces the philosophical roots of assumptions about time in contemporary political theory. The second part examines contemporary theories of world politics, including liberal and realist International Relations theories and the work of Habermas, Hardt and Negri, Virilio and Agamben. In each case, it is argued, assumptions about political time ensure the identification of the particular temporality of western experience with the political temporality of the world as such and put the theorist in the unsustainable position of holding the key to the direction of world history. In the final chapter, the book draws on postcolonial and feminist thinking, and the philosophical accounts of political time in the work of Derrida and Deleuze, to develop a new ‘untimely’ way of thinking about time in world politics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction to the question of world-political time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN<italic>The Critique of Pure Reason</italic>, Kant argued that our grasp of the world is inescapably structured through space and time. In other words, whether we like it or not, our experience of any object is always located in a spatial field and temporal duration, conceived in Newtonian terms. The novelty of Kant’s argument was that he effectively bracketed the question of the ontological status of space and time, thus evading long-standing philosophical problems, such as those inherent in Zeno’s paradox of the arrow.¹ Instead Kant focused on demonstrating that they (space and time) are transcendental conditions of sensible experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>From fortune to history</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CHAPTER 1 pointed to the ways in which accounts of world politics embody temporal narratives of repetition, progress and decline. The aim of this chapter is to deepen our understanding of the conditions of possibility of these temporal framings and the role that they play as resources for thought in the western social scientific imagination. In order to do this, I will highlight some of the contrasts and connections between neo-classical, Christian and secular historicist configurations of world, politics and time in European thought between the sixteenth and the nineteenth centuries. What follows is not an attempt to account for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Against historicism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS chapter examines accounts of political time that are premised on the critique of philosophy of history and historicism. We will begin by looking briefly at two thinkers at the end of the nineteenth century who offered alternatives to the conflation of<italic>kairos</italic>and<italic>chronos</italic>in historicist and scientific accounts of time, Nietzsche and Bergson. This then sets the scene for exploring ways in which the assumptions and implications of historicism, in particular Marxist versions of historicism, have been challenged by the following thinkers: Arendt, Benjamin, Derrida and Deleuze. The arguments of these thinkers differ, but they all involve rejecting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Prophecies and predictions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN the previous two chapters we have been exploring philosophical accounts of political time. In this and subsequent chapters we examine readings of contemporary world politics and the different ways in which they rely on and reproduce configurations of the relation between<italic>chronos</italic>and<italic>kairos</italic>in their accounts of the world-political present. In this chapter our focus is on interpretations of the nature and direction of world politics after the Cold War, including the popular ‘end of history’ and ‘clash of civilisations’ narratives offered by Fukuyama and Huntington, and responses from the social science of International Relations during the 1990s.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Time for democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN the previous chapter I argued that ‘scientific’ attempts to diagnose the post-1989 times of world politics, in spite of their explicit rejection of historicism, nevertheless depended on<italic>kairotic</italic>meta-narratives of political temporality. The familiar ghost of philosophical history, in which the scholar’s task is both to identify the ‘real’ mechanisms underlying historical development and to intervene, or enable intervention, positively in relation to time – to work<italic>with</italic>or<italic>against</italic>time – continued to be present. One of the reasons why post-Popperian social science ostensibly rejected historicism was because it was argued that historicism was normatively driven and incapable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Apocalyptic times</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CHAPTERS 4 and 5 explored assumptions about the temporality of world politics at work in different bodies of literature, seeking to explain, understand and prescribe for the<italic>present</italic>times of world politics in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries. In all cases, it was clear that predominant voices in the social science of international politics, in post-Kantian theories of cosmopolitan democracy and in post-Marxist accounts of ‘empire’ and ‘multitude’ relied upon accounts of the relation between<italic>chronos</italic>and<italic>kairos</italic>that echoed arguments previously encountered in Chapter 2. Rejecting Fukuyama and Huntington, and following Popper, International Relations scholars, both liberal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Thinking the present</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE previous three chapters have explored different approaches to thinking the ‘present’ of world politics. In every case, the diagnoses of, and prescriptions for, the current ‘times’ of world politics depended on assumptions about world-political temporality in which different conceptions of<italic>chronos</italic>and<italic>kairos</italic>, and the relation between them, were embedded. All of the theories of contemporary world politics with which we have been concerned developed from two sets of assumptions: one about time as the ground for knowledge claims about world politics, and another concerning claims about the sources of agency and change within the world-political present. The aims</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jdgf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
