<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8101.T54H83 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian literature (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Time in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Time</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Time</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">National characteristics, Canadian, in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Timing Canada</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Shifting Politics of Time in Canadian Literary Culture</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Huebener</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773545984</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773597723</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773597727</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Chicago</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1970584"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>From punch clocks to prison sentences, from immigration waiting periods to controversial time-zone boundaries, from Indigenous grave markers that count time in centuries rather than years, to the fact that free time is shrinking faster for women than for men - time shapes the fabric of Canadian society every day, but in ways that are not always visible or logical. In Timing Canada, Paul Huebener draws from cultural history, time-use surveys, political statements, literature, and visual art to craft a detailed understanding of how time operates as a form of power in Canada. Time enables everything we do - as Margaret Atwood writes, "without it we can't live." However, time also disempowers us, divides us, and escapes our control. Huebener transforms our understanding of temporal power and possibility by using examples from Canadian and Indigenous authors - including Jeannette Armstrong, Joseph Boyden, Dionne Brand, Timothy Findley, Lucy Maud Montgomery, Gabrielle Roy, and many others - who witness, question, dismantle, and reconstruct the functioning of time in their works. As the first comprehensive study of the cultural politics of time in Canada, Timing Canada develops foundational principles of critical time studies and everyday temporal literacy, and demonstrates how time functions broadly as a tool of power, privilege, and imagination within a multicultural and multi-temporal nation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>When Is Now?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Morris Panych’s play<italic>7 Stories</italic>, an unnamed man climbs to the seventh story of an apartment building and contemplates jumping. From his ledge he speaks with several of the building’s tenants, though most of them are too preoccupied with their own lives to ask about his dilemma. Only near the end of the play does an elderly woman, Lillian, lean out of a window to ask what is on his mind. He explains:</p>
                     <p>You see – my faith in the days of the week has been seriously undermined. When I woke up this morning, I wasn’t exactly sure what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Canadian Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Politics of Time in Canadian Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines a range of significant developments and representative events in Canadian culture and history in order to develop an understanding of how time has been constructed socially as a form of power within the nation. In the course of building such an understanding, several conclusions come to light. Normative structures of time such as clock time, the Gregorian calendar system, and the linear notion of progress intertwine with powerful social emphases on punctuality, productivity, acceleration, temporal universality, and particular forms of temporal framing through which shorter durations are often seen as more real than longer durations, and through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Negotiating Subjective Time in a Social World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Margaret Atwood’s short story “Hack Wednesday” begins by juxtaposing personal and social concerns. The first paragraph introduces Marcia, who is dreaming about her conflicted desire to have another child, while the second paragraph begins, “Downstairs the news is on. Something extra has happened, she can tell by the announcer’s tone of voice, by the heightened energy. A disaster of some kind; that always peps them up. She isn’t sure she’s ready for it.”³ Marcia’s uneasy task of deciding which concerns, the personal or the social, deserve the more prominent place in her mind goes on to form the crux of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Reading Time and Social Relations Critically</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Over the millennia,” writes Christopher Dewdney, “our penchant for technology and abstract thought has helped us to construct an empire of time, a chronological culture within which our lives are scheduled and measured out.”³ While Dewdney’s reference to “our” chronological culture appears to reflect a singular social entity, his use of the phrase “empire of time” also hints at the unequal and divisive nature of normative temporality; like all empires, an empire of time inevitably contains deeply entrenched biases and power divisions. I have discussed some of the ways in which human culture colonizes time, and in particular the ways</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Imagining Indigenous Temporalities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 1 I briefly traced the idea that Indigenous representations of time tend to emphasize the circular or concentric shape of temporal existence. In the words of Wendat scholar Georges Sioui,</p>
                     <p>The Circle is at the centre of our Aboriginal thinking … We believe that the day, the lunar month, the year, even human life itself, are circular phenomena, and that there are cycles of many years, representing the circular reality. We also believe that all circular phenomena have four parts, or movements: spring, summer, fall and winter; morning, noon hour, evening and nighttime; infancy, youth, maturity and old</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Disrupting and Remaking Constructions of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By now it has become apparent that literary texts have often sought not only to witness and represent temporal power relations, but also to question, test, and reshape the relationships between time, power, and everyday life. From the leap of faith that Panych’s unnamed man takes in order to escape his confinement in the days of the week, to Margaret Sweatman’s critique of the concentration of temporal power in the hands of the elite, to Jeannette Armstrong’s and Thomas King’s reshaping of Western narrative temporal sequence – literature and art have demonstrated a profound ability to articulate the often invisible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Provisional Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like so many articulations of temporality, this book remains inevitably provisional. There will always be more to learn from the particular ways in which experiences of time are tied, for instance, to spatial regions of human activity or to the ecological and geological matrices of the natural world. Rather than accounting for every possible model of time within Canada, though, my goals here have been to offer a framework for understanding the major cultural structures of time that have taken hold in the nation; to articulate the ways in which social patterns that may appear unconnected to temporality can in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1970584.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
