<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">FC330.B578 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1663 (New France)</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Acculturation</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conditions</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1763</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritualism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Whites</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Relations with Indians</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ghost Brothers</book-title>
         <subtitle>Adoption of a French Tribe by Bereaved Native America: A Transdisciplinary Longitudinal Multilevel Integrated Analysis</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BLUM</surname>
               <given-names>RONY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773528284</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773572461</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt8197x"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Devastating losses caused by diseases such as smallpox led to an epidemic of bereavement among the Natives. This loss resonated with the French, who had dealt with smaller epidemics in France and were also mourning their absent communities through a nostalgia for home. Blum traces how ghosts provided transgenerational and transcultural links that guided understanding rather than encouraging violence. Ghost Brothers insightfully examines the process of this colonial interdependent alliance between Native and European worlds.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="464"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Europeans discovered that an entire universe existed beyond that familiar to them, terror and curiosity of the unknown gave birth to both extreme intolerance and a wondrous reaching out. We have often heard of the seventeenth-century Little Ice Age, when Catholic and Protestant crossed swords, witch pyres were ablaze across the countryside, boats from Africa groaned with families in chains, and the Americas were deeply afflicted with smallpox fever. Not surprisingly, it was one of the most fanatic eras that Europe ever witnessed, excluding, of course, our own century.¹ Yet we have not often imagined that, under these circumstances,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Intertwined Twintalk</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Symbolic brotherhood and sisterhood was instituted through commercial, military, social, and familial Native alliances and was cemented by intercommunal bonding rituals. Fraternal twinships provided the basis for these alliances in both French and Native communities. "Twinning" in this context refers to a profoundly intertwined dialogue between two allies whose functions corresponded to each other yet whose comraderie or enmity goes beyond the purely utilitarian "I-it" exchanges into the<italic>Zwischenmenschliche</italic>(interhuman) dialogue defined by Martin Buber, which Emmanuel Levinas has sometimes adjusted in his own "face a face," to place the Other before himself. The "I-Thou" relationship, as Buber sees it,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Smoke Signals</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Infinitely layered echoes of past, present, and future phantoms, which reflect the interaction and transformations of internalized life and communal events within the self and society, take place within the crux of a multilevel framework that extends through time and space. Twins held the keys to one another’s lives, but their relationship also symbolically represents the communal reality. I look at communal twinship on a macro level, examining it via time and space. First, I look at political and socio-economic twinships and their demographic character. Then I map out the geographical context and spatial negotiations within which the interethnic dialogue</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Revenge of the Cradles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most salient key to why an intercommunal dialogue took place between French and Native was the necessary interdependence of French and Native communities for survival.¹ Life together brought forth common partying, commercial negotiation, inveterate friendships, canoeing, diplomatic power tactics, romantic ties, common enemies, and competing educational systems. French members were referred to as uncle, aunt, and brother. This unusually intimate French-Native intercommunal interdependence owed its urgency to extremely sparse French immigration. Due to this anemic immigration, an incomplete society full of surplus young males matched nicely with Native societies suffering from a lack of males. The men suffered especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Born Free</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>French settlement society on the St Lawrence underwent a "metamorphosis." Nativization eased and legitimated the levelling among men. The hierarchically vertical ordering of society in a tightly knit, geographically restricted area of France gave way to a transversal political and socioeconomic organization spread out geographically. Social utility and wealth, rather than Old World pedigree, became powerful. Aboriginal life on Turtle Island enabled the eco-conservation of untouched resources stretched out as far as the eye could see, while coercive measures were introduced very slowly and were hard to enforce. Transversalization increased the gap between Quebec society and those further afield at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Our Founding Clanmothers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contrast between the standing of Frenchwomen and Native women before their respective communities were joined was striking. Frenchwomen were one of the prime banes of the early modern era in France, with endless debates and treatises slighting their capacities<italic>(la Querelle des femmes,</italic>debate over the Salic Law;<italic>Le Caquet des Accouchées, Les Evangiles des Quenouilles)</italic>to their being chased and burned as witches.¹ Native women, by contrast, were in charge of the majority of family and baseline economic functions. In New France, Native women’s salutary influence upon the French settlement included providing a reverse model in which women</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Je me souviens</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Models, symbols, and myths that developed in settler society were the fruit Native influence and dialogue. The Native sharing ethic and "dread of losing face" shaped early French North American cultural ideals through their convergence with provincial French aristocratic ideals of libéralité (generosity) and honneur (bravery), both of which evinced settler reverence. Intertwined, these combined qualities comprised the older French of an "homme de coeur" - a generous man willing to risk himself to the defenceless.¹ This ideal reflects the lengthy vulnerability of small European tribes to invasions from the East and later (after the decline of the Empire) to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Hunting Otherworlds</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Belief and rituals stress an aspect of a communal shared past (Urzeit), which embodies its view of the end of time (Endzeit), in order to orient the community in the present and to enable it to make sense of how to face the future. The relinking of common meanings reinforces the boundaries of communal trust. In a multiethnic "frontierless" Fourth World society, who is inside and who is outside the community? Where does communal begin trust and end? And what does this all mean after life ends? Christian belief emphasized inherent good and evil, while most Aboriginal beliefs demonstrated the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Outside in, inside out</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Immigration strains the capacities of those who undergo it. Few immigrate without some strong necessity or ideal urging them to disrupt their at least nominally supportive home life. Immigrants become stuck in the liminal, but isolated, passageway between two worlds until they can reorient themselves, reach out to an additional social network, and re-establish themselves. The patchy and ambiguous nature of French settlement in Native North America catalyzed the anomie reverberating within the individual, who mourned the absence of his/her lost world and was surrounded by surprises in the new. The multilayered dialogue set up through twinning with Native nations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>Beating Swords into Canoe Paddles</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the seventeenth century, blood brotherhood established an intercontinental interdependence through the welcoming adoption of the tiny French band within Native North America. In a land whose resilient bounty promised that no wound need fester, an integrated, more comprehensive analysis of the past can yield some insights into dealing with the future. French Nativization was the fruit of the dialogue of a budding seventeenth-century global dialogue and interdependence, which entailed many layers of belonging. These ranged from that of the broadest scope, through intimate couplehood and twinship, down into the depths of the soul. Habermasian “webs of understanding” can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8197x.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>443</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
