<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Radical Embodiment</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Nikkel</surname>
               <given-names>David H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173534</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903407</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>David H. Nikkel</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0ht"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"Radical embodiment" refers to an anthropology and an epistemology fundamentally rooted in our bodies as always in correlation with our natural and social worlds. All human rationality, meaning, and value arise not only instrumentally but also substantively from this embodiment in the world. Radical embodiment reacts against Enlightenment mind-body dualism, as well as its monistic offshoots, including the physicalism that reduces everything to component matter-energy at the expense of subjectivity and meaning. It also rejects certain forms of postmodernism that reinscribe modern dualisms. David H. Nikkel develops the perspective of "radical embodiment" by examining varieties of modern and postmodern theology, and the nature and role of tradition-in terms of linguistic and non-linguistic experience, the religion and science dialogue on the nature of consciousness, and the immanent and transcendent aspects of God.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nikkel</surname>
                           <given-names>David H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Discerning the Spirits of Modernity and Postmodernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I count myself among those scholars of religion (and other disciplines) who believe that we live in the midst of a major shift in Western culture—that we are moving from the modern age into a postmodern age. “Postmodern” has gained supremacy over the alternative terms “postcritical” and “postliberal.” Michael Polanyi’s “postcritical” stands as probably the best single word for conveying the substance of the shift from modernity as I construe it in this chapter. The term, as I understand it, does not suggest the impossibility or undesirability of appropriate critical reflection, but rather modernity’s failure to recognize the limits</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Postmodernism(s) and Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Without tradition our lives would be as shaky as . . . as a fiddler on the roof.” So intones Tevye in a (bodily) metaphor from<italic>Fiddler on the Roof</italic>.¹ As the play suggests, the role of tradition came under increasing threat in the modern period. Indeed, the dominant modern picture of human rationality, and by extension of human life, has been deracinate and discarnate—without roots in tradition or in the human body. I will argue that tradition and the body are—and should be acknowledged as—thoroughly interconnected. And I will attempt to reclaim the cruciality of tradition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Body in Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before directly expounding the substance of the body in tradition, I will begin with a more formal consideration of the “radicalness” of radical embodiment. Etymologically,<italic>radical</italic>literally means getting to the roots of something. Our bodies as they orient us in an environment, a world, are the very roots which make possible all our living, knowing, and valuing. As such they limit and define us at the same time they grant us all our potentialities. Constructivist-essentialist debates are parasitic upon (and typically tacitly assume) the range of possibilities our bodies provide. We are normally aware of our ubiquitous rootage in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Tradition as Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tradition Having argued for the body within tradition, I now argue for tradition as body. The metaphorical phrase, “the body of a tradition,” is well-known. Indeed, as such a conventional and familiar a metaphor, its metaphorical power has long been lost in ordinary usage. I suspect though that the original inventor(s) of the phrase intuited some vital truth about the nature of tradition. In any case, I desire to make this metaphor fresh again by arguing that the prereflective givenness of tradition strongly parallels the prereflective givenness of the human body. Our traditions, like our bodies, constitute our life and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Radical Embodiment in Light of the Science and Religion Dialogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In creating humankind God sculpted “the earth being,” according to the etymology of “Adam,” the Hebrew word for “humanity” used in Genesis 2. The portrait of humankind painted by the scriptures of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam regards the human person as a psycho-somatic unity. Scientific evidence increasingly points to the truth that human beings are fundamentally embodied in nature, contrary to the Greek-influenced mind-body dualism that has reigned for most of Western theological and philosophical history. In this chapter I will highlight the significance of our embodiment relative to evolutionary biology and to the nature of consciousness in light of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Postmodern Spirit and the Status of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Preceding chapters have touched on the nature of divinity. In this chapter I propose to focus on the status of the concept of God, particularly in Western theology, in light of the postmodern spirit. I will identify three pertinent options, arguing for the superiority of one of these. Before proceeding with that identification, I will rehearse three entailments of the postmodern spirit especially important for the purposes of this chapter:</p>
                     <p>1) Human knowledge is always mediated, contextual, and constructed (at least in part).</p>
                     <p>2) Humans and animals live in interconnection with one another and with the world. Persons never exist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Radical Embodiment and Transcendence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A corollary of God’s radical embodiment is that the trope of “the absence of God” in radical postmodernism and in post-Holocaust theology (not to mention the Christian mystical tradition) can and must be taken seriously. No, God does not disappear into the universe a la 1960’ s “death of God” theology or some versions of radical postmodernism. I believe that the embodied panentheistic formulation I have advanced can account for a certain experiential sense of divine absence, while at the same time allowing for the reality and presence of the divine.</p>
                     <p>Clearly my model—and various other models as well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0ht.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
