<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccg6</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Bible through the Lens of Trauma</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boase</surname>
               <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Frechette</surname>
               <given-names>Christopher G.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884141730</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884141723</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1h1htfd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Explore emerging trends in trauma studies and biblical interpretation</p>
         <p>In recent years there has been a surge of interest in trauma, trauma theory, and its application to the biblical text. This collection of essays explores the usefulness of using trauma theory as a lens through which to read the biblical texts. Each of the essays explores the concept of how trauma might be defined and applied in biblical studies. Using a range of different but intersection theories of trauma, the essays reflect on the value of trauma studies for offering new insights into the biblical text. Including contributions from biblical scholars, as well as systematic and pastoral theologians, this book provides a timely critical reflection on this emerging discussion.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>Implications for how reading the biblical text through the lens of trauma can be fruitful for contemporary appropriation of the biblical text in pastoral and theological pursuitsArticles that integrate hermeneutics of trauma with classical historical-critical methodsEssays that address the relationship between individual and collective trauma</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="228"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Defining “Trauma” as a Useful Lens for Biblical Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frechette</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boase</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent decades biblical scholars have increasingly come to regard the concept of trauma as a powerful interpretive lens, and that interest has begun to spark significant discussion.¹ The interdisciplinary conference “Trauma and Traumatization: Biblical Studies and Beyond,” held at Aarhus University, Denmark, in 2012, brought biblical scholars into conversation with scholars from various disciplines, including anthropology, classics, history of medicine, patristics, psychology, and sociology. Subsequently, an important volume of revised conference papers appeared in 2014.² During the Annual Meetings of the Society of Biblical Literature (SBL) from 2012 to 2015, papers presented across more than thirty program units explicitly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>No Words:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Book of Ezekiel as Trauma Literature and a Response to Exile</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Poser</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The book of Ezekiel strikes us as strange. Readers find the enormous amount of violence contained in the text disturbing or even shy away from reading it altogether. The characters in the narrative appear only as people wounded, tortured, or devastated by acts of war; the catastrophe seems to have broken them all: the prophet himself, the people of Israel, the populations of surrounding nations. Even YHWH is portrayed as affected by the violence and brutality.</p>
                     <p>Over the course of time, interpreters have repeatedly seen this as an indication that Ezekiel was mentally ill, but simultaneously many have regarded the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fragmented Voices:</title>
                     <subtitle>Collective Identity and Traumatization in Lamentations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boase</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“How lonely sits the city…”</p>
                     <p>So begins the book of Lamentations (1:1), written following the Babylonian destruction of Jerusalem (586 BCE) and arguably one of the clearest expressions of trauma literature in the Hebrew Bible. The image of the isolated and bereaved woman, violated, degraded, lacking anyone to comfort her, represents well the traumatic impact of war and devastation. Metaphorically rich, this personification of the city as woman—Daughter Zion—holds in tension both the personal, individual reality of suffering and a recognition of communal suffering.</p>
                     <p>This essay explores the interplay between the individual and communal voices in Lamentations through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Daughter Babylon Raped and Bereaved (Isaiah 47):</title>
                     <subtitle>Symbolic Violence and Meaning-Making in Recovery from Trauma</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frechette</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Isa 47 YHWH declares that violence shall befall Babylon, which is characterized as “virgin Daughter Babylon” and “daughter Chaldea”¹ and referred to in this essay simply as “Daughter Babylon.” In the Hebrew Bible, cities are in many cases anthropomorphized as female within discourse that represents interaction between the city and YHWH, and such interaction may be either favorable or unfavorable for the city.² In Isa 47:3 YHWH declares to Daughter Babylon, “Your nakedness shall be uncovered, and your shame shall be seen. I will take vengeance”; 47:9 adds, “both these things shall come upon you in a moment, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shared Pleasure to Soothe the Broken Spirit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Collective Trauma and Qoheleth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Helsel</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip Browning</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Modern sociologist Kai Erikson studied human-caused disasters as a witness for plaintiffs in disaster lawsuits. He maintained that communal responses to disaster share some common features. He noted that the symptoms of collective trauma coalesce into a form of syndrome that is more than the injury to each of the individuals combined.¹ He also indicated that there is a spiritual or existential component to such harm, what we might call a collective sense of “broken-spiritedness,” to borrow a term from the psychologist John Wilson, who works with refugees.² Broken-spiritedness refers to massive disruption that interferes with sources of meaning and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fragments of Traumatic Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ṣalmê zākārand Child Sacrifice in Ezekiel 16:15–22</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Odell</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ezekiel 16, the problematic narrative of Jerusalem as YHWH’s adopted daughter and faithless wife, has been richly illuminated for contemporary readers by way of postcolonial theory and postmodern literary approaches to metaphor and gender.¹ These interpretations have helped modern readers move from initial feelings of revulsion and shock at this tale of YHWH’s violent punishment of daughter/wife Jerusalem to a more complex assessment of its symbolic treatment of the city’s destruction. To be sure, nothing can dispel the tale’s unsettling violence; nevertheless, it has become possible to appreciate how the narrative’s use of metaphor and gender allowed its ancient readers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reflections on the Prose Sermons in the Book of Jeremiah:</title>
                     <subtitle>Duhm’s and Mowinckel’s Contributions to Contemporary Trauma Readings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stulman</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of trauma has taken center stage in fields as varied as film and orthopedics, psychotherapy and education, aesthetics and international politics. This diversity speaks to the influence of trauma studies across disciplines.¹ Notwithstanding this interdisciplinary reach, biblical studies is actually a latecomer to trauma studies. Although a number of fine works have recently appeared that explore the intersection of trauma and the Bible,² until November 2013 the Society of Biblical Literature had not devoted a program unit to the hermeneutics of trauma.</p>
                     <p>At the same time, biblical scholars have long studied literary artifacts riddled with intimate and collective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Trauma, Psalmic Disclosure, and Authentic Happiness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strawn</surname>
                           <given-names>Brent A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The argument of the present essay contains four parts.¹ First, empirical studies have demonstrated that disclosure plays a key role in recovery from trauma (§1). Second, the Psalter is marked by extensive disclosure about traumatic events and the feelings of those who have been traumatized (§2). Third, insofar as the psalms are (re)read or (re)uttered texts, psalmic disclosure may function not only<italic>descriptively</italic>—as testimony to (or recovery from) past trauma—but also in a<italic>prescriptive</italic>fashion, that is,<italic>therapeutically</italic>, not just for the psalmists themselves but for all who (re)read or (re)utter these poems (§3). Fourth, the preceding points</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Legislating Divine Trauma</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Balentine</surname>
                           <given-names>Samuel E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her landmark book on trauma, psychiatrist Judith Herman records verbatim the “crisis of faith” experienced by a combat veteran of the Vietnam War:</p>
                     <p>I could not rationalize in my mind how God could let good men die. I had gone to several … priests. I was sitting there with this one priest and said, “Father, I don’t understand this: How does God allow small children to be killed? What is this thing, this war, this bullshit? I got all these friends who are dead.” That priest, he looked me in the eye and said, “I don’t know, son, I’ve</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Trauma and Recovery:</title>
                     <subtitle>A New Hermeneutical Framework for the Rape of Tamar (2 Samuel 13)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Claassens</surname>
                           <given-names>L. Juliana M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There probably are few stories that portray the reality of rape and sexual assault in the Bible as vividly as the story of Tamar and her half-brother Amnon as narrated in 2 Sam 13. Many feminist interpreters justifiably have portrayed Tamar as victim of the traumatic experience of being raped by her half-brother, silenced by the male community, and living out her days in her brother Absalom’s house a ruined woman.¹ For instance, on the aftermath of Tamar’s rape, Pamela Cooper-White writes as follows in her imaginative retelling of Tamar’s story from the perspective of Absalom’s daughter Tamar, who is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reading Biblical Texts through the Lens of Resilience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schreiter</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading scriptural texts through the lens of trauma studies is proving to be an exciting development in biblical studies and the study of other ancient Mediterranean and Near Eastern texts. The first forays into<italic>theological</italic>texts through the lens of trauma are promising as well, although this lens would seem, at least at this point, not to provide the far-reaching consequences that it may well have in biblical studies.¹ I come to this literature in biblical studies not as an expert in that field but as a systematic theologian who has become interested in trauma studies, especially as it plays</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Between Text and Trauma:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Job with People Living with HIV</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>West</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“‘Every South African has been damaged by apartheid,’ Michael Lapsley and his colleagues of the Institute for Healing of Memories used to say when they facilitated the first Healing of Memories workshops in the late 1990s.”¹ As we enter the third decade of liberation and democracy “we realise,” argues Philippe Denis, another pioneer of memory work in the South African context, “that, as part of the legacy of apartheid, a host of challenges face South African society. We are also damaged by HIV and AIDS, domestic violence, sexual abuse, violent crime, xenophobia, corruption and various forms of discrimination.” In sum,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Toward a Pastoral Reading of 2 Corinthians as a Memoir of PTSD and Healing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter Yuichi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When people endure times of crisis or trauma, they often search for meaning and hope by engaging in a bidirectional reading of texts. One direction involves hearing, reading, or witnessing the stories of others in analogous circumstances. Doing so can help people to know that they are not alone in their suffering, thus fulfilling Donne’s axiom that “no man is an island, entire of itself.”¹ The other direction points toward texts and rituals in one’s religious faith and spiritual practices, seeking a linkage between one’s own story and a larger, transcendent story: one that recounts what is sacred or ultimate.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Program Units of the Society of Biblical Literature Annual Meetings 2012–2015 for Which Session Listings Included the Keyword “Trauma”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1htfd.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
