<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">NA1.C46</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Architecture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Periodicals</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Architecture and Architectural History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Chora 7</book-title>
         <subtitle>Intervals in the Philosophy of Architecture</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pérez-Gómez</surname>
               <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Parcell</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773547018</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773598799</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773598790</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montrea; Kingston; London; Chicago</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19jch8m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For over twenty years, the Chora series has received international acclaim for its excellence in interdisciplinary research on architecture. The seven volumes of Chora have challenged readers to consider alternatives to conventional aesthetic and technological concepts. The seventy-eight authors and eighty-seven scholarly essays in the series have investigated profound cultural roots of architecture and revealed rich possibilities for architecture and its related disciplines. Chora 7, the final volume in the series, includes fifteen essays on architectural topics from around the world (France, Greece, Iran, Italy, Korea, and the United States) and from diverse cultures (antiquity, Renaissance Italy, early modern France, and the past hundred years). Thematically, they bring original approaches to human experience, theatre, architectural creation, and historical origins. Readers will also gain insights into theoretical and practical work by architects and artists such as Leon Battista Alberti, Peter Brook, Douglas Darden, Filarete, Andy Goldsworthy, Anselm Kiefer, Frederick Kiesler, Claude-Nicolas Ledoux, and Peter Zumthor. Contributors to Chora 7 include Anne Bordeleau (University of Waterloo), Diana Cheng (Montreal), Negin Djavaherian (Montreal), Paul Emmons (Washington-Alexandria Architecture Center of Virginia Tech), Paul Holmquist (McGill University), Ron Jelaco (McGill University), Yoonchun Jung (Kyoto University), Christos Kakalis (Edinburgh School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture), Lisa Landrum (University of Manitoba), Robert Nelson (Monash University), Marc J Neveu (Woodbury University), Alberto Pérez-Gómez (McGill University), Angeliki Sioli (Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education), Nikolaos-Ion Terzoglou (National Technical University of Athens), and Stephen Wischer (North Dakota State University).</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Monumentality and Contemporaneity in the Work of Tarkovsky, Goldsworthy, and Zumthor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bordeleau</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>SPEED, INNOVATION, AND CHANGE are the catchwords of our modern world, and the appeal of the ephemeral over the durable affects our conception of architecture. In projects such as<italic>Uchronia</italic>by Arne Quinze, in the celebration of the ephemeral surface, and in the growing fascination with responsive systems, architects approach the contemporary by identifying it with what resides within time’s flow. Embracing this shift from the monumental to the contemporary, architects today have a propensity to acclaim the timely over the timeless – and yet, to use the words of Paul Ricoeur, architecture always materializes as a “temporary victory over the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Public Boudoir of an Actress:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Petite Maison of Mademoiselle Dervieux</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cheng</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN JEAN-FRANÇOIS DE BASTIDE’S tale of architectural seduction from 1758, the<italic>petite maison</italic>is an exemplary site of erotic affect. In this novelette, an aristocrat wagers with a young, beautiful woman that his little house can convince her to fall in love with him.¹ Not merely fictional licence, this little house was based on contemporary petites maisons where love affairs and libertinage were conducted. Gaillard de la Boissière’s pavilion (1751), designed by Antoine-Mathieu Le Carpentier and considered by Jacques-François Blondel to be one of the best architectural examples of its kind, was the real-life inspiration for Bastide’s setting.² Although</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Peter Brook’s “Empty Space”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Orghast at Persepolis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Djavaherian</surname>
                           <given-names>Negin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN<italic>THE EMPTY SPACE</italic>, Peter Brook (1925–), one of the most influential directors in modern theatre, describes his concept of Immediate Theatre by bringing together two others: Holy Theatre, which deals with the “invisible” and its hidden impulses, and Rough Theatre, which focuses on the actions of human beings.² In Brook’s view, Immediate Theatre is able to “slide” us between our “ordinary level and the hidden level of myth.” It awakens in us a sudden insight into hidden folds of the “fabric of reality.”³ This is achieved through what he calls “empty space.” Emptiness allows our imagination to fill</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Bodies, Books, and Buildings:</title>
                     <subtitle>Encountering the Renaissance Frontispiece</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Emmons</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE FRONTISPIECE IS AN encounter between reader and book, inhabitant and building, as well as self and other. With the increasing use of personal devices and impresas in the Renaissance, close relationships were reinforced among clothing, books, and buildings.² The word<italic>frontispiece</italic>was used in Renaissance England to triply name the human forehead, the illustrated title page of a book, and the pedimented front of a building. Deriving from the Latin<italic>frontispicium,</italic>it means literally “looking at the forehead.” In Latin,<italic>frōns</italic>is the forehead and<italic>specere</italic>is “to look,” later corrupted into English as “piece.”³<italic>Frontispicium,</italic>as looking at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“More Powerful than Love”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Imagination and Language in the Oikéma of Claude-Nicolas Ledoux</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holmquist</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>OF ALL THE INSTITUTIONS proposed by Claude-Nicolas Ledoux for the ideal city of Chaux, none has resisted interpretation more than his enigmatic “workshop of corruption,” the Oikéma. In his<italic>L’architecture considérée sous le rapport de l’art, des moeurs et de la législation</italic>(1804), the Oikéma appears as a civic brothel for the city that Ledoux imagined around the Royal Saltworks (1779) he had built at Arc-et-Senans. Proclaiming that he had done what no government would dare, Ledoux presents the Oikéma as a temple in which the “boiling and unfaithful youth” of Chaux are free to indulge their sexual appetites to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Adrien Auzout and the Origins of the Paris Observatory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jelaco</surname>
                           <given-names>Ron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CLAUDE PERRAULT’S authorship of the east façade of the Louvre has been debated since its earliest years.¹ Curiously, none of that doubt has ever spread to his association with the Paris Observatory, even though the two projects shared nearly every other aspect of their milieu.² Only historian Albert Laprade has ever questioned Perrault’s role as the observatory’s architect, dismissing him by lampooning his woeful architectural skills.³ Subsequent biographers not only have disregarded Laprade and his critique but have declared that Perrault’s design role was inevitable.⁴</p>
                     <p>This confidence in Perrault’s design authorship could be undermined by the following biographical passage from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Constructing Architectural History in the Joseon Industrial Exhibition of 1915</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jung</surname>
                           <given-names>Yoonchun</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS ESSAY DISCUSSES the Joseon Industrial Exhibition in Seoul in 1915 and how modern Japan developed its “historical” intentions by incorporating Korean architectural traditions. Constructing its history was an important part of Japan’s attempt to achieve a political status on par with the West. In this sense, “Japan as a modern state cannot be found outside the West … Criticism of Japan includes that of the West.¹ In other words, modern Japan – as well as Korea and other modern Asian nations – cannot be considered without recognizing Western influence.</p>
                     <p>This relationship between Asia and the West underlies the nationalistic characteristics of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Silence and Communal Ritual in an Athonian Coenobitic Monastery</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kakalis</surname>
                           <given-names>Christos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS ESSAY STUDIES conditions of silence in the Gregoriou monastery at Mount Athos, a mountainous peninsula in northeastern Greece, a unesco World Heritage Site since 1988, and one of the most important contemporary pilgrimage sites. My fieldwork there in 2010–12, supported by secondary sources, notes how the community faces challenges to preserve the silence that is needed for its ascetic meditation.¹ The entire monastery is not silent at all times. Rituals performed by the eighty monks sometimes occur in the open spaces, temporarily breaking the silence with planned religious messages. Meanwhile, visitors often intrude on the monastery’s religious atmosphere.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Language of the Street:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Vocabulary of Communal Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nelson</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THERE IS MUCH CONTENTION over the design and regulation of streets: what kind of buildings and businesses are allowed along them, how many vehicles and what type, how much their spaces afford cultural capital and create friendly pedestrian precincts, and what rights a citizen has to the space and even the sunlight.¹ There are also fervent environmental debates about the regulation of urban density, as sprawling automotive cities consume great amounts of fossil fuel. These debates consider what kinds of amenity or conservation should rise to priority, and therefore what kinds of streets a community will accept.²</p>
                     <p>Whereas a building</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Laughing Girls</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Neveu</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THOUGH VERY LITTLE has been written about Douglas Darden, he is well known for his exquisite pencil drawings, displayed in various exhibitions, and for his book<italic>Condemned Building</italic>, published in 1993.¹<italic>Condemned Building</italic>describes ten acts of building. Each begins with a canonical statement and the overturning of that canon. The act of turning over is a tactic often used and represented by Darden. Two details on the left side of the frontispiece of<italic>Condemned Building</italic>, for example, show the turning over of a turtle to reveal its underbelly.² Turning over was considered by Darden to be an architectural trope;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Filarete’s Sforzinda:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ideal City as a Poetic and Rhetorical Construction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pérez-Gómez</surname>
                           <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE ARCHITECT ANTONIO DI PIERO AVERLINO (ca 1400–1469 ) characterized his life’s work rhetorically by adopting the pseudonym Il Filarete, coupling the Greek words<italic>philia</italic>and<italic>areté</italic>to refer to himself as a lover of virtue. In the mid-fifteenth century he became the first “modern” to design an ideal city in its totality, founded from scratch in a natural site without history. This ideal city, named Sforzinda after his patron Francesco Sforza, is the central topic of his<italic>Trattato di architettura</italic>.¹ Although the operation that Filarete describes has been interpreted generally as a precursor of rational planning, it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Is the Endless a House?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sioli</surname>
                           <given-names>Angeliki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ON THE NIGHT OF 16 June 1904, after spending a whole day in James Joyce’s literary Dublin, Leopold Bloom returns home, bringing with him the drunken Stephen Dedalus. In the kitchen, Bloom begins to prepare coffee by turning the faucet and letting the water flow.</p>
                     <p>What in water did Bloom, waterlover, drawer of water, watercarrier returning to the range, admire?</p>
                     <p>Its universality: its democratic equality and constancy to its nature in seeking its own level: … the restlessness of its waves … its hydrostatic quiescence in calm: its hydrokinetic turgidity in neap and spring tides: … its capacity to dissolve</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Juridical Character of Alberti’s Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Terzoglou</surname>
                           <given-names>Nikolaos-Ion</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PICO DELLA MIRANDOLA, in<italic>Oration on the Dignity of Man</italic>, codified a new idea of the humanist subject in the early Renaissance, writing, “Who would not admire this our chameleon?”¹ Leon Battista Alberti seems to incarnate the ideal human type that Pico della Mirandola envisaged. This had been recognized already by Alberti’s contemporaries; the striking versatility of his writings led Cristoforo Landino to characterize him as a “new chameleon” (<italic>nuovo cameleonta</italic>) in 1481.² A few years later, in 1486 , Angelo Poliziano’s preface to the first edition of<italic>De re aedificatoria</italic>for Lorenzo de’ Medici noted the many-sidedness of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Architecture of Anselm Kiefer:</title>
                     <subtitle>La Ribaute and the Space of Dramatic Representation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wischer</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>BECAUSE ART AND ARCHITECTURE SINCE the eighteenth century typically have been understood as specialized and separate, elucidating relationships between the German artist Anselm Kiefer’s creation at La Ribaute and modern architectural practice may seem precarious. Yet, having recently visited Kiefer’s former home and studio, I will argue that his integration of painting, sculpture, photography, bookmaking, and construction at La Ribaute pursues the fundamental task of architecture. Kiefer’s creations rely on a poetic form of making that disregards conventional art historical categories and reveals significant connections with architectural origins. It should not be surprising that an artist who is so concerned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Chōra before Plato:</title>
                     <subtitle>Architecture, Drama, and Receptivity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Landrum</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS ESSAY INITIATES a new approach to the architectural interpretation of<italic>chōra</italic>by considering the pre-philosophical meanings of<italic>chōra</italic>as an inhabited “region” or “land,” and by drawing attention to certain situationally transformative scenes from Athenian drama in which<italic>chōra</italic>appears in the script. Through this approach, I intend to reveal the relatively ordinary meanings of<italic>chōra</italic>from the time just before Plato recast it, in<italic>Timaeus</italic>, as a highly enigmatic entity fundamental to cosmological formation and human making. Unfortunately, Jacques Derrida, whose philosophy of deconstruction influenced architectural theory in the 1980s and 1990s, generally ignored and even dismissed the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jch8m.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
