<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9m0s24</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Gift of Love</book-title>
         <subtitle>Augustine, Jean-Luc Marion, and the Trinity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Staron</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506423401</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">150642340X</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506416717</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506416713</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ggjhcg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Gift of Love builds upon recent scholarship and reads Augustine’s De Trinitate as a rational study of the limits of theological language and the possibility of knowing the Trinity because of those limits. Marion’s description of the gift of love offers to Augustine’s theology a phenomenological texture by which the trinitarian love given might be made incarnate in one’s life. The Gift of Love presents a reason for hope that the signification of “the Trinity that God is," while impossible for human beings is not impossible for God.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="480"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“To say and mean ‘God,’” writes David Tracy, “is what must drive all theology, whenever, wherever and whoever speaks.”¹ But as driving theology, to so<italic>say</italic>and<italic>mean</italic>rouses and draws not a disciplined, abstract, faith-seeking understanding but theologians. God is neither said nor meant by “theology,” as such, but by particular women and men who find themselves in the middle of life’s way, responding to this restless drive that is itself a response to an always already given gift. Whenever and wherever we say “God,” we hope to mean not the idea, image, or model of God, but<italic>God</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Language and Conversion Within the Limits of De Trinitate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As he begins the work, Augustine presents his<italic>De Trinitate</italic>as a response to the cry of the Psalmist, “Seek his face always,”¹ through a pursuit of “the unity of the three, of Father and Son and Holy Spirit”²—an endeavor, he warns, in which no “mistake is more dangerous, or the search more laborious, or the discovery more advantageous.”³ Having struggled with his own conception of God for years⁴ and all too aware of the difficulty of the text to come, the Bishop of Hippo invites his reader along the path of charity, in hope that this “gentle authority”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Books 1–4:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Revelation of God in Salvation History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Arising from christological roots and “designed to preserve faith in Christ, the Son of God, and to direct the Christian hope toward full salvation in the divine fellowship,”¹ the doctrine of the Trinity was forged by the blows struck in the heat of contentious intellectual and ecclesiastical negotiations about the language with which we might talk about, and more importantly address, God. Speculation about the nature of the God and the Nicene priority placed on the same substance of the Father, Son, and Spirit has its historical roots in practical and polemical formulations intended to respond to threats against both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Books 5–7:</title>
                     <subtitle>Naming God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Concluding book 4, the bishop writes of the books to follow, “we shall see with the Lord’s help what sort of subtle crafty arguments the heretics bring forward and how they can be demolished.”² With a focus and methodology significantly influenced by the theological controversies with the Homoeans (Arians), these next three books, which according to Hill form “a distinct unit,”³ engage the question of speaking about God as Trinity, of how we might name the one God of Jesus Christ as “Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.” But although we would do well to read these books within their polemical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Books 8–15:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Gift of Love to the Image of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Words have force only to the extent that they remind us to look for things,” Augustine instructs his son, “they don’t display them for us to know.”¹ How then can theological language remind us to look for the Trinity—and not simply any trinity but “the Trinity that God is”?² Book 8 marks a transition from the historical accounts of the divine missions and the rules of theological language by which we might speak of God to a more inward path,³ which is, for the Doctor of Grace, also the possibility of a path upward to God. Precisely how we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion to Part One</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is my intention that part 1 presents<italic>De Trinitate</italic>in light of two primarily complementary contexts. First, contemporary scholarship on<italic>De Trinitate</italic>(and that on Augustine in general) has shed the cumbersome weight of the long-standing dominant interpretation of the text as one burdened by the presentation of the Trinity made in the image of the three faculties of the one human mind. Instead, the text can be read as an illuminating study of “how we come to knowledge of God, how we become wise.”¹ In this way,<italic>De Trinitate</italic>offers rational inquiry into the God’s healing and saving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>[For]giving Theology its Groundlessness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“One must obtain forgiveness for every essay in theology. In all senses.”¹ This, because Marion understands theology to be a responsive discipline, demands that we speak beyond our means, speak another’s words, and speak for another (and even to speak against ourselves if necessary).² The end of theology to which each essay is ordered demands that the theologian abandon all pretense of speaking both authentically (of speaking for oneself and of oneself) and about the divine (as though God were an object of study). To the degree that such so-called authentic discourse marks one’s theology—that I speak<italic>for</italic>myself,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Marking Excess:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Saturated Phenomenon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To have a discourse dealing with the impossible—what can justify this privilege? What can justify Marion’s turn to the unconditioned, away from the<italic>as such</italic>by which individual instances appear under a horizon of possibility, conditioned and defined in advance by what we conceptualize their essence to be, by what we understand they can be? By what criteria might we justify impossibility so we might pass judgment on the veracity of discourse—to deem such discourse meaningful amidst the possibility of vanity? Indeed, such questions do not remain obediently restrained in phenomenological circles but reach as well (or perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Impossible Gift</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The icon offers a paradox: it is only in my openness to excess that I might see the image as icon, but such openness is always already a received response to the excess. It is through this reception that Marion hopes to speak of the rationality of a discourse dealing with the impossible, particularly with reception in the context of the gift. This chapter will begin with a brief recapitulation and furthering of the “new subject”: the one who is given themselves in receiving the phenomenon as it gives itself. It will continue with a consideration of the gift and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A Love that Bears All Things</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the<italic>adonné</italic>is a gifted self, in what sense is it devoted? This discourse on the impossible rests significantly upon a phenomenology of saturation rooted in an openness to otherness appearing in excess of my finitude and perspective and allowing the other to show themselves or Godself, truly. To allow the other to appear to me as particular and “unsubstitutable”²—to appear just as the other gives themselves—rather than appear as an instance of essence, a manifestation of some further reality; to allow the other to impact me, appear in me, and thereby form me from a depth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Appraising the Gift of Love</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the theologian must obtain forgiveness for every essay in theology—forgiveness for speaking beginning with another, for speaking in another’s words, and also for speaking these groundless words that are always haunted by the impossibility of the very unconditionality the theologian hopes to signify through them—then must Marion also do so? That is, if Marion names the unconditioned and names it God, then surely he too must seek permission for this presumptive attempt at impossible signification. It is thinking the unconditioned, the<italic>excess</italic>, that drives Marion’s phenomenological work, but theologically considered, he is seeking not the unconditioned<italic>as</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion to Part Two</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marion’s phenomenology is characterized by its attention to excessive givenness, to that which saturates our intentionality and concepts and therefore appears to us in the only way that it can—as impossible (according to the rules of metaphysics) or invisible (as that which can never be conceived by our minds or fully grasped within our hearts). Marion’s exploration of the gift sharpens the impact of this excess as something always first received and to which I am called to respond sacrificially by acknowledging its arrival from an elsewhere that precedes me and is other than me. But this phenomenology of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>A Beginning Given in Advance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“It is a question of beginning where one is, as Derrida tells us,” John Caputo observes, “not where God is, we may add.”¹ To begin where we are—indeed little more can be asked of us. But to know where we are as readers of Augustine—to know where we stand when encountering a mind across the distances of time and culture, and across the personal (although for the author of<italic>Confessions</italic>, not private) distance between ourselves and this particular man’s restless struggle to know and love the God whose call broke through his deafness and whose radiance dispelled his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Praising the Trinity that God Is</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What reason might we have to hope in love’s advance? What reason might invite progress into an “inquiry into things incomprehensible”²<italic>as incomprehensible</italic>, an inquiry that promises to make the impossible God possible,<italic>as impossible</italic>? Augustine concludes<italic>De Trinitate</italic>with an encouraging appeal to those who have begun to “comprehend the incomprehensibility of God”³: the Trinity is not only sought so as to be found but, indeed, is found (insofar as it is found) so that it will continually be sought. Creation, with its many unities and distinctions, generously offers to the inquirer its own limitations, not so we might</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion to Part Three</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To set about making an inexpressible reality inexpressibly seen¹ (or the invisible God visible<italic>as invisible</italic>, the impossible possible<italic>as impossible</italic>) in a work of theology is, itself, an impossible task and one that was never my intention. It was never my desire to try to present the Trinity to my readers, to present God<italic>as such</italic>. It is my hope, however, that this work might instead serve as an exercise in phenomenological theology, whereby the reception of the gift of love can be explored in the transformation it effects within us. It was never my intention to put this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhcg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>412</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
