<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS476.P67 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Hermeneutics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Postmodernism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Postmodern Bible</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Bible and Culture Collective</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Aichele</surname>
               <given-names>George</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Burnett</surname>
               <given-names>Fred W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Castelli</surname>
               <given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>editor</role>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Fowler</surname>
               <given-names>Robert M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jobling</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib6">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moore</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>editor</role>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib7">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Phillips</surname>
               <given-names>Gary A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>editor</role>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib8">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pippin</surname>
               <given-names>Tina</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib9">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schwartz</surname>
               <given-names>Regina M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>editor</role>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib10">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wuellner</surname>
               <given-names>Wilhelm</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300068184</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300158120</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dr3804"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The burgeoning use of modern literary theory and cultural criticism in recent biblical studies has led to stimulating-but often bewildering-new readings of the Bible. This book, argued from a perspective shaped by postmodernism, is at once an accessible guide to and an engagement with various methods, theories, and critical practices transforming biblical scholarship today.Written by a collective of cutting-edge scholars-with each page the work of multiple hands-<italic>The Postmodern Bible</italic>deliberately breaks with the individualist model of authorship that has traditionally dominated scholarship in the humanities and is itself an illustration of the postmodern transformation of biblical studies for which it argues.The book introduces, illustrates, and critiques seven prominent strategies of reading. Several of these interpretive strategies-rhetorical criticism, structuralism and narratology, reader-response criticism, and feminist criticism-have been instrumental in the transformation of biblical studies up to now. Many-feminist and womanist criticism, ideological criticism, poststructuralism, and psychoanalytic criticism-hold promise for the continued transformation of these studies in the future. Focusing on readings from both the Hebrew Bible and the New Testament, this volume illuminates the current multidisciplinary debates emerging from postmodernism by exposing the still highly contested epistemological, political, and ethical positions in the field of biblical studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="418"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin with a truism: the Bible has exerted more cultural influence on the West than any other single document. Understanding that influence in late twentieth-century Western culture presents a major challenge to biblical scholarship. Yet the dominant methodologies of historical criticism have been both the very foundation of modern biblical interpretation and the major obstacle to making sense of the Bible’s ongoing formative influence over culture and society. Historical criticism brackets out the contemporary milieu and excludes any examination of the ongoing formative effects of the Bible. By embracing scientific method as the key in the search for historical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Reader-Response Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Readers of the Gospel of Mark have long puzzled over two very similar episodes, the feeding of the five thousand in Mark 6: 30–44 and the feeding of the four thousand in Mark 8:1–10. In both episodes Jesus feeds a large crowd with just a few loaves and fishes. In both episodes the disciples collect baskets full of leftover pieces of bread and fish. Perhaps most perplexing of all, in both episodes the disciples seem utterly unaware of what Jesus is capable of doing to feed the crowd. Granted, they might not have understood what Jesus was doing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Structuralist and Narratological Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Along with reader-response criticism, structuralist and narratological criticism has offered biblical interpreters a crucial entryway into literary theory and the reading of the Bible. The theoretical models and language associated with structuralism and narratology, however, are quite distinct. Readers unfamiliar with these approaches may find the technical terminology complex and confusing. For this reason we concentrate our discussion on five key terms:<italic>structuralism, formalism, semiotics, narratology</italic>, and<italic>poetics</italic>. Their interrelations will be dealt with along the way. Suffice it to say here, by way of explaining the chapter title, that formalism and semiotics will be taken up in relation to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Poststructuralist Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Structuralism, poststructuralism, deconstruction</italic>—these three terms are tightly knotted.¹ Derrida himself has fumbled with the knot on more than one occasion. “When I chose this word [deconstruction),” he explains, “or when it imposed itself upon me—I think it was in<italic>Of Grammatology</italic>[1967]—I little thought it would be credited with such a central role” (1988a:1; cf. Derrida, 1985a:85–86, 142).</p>
                     <p>At that time structuralism was dominant. “Deconstruction” seemed to be going in the same direction since the word signified a certain attention to structures .… To deconstruct was also a structuralist gesture .… But it was also an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Rhetorical Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past twenty-five years we have witnessed an explosion of publications on the rhetoric of biblical texts. The rich legacy of Western rhetoric, which has been neglected by scholars for several centuries, is now being reclaimed. As a result, rhetoric is no longer being reduced to a study of the biblical writer’s style. Rhetoric as the use by biblical writers of commonly accepted rules and techniques for persuading their audiences of certain viewpoints, or for reaffirming them, is now being recovered. The revival of rhetorical criticism, conceived as a set of rules and techniques sanctioned by the scholarly guild,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Psychoanalytic Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the time Sigmund Freud published<italic>The Interpretation of Dreams</italic>(1900), the principles of psychoanalysis were in place. What were they? Laplanche and Pontalis’s scrupulous definition of psychoanalysis begins: “a method of investigation which consists essentially in bringing out the unconscious meanings of the words, the actions and the products of the imagination … of a particular subject” (367; cf. Freud, 1923b:235). This discovery or institution of the unconscious, that dark realm that governs us but which we cannot govern, whose contents express themselves obliquely—not transparently—in displacements, sublimations, condensations, and substitutions, was to be defining for psychoanalysis. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Feminist and Womanist Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the distinctive features of<italic>The Postmodern Bible</italic>is its effort to expose the interestedness of both texts and their readings and to argue for theory’s role in developing methods and strategies that lay these interests bare. This chapter focuses on issues of gender and power relations. It presents a range of feminist and womanist readings-readings that demonstrate how texts construct readers by imposing ideologies of gender and power and how readers can resist those constructions through a critical engagement with<italic>feminism</italic>and<italic>womanism</italic>.</p>
                     <p>We begin with several feminist and womanist readings of a single biblical text, Hosea 1</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Ideological Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most complex problem in this chapter is also the most basic: defining<italic>ideology and ideological criticism</italic>. Definitions of ideology abound, and they differ widely on what is of central or marginal importance. Such definitions are, of course, never neutral; they are vested with sociopolitical significance in their own right, that is they are as “ideological” as ideological criticism itself.</p>
                     <p>Michèle Barrett provides us with a place to begin: “Ideology is a generic term for the processes by which meaning is produced, challenged, reproduced, transformed” (1980:97). Ideological criticism, it follows, is concerned with theorizing and critiquing those processes of meaning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Postmodern Bible</italic>emerges in a world of competing discourses and global conflicts and connections. Readers of literary and cultural critical theory on the Bible will continue to face a multitude of methodologies and readings that give no promise of a coherent picture. When we first began to imagine writing this book, we thought we could provide a guide to the terrain of contemporary culture and criticism. What we now better understand is that the ideological gesture of providing such a map communicates the notion that somehow we know everything that is going on and can assess and communicate it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dr3804.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
