<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HM706.W55 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">SOCIAL STRUCTURE</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">SOCIAL INTERACTION</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">SOCIAL INSTITUTIONS</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">SOCIAL NETWORKS</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">SOCIAL CONTROL</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Identity and Control</book-title>
         <subtitle>How Social Formations Emerge (Second Edition)</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>White</surname>
               <given-names>Harrison C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691137155</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691137153</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400845903</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRESS</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1r2fg1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this completely revised edition of one of the foundational texts of network sociology, Harrison White refines and enlarges his groundbreaking theory of how social structure and culture emerge from the chaos and uncertainty of social life. Incorporating new contributions from a group of young sociologists and many fascinating and novel case studies, Identity and Control is the only major book of social theory that links social structure with the lived experience of individuals, providing a rich perspective on the kinds of social formations that develop in the process. Going beyond traditional sociological dichotomies such as agency/structure, individual/society, or micro/macro,<italic>Identity and Control</italic>presents a toolbox of concepts that will be useful to a wide range of social scientists, as well as those working in public policy, management, or associational life and, beyond, to any reader who is interested in understanding the dynamics of social life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="472"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>DETAILED CONTENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PROLOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>PREVIEW OF THEMES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From studies of sociocultural process of interest this book distills and integrates analytic themes. “Of interest”? To whom? Use “observer” as placeholder for the great variety of perceivers (personal or not) who may, singly or jointly, figure in and/or influence and/or unobtrusively observe:</p>
                     <p>What is going on here?</p>
                     <p>What matters, to whom?</p>
                     <p>For each ongoing sociocultural situation some implied searchlights from the different chapters of this book give us cues. We work outward from situations rather than impose boundaries.</p>
                     <p>The data-mining of Quentin Van Doosselaere (2006) will suggest how, over two centuries, a capitalist trade economy spun out in networks</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>IDENTITIES SEEK CONTROL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitschele</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godart</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederic</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Identities spring up out of efforts at control in turbulent context. But our everyday sense of reality then guides us. Being common sense, it enables communication among us, and thus makes our lives work. This book argues that “common sense” also obscures the social processes that lie behind us and our everyday perceptions.</p>
                     <p>An identity emerges for each of us only out of efforts at control amid contingencies and contentions in interaction. These control efforts need not have anything to do with domination over other identities. Before anything else, control is about finding footings among other identities. Such footing is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>NETWORKS AND STORIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lietz</surname>
                           <given-names>Haiko</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wuerkner</surname>
                           <given-names>Sabine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Identities seek control. Any identity may see control as slipping away and going to other identities. Each control effort presupposes as well as shapes some context of particular relations across identities, particularly in talk. The netdom described in chapter 1 is the local and short-term context for relations between pairs of identities. These relations are called<italic>ties</italic>. The present chapter canvases larger, continuing contexts in patterns of ties, called<italic>networks</italic>. “Network” has entered common speech as a verb, but only recently.</p>
                     <p>Social networks are traces from dynamics across netdom switchings. As two identities come over time to focus control attention</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>THREE DISCIPLINES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Redd</surname>
                           <given-names>Rozlyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steiny</surname>
                           <given-names>Don</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Disciplines offer rules of the games that yield coordination in tasks in an otherwise messy world. Joint tasks of many sorts get done and keep getting done. Disciplines order ties between identities, enabling joint accomplishment of tasks. To persist and reproduce itself, any joint accomplishment must root in and emerge from some focusing, some disciplining of the<italic>ties and talk</italic>, as presented in chapter 2, among the<italic>identities</italic>, presented in chapter 1.</p>
                     <p>In chapter 1, we saw that a public was produced jointly as a forum for the fleeting netdoms—that are the phenomenological base of networks—and disciplines can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>STYLES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godart</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederic</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buchholz</surname>
                           <given-names>Larissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A sensibility is how style presents itself in experience. For the observer, style may become apparent as an interpretative tone, deployed by native expertise. As such it exhibits a distinctive texture in social process, sensed by those immediately involved. Analytically, style can be of any scope and level: it is a scale-invariant concept. And whatever the scope, two basic aspects of style come intertwined: (a) the interpretive tone along with (b) the feedback dynamics. Style is not transposable, though it may get reconstituted.</p>
                     <p>Style is immediately available through attending to the sensibility that goes with texture in life. Some family</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>INSTITUTIONS AND RHETORICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corona</surname>
                           <given-names>Victor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thiemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthias</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Going to an appointment is an institution, sustained by a rhetoric of promptness played out in some public, large or small.¹ An institutional system shepherds social processes by channeling them, by configuring institutions through rhetorics in a way that proves self-sustaining. They draw heavily on structural equivalence as they invoke story-sets across networks. Blockmodels, introduced in chapter 2, can suggest architectures, blueprints for institutional systems. A given institutional system has selected only some among the very many homomorphisms which as analysts we can compute from blockmodels as being possible (Boyd 1991).</p>
                     <p>Kinship is the earliest exemplar and remains ubiquitous and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>REGIMES OF CONTROL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thiemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthias</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Su</surname>
                           <given-names>Millie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aregime generates control over the controls always being attempted by identities. It does so as a by-product of continuing commitments to valuation within a realm, set in contrast with another realm, or other realms. A control regime can thus develop when one realm is in conflict with another. These regimes are akin to, but generalize beyond, the three disciplines of chapter 3. The valuation order of a discipline can be derived from, as well as built into, some control regime, yet it is of more restricted scope than in realms. Furthermore, control regimes can be interlocked, as in the political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>GETTING ACTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buchholz</surname>
                           <given-names>Larissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lietz</surname>
                           <given-names>Haiko</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social life shows two faces. On one side is the challenge of blocking larger waves from the endless upsets and contingencies that are inseparable from living. From this blockage comes some sense of coherence among everyone, as well as some continuity for some locales. This is known as solving the problem of order. This has been the face examined in the chapters thus far, a view of the interaction of organization and action.</p>
                     <p>The other face cuts open the Sargasso Sea of social obligation and context to achieve openness sufficient for getting action. Any changes must originate from countering the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>OVERVIEW AND CONTEXTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godart</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederic</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corona</surname>
                           <given-names>Victor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>334</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How does the approach of this book differ from existing analyses of social process? I start this overview with that question. Then I develop how contexts and contextualizing are central to all the previous chapters. Following that, I sketch the gist of each of the chapters, and point to some alternative angles, after which I return to linguistics, as in the prologue. The central third of this overview deals with operationalizing my approach through explicit modeling. The chapter ends with two sections of further musings about context.</p>
                     <p>In asking how my approach in this book differs from prior analyses of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2fg1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
