<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>An Unexpected Light</book-title>
         <subtitle>Theology and Witness in the Poetry and Thought of Charles Williams, Micheal O'Siadhail and Geoffrey Hill</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mahan</surname>
               <given-names>David C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173367</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903575</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>David C. Mahan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0tg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A growing number of professional theologians today seek to push theological inquiry beyond the relative seclusion of academic specialization into a broader marketplace of public ideas, and to recast the theological task as an integrative discipline, wholly engaged with the issues and sensibilities of the age. Accordingly, such scholars seek to draw upon and engage the insights and practices of a variety of cultural resources, including those of the arts, in their theological projects. Arguing that poetry can be a form of theological discourse, Mahan shows how poetry offers rich theological resources and instruction for the Christian church. In drawing attention to the peculiar advantages it affords, this book addresses one of the greatest challenges facing the church today: the difficulty of effectively communicating the Christian gospel with increasingly disaffected late-modern people.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="246"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Permissions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Quash</surname>
                           <given-names>Ben</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most valuable tasks that can be undertaken by Christian thinkers in our present time is the re-equipping of people’s imaginations—helping Christians and non-Christians alike to have imaginations that are capable of responding to the divine dynamics of their reality. Today’s Christianity may try to achieve this education of the imagination in various ways. It may find help by returning afresh to its sources in Scripture, liturgy and prayer. Or it may do so (and this is not incompatible with the first possibility) by renewing and deepening its relationship with other religious traditions and their practices. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Can Poetry Matter” [to Christian Theology]?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An essay written in 1991 for<italic>The Atlantic Monthly</italic>¹ by the poet and literary critic Dana Gioia generated thunderous reaction, sending rumbles through the offices of academics and public intellectuals alike. Gioia’s theme was as straightforward as it was provocative. He asked, simply: “Can Poetry Matter?” Inquiring after the decline in poetry’s “cultural importance” Gioia laid down a gauntlet of sorts, one charged with implications not only for the status of poetry in contemporary Anglo-American society at large, but for a diverse range of more specified intellectual enterprises as well. It is not the aim of my book to explore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“From the Exposition of Grace to the Place of Images”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Incarnational Witness and “the Way of Images” in Charles Williams’ Arthuriad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have taken the title phrase for this chapter from Williams’ poem “The Vision of the Empire,” found in the first series of his “Arthuriad,”<italic>Taliessin Through Logres</italic>.² In this poem, Williams depicts the visit of his protagonist and soon to be “king’s poet” Taliessin to the Empire’s capital city Byzantium. Having arrived in the Imperial city, the poem continues,</p>
                     <p>Taliessin walked through the hither angels,</p>
                     <p>from the exposition of grace to the place of images.³</p>
                     <p>Several questions arise immediately from this brief description of his protagonist’s movements. What is meant by<italic>“the exposition of grace”</italic>and<italic>“the place of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Poetry as Remembrance:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Poetics of Testimony and Historical Redress in Michael O’Siadhail’s The Gossamer Wall</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The difference in landscapes we find between the Arthurian poetry of Charles Williams and the<italic>“Poems in Witness to the Holocaust”</italic>of Micheal O’Siadhail’s<italic>The Gossamer Wall</italic>marks the distinct set of challenges these two poets undertook to address in their verse. Although in each sequence we find a portrayal of history as a “failed landscape,” for Williams that feature of his cycle designated a clear counterpoint within a larger vision of glory, and one which is made to harmonize with that emergent vision by the logic of the Incarnation—as the summing up and reconciling of<italic>all things</italic>in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Geoffrey Hill’s “Pitch of Attention” and “Poetic Kenosis” in The Triumph of Love</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Charles Williams’ Arthuriad and Micheal O’Siadhail’s<italic>The Gossamer Wall</italic>, Geoffrey Hill’s<italic>The Triumph of Love</italic>is also a “landscape” poem, albeit in many respects different from our ordinary sense of the term. From its opening, one line section we are presented with an image that introduces a dramatic sense of place:<italic>“Sun-blazed, over Romsley, a livid rain-scarp”</italic>(I, 1).¹ Immediately following, the next section then imbues the lyric geography evoked in the first line with a sense of time and the landscape of personal history.<italic>“Guilts were incurred in that place, now I am convinced”</italic>(II), the poet announces,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We might apply MacKinnon’s salient phrase to all manner of discourse, insofar as it captures a common ambition (if not always a result) to make recognizable the object(s) being contemplated or the subject being conveyed. In the discourses of Christian theology the endeavors to clarify, to confirm, to compel attention and to persuade, may all be said to involve the pursuit of such capacities. Because theologies of the Christian faith inherently look towards a public horizon—comprising<italic>a holding forth</italic>as well as a<italic>holding together</italic>—the aim to make Christ and Christian beliefs recognizable seems specially urgent as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0tg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
