<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1fzhh18</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Research Methods for English Studies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Griffin</surname>
               <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748683437</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748683444</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748683445</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 2</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Gabriele Griffin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b4xz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>With a revised Introduction and with all chapters revised to bring them completely up-to date, this new edition remains the leading guide to research methods for final-year undergraduates, postgraduates taking Masters degrees and PhDs students of 19-20th century Literary Studies.&lt;/P&gt;</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Research Methods for English Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffin</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was working on the first edition of this volume I started it by stating that ‘Until very recently, research methods were not widely discussed in English studies.’¹ In many respects this remains the case in 2013. In the 1980s, when I was a postgraduate student, research methods did not figure at all – research was what you did, and the best you could hope for was a brief introduction to the vagaries of the library. There was no sense that you needed to know about the process of conducting research, or that how you did it might influence the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Archival Methods</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steedman</surname>
                           <given-names>Carolyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Archives and ‘the archive’ now have a wider range of meanings and potential meanings attached to them than at any point since the inauguration of European and North American state archives in the early nineteenth century.¹ There is, for a start, Jacques Derrida’s compelling philosophy of the archive in<italic>Mal d’archive</italic>(<italic>Archive Fever</italic>, 1995) in which the<italic>arke</italic>of the Greek city state is named as the place where things begin, where power originates, with power’s workings inextricably and for all time bound up with the authority of beginnings, origins, starting points.² Those who make their way through<italic>Archive Fever</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Auto/biography as a Research Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Evans</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first question that should engage our attention is that of why we wish to do research. The issue is in no sense straightforward, since ‘doing research’ is a common mantra of academic life, and is, of course, an activity in which we are all expected to partake.<italic>Not</italic>‘doing research’ is nowadays an unacceptable position for academics; to be described as ‘not research active’ implies (and indeed invokes) isolation in the distant steppes of the academic world, in which the only possible redemptive activity is teaching undergraduates. So let us not assume that ‘doing research’ is always, and simply,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Oral History as a Research Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Summerfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Penny</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oral history has a salience and familiarity at the beginning of the twenty-first century that is both popular and academic. The oral telling of public and personal histories is an everyday event on radio and television and in film, as well as occupying a recognised place within the scholarly practices of numerous academic disciplines, including anthropology, education, history, geography, political science and sociology.¹ Oral history offers several benefits to the discipline of English. Interviews with literary authors, as well as recordings of personal experiences of cultural phenomena such as theatre-going and reading, are available for study in collections in, for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Visual Methodologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rose</surname>
                           <given-names>Gillian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Visual images have been the object of study for a variety of disciplines for as long as those disciplines have existed. They include art history in the humanities, most obviously, but also, within the social sciences, the sub-disciplines of visual anthropology and visual sociology. Geography has long understood maps and photographs as central to its project (Harley 1992; Matless 1996; Cosgrove 1998), and clearly many natural sciences use various kinds of images as evidence for their claims. More recently, however, certain kinds of images, and some discipline-specific modes of approaching them, have started to cross those disciplinary boundaries, with interesting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Discourse Analysis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffin</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discourse analysis is concerned with the investigation of language,¹ both written and oral,² as it is actually used (as opposed to an abstract system or structure of language). It is different from textual analysis (see Chapter 9 in this volume) in that it assumes from the outset that language is<italic>invested</italic>, meaning that language is not a neutral tool for transmitting a message but rather, that all ‘communicative events’ (van Dijk 2001: 98) – whether these be, for instance, readings of novels, plays, poetry, a notice on a billboard, a conversation, or an interview – constitute ‘a particular way of talking about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>The Uses of Ethnographic Methods in English Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alsop</surname>
                           <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is ethnography? Is it relevant to English studies? And, if so, how? This chapter is concerned with these questions. In academia, ethnography as a research methodology is typically associated with the social sciences, most usually, although not exclusively, with the discipline of anthropology. It is chiefly a qualitative research strategy that relies primarily on participant observation and concerns itself in its most general sense with the study and interpretation of cultural behaviour. The conventional image of the ethnographer is the academic who goes out into the field (traditionally a distant land of whose people and way of life little</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Numbers and Words:</title>
                     <subtitle>Quantitative Methods for Scholars of Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hudson</surname>
                           <given-names>Pat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter considers the virtual absence of statistical techniques and quantitative methods from literature studies and the arts more generally. It starts by defining the nature and boundaries of literary analysis and of literature as a discipline, and asks what encounters with numbers specialists in these areas commonly have. It then explores why there is a tension between quantitative and qualitative approaches to research, and argues that literary studies are impoverished by the continued avoidance of quantification. Finally, some basic computational and statistical procedures and techniques, likely to be useful to literature research, are introduced. It is suggested that these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Textual Analysis as a Research Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Belsey</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How important is textual analysis in research? What is it? How is it done? And what difference does it make? My contention will be that textual analysis is indispensable to research in cultural criticism, where cultural criticism includes English, cultural history and cultural studies, as well as any other discipline that focuses on texts, or seeks to understand the inscription of culture in its artefacts. And since textual analysis is in the end empirical, I shall set out to exemplify my methodological account with a single instance. The project is to imagine that Titian’s painting of<italic>Tarquin and Lucretia</italic>constitutes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Interviewing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffin</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his review of Diane Middlebrook’s biography<italic>Her Husband: Hughes and Plath – A Marriage</italic>, Andrew Motion remarks that Middlebrook’s text shows ‘only a few signs of interviews with surviving friends’ (Motion 2004: 15). This remark forms part of a brief litany of omissions which Motion presents as an implicit criticism of Middlebrook’s work. It highlights the assumption that, where possible, interview material should form part of the research conducted for a biography, and functions in this introduction as an emblem of what has been referred to as ‘the interview society’ we now live in (Atkinson and Silverman 1997).</p>
                     <p>Interviews of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Creative Writing as a Research Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cook</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea of creativity or creative writing as a research method may seem a contradiction in terms. Long-held beliefs about the nature of creativity identify it as something that is outside or beyond methodical thought. Plato presented his philosopher, Socrates, as charmed by poets, but sceptical about the latters’ capacity to be governed by reason: ‘a poet is a light and winged thing and holy, and never able to compose until he has become inspired, and is beside himself, and reason is no longer in him’.¹ Romanticism is often taken to reinforce these beliefs in its account of the poet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>English Research Methods and the Digital Humanities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deegan</surname>
                           <given-names>Marilyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the first version of this volume appeared, much has changed in the uses of digital methods in the humanities, and what was previously known variously as humanities computing, digital scholarship, or ICT in the humanities has been broadly subsumed under the newer term, digital humanities. What digital humanities actually is has been the subject of intense discussion since it was pronounced as ‘the next big thing’ by William Pannapacker at the 2009 MLA conference, where ‘digital humanists (as they are often called) stole the spotlight’.²,³ Since then, the number of sessions at the MLA that treat of digital humanities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4xz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
