<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hj9w7s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DA926.M3M3 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conditions</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching (Higher)</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Memory Ireland</book-title>
         <subtitle>James Joyce and Cultural Memory, Volume 4</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Frawley</surname>
               <given-names>Oona</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>O’Callaghan</surname>
               <given-names>Katherine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780815652656</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0815652658</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Syracuse, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>4</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Syracuse University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j1nvx9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the fourth and final volume of the Memory Ireland series, Frawley andO'Callaghan explore the manifestations and values of cultural memory inJoyce's Ireland, both real and imagined. An exemplary author to considerin relation to questions of how it is that history is remembered and recycled,Joyce creates characters that confront particularly the fraught relationshipbetween the individual and the historical past; the crisis of colonial historyin relation to the colonized state; and the relationship between the individual'smemory of his or her own past and the past of the broader culture.The collection includes leading Joyce scholars including Luke Gibbons,Vincent Cheng, and Declan Kiberd and considers such topics as Jewishmemory in Ulysses, history and memory in Finnegans Wake, and Joyceand the Bible.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frawley</surname>
                           <given-names>Oona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Callaghan</surname>
                           <given-names>Katherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>James Joyce, Cultural Memory, and Irish Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRAWLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>OONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Joyce’s relation to “cultural memory” is inordinately complex. Joyce’s texts have come to be seen as embodying and somehow representing both memory and history, particularly in an Irish context, but also in an international one. When considered individually but especially as a collective, Joyce’s works function as narratives of the gigantic, in Susan Stewart’s phrase (Stewart 1994), that have consumed not just the particular periods in which they are set, not only whole swathes of Irish history and culture, but have come to function as digestives of world histories, languages, cultures: so that what we confront is the notion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Amnesia, Forgetting, and the Nation in James Joyceʹs Ulysses</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHENG</surname>
                           <given-names>VINCENT J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me begin on a personal note. Although I am known among my family and friends for having a good memory, I have long been aware, since childhood, of the attractions, even the desirability, of forgetting. Indeed, in my teens and twenties, I used to regularly experience what I grew to call “amnesia fantasies”: wish-fulfillment fantasies in which I imagined myself suffering from amnesia and having no idea who I was. In that condition, I could be unburdened of my own troubles and free to move on. I suspect I am not alone in having had such fantasies: after all,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>History and Trauma in Joyceʹs Ulysses</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GARRATT</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joyce’s Irishness has become so thoroughly established and accepted that we forget how recently this idea took root, especially in his native land. Initial reception of Joyce’s fiction was dominated by Americans, first Ezra Pound and T. S. Eliot—expatriate writers like Joyce—and then Edmund Wilson, Hugh Kenner, and Richard Ellmann, all of whom read Joyce as an international modernist who turned his back on the parochial nationalism of Ireland and embraced the cosmopolitan culture of Europe.¹ It was not until the late 1960s that the first sustained and forceful case for Joyce as a national writer appeared, when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>ʺI think he died for meʺ</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory and Ethics in “The Dead”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FOGARTY</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joyce, it is well known, composed the “The Dead” as a counterweight to the other stories in<italic>Dubliners</italic>. If the earlier tales aimed bluntly to expose the shortcomings of life in this colonial city, then the concluding novella sets out by way of recompense to foreground very different and more benign aspects of this urban center, highlighting in particular its convivial nature. Joyce wrote in a letter to Stanislaus that he had been “unnecessarily harsh” about Dublin and had reproduced nothing of “its ingenuous insularity and its hospitality” (<italic>JJII</italic>166). Of all the stories in Joyce’s collection it is set</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Bloomsday Seder</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce and Jewish Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BENDER</surname>
                           <given-names>ABBY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Ulysses</italic>James Joyce offers a glimpse of an Irish Promised Land—a “new Bloomusalem in the Nova Hibernia of the Future” (<italic>U</italic>461)—but it is clouded with the irony of foreknowledge. Joyce saw that the most immediate result of Irish independence would be, just as Leopold Bloom intimates, another type of oppression: “out of the land of Egypt and into the house of bondage” (<italic>U</italic>114). It is not surprising, then, that<italic>Ulysses</italic>confronts us with the apparent failure of the Irish-Israelite analogy as a narrative for Ireland; Parnell-as-Moses did not reach Canaan, and the many Moseses in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>ʺFabled by the daughters of memoryʺ</title>
                     <subtitle>Roger Casement, James Joyce, and the Irish Nationalist Hero</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHWARZE</surname>
                           <given-names>TRACEY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sir Roger Casement—Irish crusader for the rights of Congolese Africans and Putumayo Indians of the Peruvian Amazon basin, knighted for this work by the British government in 1911, and hanged by the same government for treason in August 1916 after a failed attempt to secure German arms and recruit Irish POWs to aid the Easter Rising in Ireland—is undoubtedly a figure of complex personal and political identities. Stripped of his knighthood on June 30, 1916, immediately following his conviction of high treason, Casement had enjoyed a significant career in the British consular service. His report detailing atrocities in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Joyceʹs ʺtreeless hillsʺ</title>
                     <subtitle>Deforestation and Its Cultural Resonances</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’CALLAGHAN</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHERINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the final passages of “The Dead” Joyce depicts a barren and wasted landscape with small fences, crooked crosses, and treeless hills. This shorn, infertile land of the west of Ireland, defined by what it lacks, bears in its geography the scars of its past. The “treeless hills” (<italic>D</italic>225) of Gabriel Conroy’s dreamscape represent the absent presence of the ancient forests that had covered the land, and that are now lost but long-lamented in Irish ballads, poetry, and cultural memory. The bleakness of Joyce’s description of the Connaught landscape will find literary echoes in the wasteland of Samuel Beckett’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>ʺNow, just wash and brush up your memoiriasʺ</title>
                     <subtitle>Nation Building, the Historical Record, and Cultural Memory in Finnegans Wake 3.3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PLATT</surname>
                           <given-names>LEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joyce scholars have always been interested in situating Joyce in historical context, but only since the late 1980s has the “Joyce and History” formulation become central. In part, this turn toward “history” has been philosophical. Less concerned with Joyce as a historical subject, the American academy in the 1980s and early 1990s produced a Joyce engaged with the subject of history—that is with history as historiography. Such critics as Robert Spoo and James Fairhall, then, constructed a Joyce preoccupied with history as ideological formation, particularly in relation to the orthodoxies of late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century historiography (Fairhall 1993;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Ghosts through Absence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JONES</surname>
                           <given-names>ELLEN CAROL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Borrowing and disjoining the language of the past, James Joyce’s work both parodies that past and bears witness to its truth.¹ To bear witness to the past is to comprehend its spectral repetition in the present. Indeed, even if acts of historical retrieval are intended to serve also as gestures of psychic restitution, the net effect of such reiterative reworkings of history is a repetition of the same in nightmarish, spectral,<italic>unheimlich</italic>, returns (Leerssen 2001, 220): “history repeating itself with a difference” (<italic>U</italic>616). Homi Bhabha delineates how the “mimesis of memorialization—the restitution of record, date, time, name—anxiously</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Old Testaments and New</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KIBERD</surname>
                           <given-names>DECLAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When asked why he chose Odysseus rather than Christ as a model for Bloom, Joyce was curt. Living with a woman was one of the most difficult things a man could do—and Jesus was a bachelor who never did (Budgen 1972, 191).¹ Yet Joyce was haunted by the mystery he flouted. According to Francini Bruni, his friend in Trieste, “he only completely admires the unchangeable: the mystery of Christ and the mute drama that surrounds it. I can well imagine that his head was full of this mystery when he wrote<italic>Ulysses</italic>and that therein lies the allegorical point</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Weaving the Wind</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce’s Uses and Abuses of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BEPLATE</surname>
                           <given-names>JUSTIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joyce, it seems, prized memory above all human faculties, going so far as to declare to his friend Frank Budgen that “[i]magination is memory” (Budgen 1970, 187). While the comment suggests a neat equivalence of imagination and memory, Joyce’s apparent monism is belied by the considerably more nuanced treatment of this theme in his writings. While he may have championed Giambattista Vico’s belief that the artist’s imagination is essentially a reworking of memory, it does not follow that mastering one’s powers of recall is always sufficient in controlling one’s creative material. As the “hides and hints and misses in prints”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Commemorating Ulysses, the Bloomsday Centenary, and the Irish Citizenship Referendum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KING</surname>
                           <given-names>JASON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before coming to Dublin, Bosnian immigrant Selma Harrington “hardly knew anything about Ireland except for the Troubles, and James Joyce [who] was compulsory in school literature:<italic>A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</italic>and a bit of<italic>Ulysses</italic>… That said,” she adds, “the Irish people I met abroad were open-minded, cosmopolitan. Living here [in Dublin], I am finding other sides to the mentality” (quoted in Knight 2001, 67). In Roddy Doyle’s short story “Home to Harlem,” his protagonist Declan claims to feel “like Bloom” when he is stigmatized for not being “Irish enough” or “less Irish” than</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>ʺOld Hauntsʺ</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce, the Republic, and Photographic Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GIBBONS</surname>
                           <given-names>LUKE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his early review of<italic>A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</italic>, Ezra Pound noted in passing that Joyce’s work acquired an additional currency for readers in the aftermath of the Easter Rising of 1916: “If more people had read<italic>A Portrait</italic>and certain stories in Mr Joyce’s<italic>Dubliners</italic>there might have been less recent trouble in Ireland. A clear diagnosis is never without value” (Pound 1970, 83). For Pound, it is as if Joyce is writing in the prose of<italic>counter</italic>-insurgency, diagnosing the ills that should have been redressed to prevent revolution, but for others his writing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nvx9.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
