<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmsm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Questions of Phenomenology</book-title>
         <subtitle>Language, Alterity, Temporality, Finitude</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DASTUR</surname>
               <given-names>FRANÇOISE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Vallier</surname>
               <given-names>Robert</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Caputo</surname>
               <given-names>John D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823233748</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275908</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823275906</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr5sw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Dastur is well respected in France and Europe for her mastery of phenomenology as a movement and her clear and cogent explications of phenomenology in movement. These qualities are on display in this remarkable volume.</p>
         <p>The book is organized into four areas of inquiry: "Language and Logic," "The Self and the Other," "Temporality and History," and "Finitude and Mortality." In each, Dastur guides the reader through a series of phenomenological questions that also serve to call phenomenology itself into question, testing its limits and pushing it in new directions. Taking a cue from Merleau-Ponty, Dastur sees phenomenology not as a doctrine, a catalogue of concepts and catchphrases authored by a single thinker, but rather as a movement in which several thinkers participate, each contributing to and inflecting the movement in unique ways.</p>
         <p>Through her critical and productive dialogue with multiple phenomenological thinkers, Dastur concisely shows each thinker's debts to and departures from others, as well as each thinker's innovations and limitations. She does this judiciously, without choosing sides because, for her, phenomenology is above all a way of thinking through a problem and practicing a method. The fecundity of the movement is appreciated only by participating in it-phenomenology has always thought of itself as philosophical research undertaken by and through a community of thinkers who share certain fundamental questions and ways of approaching those questions, even if their responses to these questions often differ. In this regard, Dastur is both one of the clearest guides to phenomenology and one of its ablest practitioners.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Logic of “Validity” (Husserl, Heidegger, Lotze)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the name of Lotze is known to us, it is largely because he is mentioned in the<italic>Prolegomenon to Pure Logic</italic>alongside those great thinkers under whose authority Husserl placed himself—namely, Leibniz, Kant, and Herbart.¹ Husserl even dedicates a paragraph to explaining his connections to Herbart and Lotze, but in fact, with the exception of the last few lines, the paragraph is devoted entirely to Herbart’s merits and errors. Lotze is credited only with the merit of having the great perspicacity to deepen some of Herbart’s suggestions and for developing them in an original manner; but like Herbart,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Project of a Pure Logical Grammar (Husserl)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we ask about the meaning and genealogy of the notion of a “philosophical grammar,” we cannot but linger for a while over the fourth of Husserl’s<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>, entitled “The Difference between In de pendent and Dependant Significations and the Idea of a Pure Grammar.”¹ We can say, just as Heidegger does in his 1916<italic>Habilitationsschrift</italic>on “The Doctrine of the Categories and of Meaning in Duns Scotus,” that in our epoch, Husserl “restored honor to the idea of a pure grammar and showed that there are a priori laws of meaning that disregard the objective validity of meanings.”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Pre-Predicative Experience (Husserl)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>to the<italic>Cartesian Meditations</italic>, Husserl always saw in phenomenology a new “critique of reason,” giving himself the task of “the elucidation of knowledge”¹—the title of the sixth<italic>Investigation</italic>—redefining it later, in the transcendental perspective developed in the<italic>Paris Lectures</italic>in 1929, as a “theory of knowledge.”² Beyond this essential definition of phenomenology as phenomenology of knowledge, the permanence of the theme of the foundation (<italic>Fundierung</italic>) of the formal sciences must be underlined, as we see it throughout Husserl’s entire itinerary, from the<italic>Philosophy of Arithmetic to Experience and Judgment via the Logical Investigations</italic>and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Phenomenological Gaze and Speech (Husserl and Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The mouth and the eye do not live on the same continent. Their sources are of opposed inspiration, their waters of different colors, their effects variable in their analogies.” René Char’s words, from his<italic>Recherche de la base et du sommet</italic>,¹ bring poetic confirmation to what at first sight seems like an antagonism between the orders of seeing and saying. The separate continents of the gaze and speech would therefore refer not only to the heterogeneity of the two forms of art, painting and poetry (whose dialogue René Char knew how to celebrate better than anyone else—consider just those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Reduction and Intersubjectivity (Husserl)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1930 preface to the English edition of<italic>Ideas I</italic>, Husserl defines phenomenology as “the science of beginnings”—that is, as the resumption of the original idea of philosophy, found in Plato, as a “universal science.”¹ The idea of philosophy for Husserl is, and will be to the end, the idea of a rigorous science, as indicated by the title of the famous 1911 article “Philosophie als strenge Wissenschaft” (Philosophy as Rigorous Science).² As a “universal science” and a “rigorous science,” philosophy is radically distinct from every positive science and, as Husserl already said in<italic>The Idea of Phenomenology</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Time and the Other (Husserl, Heidegger, Levinas)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Time and the Other</italic>is the title of a short but famous work published in 1948, reproducing the stenographic record of four lectures given in 1946 and 1947 by Emmanuel Levinas at the Collège Philosophique founded by Jean Wahl in the Latin Quarter. In this text, for the first time, Levinas accomplished what we could call, borrowing from the title of an essay he had published in 1935, an “evasion”¹ of the thought of being by trying to understand the relation to the other, not in accordance with the Heideggerian horizon of<italic>Mitsein</italic>, being-with, but rather as time—that is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology and Therapy:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Question of the Other in the Zollikon Seminars (Heidegger and Boss)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a book published one year after Heidegger’s death, gathering the recollections of those who were close to and knew Heidegger,¹ Medard Boss spoke of the seminars that Heidegger gave several times each year over a ten-year period (1959–69) in Boss’s home at Zollikon in front of an audience of fifty to seventy medical students and young psychiatrists.² Perhaps because it is entirely dedicated to the memory of a friend who had just died, this text is more explicit than the preface to the<italic>Zollikoner Seminare</italic>about why Boss wrote to Heidegger in 1946,³ a few years after he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conscience:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Most Intimate Alterity (Ricoeur, Heidegger, Levinas)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Must we say, as Levinas does, that in the Western tradition there is a primacy of ontology that does not allow for taking the alterity of the Other into account? We know Levinas’s argument: the Other is neither “Being” [<italic>être</italic>] nor a “being” [<italic>étant</italic>] easily grasped by a concept, and understanding the Other within the ontological dimension would therefore be to objectify and do violence to the Other. What Levinas calls “the face” is the signification of the Other that does not come from me and that invokes my responsibility to the Other. This ethical address of the Other fundamentally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Temporality and Existence (Merleau-Ponty between Husserl and Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the chapter “Temporality,” found in the third part of<italic>Phenomenology of Perception</italic>, Merleau-Ponty recalls that starting in his first book,<italic>The Structure of Behavior</italic>, his concern is specifically to understand the relation between consciousness and nature and to link together the realist and idealist perspectives—that is, to link the point of view of a consciousness<italic>constituting</italic>the object to the point of view of a consciousness<italic>constituted</italic>by the objective world and inserted into it.¹ Consciousness and the world, the inside and the outside, sense and non-sense, had for him never been separate beings that required an external</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology of the Event:</title>
                     <subtitle>Expectation and Surprise (Husserl and Heidegger)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is philosophy ready to take account of the sudden emergence and factuality of the event, which since Plato has been defined as a thought of the generality and invariance of essence? Such is the very general question with which I would like to begin. As Husserl recalls at the very beginning of his lectures on the phenomenology of internal time-consciousness, the question of time and its contingency has always constituted the most crucial challenge for philosophy, marking the limits of its enterprise to intellectually possess the world because, as the very stuff of things, time seems to escape radically from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology and History (Dilthey, Husserl, Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is it possible to come to an understanding of the historical dimension in its totality without relating it to an anthropological agency [<italic>instance</italic>]? This question may seem altogether meaningless at first glance, since it seems perfectly obvious that Karl Marx was right to claim that it is humans who make history.¹ Do we other moderns agree with his fundamental thesis that humans are by definition historical beings? What meaning should be given to the historicity of human beings? Does it mean the decline of the absolute in all its forms and the domination of the most unbridled form of relativism,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>History and Hermeneutics (Ricoeur and Gadamer)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A ten-day conference dedicated to Paul Ricoeur’s work was organized at Cerisy in August 1988 by Jean Greisch and Richard Kearney around the theme of “Les metamorphoses de la raison herméneutique.” There, David Carr, author of a remarkable study on Husserl’s<italic>Crisis</italic>,¹ focused his intervention on the question of the philosophical status of the story. I would like to begin by citing the first lines of his conference:</p>
                     <p>A question that the reader of<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>might pose is the following: what finally is the philosophical status of narrative? Is it an epistemological principle or is rather, or at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology and the Question of Man (Patočka and Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In one of his last texts, dedicated to “Heidegger, thinker of humanity,”¹ Jan Patočka claims that Heidegger is the thinker who realized Dilthey’s idea of “understanding the human on the basis of the human” by starting from what separates the human from all other beings, without recourse to anything foreign to humanity.² For Heidegger, the human is the only being capable of truth, which at first sight has the air of a truism, but in fact refers to an entirely new manner of posing the problem of truth. It is no longer a matter of the traditional view of judgment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Phenomenology of Finitude (Heidegger and Patočka)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the course of these last few years, it has been a plea sure to discover that among all the readings undertaken in Europe and elsewhere of Heidegger’s work, one of them, which is also the work of a great philosopher and not merely an epigone, was able to touch on and take the true measure of the coherence of Heideggerian thought. Should we be astonished that such a reading comes to us from Eastern Europe, from that “engaged” thinker Jan Patočka? In order to move with such assurance directly to the keystone of Heidegger’s thought, to the assumption of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Worldliness and Mortality (Fink and Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Worldliness and mortality,”<italic>Weltlichkeit und Sterblichkeit</italic>—the title sounds better in German and somewhat recalls the course that Fink gave in the Summer Semester 1949 and then again some seventeen years later, under the title<italic>Welt und Endlichkeit</italic>, “World and Finitude,” edited by Franz-Anton Schwarz and published in 1990 by Königshausen and Neumann. We know that it takes up in an original manner the theme of Heidegger’s course (attended by Fink) in the Winter Semester 1929–30 course entitled<italic>Fundamental Concepts of Metaphysics: World, Finitude, Solitude</italic>,¹ which Heidegger dedicated in memoriam to Fink, who had died on July 26, 1975</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>The “Last God” of Phenomenology (Husserl and Heidegger)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although it is formed of two Greek roots, the term “phenomenology” itself appears only very late in the philosophical tradition. It had probably been coined by Lambert, who, in his<italic>Nouvel Organon</italic>of 1764, baptized “phenomenology” as a discipline whose task is to allow the recognition of appearances and to furnish the means to escape them and arrive at the truth.¹ In the 1770 letter accompanying the copy of the<italic>Dissertation</italic>he sent to Lambert, Kant, situating himself in the framework of the traditional opposition between the sensible and intelligible worlds, also recognized the necessity of elaborating a “<italic>phaenomenologia generalis</italic>”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5sw.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
