<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BR127 .C587 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity and other religions</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Comparing Faithfully</book-title>
         <subtitle>Insights for Systematic Theological Reflection</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROBERTS</surname>
               <given-names>MICHELLE VOSS</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>EDITOR</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823274666</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823274697</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d391px"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Every generation of theologians must respond to its context by rearticulating the central tenets of the faith. Interreligious comparison has been integral to this process from the start of the Christian tradition and is especially salient today. The emerging field of comparative theology, in which close study of another religious tradition yields new questions and categories for theological reflection in the scholar's home tradition, embodies the ecumenical spirit of this moment. This discipline has the potential to enrich systematic theology and, by extension, theological education, at its foundations. This resource for pastors and theology students reconsiders five central doctrines of the Christian faith in light of focused interreligious investigations. The dialogical format of the book builds conversation about the doctrine of God, theodicy, humanity, Christology, and soteriology. Its comparative essays span examples from Hindu, Buddhist, Jewish, Muslim, Jain, and Confucian traditions, indigenous Aztec theology, and contemporary "spiritual but not religious" thought, to offer exciting new perspectives on Christian doctrine. The essays in this volume demonstrate that engagement with religious diversity need not be an afterthought in the study of Christian systematic theology; rather, it can be a way into systematic theological thinking. Each section invites students to test theological categories, to consider Christian doctrine in relation to specific comparisons, and to take up comparative study in their own contexts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Place for Comparative Theology in Christian Systematic Reflection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roberts</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle Voss</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The North American religious context is changing. If, in recent generations, the dominant Protestant Christianity came to terms first with Catholicism and then again with Judaism and Islam as fellow “Abrahamic” faiths, today the pluralism within public, intellectual, and family life is even more evident. Many Christians are curious about this reality and open to learning about it. They are encountering religious diversity and evaluating their beliefs and practices in light of it.</p>
                     <p>Each generation of theologians must respond to its context by reart-iculating the central insights of the faith. Christian thinkers have always made reference to the cultures and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Dance of Emptiness:</title>
                     <subtitle>A CONSTRUCTIVE COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY OF THE SOCIAL TRINITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sydnor</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human beings respond to difference, especially religious difference, in varying ways. Some people are repulsed by religious difference and attempt to insulate themselves from it. Others are fascinated by difference and see it as an opportunity to learn more about “the other”—the one who is different from us, the one who is not “the same”—and about themselves. For these people, otherness provides an opportunity to compare, which is a powerful means of insight. For example, democracy is understood in relation to dictatorship, freedom is understood in relation to slavery, and prosperity is understood in relation to poverty. So,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Flower and Song:</title>
                     <subtitle>A COMPARATIVE STUDY ON TEOTLIZING IN AZTEC THEOLOGY AND KARL RAHNER’S VIEW OF DIVINE SELF-DISCLOSURE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Padilla</surname>
                           <given-names>Elaine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Each Sunday, many Christians find themselves faithfully reciting the above words of belief embedded in the Nicene Creed. As if what is being stated is a self-evident truth, this phrase is echoed almost unquestioningly all over the globe. Yet the expansiveness of the statement, which includes an ambiguous interplay between things visible and invisible, placed as a poetic chiasm paralleling that of heaven and earth, might haunt us. Whereas one might find comfort in things divinely made being heavenly, would not their tangible manifestation in time and space offer an occasion to wonder about such divine makings? If we take</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Comparative Theology and the Postmodern God of “Perhaps”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A RESPONSE TO SYDNOR AND PADILLA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kiblinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Kristin Beise</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay responds to Elaine Padilla and Jon Paul Sydnor by considering their arguments in light of the view of God developed by John D. Caputo. Caputo’s view of God was chosen because it represents new, promising directions for conceiving God in our times and has important implications for comparative theology.</p>
                     <p>To place Caputo’s God in context in very broad strokes, in the first half of the twentieth century, talk of God and religion had fallen out of favor among many philosophers, but then God made a comeback in philosophy in the late twentieth century with the postmodern movement. However,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Developing Christian Theodicy in Conversation with Navid Kermani</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Stosch</surname>
                           <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my understanding of theology, the meaning of religious convictions always depends on a particular language game, i.e. on a certain theological context.¹ Because, for example, the sentence “God is love” can point to different meanings depending on to whom and in what context it is said, one can understand it adequately only if one perceives it as embedded in a particular dialogue or language game. Therefore, comparative theology can never result in a universal theory about religions and truth.² Because the meanings of basic religious beliefs within particular traditions are diverse, comparative theology focuses on select details within particular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Like a Dog’s Curly Tail:</title>
                     <subtitle>Finding Perfection in a World of Imperfection A HINDU THEODICY IN THE TRADITION OF SRI RAMAKRISHNA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Long</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffery D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter develops a theodicy in the Vedanta tradition of Sri Ramakrishna and Swami Vivekananda, building on the teachings of these two masters as found, in the case of Sri Ramakrishna, in the primary sources available on his life and teaching, and in the case of Swami Vivekananda, in the Swami’s own<italic>Complete Works</italic>. This shall be a comparative project to the degree that it engages with the thought of two prominent Christian thinkers—John Hick and David Ray Griffin—as it unpacks the deep implications of Ramakrishna’s and Vivekananda’s teaching on the nature of suffering and evil: namely, that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“Only Goodness Matters”:</title>
                     <subtitle>REFLECTIONS ON THEODICY WITH KLAUS VON STOSCH AND JEFFERY LONG</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farley</surname>
                           <given-names>Wendy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rory Block, the great blues singer, poses the question of evil in her wonderful song, “Faithless World.”¹ In her characteristic way, she evokes the poignancy of suffering, leaving the question of meaning visceral and open. She identifies us as “travelers” in this place of “many wonders” and “tears.” Her hard road has taught her that suffering is not punishment but rather a task given to the “enlightened,” a “lesson to be learned,” which each individual must learn for themselves. This “faithless world” is as, Jeffery Long puts it, a kind of moral gymnasium; it is a place of suffering against</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Longing and Letting Go:</title>
                     <subtitle>LESSONS IN BEING HUMAN FROM HADEWIJCH AND MIRABAI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hillgardner</surname>
                           <given-names>Holly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Longing is the heart’s bosom; we shall receive if we would stretch out our longing as far as we can,” wrote Augustine, recognizing longing and its cultivation as a worthy goal.³ At the same time, he viewed longing as having a direct purpose toward a clear end: “Our hearts are restless until they rest in thee, O God.”⁴ In other words, we desire fervently until we find ultimate repose in God. From this perspective, on the other side of longing the self rests—at peace, in wholeness, completed. What a consoling thought in a world where we often suffer and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Women’s Virtue, Church Leadership, and the Problem of Gender Complementarity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tiemeier</surname>
                           <given-names>Tracy Sayuki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Recently, I was asked how a thinking woman could be Catholic. The question threw me—not because I had never been asked that before (indeed, I have been asked the question many times), but because it was a prominent Christian leader whose work focused on collaborating with Catholic communities who had asked the question. Although he knew many “thinking women” who were Catholic, he still did not understand how we could stay Catholic.</p>
                     <p>Of course, many have left the Catholic Church over concerns of sexual prejudice and violence. For these people, the Church has been abusive. And just as I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Longing and Gender:</title>
                     <subtitle>A RESPONSE TO HOLLY HILLGARDNER AND TRACY SAYUKI TIEMEIER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hussain</surname>
                           <given-names>Amir</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a believing Muslim, I begin with thanks. In the Qur’an, the word for unbelief,<italic>kufr</italic>, is almost always linked with the word for thanks,<italic>shukr</italic>. The implication is clear: The one who does not believe is the one who is not thankful. Thanks to Holly Hillgardner and Tracy Sayuki Tiemeier for their contributions to this volume. It was a privilege to read them, and an honor to be asked by Michelle Voss Roberts to respond to them when they were first presented at the conference she hosted at Wake Forest University in March 2014.</p>
                     <p>The chapters are superb, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>What Child Is This?</title>
                     <subtitle>JESUS, LORD LAO, AND DIVINE IDENTITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bidlack</surname>
                           <given-names>Bede Benjamin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Comparative theology begins with reading across religious bound aries until the reader finds a doctrine—or a practice, trope, or work of art—that resonates with his or her own faith. Close study disturbs the theologian’s categories and presuppositions. Usually, such a disturbance results in the expansion of a category, its rediscovery, or simply the growth of the reader. Such is the supposed path of the theological explorer.</p>
                     <p>In a process of exploration, however, unexpected turns are bound to occur. One such possibility is that reading across religious bound aries brings the reader to foreign territory that appears so familiar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Who Is the Suffering Servant?</title>
                     <subtitle>A COMPARATIVE THEOLOGICAL READING OF ISAIAH 53 AFTER THE SHOAH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moyaert</surname>
                           <given-names>Marianne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The years after the Shoah saw a growing awareness of a connection between two thousand years of Christian anti-Judaism and certain Christological beliefs. Rosemary Radford Ruether expressed this cogently in her claim that “anti-Judaism is the left hand of Christology.”¹ This chapter is a contribution to the construction of a Christology aft er the Shoah, based on a comparative theological reading of Isaiah 53 and its Jewish and Christian commentaries.</p>
                     <p>Isaiah 53 played an important role in Christianity’s self-definition as it parted ways with Judaism, and it continued to have an impact far into the Middle Ages in theological-hermeneutical disputes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>CHRISTOLOGY IN COMPARATIVE PERSPECTIVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nicholson</surname>
                           <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The heart of Christian theology is Christology. Christology can be de-fined as theological reflection on the question of who Jesus was—and is—for Christians. The multiplicity of Christological titles in the New Testament—Messiah, Lord, savior, prophet, high priest, Son of God, and so on—all qualify each other and become reinterpreted in light of the Christ event. Together they express the centrality and sui generis nature—in short, the uniqueness—of Jesus for Christian faith. The New Testament evinces a process by which early Christians drew upon the available concepts and images, whether found in the biblical (Jewish)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Way(s) of Salvation:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE FUNCTION OF THE LAW IN JOHN CALVIN AND ABU HAMID AL-GHAZALI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ralston</surname>
                           <given-names>Joshua</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The majority of Christian soteriologies written in context of religious diversity have focused on the possibility of salvation for those who are not Christian. Traditionally, these theologies of religious diversity have been divided into three major paradigms: exclusivism, inclusivism, and pluralism.<italic>Exclusivism</italic>maintains that salvation is given only through Christ to those that explicitly embrace faith, the Church, and/or Christianity. The assertion that there is no salvation apart from the church serves as a classical articulation of this position. The second category,<italic>inclusivism</italic>, recognizes the unsurpassed saving power of Christ and Christianity but also recognizes that truth is present in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Sleeper, Awake:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONSIDERING THE SOTERIOLOGICAL PROMISE OF POPULAR SPIRITUAL GURUS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Betcher</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharon V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her novel A<italic>Tale for the Time Being</italic>, author and Zen Buddhist priest Ruth Ozeki sets before the reader—in the figure of a young Japanese girl, raised by her grand mother, a Buddhist nun—the question of how we live as “a time being,” as a floating speck of stardust in cosmic vastness: “Our human body appears and disappears moment by moment . . . , and this ceaseless arising and passing away is what we experience as time and being . . . In even a fraction of a second, we have the opportunity to . .</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Salvation in the After-Living:</title>
                     <subtitle>REFLECTIONS ON SALVATION WITH JOSHUA RALSTON AND SHARON BETCHER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rambo</surname>
                           <given-names>Shelly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Leafing through introductory textbooks in Christian systematic theology, you will find discussions of salvation located in multiple places—under the topics of Christology (the nature and work of Christ), the “other” religions, and eschatology, the study of last or final things. Insofar as these primers orient elementary readers into knowledge of Christian faith, they set out the major points for theological discussion and debate. Eschatology often becomes the major landing point for discussions of salvation because the question of salvation is often framed in terms of ultimate ends. Under the doctrine of eschatology, soteriological discussions will circle around Jesus’s saying,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391px.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
