<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B829.5.H87 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Husserl, Edmund, 1859-1938</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy and science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>General Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Husserl and the Sciences</book-title>
         <subtitle>Selected Perspectives</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FEIST</surname>
               <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616117</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616110</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, ON Canada</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpfgz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Edmund Husserl (1859-1938) is one of the previous century's most important thinkers. Often regarded as the "Father of phenomenology," this collection of essays reveals that he is indeed much more than that. The breadth of Husserl's thought is considerable and much remains unexplored. An underlying theme of this volume is that Husserl is constantly returning to origins, revising his thought in the light of new knowledge offered by the sciences.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="150"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE AUTHORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Feist</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The founder of the phenomenological movement, Edmund Husserl (1859-1938), lived through a dynamic time for the sciences.¹ Not only were there major developments in mathematics and physics, but some of the greatest practitioners of these disciplines were pursuing foundational questions with an unprecedented depth and rigour. Although Husserl did not directly contribute to these developments, it is not correct to say that he simply sat on the sidelines. He personally knew and corresponded with several of the finest scientific and mathematical minds of the time. It is, therefore, not surprising that the relationship between Husserl’s philosophy and the sciences is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>EDMUND HUSSERL AND THE HISTORY OF CLASSICAL FOUNDATIONALISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Philipse</surname>
                           <given-names>Herman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to many present-day epistemologists, the justification of scientific theories is relative in at least two respects. Whether a specific theory is justified at time<italic>t</italic>depends both upon the set E of empirical data available at<italic>t</italic>, and upon the set R of rival theories which are considered by the relevant scientific community at that time. Indeed, a theory is justified at time<italic>t</italic>if and only if it performs better than its rivals in terms of the accepted criteria for theory choice, and one decisive criterion for theory choice is some version of the criterion of empirical superiority.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>WHAT IS WRONG WITH NATURALIZING EPISTEMOLOGY?</title>
                     <subtitle>A PHENOMENOLOGIST’S REPLY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rinofner-Kreidl</surname>
                           <given-names>Sonja</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent philosophical disputes the odds are on the naturalist’s side. Despite regular complaints about the ambiguity of the term ‘naturalism,’ there exists a tacit agreement among scientists and a growing group of philosophers that defending some version of naturalism is the only tenable position. I shall not discuss the prospects of naturalism in general; rather, I shall criticize the idea of naturalizing epistemology as considered in the light of transcendental phenomenology. My examination of Quine’s and Husserl’s views focuses on the problems of circularity and foundationalism and concludes with a sketch of how naturalized epistemology and phenomenology handle the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Erläuterungen:</title>
                     <subtitle>Logical Analysis vs. Phenomenological Descriptions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fisette</surname>
                           <given-names>Denis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Husserl, a trained mathematician, just like Frege and Bolzano, and student of two of the most notable scholars of that field, Kronecker and Weierstrass, had first-hand knowledge of his contemporaries’ scientific work. Although his contribution to mathematics as such remains modest, one would be wrong to minimize the importance of formal and natural sciences within Husserl’s philosophical itinerary. For instance, his project of a universal<italic>mathesis</italic>and the articulation of his doctrine of definite manifolds were Husserl’s response to mathematical problems, namely, those of imaginary numbers, and are among the few ideas to which Husserl remained faithful until the end</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>HUSSERL AND HILBERT ON GEOMETRY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Majer</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulrich</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone who attempts to compare Husserl’s and Hilbert’s approach to geometry faces an almost insurmountable difficulty. Whereas Hilbert, over a period of more than ten years, worked out a systematic and detailed presentation of geometry which was published in his book Grundlagen der Geometric, there is nothing comparable in Husserl’s work.¹ All that we find in Husserl’s<italic>Nachlafβ</italic>² is a blueprint for a book on geometry, some scattered remarks about the epistemological origin of our knowledge of space, two somewhat longer scripts (one on the history of geometry, the other on topological questions), and last but not least, some shorter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>HUSSERL AND THE THEORY OF MULTIPLICITIES</title>
                     <subtitle>“MANNIGFALTIKEITSLEHRE”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gauthier</surname>
                           <given-names>Yvon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Husserl’s idea of a general theory of deductive systems was motivated by the mathematical theory of multiplicities. Husserl mentions the names of Riemann and Grassmann as the originators of the concept of multiplicity and he adds the names of Lie, Hamilton, and Cantor.¹ However, it is Riemann’s theory of varieties or n-dimensional spaces and Grassmann’s extension theory that are the true sources of the concept. Husserl believes that he contributes to the theory with his notions of pletho’id, ortho’id, and cyclic multiplicities.² Though some real contribution from Die Philosophic der Arithmetik, where a general definition of multiplicity is attempted, might</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>HUSSERL’S LEGACY IN THE PHILOSOPHY OF MATHEMATICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM REALISM TO PREDICATIVISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Mathieu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The list of mathematicians and philosophers of mathematics who claimed to have been influenced by Husserl is rather impressive. It includes Weyl, who successively claimed that his own predicativist programme in his 1918 book<italic>The Continuum</italic>, and a few years later, the intuitionism of Brouwer that he espoused at that stage were to be linked, as far as epistemology is concerned, to Husserlian phenomenology. In the preface to<italic>The Continuum</italic>, one reads:</p>
                     <p>Concerning the epistemological side of logic, I agree with the conceptions which underlie Husserl’s<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>. The reader should also consult the deepened presentation in Husserl’s<italic>Ideas Pertaining</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>HUSSERL AND WEYL:</title>
                     <subtitle>PHENOMENOLOGY, MATHEMATICS, AND PHYSICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Feist</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early years of the twentieth century, Edmund Husserl and Hermann Weyl exchanged a number of letters on the foundations of mathematics and science.¹ On 10 April 1918, Husserl writes that reading Weyl’s<italic>The Continuum</italic>was a meaningful event since he himself had been on a “similar path” for many years.² The following comment of Husserl’s offers some idea as to what he meant by this similar path.</p>
                     <p>At last a mathematician, who, by understanding the necessity of a phenomenological approach to all questions concerning the clarification of foundational concepts, returns to the primary ground of logico-mathematical intuition, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>HERMANN WEYL’S LATER PHILOSOPHICAL VIEWS:</title>
                     <subtitle>HIS DIVERGENCE FROM HUSSERL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bell</surname>
                           <given-names>John L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In what seems to have been his last paper,<italic>Insight and Reflection</italic>(1954), Hermann Weyl provides an illuminating sketch of his intellectual development, and describes the principal influences – scientific and philosophical – exerted on him in the course of his career as a mathematician. Of the latter the most important in the earlier stages was Husserl’s phenomenology. In Weyl’s work of 1918–22 we find much evidence of the great influence Husserl’s ideas had on Weyl’s philosophical outlook - one need merely glance through the pages of<italic>Space-Time-Matter</italic>or<italic>The Continuum</italic>to see it. Witness, for example, the following</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>FROM THE LIFEWORLD TO THE EXACT SCIENCES AND BACK</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kerszberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ever since the rise of the modern exact sciences, it has become more and more clear that the scientific mind is not bound by an exhaustive understanding of its own doings. The fact is that, while discovering the inner structure or the nexus of relations pertaining to an object, science ignores the paths that led to this structure or these relations; but these paths lie precisely at the basis of the ontological ground of the object. Husserl reflected on this legacy of the scientific revolution when he argued that “it is not always natural science that speaks when natural scientists</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>HUSSERL ON THE COMMUNAL PRAXIS OF SCIENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buckley</surname>
                           <given-names>R. Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is well known that for a long period within the phenomenological tradition itself, there was a tendency to view the<italic>Crisis</italic>-texts of Husserl’s last years as marking a radical shift in his thought. Major figures such as Gadamer and Merleau-Ponty¹ are well-known exponents of this view, and even circumspect and insightful subsequent scholars such as Carr tend to stress the novelty, for example, of the infusion of history into Husserl’s later philosophy² Some treat this ‘novelty’ as a reaction to the historical crisis of the 1930s, and also imply that the proximity and popularity of Heidegger should not be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpfgz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
