<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR3562.R27 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674. Paradise lost</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674. Paradise regained</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Epic poetry, English</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian poetry, English</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. O.T. Psalms</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Milton's Epics and the Book of Psalms</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RADZINOWICZ</surname>
               <given-names>MARY ANN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400860456</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400860458</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztqxb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Psalms were of intense interest to Milton, who read them not only as impassioned voices conveying significant moments in life's journey, but also as examples of various genres, each containing rhetorical and poetical conventions appropriate to the expressive intent of the speaker. In this book Mary Ann Radzinowicz describes the pervasive influence of these biblical works on Paradise Lost and Paradise Regained. She shows that the dramatic moments when Milton's characters respond to the numinous are shaped by his appreciation of the lyricism of the Psalms and by his studies of their thematic relationships.</p>
         <p>This book traces the density of poetic voices in the epicsvoices arising from the echoing of psalm kindsand the ironic paralleling of important episodes in them. At the same time, Radzinowicz's book relates to each other Milton's two remarkable poetic oeuvres derived from the Old and New Testaments: one an anonymous, powerful, ancient, worship-centered, lyric work, the other an individually determined, revolutionary, heroic work.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1989.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="246"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>How Milton Read the Book of Psalms: His Formal, Stylistic, and Thematic Analysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Milton read the Book of Psalms as the record of a journey through life traversing all the tempers, moods, passions, and uneven reactions that mark the psalmist’s search for an adequate faith. Such a mode of reading was common to Englishmen in his day, guided by the Geneva Bible’s representation of Psalms as a course of life by which “at length [to] atteine to [an] incorruptible crowne of glorie.”¹ Since the journey is not a consistent progress toward enlightenment, individual psalms register backsliding, fear, self-deception, even inadequacy of response no less truly than nobility of spirit. Milton did not congratulate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>“Where God is prais’d aright”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psalm Themes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When milton began to write<italic>Paradise Regained</italic>on the model of Job, he brought to the new poem hermeneutic habits made precise and boldly imaginative by having written both<italic>Christian Doctrine</italic>and<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>. The new theme came to him inspired and authorized by the Book of Psalms, “Where God is prais’d aright, and Godlike men” (4.348).<italic>Paradise Regained</italic>quickly exposes the inadequacy of the term<italic>literal</italic>to describe Milton’s thematic analysis of psalms and directs the modern reader to reinstate the distinction English Reformed exegetes sought to make in using the terms<italic>carnal</italic>and<italic>spiritual</italic>for biblical interpretation. Psalms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>“With Hymns, our Psalms . . . our Hebrew Songs and Harps”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psalm Genres</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Milton’s imitations of psalm genres in<italic>Paradise Regained</italic>reflect New Testament psalms, either those written in adaptation of Old Testament models or those psalms from the Old Testament quoted in the New Testament.¹ Just as the wisdom song has fullest representation in the New Testament, so Milton makes greatest use of that genre. He inscribes its preoccupations and themes in the very plot of the poem. Just as his text of authority, Luke’s gospel, imitates hymns, so Milton frames the Son’s heroic witness within two angelic songs of praise. Since that gospel shows reason for tragic lament but converts lamentation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTERCHAPTER</title>
                     <subtitle>“Sion’s songs, to all true tasts excelling”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Milton’s engagement with the psalms as preeminent instances of the poetry of the Bible, poetry capable of recapture in English versification, began early, persisted through his public career, and came to fruition in his two epic poems. As early as<italic>The Reason of Church Government</italic>he had written that psalms, “not in their divine argument alone, but in the very critical art of composition may be easily made appear over all the kinds of Lyrick poesy, to be incomparable.” When he then desired a multivocality in<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>that would enable him to “[teach] over the whole book of sanctity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>“Smit with the love of sacred Song”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psalm Genres</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Milton’s use of psalm genre in<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>is not only prior to that in<italic>Paradise Regained,</italic>but richer. This richness owes something to the greater sweep of<italic>Paradise Lost,</italic>a sweep that allows him both to exploit all the literary capacities of those genres prominent in<italic>paradise Regained</italic>—hymns, laments, and wisdom songs—and to deploy the three genres not significant in the briefer epic: prophetic psalms, blessing psalms, and thanksgiving psalms.</p>
                     <p>Hymns are sung across<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>not only by angelic choirs, praising both God’s nature and his specific acts, but also by the human pair, extemporizing occasional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>“Light . . . from the Fountain of light”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psalm Themes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The epic poet builds a world into his poem and makes it palpable through passages of varying emotional timbre, now pastoral, now contemplative, now devotional, now celebratory, now tragic. But he builds that world as understandable in terms of the best information or knowledge available to him. Epic places human beings within a cosmos; Milton writes for an audience interested in that cosmos not simply as a storehouse for metaphor but as a structure under investigation by the liveliest minds of his age. He designs his diffuse epic to engage the interest of the seventeenth-century reader in geography, medicine, astronomy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the margins of his own Bible, Milton singled out fifteen psalms in some way: he underlined part of Psalm 2; initialed with “KJ” parts of Psalms 56, 66, and 89; ticked 50, 55, 105, 141, 142, and 146; bracketed 98: 12–13; otherwise marked 51, 55, and 96; and smudged 1, 42, and 78 with wear.¹ In<italic>Christian Doctrine</italic>he most frequently cited proof texts from Psalms 2, 18, 19, 33, 37, 51, 78, 94, 102, 103, 104, 119, and 147.² He translated or paraphrased Psalms 1 through 8, 80 through 88, 114, and 136. Finally, throughout the English</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CONSULTED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztqxb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
