<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6t9j6w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B935.G86 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, American</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pragmatism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Globalization</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ideas to Live For</book-title>
         <subtitle>Toward a Global Ethics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GUNN</surname>
               <given-names>GILES</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813937304</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813937302</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CHARLOTTESVILLE; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16kdw0h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Over the course of his distinguished interdisciplinary career, Giles Gunn has sustained his focus on the continuing threats to our collective sense of the human that seem to result from the link between the collision of fundamental values and the increase of systemic violence. He asks whether such threats can be at least mitigated, even if not removed, by understanding as opposed to force and what resources a more pragmatic cosmopolitanism might provide for doing so. How, in other words, might our sense of the human be reconstructed, not around suspicion or antipathy toward others, but around an epistemological and moral need of them?</p>
         <p>In this narrativized collection of his essays, Gunn introduces each one with a set of comments designed to explain his goal when first writing them and what they mean to him now. The variety of issues he addresses ranges from the theory of culture and cultural criticism (particularly in America), the philosophy of inter- and cross-disciplinary studies, and the psychology and politics of pragmatism to the ethics of human solidarity, the place of culture in the misshaping of international affairs, and the quest of both religion and culture for a new basis for the normative.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ten essays in this volume were published between 1987 and 2012. They cover a period of a quarter of a century in which I have moved through several different fields of inquiry, from religious studies, to literary and critical studies, to American cultural and philosophical studies, to global studies. As with evolution generally, this has been a process during which earlier disciplinary interests were by no means set aside or left behind but rather reappropriated and restructured to address new problems that have become steadily more inter-and transnational in scope. That task of reappropriating and restructuring for the sake</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Who Are You Really, and What Were You Before?</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on a Thinking Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Humphrey Bogart turns to Ingrid Bergman in<italic>Casablanca</italic>and puts to her the question that forms the title of this essay—asking in addition, “What did you do, and what did you think?”—she gently puts him off with the reminder, “We said no questions.” Bergman’s refusal to answer does not mean that for her the past has no place in their relationship; indeed, the past will eventually determine the limits on where their relationship can go and what it can become. While Bergman has something she prefers to keep private, even though she has no reason at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>The Semiotics of Culture and the Diagnostics of Criticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Clifford Geertz and the Moral Imagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an essay in progress at the time of his death, Lionel Trilling initiated an unusually fruitful dialogue with the social and cultural anthropologist Clifford Geertz.⁵ The ostensible reason for Trilling’s interest in Geertz’s work was the way it confirmed certain suspicions Trilling had come to entertain about the traditional assumptions of humanistic scholarship as a result of a course he had recently taught on Jane Austen. However, the substance of his own unfinished meditation, together with Geertz’s subsequent response, possesses a critical importance that far transcends the particular circumstances of their origin.⁶ By setting the discussion of literary as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Rorty’s Novum Organum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a variety of books from<italic>philosophy and the Mirror of Nature to contingency, irony, and solidarity</italic>and a spate of influential articles, Richard Rorty has mounted a far-reaching critique of what might be called our contemporary intellectual<italic>pseudodoxia.</italic>That term, Francis Bacon’s, was employed to refer to various notions in the human mind that stand in the way of the advancement of human knowledge. These notions, or Idols, were, Bacon said, of four kinds, and they needed to be overcome in the furtherance of knowledge: “Idols of the Tribe,” being “inherent in human nature,” seduce us into believing that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Interdisciplinarity and the Deepening of the American Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Interdisciplinarity has recently become a subject of considerable interest in the academy. No doubt some of its topicality derives from the perennial American fascination with borders, frontiers, and unexplored territory. Much of the current fascination with interdisciplinarity, however, now also derives from its appeal to leftist ideology that associates intellectual disciplines with the institutional structures that create and empower them and that, in the hyperbolic mood of a good deal of critical discourse these days, are prepared to view the demarcation of intellectual territorialities as potentially a police tactic that is both imprisoning and oppressive. The radical response is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Multiculturalism, Mourning, and the Americas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a New Pragmatics of Cross- and Intercultural Criticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the recent passage of the Columbus quincentennary has posed for us any new questions, one of them surely has to do with the relationships among the various cultures that Columbus’s voyage, or rather our reconstruction of its consequences, has bequeathed to us. For if Columbus’s voyage succeeded in producing anything other than a holocaust to Native peoples, it resulted in an explosion of new cultures in the Americas that has now left us with an elaborate assemblage of societies and nations whose relations with one another, however carefully documented in other terms, are still comparatively unexplored in cultural terms.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Religion and the Recent Revival of Pragmatism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Religion, it must be said, has not played a very significant role, except perhaps negatively, in the recent renewal of pragmatism. There are no doubt many reasons for this, but none is more important than the responsibility that Richard Rorty deservedly bears for helping to promote this revival and the connection he has made between the development of pragmatism and liberalism’s project of disenchanting the world religiously.</p>
                     <p>If Rorty is now prepared in “Pragmatism as Romantic Polytheism” to revise, or at any rate to modify, this liberal agenda, it should not go without notice that several of Rorty’s own heroes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Human Solidarity and the Problem of Otherness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the notion of human solidarity has long functioned as one of the ways that in the West we have expressed our sense of shared humanity not only with ourselves but presumably with others, what happens, I want to ask, when so many of the languages in which that sense was expressed have for various reasons become outworn or discredited? The reasons are not only empirical and political but also moral. If a fair number of physical anthropologists now maintain that there may be no such thing as universal human qualities, and we are everywhere confronted with the spectacle of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>The Place of Culture in the Play of International Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is organized around the belief that cultural assumptions, principles, and aspirations have played a much larger role in international politics than is often conceded. In the American academy as well as the public arena, there has until fairly recently been considerable skepticism about, if not resistance to, such an idea. Not that anyone has considered international affairs immune to the influence of ideologies, values, or even symbols, but only that the conventional orthodoxy in international relations has tended either to downplay the effects of such factors or, more likely, to presume that the best way of understanding their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>The Transcivilizational, the Intercivilizational, and the Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Quest for the Normative in the Legitimacy Debate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a world where traditional international rules have sometimes proved inadequate, recent interest in the notion of “legitimacy” as a complementary source of legal authority has raised a number of issues—legal, moral, and what some would call “ontological.”⁴ These issues came to the fore most dramatically, though not for the first time, during the Kosovo War of 1999, when in the face of grave and intolerable human rights abuses it became necessary to override legal protections against intervention into the activities of sovereign states. These questions were soon to become still more urgent and vexed when “legitimacy” was employed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Global Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Global ethics refers to a diverse field of intellectual inquiry devoted to establishing norms, procedures, and practices for addressing issues of conduct, collaboration, and conflict in the global sphere. Such issues can be of consequence to individuals, communities, states, transnational organizations, or any combination thereof. What makes them global is their sphere of reference and resonance. Do they register on scales of import or signifi-cance and consequence that require interpretation within a global as opposed to a national, transnational, regional, or local frame?</p>
                     <p>From this perspective, there is always both a theoretical and a practical dimension to global ethics, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmopolitanism in an Era of Globalized Absolutisms</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the utility of a cosmopolitan perspective in a globalized world? This is a world many of whose most serious challenges arise not just from geopolitical, social, and economic disputes between and across nationstates but also from intercultural and cross-cultural misunderstandings and conflicts going on around and within them. By<italic>cosmopolitan</italic>most people mean “worldly,” “universalist,” “tolerant,” or “civilized,” but there are in fact almost as many versions of cosmopolitanism as there are brands of dry cereal. Cosmopolitanism not only comes in various kinds—political, social, economic, cultural—but also in various forms—“vernacular,” “situated,” “realistic,” “patriotic,” “Eurocentric,” “emancipatory,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16kdw0h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
