<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Narrative Concepts in the Study of Eighteenth-Century Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Steinby</surname>
               <given-names>Liisa</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mäkikalli</surname>
               <given-names>Aino</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789048527380</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>All authors</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Amsterdam University Press B.V.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wn0r6q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This collection of essays studies the encounter between allegedly ahistorical concepts of narratology and eighteenth-century literature. It questions whether the general concepts of narratology are as such applicable to historically specific fields, or whether they need further specification. Furthermore, at issue is the question whether the theoretical concepts actually are, despite their appearance of ahistorical generality, derived from the historical study of a particular period and type of literature. In the essays such concepts as genre, plot, character, event, tellability, perspective, temporality, description, reading, metadiegetic narration, and paratext are scrutinized in the context of eighteenth-century texts. The writers include some of the leading theorists of both narratology and eighteenth-century literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>The Place of Narratology in the Historical Study of Eighteenth-Century Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steinby</surname>
                           <given-names>Liisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mäkikalli</surname>
                           <given-names>Aino</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Narratological concepts, such as focalization, perspective, implied author, the distinction between story and discourse, and even homo- and heterodiegetic narration, today belong to the toolkit of scholars of literature, including those who do not consider themselves narratologists. Since literary analysis almost always also encompasses formal aspects of works, narratological concepts concerning the structure and forms of a narrative are taken by many as a ‘natural’ choice. Narratologists did not originally see their work as ‘a handmaiden to interpretation’; their theoretically-based taxonomic description of narrative was separated from interpretation, which always also has to do with the content of the narrative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Eighteenth-Century Challenge to Narrative Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McKeon</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I’ll begin with a narrative. Years ago in graduate school, as I became aware of the novel as something to study as well as to read, my eye was caught by two recent books whose claim was that the novel was getting a lot more attention than it deserved. Although very different in other respects, both Frye’s<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>and Scholes and Kellogg’s<italic>The Nature of Narrative</italic>made the point that in those days, the dominance of novel studies was such that to speak of the novel, it seemed, was to speak of narrative as such. Their influential books</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Formalism and Historicity Reconciled in Henry Fielding’s Tom Jones</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Richetti</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every student of Henry Fielding’s<italic>Tom Jones</italic>quotes Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s remark in his<italic>Table Talk</italic>: ‘What a master of composition Fielding was! Upon my word, I think the<italic>Oedipus Tyrannus</italic>, the<italic>Alchemist</italic>, and<italic>Tom Jones</italic>, the three most perfect plots ever planned’ (Coleridge, 1856, p. 521). The novel’s justly-celebrated plot with its twists and turns and surprises seems to involve for readers a series of uncertainties about the ultimate fates of its characters. And yet Fielding’s plot is distinct from what we now think of as ‘plot’. For one thing, the narrative unfolds in a supremely leisurely and digressive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Perspective and Focalization in Eighteenth-Century Descriptions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fludernik</surname>
                           <given-names>Monika</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Cynthia Wall has so magisterially illustrated in<italic>The Prose of Things</italic>(2006), descriptions of rooms hold a marginal position in eighteenth-century texts. This is due partially to conventions of writing and partially to the absence of fixed furniture arrangements before the end of the eighteenth century. On the one hand, literary descriptions before the eighteenth century were often stylistic exercises in rhetorical enumeration. Mieke Bal, in her superb essay on description, cites (a translation of) a<italic>locus amoenus</italic>passage from Longus’s novel<italic>Daphnis and Chloë</italic>:</p>
                     <p>And that garden indeed was a most beautiful and goodly thing and such as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Temporality in Aphra Behn’s Oroonoko and Daniel Defoe’s Robinson Crusoe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mäkikalli</surname>
                           <given-names>Aino</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the<italic>Routledge Encyclopedia of Narrative Theory</italic>(2005) Monika Fludernik suggests that time in narrative can be viewed from three different perspectives: first, the general,<italic>philosophical</italic>aspect of temporality and its significance for the levels of story and discourse; second, the relationship between the<italic>story</italic>and<italic>discourse</italic>levels; and third, the<italic>grammatical</italic>and<italic>morphological</italic>devices used (tense markers) and their significance for the levels of discourse and story. She stresses the study of two temporal levels, that of the<italic>story</italic>and that of the<italic>discourse</italic>, leading to the analysis of chronological distortions of the surface level of the narrative text</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Temporality, Subjectivity and the Representation of Characters in the Eighteenth-Century Novel</title>
                     <subtitle>From Defoe’s Moll Flanders to Goethe’s Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steinby</surname>
                           <given-names>Liisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the course of the eighteenth century, the experience of time – and, connected to this, the experience of human existence – underwent profound changes. Here I trace these changes as expressed in the eighteenth-century novel mainly on the basis of two examples, representing two different phases of temporalization of experience: Defoe’s<italic>Moll Flanders</italic>(1722) and Goethe’s<italic>Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre</italic>(1795-1796).</p>
                     <p>If we agree with Ian Watt’s view of the ‘rise’ of the modern novel in England in the first half of the eighteenth century, what we have here is the first radical temporalization of experience in that century. According to Watt,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Authorial Narration Reconsidered</title>
                     <subtitle>Eliza Haywood’s Betsy Thoughtless, Anonymous’ Charlotte Summers, and the Problem of Authority in the Mid-Eighteenth-Century Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Birke</surname>
                           <given-names>Dorothee</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From a narratological point of view, one of the most controversial legacies the eighteenth-century novel has bestowed onto its inheritors is the technique of authorial narration. Described by Franz K. Stanzel as one of three typical narrative situations, authorial narration as defined in the<italic>Routledge Encyclopedia of Narrative Theory</italic>is ‘characterized by a highly audible and visible narrator’ who ‘sees the story from the ontological position of an outsider, that is, a position of absolute authority which allows her/him to know everything about events and characters, including their thoughts and unconscious motives’ (Jahn, 2005, p. 364). This association of authorial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Problems of Tellability in German Eighteenth-Century Criticism and Novel-Writing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kukkonen</surname>
                           <given-names>Karin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘My God, said the Duchess. I am pregnant. Who done it?’ Marie-Laure Ryan cites this mock-formula of French bestsellers in her entry on ‘tellability’ in<italic>The Routledge Encyclopedia of Narrative</italic>(Ryan, 2005, p. 590). What makes a narrative worth telling, it suggests tongue-in-cheek, are religion, aristocracy, sex and mystery. The formula illustrates how tellability depends on the subject matter of the narrative. Ryan points out that such salience can be, on the one hand, grounded in universally relevant topics (such as sex and death) and, on the other hand, be related to cultural contexts (for example the interest in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Immediacy</title>
                     <subtitle>The Function of Embedded Narratives in Wieland’s Don Sylvio</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nitschke</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Systematic narratological classification helps identify ‘trans-historical’ phenomena which share defining characteristics, but can still change over time in terms of form or function. In the eighteenth century, seminal, longterm social and political shifts (even before the French Revolution) became widely tangible. With society undergoing massive structural changes, literature formed no exception: writers began taking stock and started rigorously to probe and investigate the semantic potential of emergent genres such as the novel, but also the narrative medium itself.</p>
                     <p>As a means of observing and analysing this historical self-exploration embedded narratives – here more specifically the metadiegetic level – seem particularly well-suited: they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Tension between Idea and Narrative Form</title>
                     <subtitle>The Example as a Narrative Structure in Enlightenment Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Waldschmidt</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the literature of the eighteenth century, particularly for those works that are seen as part of the Enlightenment, critics have foregrounded the moral, didactic interest of these texts. In the Enlightenment view, literature is supposed to serve a purpose (cf. Pizer, 2005, p. 91), and literary texts are always understood in terms of their function as serving moral goals. This penchant for the usefulness of literature is not very surprising: The Enlightenment defines itself as a movement towards greater intellectual independence and moral instruction – leading mankind out of its ‘selfinflicted immaturity’.² Hence the Enlightenment tends to explain the (ever-noticeable)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘Speaking Well of the Dead’</title>
                     <subtitle>Characterization in the Early Modern Funeral Sermon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pritchard</surname>
                           <given-names>Penny</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In depicting the character and personality of their deceased subject, English Protestant ministers in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries employ features of writing strikingly comparable to contemporary works of fictional narrative. Such features include not only the selective inclusion of biographical details from the subject’s life and death, but a spectrum of seemingly ‘literary’ devices such as the portrayal of multiple points of view through eyewitness ‘testimonials’, direct quotation of correspondence, poetry, diary entries, and vividly-realized deathbed scenes (some of which include dialogue).</p>
                     <p>These correlations illustrate the extent to which, as J. Paul Hunter has observed, such writing ‘may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Use of Paratext in Popular Eighteenth-Century Biography</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Edmund Curll</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rogers</surname>
                           <given-names>Pat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why Curll, of all people? A natural reaction to the title of this essay might be to wonder what the rascally publisher Edmund Curll has to do with narratology, the theme of this volume. It might be thought that Curll (1683-1747) was an interesting fellow, no doubt, but scarcely a pioneer of writerly innovation. The case I shall try to make here is that Curll’s most characteristic productions, above all the instant biographies he brought out in the late 1720s and early 1730s, do tell us something about paratext – specifically on the way it constitutes a type of narrative statement</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Peritextual Disposition in French Eighteenth-Century Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ikonen</surname>
                           <given-names>Teemu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of the so-called transnational novel has demonstrated the variety of practices of rewriting inside and across linguistic borders in the eighteenth century Europe (see e.g. Montandon, 1999; Stewart, 2009). Original works from the period are hard to distinguish from translations, translations of translations, pseudo-translations, authorial revisions, free adaptations, impostures, crudely abridged editions and other versions (Stewart, 2009, pp. 164-65). According to Coulet (1992), French authors were particularly busy revising their own works. Significant changes in narration and plot were common. Well-known is marquis de Sade’s transposition from first-person narration in<italic>Justine</italic>(1791) to third person in<italic>La Nouvelle</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0r6q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
