<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Why Resurrection?</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Introduction to the Belief in the Afterlife in Judaism and Christianity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Blanco</surname>
               <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718892524</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843076</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Carlos Blanco</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdxgw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Few questions exert such a great fascination on human conscience as those related to the meaning of life, history, and death. The belief in the resurrection of the dead constitutes an answer to a real challenge: What is the meaning of life and history in the midst of a world in which evil, injustice, and ultimately death exist? Resurrection is an instrument serving a broader, more encompassing reality: the Kingdom of God. Such a utopian Kingdom gathers the final response to the problem of theodicy and to the enigma of history. &lt;CR&gt;&lt;CR&gt; This book seeks to understand the idea of resurrection not only as a theological but also as a philosophical category (as expression of the collective aspirations of humanity), combining historical, theological, and philosophical analyses in dialogue with some of the principal streams of contemporary Western thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="242"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The belief in the afterlife in Judaism and Christianity emerges as a response to a real challenge: the problem of evil. As the Swedish theologian Krister Stendahl wrote, “in its original setting the resurrection is an answer to the question of Judaism in the time of Jesus: the question of theodicy. Will justice win and the promises of God to the faithful be fulfilled?”¹</p>
                     <p>The fundamental question is that of theodicy: What is the meaning of life and history in the midst of a world in which evil, injustice, and ultimately death persist and seem to achieve a constant triumph</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Theodicy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophy of Religion and the Problem of Evil</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evil is everywhere. We can experience it in different ways, but it is certain that such a reality surrounds us. We see people suffering, and when we watch the news, we hear about wars, conflicts of various kinds, unending wills of power, constant violations of human rights, oppression, poverty, lack of freedom and equality, etc. Even in the developed countries, we perceive the huge social differences that build barriers between human beings, and within the most privileged groups of these affluent societies, evil is still present, taking the shape of illnesses that affect both the rich and the poor, learned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>History and Meaning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Heidegger, Bloch, Hegel, and Pannenberg</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of evil is closely related with the question about the meaning of history. Some people could argue that the idea of a meaning in history is not clear at all: why is it necessary that there be a meaning, a sense for the historical events? Isn’t history an abstraction, the generalization of particular experiences that the individuals have in their own lives, and that we project onto a universal scenario which encompasses the whole of humanity?</p>
                     <p>As we can see, there are many interesting, convenient, and legitimate questions to pose regarding the nature of history. The doubts that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Apocalyptic Conception of History, Evil, and Eschatology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of the sociological analysis of religious ideas is to help clarify the nature of the context in which they emerged, paying special attention to the motivations of the actors involved (individuals and groups with affinities and common interests). This is the way to reach a better understanding of the impact of the conceptions of some social groups and of why these ideas became hegemonic in a certain cultural space.</p>
                     <p>These considerations can be projected onto two fundamental axes: the one that links Hellenism and apocalypticism, and the one which connects apocalypticism and Judaism. We aim to study, on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of evil is closely related to the question of the meaning of life, and the question about such a meaning seems to be inevitably bounded to the development of a higher consciousness, as it has happened in the latest stages of human evolution.</p>
                     <p>Virtually all religious traditions have offered some sort of hope in the form of overcoming death. Even the Neanderthal man believed in some way or another in a future life, which he thought to be rather similar to the present existence. On account of this, Neanderthals buried the dead equipping them with the food and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Kingdom of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The belief in the persistence of life after death is not a goal in itself. People who believe in immortality of the soul and in resurrection of the dead do not do so just to state that personal identity will endure. They do so in order to state that the personal identity will endure in a different world, in a different kind of life. The belief in life beyond death is therefore meant to affirm that there is a new world waiting for us, and that life on Earth is not the definitive, final reality.</p>
                     <p>It would be quite pointless</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxgw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
