<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX713.M95 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Srpska pravoslavna crkva</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nationalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Srpska pravoslavna crkva</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History of doctrines</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Church and state</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Srpska pravoslavna crkva</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Church and state</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Yugoslavia</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Serbia</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Serbia</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Serbia</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Church history</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Serbian Orthodox Fundamentals</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Quest for an Eternal Identity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mylonas</surname>
               <given-names>Christos</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789639241619</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9786155211201</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Christos Mylonas</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt1cgf87j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is a comprehensive exposition of the interaction of a national (the Serbian people) and a religiou (the Orthodox Christian faith) content, in the formation of a distinctive national identity and a mode of being. Its interdisciplinary approach, drawing on sociology, social anthropology, theology, political theory, Balkan historiography, and Serbian folklore, is deployed to provide a powerful and original analysis of how Serbian Orthodoxy has resulted in the sacralisation of the Serbian nation by framing the parameters of its existence. Addresses the following questions: what 'makes' a Serb? Are meaningful assumptions possible by introducing Serbian Orthodoxy as the primal point of reference? Why does religion appear to have an especially strong appeal?</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="306"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>NATION, RELIGION AND FUNDAMENTALISM LOCATING THE THEMATICAL PARAMETERS AND CONTEXT OF THE SERBIAN COSMOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“... What irrational laws do we obey, what subjective signals allow us to establish the right direction at any moment, which symbols and myths predominate in a particular conjunction of objects or webs of happenings, what meaning can be ascribed to the eye’s capacity to pass from visual power to visionary power?”¹</p>
                     <p>The aforementioned statement belongs to André Breton and more specifically, forms a part of his introductory essay,² on Frida Kahlo’s exhibition in New York in 1938. In an effort to grant a more objective perspective to the interior “meaning” of her paintings, he described her work in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>ORTHODOXY AND SERBIAN NATIONAL IDENTITY “BLESSED IS THE NATION THAT PROFESSES ONE AND THE SAME FAITH.”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In untangling this complicated subject it will be helpful to resort to a simplified schema, founded upon the following point of departure: that religion—Serbian Orthodoxy, in this particular context—defines man and his place in the universe. In order to function effectively, it is essential that a person or group have a precisely focused and systematically conceived definition of its environment and of itself. Such a definition of the system and the cosmos to which it is related is a conception of identity. Orthodoxy can be understood only as an integrated system of thought, logically sound and epistemologically valid,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>HOMO SERBICUS</title>
                     <subtitle>DEFINING THE NATURE AND RELATIONSHIPS OF THE “CREATURE”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Orthodox experience, as the primordial factor of Serbianhood, nurtures upon doctrinal and functional precepts, distinctive cultural and institutional patterns that provide a sense of “protection” and of national be longing to its members. This sense of protection pertains to divinely sanctioned exegeses, concerned with human origins and behaviour and in particular, with the Manichean distinction between good and evil, right and wrong. Orthodoxy as a signifier of collective representation, crystallises rules, symbols, behavioural inducements and consequences for actions, whose justification is also reflected in the internal necessities and functional core of the Serbian society. The creation of forms and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>THE PURSUIT OF “SECULAR” SALVATION THE INFLUENCE OF ORTHODOXY IN THE SERBIAN POLITICAL CULTURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Orthodoxy, as a holistic, religious experience, may initially appear to be an incompatible referent when considered with purely political forms of personal and societal expression. From a Serbian historical perspective, this almost unequal relation originates in the territorial organisation of the church, which transcends political boundaries in an encompassing pursuit of her congregation’s existential problems, sacred or profane. The political encroachment of the Orthodox laity, the separation of<italic>vox Dei from vox populi</italic>, was forcibly pronounced under the secular conditions of Yugoslav communism, which limited the scope, intensity and formal depth of confessional affinities. In an Orthodox environment, communism’s appeal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>THE PURSUIT OF “SACRIFICIAL” SALVATION</title>
                     <subtitle>THE KOSOVO MYTH IN THE SERBIAN COLLECTIVE CONSCIOUSNESS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When applied to explicit or implicit (cognitive) statements about the “placement” of man in his environment, human rational faculties are often inadequate in the decipherment and revelation of an esoteric content. Humanity’s integrative roots with the universe and the creation of a graspable consciousness, as a means of orientation in time and/or space (in the concrete, but also in the dimension of ontological reality) embrace the totality of the past with the help of symbols, rituals, ceremonies and myths. A community could not regard itself as truly constituted until a sacred beginning is ascribed to it and an inseparable, “invisible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>“TO LOVE YOUR NEIGHBOUR AS YOURSELF” “VIOLENCE AS ANTITHETICAL TO THE LIFE OF (ORTHODOX) CHRISTIANS AND VIOLENCE AS PART OF THE DYNAMIC PROCESS BY WHICH ‘JUSTICE IS ESTABLISHED AMID THE TENSIONS OF HISTORY’”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The exercise of impetuosity, an instance of devastating and powerful force or an unjust and unwarranted display of physical intention for the purpose of intimidation, injury and destruction, are all aspects of violence, an elusive concept often applied in the description of a recognisable reality and an actual situation. Within the institutional confines and structures of a society, violence is roughly definable as “the illegal employment of methods of physical coercion”³ in the pursuit of individual and collective objectives. Étatist traditions are conterminal with the use of constitutionally sanctioned coercion⁴ in the defence and consolidation of state authority. All human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>THE BALKAN ORTHODOX COMMONWEALTH “I BELIEVE IN ONE GOD… THE CREATOR OF HEAVEN AND EARTH, OF ALL VISIBLE AND INVISIBLE ENTITIES… AND IN ONE HOLY, APOSTOLIC AND CATHOLIC CHURCH.”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Orthodoxy, as already suggested, through the dialectical interaction of her religious content—doctrinal and functional—with the national substance of the Serbian being, sacralises the identity of the latter in the confines of the human–divine communion. Spatial, sacramental, historical, temporal, aesthetic, and spiritual signifiers or referents of faith contribute toward the constitution of a holistic and objectified experience that permeates the nature of the national collectivity. A genealogy of right belief, underlined by the “mediative” presence of venerated patriots and the autocephaly of ecclesiastical institutions, concretise the convergence of the catholic and universal character of Orthodoxy into a unique</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>George Seferis’<italic>Mythistorema</italic>—the colloquial meaning of the title is novel—connotes to the components of istoria—both history and tale—as an expression with some coherence of the circumstances that are independent of the reader—as the characters in a novel—and<italic>mythos</italic>, a certain mythology, clearly alluded to in the thematical substance of the verse. Beyond the etymological binary of a “heading”, Seferis’ work gradually reveals to its audience his enduring inspiration from the past, in the collective recollection of creation, war or destruction and as a personal reminder of loss and exile. The emergent image is seemingly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf87j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
