<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Edinburgh Companion to Twentieth-Century Philosophies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boundas</surname>
               <given-names>Constantin V.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748620975</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748629299</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748629297</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Edinburgh University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g09xfc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Companion is organized into two sections, each one of which reflects the developments of the Anglo-American Analytic and the Continental European philosophical traditions respectively. An appendix presents the main accomplishments of non-Western philosophies in the same time frame.</p>
         <p>Each section discusses the main movements and fields of the discipline throughout the century. The authors have maintained a balance between the historian's commitment to breadth and accuracy with the commitment of the systematic philosopher to the engaged point of view and to critical reflection. The result is a distinctive reference book made up of a series of philosophical studies -an invaluable companion to anyone who is searching for a panoramic but also reliable and challenging presentation of the philosophical ideas which shaped the last century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boundas</surname>
                           <given-names>Constantin V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy looked poised to enter the twentieth century confident in its future. The leading professional journals of the year 1900 display, thematically and stylistically, a healthy pluralism, a critical attitude, tempered by an acute awareness of differences, the will to subject differences to rational scrutiny, and a commendable spirit of collegiality and internationalism. This spirit is also evident in the impressive gathering of philosophers for the World Philosophy Congress that takes place between the 1st and the 5th of August of 1900, at the Lycée Louis-le-Grand, in Paris, under the presidency of Emile Boutroux, and with the capable assistance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How to recognize Analytic Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boundas</surname>
                           <given-names>Constantin V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The distinction between analytic and continental European philosophies is nowadays yawning – which does not mean that there have not been, until the very end of the twentieth century (or that they are not now) philosophers passionately defending it. It has become a liability for those who wish to maintain the philosophical identities that this exclusive disjunction proposes because what they maintain is demonstrably false. No one has come up with a list of necessary and sufficient objective criteria for grouping philosophers according to the disjuncts. Claims that it is possible to concoct such a list depended on ignorance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kant and the Analytic Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanna</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The influence of the eighteenth-century Critical Philosophy of Immanuel Kant (1724–1804) on the analytic tradition is both originative and protean.¹ Analytic philosophy historically emerged from an extended theoretical struggle with Kant’s Critical metaphysical doctrine of<italic>transcendental idealism</italic>. But even more than that, the very idea of analysis can be made theoretically intelligible only in relation to Kant’s basic Critical philosophical aims, methods, and theses. Quite ironically, however, precisely to the extent that the analytic tradition finally pulled itself free from its Kantian roots and became an independent philosophical enterprise closely associated with the methods, epistemology, and metaphysics of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Metaphysical and Moral Idealism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Armour</surname>
                           <given-names>Leslie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The metaphysical and moral idealism that dominated philosophy in Britain and North America in the last decades of the nineteenth-century reached its zenith in the early years of the twentieth-century. It then faced serious challenges, but it also received support from unexpected sources – first from physicists like Sir James Jeans and Sir Arthur Eddington and then from Kurt Gödel, thought by many to be the most original logician and mathematician of the century. Idealism’s proponents continued to struggle, but at the end of the century the movement was showing signs of returning to its roots in reflection on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anglo-American Neo-Idealism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rescher</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historically, idealists have emphasized and indeed often prioritized the role of our human mind-guided modus operandi over that of nature-at-large as basis for the philosophical understanding of ourselves and our place in the world’s scheme of things. Idealism has many versions. To begin with, there is the<italic>causal</italic>idealism that looks to the productive role of mind or spirit in the constituting of nature.¹ Then, too, there is the<italic>axiological</italic>idealism that assigns a formative role to values.² There is also the<italic>absolute</italic>idealism which, despite Hegelian kinship, found its root inspection – at least among English-speaking philosophers – in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ordinary Language Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jolley</surname>
                           <given-names>Kelly Dean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ludwig Wittgenstein revered the work of Gottlob Frege and kept tabs on the location of obscure works of Frege in the Cambridge library. J. L. Austin translated Frege’s<italic>Foundations of Arithmetic</italic>into English and made it a part of the philosophy curriculum at Oxford. I mention these facts because the tradition of Ordinary Language Philosophy (OLP) began with Frege. Frege’s three essays in his<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>, along with his ‘On Concept and Object,’ were the first essays of OLP. Beginning the story of OLP with Frege helps to bring certain features in the tradition rightly to the front: in particular,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Logical Positivism and the Vienna Circle</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hodgson</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The philosophical movement of logical positivism originated in the early 1920s with a group of philosophers and scientists who gathered around Moritz Schlick when he became professor of Philosophy at the University of Vienna – hence, the alternative designation of the Vienna Circle. Among the leading philosophers, besides Schlick, were Rudolph Carnap, Otto Neurath, Herbert Feigl, and Friedrich Waismann. Allied with the Vienna group were philosophers from the Berlin school of which Hans Reichenbach, Richard von Mises and Carl Hempel were prominent members. The group was later joined in the early 1930s by a philosopher who became its leading exponent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Naturalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loptson</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea of naturalism as a comprehensive philosophical stance is one that is widely regarded as clear, reasonably stable in intension, and tolerably well understood, whether one is an advocate or an opponent of that stance. The approximate idea is one according to which the world is a unitary causally interconnected system, without ‘gods’ or systemic ‘purposes,’ and best understood, or only rationally intelligible, by scientific means. Yet it proves quite challenging to give the idea detail and precision, with a result that won’t be bland and uncontroversial, at least for most philosophers, or with a result that won’t be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pragmatism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rescher</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pragmatism as a philosophical doctrine traces back to the Academic skeptics in classical antiquity. Denying the possibility of achieving authentic knowledge (<italic>epistēmē</italic>) regarding the real truth, they taught that we must make do with<italic>plausible information</italic>(<italic>to pithanon</italic>) adequate to the needs of practice. However, pragmatism as a determinate philosophical doctrine descends from the work of Charles Sanders Peirce. For him, pragmatism was primarily a theory of meaning, with the meaning of any concept that has application in the real world inhering in the relations that link experiential conditions of application with observable results. But by the ‘practical consequences’ of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Promise of Process Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rescher</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, ‘process philosophy’ has virtually become a code-word for the doctrines of Alfred North Whitehead and his followers. But of course, this cannot really be what process philosophy is ultimately about: if there indeed is a ‘philosophy’ of process, it must pivot not on a<italic>thinker</italic>but on a<italic>theory</italic>. What is at issue must, in the end, be a philosophical position that has a life of its own, apart from any particular exposition or expositor.</p>
                     <p>Whitehead himself fixed on ‘process’ as a central category of his philosophy because he viewed time and change as definitively central and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Metaphysics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McDermid</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin in paradox: not with philosophy, but poetry; not with the twentieth century, but the nineteenth; and not with an argument, but with a rhyming couplet. The couplet comes from the Dedication to<italic>Don Juan</italic>, where Byron mocks Coleridge’s addiction to obscure metaphysics with a quip both wry and wise: ‘Explaining metaphysics to the nation – I wish he would explain his Explanation (Byron 1824: 15–16). Byron was no philosopher; but here his wish was sound and I will honour its spirit. Before attempting to explain recent Anglophone ‘metaphysics to the nation,’ then, I shall very briefly explain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epistemology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Greco</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Epistemology has been traditionally concerned with two major questions: what is knowledge? and what can we know? These questions about the nature and scope of knowledge quickly lead to others: assuming that knowledge is superior to mere opinion, what is it that distinguishes the two? What makes knowledge ‘justified’ or ‘warranted’? A related question concerns the structure of knowledge: is knowledge like a pyramid, with a sure foundation supporting the remaining edifice? Or is knowledge more like a raft, with all parts of the structure tied together in relations of mutual support? More generally: what is the nature of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Language:</title>
                     <subtitle>1950–2000</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burge</surname>
                           <given-names>Tyler</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last half of the twentieth century in philosophy of language has seen, I hazard to say, some of the most intense and intellectually powerful discussions in any academic field during the period.¹ Yet the achievements in these areas have not been widely appreciated by the general intellectual public. This is partly because they are abstract and difficult. But it is also partly a reflection of the lamentably weak lines of communication between philosophy and the rest of culture, especially in America. In my view, this situation developed during the professionalization of philosophy in the positivist period. Indeed, positivism’s harsh</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Mind:</title>
                     <subtitle>1950–2000</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burge</surname>
                           <given-names>Tyler</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to outline some of the main developments in the philosophy of mind in the last half of the twentieth century. Behaviorism dominated psychology during approximately the same period that logical positivism dominated philosophy. The principles of behaviorism are less easily stated than those of logical positivism. It is perhaps better seen as a method that eschewed use of mentalistic vocabulary in favor of terms that made reference to dispositions to behavior. Both movements aimed at banishing nonscientific speculation, and forcing theory to hew as closely as possible to methods of confirmation. Both methodological doctrines came to be seen</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Mathematics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Avigad</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The philosophy of mathematics plays an important role in analytic philosophy, both as a subject of inquiry in its own right, and as an important landmark in the broader philosophical landscape. Mathematical knowledge has long been regarded as a paradigm of human knowledge with truths that are both necessary and certain, so giving an account of mathematical knowledge is an important part of<italic>epistemology</italic>. Mathematical objects like numbers and sets are archetypical examples of abstracta, since we treat such objects in our discourse as though they are independent of time and space; finding a place for such objects in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Logic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Mathieu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Logic originates with Aristotle and the Megaric-Stoic school in Ancient Greece but, while the logic of terms or syllogistic has acquired many accretions since, there was no real progress until the nineteenth century, when it was replaced by ‘modern’ or formal logic at the hand of mathematicians such as Boole, Schröder, Frege, and Peano. The developments that this revolution sparked throughout the last century cannot be encompassed in this chapter and only some central threads will be sketched.</p>
                     <p>Although it has sometimes been described since Frege as the pursuit of truth (Quine 1982: 1), logic is in fact the study</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Century of Transition in the Philosophy of Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Castle</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones-Imhotep</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>270</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy of science, in the past 100 years, has been propelled forward by the rapid expansion of the natural sciences, and by the coincidental rise of analytic philosophy. Many of the core issues galvanized in the philosophy of science from the 1930s through the 1960s continue to be debated – for example, the nature of causation, the realism/anti-realism controversy in science, and the intricacies of what constitutes scientific explanation.¹ Perhaps less appreciated as a trend in the philosophy of science, however, is the inclusion into the discipline of explanations and theories that have a social or sociological aspect. These issues</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Narveson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ethical theory in the twentieth-century Anglo-American philosophical world may be said to have begun with a bang, with the publication of G. E. Moore’s<italic>Principia Ethica</italic>(1903), which proclaimed that all forms of ethical naturalism are doomed to fallacy, in the form of what he famously called the ‘naturalistic fallacy.’ For this purpose, ‘naturalism’ refers to the view that we can define ethical notions, without loss of meaning, in purely naturalistic terms – terms designating properties or states of affairs whose presence can be confirmed by the methods of empirical science. Soon thereafter, identifying the ‘naturalistic fallacy,’ or, more rarely,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Political Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Neumann</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Political philosophy plays virtually no role in the early history of analytic philosophy. The most prominent political philosopher after Mill, Thomas Hill Green, had too much of Kant and Rousseau to suit the tastes of the early analytic philosophers. G. E. Moore and C. D. Broad concerned themselves with ethics, not political philosophy. Bertrand Russell went on to write political works, but they had virtually no philosophical stature or influence. But what really blocked the development of an analytic political philosophy was the rise of logical positivism and ordinary language philosophy. These movements manifested not only suspicion but contempt for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Taliaferro</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Christopherson</surname>
                           <given-names>Erik S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Analytical philosophers in the twentieth century have produced a rich literature that includes the philosophy of religious language and practice, analyses of divine attributes, arguments for and against the existence of God, and arguments over the significance of religious diversity, religious experience, and religious values. Theists, atheists, agnostics, and adherents to both Christian and nonChristian religions have engaged in a fruitful exchange on these topics with all the hallmarks of analytical philosophy: an emphasis on conceptual clarity, the use of analyses with examples and counter-examples, concentrated arguments about whether concepts of what exists (God, the soul, the afterlife) may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Donovan</surname>
                           <given-names>Josephine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>324</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The feminist engagement with the analytic tradition in the twentieth century was for the most part a contentious one. Beginning in the early 1970s – when feminist academics began applying propositions formulated in the women’s liberation political movement of the late 1960s and early 1970s to their respective intellectual fields, feminist philosophers at first used analytic methodologies and assumptions to examine feminist questions. This was not surprising, given that the dominant philosophical tradition in academic departments at the time was the analytic and that these (mostly women) philosophers had been trained in the analytic tradition. Soon, however – by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schellekens</surname>
                           <given-names>Elisabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>338</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The expression ‘Analytic Aesthetics,’ generally used to refer to Philosophical Aesthetics as pursued in the Anglo-American academic world since the middle of the twentieth century, is best understood in terms of its emphasis on conceptual analysis. The rise of the discipline is clearly related to the widespread championing of cognitive and linguistic causes that distinguishes the broader framework of Analytic Philosophy, and should not in the first instance be thought of as unveiling a hitherto buried treasure of questions and concerns. The novelty of Analytic Aesthetics had rather to do with the approach used to tackle issues about aesthetic value</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Continental Themes in Analytic Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carman</surname>
                           <given-names>Taylor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many decades academic philosophy – not only in Europe and English-speaking countries, but throughout much of the world – has regarded itself as divided between two distinct, at times competing, traditions: ‘Continental’ and ‘analytic.’ That distinction, however, is problematic in many ways.</p>
                     <p>To begin with, whereas the term ‘analytic’ is meant to describe a style or method of inquiry, ‘Continental’ refers to a large, rather vaguely defined landmass in Europe; contrasting the two seems to involve a category mistake. Of course, neither term can be taken literally: there is no single ‘analytical’ method in philosophy, just as ‘Continental’ philosophers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How to recognize Continental European Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boundas</surname>
                           <given-names>Constantin V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my introduction to the analytic philosophical tendencies in twentieth-century philosophy, I argued that the distinction between analytic and Continental philosophy is unhelpful and that it reflects only a pre-philosophical<italic>doxa</italic>whose origins are found in the national, social, economic, political, and institutional differences of the countries and the type of ‘public intellectuals’ identified with the one or the other ‘school.’ Also, in the same introduction, I introduced my view that the obstinacy with which the division has been maintained is due (to agree with Foucault) to the contingent knowledge/power nexus prevalent in different times and spaces (which also includes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Hegelian Legacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baugh</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hegel’s philosophy was renewed and transformed by twentieth-century Continental philosophy. Instead of being a conservative Idealist, Hegel emerged as a revolutionary in thought and politics, a Romantic theorist of the strivings for unity of an alienated and divided self, a thinker who anticipated Freud by attempting to subject the unconscious to rational analysis, and a ‘dramatist’ of the struggle or<italic>agon</italic>of Being itself. In Merleau-Ponty’s oft-cited words:</p>
                     <p>All the great philosophical ideas of the past century – the philosophies of Marx and Nietzsche, phenomenology, German existentialism and psychoanalysis – had their beginning in Hegel; it was he who started</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lawlor</surname>
                           <given-names>Leonard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term ‘phenomenology’ enters philosophical discourse for the first time in 1764, when J. H. Lambert uses it in his<italic>Neues Organon</italic>. In a 1770 letter to Lambert, Kant defines the term as a ‘negative science,’ presupposed by metaphysics, in which the principles of sensibility would be determined. The term remains obscure until Hegel’s 1807<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>. As in Kant, in Hegel too, phenomenology is presupposed by metaphysics but also subordinated to metaphysics; phenomenology is a part of the philosophy of spirit, which itself is a part (along with the philosophy of nature and the logic) of the encyclopedia</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grondin</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>402</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hermeneutics serves to characterize a broad current in contemporary Continental philosophy that deals with the issues of interpretation and stresses the historical and linguistic nature of our world-experience. In contemporary thought, it is mostly associated with the thinking of Hans-Georg Gadamer (1900–2002) and Paul Ricoeur (1913–2005), who situate themselves in the hermeneutic tradition of thinkers such as Wilhelm Dilthey (1833–1911) and Martin Heidegger (1889–1976). All these authors unfolded a distinct<italic>philosophical</italic>understanding of hermeneutics that drew on the more ancient tradition of hermeneutics, which was traditionally understood as an art of interpretation (<italic>ars hermeneutica, Auslegungslehre</italic>) that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Existentialism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McBride</surname>
                           <given-names>William L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word ‘existentialism’ became widely used to identify a major movement of twentieth-century thought during the mid-1940s, immediately following the end of World War II. It had, it is true, already been employed by some philosophers: Gabriel Marcel, a committed Christian thinker, had made use of the language of existentialism in the 1920s; the Italian Nicola Abbagnano had elaborated a version of it in his<italic>La struttura dell’esistenza</italic>(1939); and in the form of<italic>Existenzphilosophie</italic>, for which ‘existential philosophy’ was regarded by many as the most suitable English translation, it had been appropriated by both Martin Heidegger and Karl Jaspers.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Marxisms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wernick</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taking as my point of departure the (re)constitution of a ‘Western,’ as opposed to Soviet Marxism in the first decades of the twentieth century, my aim in the following remarks is to trace, and reflect upon, some of that tradition’s main lines of development. An account of modern Marxism that omits developments to the East, ignores its relation to anti-colonial struggles, and limits itself mainly to Europe, is no doubt ethnocentric. It has the benefit however – beyond sheer convenience – of directing us to examine what has happened to Marxism on its intellectual home ground. Since my concern here</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Frankfurt School and Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kellner</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>444</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term ‘Frankfurt School’ refers to the work of members of the<italic>Institut für Sozialforschung</italic>(Institute for Social Research) which was established in Frankfurt, Germany, in 1923 as the first Marxist-oriented research centre affiliated with a major German university. Under its director, Carl Grünberg, the institute’s work in the 1920s tended to be empirical, historical, and oriented towards problems of the European working-class movement. (On the Frankfurt School, see the readers edited by Arato and Gebhardt 1978 and Bronner and Kellner 1989, and the critical studies in Jay 1973, Kellner 1989, and Wiggerhaus 1994.)</p>
                     <p>Under the directorship of Max Horkheimer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Psychoanalysis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zupancic</surname>
                           <given-names>Alenka</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>457</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this chapter is exclusively on Sigmund Freud’s discoveries and theoretical propositions and on Jacques Lacan’s ‘return to Freud’ in his stunning enterprise, in which he cast psychoanalysis on the centre stage of contemporary philosophical debate. The presentation of the theoretical insights of Freud and Lacan follows the thread of two major concepts, that of the unconscious and that of the drive (or sexuality), while trying to indicate the way in which other crucial concepts enter into their scope or follow from them.</p>
                     <p>From the very beginning, psychoanalysis was surrounded by debates about whether its scope lay more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Structuralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dosse</surname>
                           <given-names>François</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>469</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Broadly speaking, the term ‘structure’ has functioned as a password for many human sciences and provided them with a unified program. Where does the concept ‘structuralism’ come from, that caused so much passion and opprobrium? The term initially had an architectural sense deriving from ‘structure,’ which designated the manner in which an edifice is built. (<italic>Dictionaire de Trévoux</italic>, edition of 1771) During the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, the meaning of the term ‘structure’ was modified and enlarged by analogy with living beings: language, for Vaugelas and Bernot, is like the construction that Fontenelle attributes to a man’s body. Following this,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Discourse about Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schrag</surname>
                           <given-names>Calvin O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discourse about difference, as it plays itself out in the philosophical arena, has been on the table for some time. It is not a philosophical topic of recent date. Questions about the role of discourse about difference extend all the way back to the beginnings of Western philosophy, and there is a substantial literature that testifies of difference as a topic that elicited attention in the Eastern philosophy and religion of more distant times. It would appear to be an issue that resides at the very core of philosophical reflection both past and present.</p>
                     <p>A mark of the trade of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Different/ciations:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Gilles Deleuze</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boundas</surname>
                           <given-names>Constantin V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophies of difference, where difference holds its ground without being subordinated to identity, are exceedingly rare. It is not by chance that the fortunes of philosophical heterologies are better served inside process philosophies. Although to be a process philosopher is not a guarantee that one will also be a philosopher of pure difference, movement and the reflection on movement that constitute the raison d’être of the philosophies of process offer a rich soil for the nurture of difference. But a process philosophy, in order to support a purely heterological thought, has to be capable of doing without subjects steering the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postmodernism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Scott</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>504</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I begin this chapter, I confess to having reservations about the term, ‘postmodernism.’ My reservations have less to do with the philosophical irrelevance of the term that some scholars have alleged, and more with the suffix, -<italic>ism</italic>; the ways of thinking and writing that ‘postmodern’ names are characterized by departures from thought that is governed by categories and their classifications. This tradition emerged in part as a critique of the ability of categorical thinking to recognize and address appropriately many of the perceptions, processes of thought, experiences, and things that we encounter. This chapter will discuss alternatives to such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Essay on the Overcoming of Metaphysics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lawlor</surname>
                           <given-names>Leonard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>517</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Life by itself does not constitute a ‘twentieth-century philosophy.’ But it amounted to a constant theme throughout the twentieth century since European philosophers in particular continuously appropriate and transform the concept of life. So, after the nineteenth-century philosophies of vitalism and<italic>Lebensphilosophie</italic>, two major philosophical movements centering on the concept of life – Bergsonism and Husserlian phenomenology – dominated European philosophy up to the end of the 1920s. However, in 1927, Heidegger published his<italic>Being and Time</italic>. Heidegger himself told us that<italic>Being and Time</italic>was written out of the experience of the ‘forgetfulness of being’ in Western metaphysics (Heidegger</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morris</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>531</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most distinctive feature of philosophy of mind in the Continental tradition is that for the most part there has been no such thing. While the Continental tradition richly contributes to the study of mind, it has not considered the topic a separate department of philosophy. Indeed, the Continental tradition’s foremost results challenge typical projects of philosophy of mind.</p>
                     <p>The reasons for this are three Continental tendencies. First, the tendency is to begin all philosophical study by scrutinizing the philosophizing subject, philosophical method, and the conceptual prejudices of philosophy. Study of what amounts to mind becomes inseparable from ontology, epistemology,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Babich</surname>
                           <given-names>Babette E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>545</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Continental philosophies of science tend to exemplify holistic themes connecting order and contingency, questions and answers, writers and readers, speakers and hearers. Such philosophies of science also tend to feature a fundamental emphasis on the historical and cultural situatedness of discourse as significant; relevance of mutual attunement of speaker and hearer; necessity of pre-linguistic cognition based in human engagement with a common socio-cultural historical world; role of narrative and metaphor as explanatory; sustained emphasis on understanding questioning; truth seen as horizonal, aletheic, or perspectival; and a tolerance for paradoxical and complex forms of expression.</p>
                     <p>Philosophy of science in the Continental</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Raffoul</surname>
                           <given-names>François</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>559</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The development of many ethical theories in the twentieth-century Continental tradition has taken place against the background of Nietzsche’s celebrated critique of morality, as well as in response to the Holocaust and the unprecedented horrors of the century. While there have been many noteworthy developments in the areas of feminist ethics, the ‘discourse ethics’ of Habermas, and the work of the later Foucault, we will focus within the confines of this chapter on Nietzsche, Sartre, Heidegger, Levinas, and Derrida, as representative works in Continental philosophies of ethics.</p>
                     <p>Nietzsche’s attacks on morality have often been described as a nihilistic enterprise of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Political Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ingram</surname>
                           <given-names>David B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Protevi</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>570</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Political philosophy as usually conceived has two branches. On the one hand, it addresses the concerns of already established political life: the moral justification of political authority, the limits of power in maintaining that authority, the rights and duties of citizens with respect to that power, and other such topics. On the other hand, it also addresses the ontology of political life: the basic concepts of human plurality, living in common in ordered societies, freedom, sovereignty, and the like. Continental political philosophers tend to deal with these topics somewhat differently from their Anglo-American (or analytic) counterparts. By and large, Continental</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminist Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Angelova</surname>
                           <given-names>Emilia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>590</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Continental feminist philosophy is a movement of thought unified by the theme of the difference of woman and the difference of the feminine. But it is by no means monolithic in method or content. It begins with Simone de Beauvoir’s existentialist feminism in the 1940s. For de Beauvoir, the free transcendence of the ‘independent woman’ wrests her from linear history and orients her to something more than equal rights for man and woman, something more than egalitarian ideals. With May 1968 a new phase of French feminist theory began, bringing along with it aesthetic experiences, influences from deconstruction, psychoanalysis and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philosophy of Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Westphal</surname>
                           <given-names>Merold</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>603</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of Continental philosophy of religion is reflection on faith (as response to revelation) and reason (as philosophical reflection). Having made the linguistic turn, it intersects with analytic discussion of the problem of religious language, at least if the question is understood as concerning the nature and limits of our God-talk rather than its warrant. Since philosophy often takes the form of phenomenology, the question can be put this way: does reason, so conceived, prescribe the limits within which our Godtalk must stay (as in Kant’s<italic>Religion Within the Limits of Reason Alone</italic>), or does it describe the limits that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davey</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>615</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whitehead described Western philosophy as a footnote to Plato’s. As recent philosophical tradition has shown, some footnotes have established texts of their own. Aesthetics is one such footnote. Whereas Plato banished aesthetics to the realm of<italic>doxa</italic>, Continental philosophy stands witness since the late nineteenth century to a renaissance of aesthetic thought. Now, not only has the discipline achieved a philosophical autonomy but aesthetics has come to haunt those philosophies that marginalize the apparent and the subjective. If earlier forms of aesthetics feted order, recent forms of twentieth-century Continental philosophy are attracted to the sublime and its disruptive power. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Analytic Themes in Continental Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>May</surname>
                           <given-names>Todd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before I started my graduate work in Continental philosophy at Penn State in the mid-1980s, I took several courses in analytic philosophy at the University of Pittsburgh. I recall a particular evening before class, overhearing one graduate student tell another that she had just read some Foucault and had found him to be interesting, except that he was a terrible writer. I was irritated at the swipe at Foucault’s prose, particularly coming from someone enrolled in a program whose mainstay was Wilfrid Sellars. In retrospect, however, the scene takes on a different hue. Rather than seeing it as just another</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Indian Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dalvi</surname>
                           <given-names>Rohit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>645</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At least since Hegel, Indian thought has been excluded from the proper domain of philosophy. Despite the vigorous affirmation by the German Romantics of the value of Sanskrit poetry and literature, and the celebration by philologists like Max Mueller of the cultural and linguistic proximity of Sanskritic civilization to Europe, the European philosophical tradition, with perhaps the exception of Schopenhauer, has rejected the idea of an Indian ‘philosophy.’ Classical Indian ‘philosophy’ was not regarded as at par, in terms of rigor and rationality, with the products of European civilization. Indian thinking was devalued as being thoroughly religious in character or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chinese Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ames</surname>
                           <given-names>Roger T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>661</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mainstream philosophy in the twentieth century has been Anglo-European philosophy. This observation is as true in Tokyo, Seoul, Beijing, Delhi, Nairobi, as it is in Boston London, Paris, and Frankfurt. That is, the indigenous philosophies of East Asia, South Asia, Africa, and indeed America too have been marginalized within their own cultural sites by the dominance of what has been called the Anglo-European analytic and Continental traditions of philosophy. It is within this historical framework that we must distinguish clearly between ‘philosophy in China’ on the one hand, and ‘Chinese philosophy’ on the other.</p>
                     <p>In some academic quarters the important</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Japanese Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carter</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>675</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may be that the most striking and penetrating cross-cultural philosophical exploration of the twentieth century originated in Japan. Nishida Kitaro (1870–1945) and the ‘Kyoto School’ had as their focal purpose the establishing of a dialogue of quality between traditional Eastern ways of thinking and the long established philosophical traditions of the West. Japan had isolated itself from nearly all possible external influences for two and a half centuries, and it was the American captain, William Perry, who forcibly opened Japan to the outside world once more in 1854. It was not a change that was entered into willingly,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>African Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Janz</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>689</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>African philosophy’s development in the twentieth century is both relatively recent, traceable to some seminal texts, and ancient, drawing on cultural forms that stretch back in time and space. This seeming contradiction can be understood if we realize that philosophy itself is ambiguous. It designates on one hand a set of reflective practices rooted in culture and reason, which rigorously and critically explicate a life-world, and on the other a discipline in the university, with a set of codes, standards, recognized practitioners, and customs. More than almost any other site of philosophy, African philosophy has struggled with the similarities and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>703</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chronology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>713</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09xfc.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>729</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
