<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kw28k1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX350 .B873 2018</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Liturgics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Orthodox Eastern Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Doctrines</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shmeman, Aleksandr, 1921–1983</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ricoeur, Paul</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Liturgical Theology after Schmemann</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Orthodox Reading of Paul Ricoeur</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Butcher</surname>
               <given-names>Brian A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Louth</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823278275</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823278299</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823278298</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xzh13v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While only rarely reflecting explicitly on liturgy, French philosopher Paul Ricoeur (1913-2005) gave sustained attention to several themes pertinent to the interpretation of worship, including metaphor, narrative, subjectivity, and memory. Inspired by his well-known aphorism, "The symbol gives rise to thought," Liturgical Theology after Schmemann offers an original exploration of the symbolic world of the Byzantine Rite , culminating in a Ricoeurian analysis of its Theophany "Great Blessing of Water." .</p>
         <p>The book examines two fundamental questions: 1) what are the implications of the philosopher's oeuvre for liturgical theology at large? And 2)how does the adoption of a Ricoeurian hermeneutic shape the study of a particular rite? Taking the seminal legacy of Orthodox theologian Alexander Schmemann (1921-1983) as its point of departure, Butcher contributes to the renewal of contemporary Eastern Christian thought and ritual practice by engaging a spectrum of current theological and philosophical conversations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Louth</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is generally recognized that “liturgical theology,” as a notion or a discipline, owes its existence to the great Orthodox theologian of the last century, Fr. Alexander Schmemann. Liturgical theology, as Fr. Alexander understood it, is distinct from liturgiology, the study of the history and development of liturgical rites through (primarily) liturgical texts, and from a theology of liturgy, understood as a fundamental dimension of theology of worship. Both these disciplines are impor tant—indeed liturgical theology depends upon them—but liturgical theology, as Fr. Alexander understood it, is theology derived from, or validated by, the liturgical practice of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Several years ago, Pantelis Kalaitzidis issued a clarion call to fellow Orthodox theologians to renew their dialogue with con temporary philosophy, lamenting that such an enterprise has in recent times been commonly held in disfavor in the Christian East—a perhaps unintended result, he suggests, of the twentieth-century “neo-patristic synthesis” promoted by the renowned Georges Florovsky (1893–1979). In “From the ‘Return to the Fathers’ to the Need for a Modern Orthodox Theology” Kalaitzidis cites approvingly the following exhortation of Alexander Schmemann (1921–83):</p>
                     <p>Orthodox theology must keep its patristic foundations, but it must also go “beyond” the Fathers if</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>“After Schmemann”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Introducing Ricoeur into the Conversation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We may begin with the commonplace premise that in Orthodox tradition the primary meaning of theology has been taken to be<italic>prayer</italic>itself—the knowledge and experience of God acquired through participating in a relationship with him. Only secondarily does it imply (as the etymology indicates) “words<italic>about</italic>God.”¹ Hence the notion of<italic>liturgical</italic>theology, the<italic>theologia prima</italic>discussed above, whose elaboration was, of course, the goal of Fr. Alexander Schmemann’s life work.² It is no exaggeration to say that for him the liturgy itself is the fundamental object of interpretation. Regarding Schmemann’s approach to the Eucharist, for example, Peter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Western Perspectives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we set the stage for a Ricoeurian reading of liturgy: After considering the centrality of the Church’s<italic>lex orandi</italic>within the Orthodox Weltanschauung, we explored the potential role of philosophy in further developing a liturgical theology “after Schmemann.” We also probed the challenges of integrating stereo typically Western forms of thought into Eastern Christian reflection, concluding that although liturgy figures as a sine qua non in Orthodox thinking, it is yet in need of being subjected to a hermeneutical analysis. The next step of our inquiry will be to situate the appropriation of Ricoeur hitherto by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Meaning in/and Metaphor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this chapter and the next is the functioning of religious language and the role played therein by metaphor. The task is to consider the properties by which metaphor undertakes the “redescription of reality” with which Ricoeur credits it. To navigate this major current in his thought, we will proceed in three stages. In this chapter, we introduce the “linguistic turn” and then follow the course of Ricoeur’s exegetical works to gain an appreciation of how his general theory of metaphoricity relates specifically to religious discourse: that is, the way in which the scriptural naming of God functions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>At the Intersection of the Via Positiva and the Via Negativa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we extend the preceding discussion of metaphor by focusing on the question of the kind of<italic>truth</italic>communicated in metaphorical utterance. Given the primacy of metaphor in liturgical speech, this question is of particular importance. Dialogue with several interlocutors will set up our concluding consideration of how Byzantine worship characteristically combines kataphatic and apophatic forms of discourse—resulting in a peculiar approach to naming (and experiencing) God.</p>
                     <p>In exploring the world of a poetic text, Ricoeur’s colleague David Tracy suggests that one confronts a “forgotten notion of truth: truth as manifestation.” Crediting Heidegger with its rediscovery amd</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>“The Summoned Subject”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we trace the shape of liturgical subjectivity, employing the template provided by Ricoeur in his later works, especially<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>and<italic>The Course of Recognition</italic>. The focus here will be on the nature of human capability itself, as fulfilled within a liturgical context; having reflected in previous chapters on the polyphony of liturgical language and symbolism, we must now consider the kind of self that may respond to such “music.” The subsequent chapters will afford the opportunity to examine the way in which the capable subject experiences the configuration of memory through the work of liturgy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Truth as Attestation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As has by now become evident, Ricoeur approaches questions of selfhood via the “long route” of symbols, metaphors, and narratives. There is no a priori grasping of truth—although there is an intuitive guess in its regard—but only the arduous path of the imaginative exploration of, and eventual ontological validation of, possible worlds.¹ This dual sense of description of a world of meaning and subscription to it in the form of a corresponding way of life is conveyed by the notion of truth as “attestation.” In the first part of this chapter, therefore, we further probe<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Liturgical Time, Narrative, Memory, and History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I propose a Ricoeurian approach to the mnemonic operations animating the ritual process—implicit though they may be. Specifically, through an investigation of several key sections of his magisterial antepenultimate work,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>(henceforth,<italic>MHF</italic>), we will come to apprehend the complexity of the liturgical act construed as a quintessential form of “remembering.” In order to bring into relief certain elements of<italic>MHF</italic>that will prove germane to our intended liturgical application, we will first enter into a recent debate concerning the role of history (and historiography) in liturgical theology: The resolution of this debate (or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Manifestation and Proclamation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we will finally endeavor to apply the insights acquired from our reading of Ricoeur to the interpretation of a particular liturgical rite—namely, the Byzantine tradition’s “Great Blessing of Water” (<italic>GBW</italic>) to which we have hitherto referred only obliquely. Following a brief description of the service, I provide a historical overview of its development. Then I offer an analysis according to the threefold schema proposed in Parts II and III above, treating in turn the rite’s metaphors and symbols, its models of subjectivity and, finally, its dynamics of mnemonic transformation.</p>
                     <p>Before proceeding any further, it will be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Inspired by Ricoeur’s well-known aphorism “The symbol gives rise to thought,” this book has engaged the symbolic manifold of the Byzantine Rite, and specifically its Theophany “Great Blessing of Water,” by means of Ricoeur’s own hermeneutical philosophy. It has sought to make a contribution to Orthodox liturgical theology, inspired by the legacy of Schmemann, through whom I first discovered the power of a Weltanschauung grounded in the worship of the Church. While respecting Schmemann, I have sought to go “beyond” him by questioning, at various removes, what it means to “seek in the liturgy the vision implied in its own</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Service of the Great Blessing of the Waters”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xzh13v.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
