<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX3701.5 .E97 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jesuits</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Exploring Jesuit Distinctiveness</book-title>
         <subtitle>Interdisciplinary Perspectives on Ways of Proceeding within the Society of Jesus</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Maryks</surname>
               <given-names>Robert Aleksander</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789004313354</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>BRILL</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LEIDEN; BOSTON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Editor and Authors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1163/j.ctt1w76ttq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The volume theme is the distinctiveness of Jesuits and their ministries. It explores the<italic>quidditas Jesuitica</italic>, or the specifically Jesuit way(s) of proceeding in which Jesuits and their colleagues operated from historical, geographical, social, and cultural perspectives. Thanks to generous support of the Institute for Advanced Jesuit Studies at Boston College</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures and Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VIII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maryks</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert Aleksander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following twelve essays are a selection of papers presented at the first International Symposium on Jesuit Studies held at Boston College’s Institute for Advanced Jesuit Studies in June 2015. The symposium theme was the distinctiveness of Jesuits and their ministries. The participants explored the<italic>quidditas jesuitica</italic>, or the specifically Jesuit way(s) of proceeding in which Jesuits and their colleagues operated from historical, geographical, social, and cultural perspectives. They asked whether there was an essential core of distinctive elements that characterize the way in which Jesuits lived their religious vocation and conducted their various works and how these ways of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Francesco Benci and the Origins of Jesuit Neo-Latin Epic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gwynne</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Quinque martyres e Societate Iesu in India</italic>(Venice: Muschius, 1591) by Francesco Benci, S.J. (1542–94), professor of rhetoric at the Collegium Romanum, is a remarkable poem for many reasons, not least because it is the first poem of a new genre: the Jesuit epic.¹ The six-book poem centers upon the first Jesuit mission to India (1580–83) and culminates in the journey of five Jesuits led by Rodolfo Acquaviva (1550–83) to the province of Salcete in the summer of 1583; their attempt to found a new church; their subsequent martyrdom in a local riot; and reception into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Exploring the Distinctiveness of Neo-Latin Jesuit Didactic Poetry in Naples:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Nicolò Partenio Giannettasio</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schindler</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Jesuit Nicolò Partenio Giannettasio (1648–1715) was one of the most intriguing and influential authors of seventeenth-century Naples.¹ Born in 1648, in Parthenope (i.e., Naples), as he used to call his home city, he entered the Jesuit order at the age of sixteen, having lost his family during the plague of 1656. Like other members of the Society of Jesus, Giannettasio was a highly educated man with a wide range of interests: he studied Scholastic philosophy at Palermo, taught mathematics at the Collegio Massimo in Naples for more than ten years, traveled in Egypt,² and designed the Santa Maria</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Civic Education on Stage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Civic Values and Virtues in the Jesuit Schools of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rzegocka</surname>
                           <given-names>Jolanta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Jesuit order and its theater have played a vital part in the history of Europe and its cultural heritage.¹ Ever since the founding of the Society in 1540, the Jesuits have been active preachers, distinguished theologians and disputants, and have served as confessors and tutors to sovereigns and members of royal families across Christendom.² However, it is the order’s emphasis on education and the Jesuits’ role as teachers that put the activities of the Society at the heart of the present chapter. Jesuit colleges modeled after their prominent school, the Collegium Romanum (1551), offered a combination of high-quality teaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>“Ask the Jesuits to Send Verses from Rome”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Society’s Networks and the European Dissemination of Devotional Music</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Filippi</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniele V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1581, Philippe de Monte (1521–1603), the chapel-master of Emperor Rudolf ii (r.1576–1612) of Habsburg, published his first book of spiritual madrigals (<italic>Il primo libro de’ madrigali spirituali a cinque voci</italic>) in Venice. He dedicated it to the newly elected superior general of the Society of Jesus, Claudio Acquaviva (1543–1615), and in the dedicatory letter—printed, as was customary, at the beginning of each partbook—he explained why. “When the news came that Your Reverend Fatherhood had been elected with broad consensus Superior-General of your most holy order, it seemed to me, that, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Priestly Violence, Martyrdom, and Jesuits:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Diego de Alfaro (Paraguay, 1639)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Redden</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of what makes a Jesuit, the<italic>quidditas jesuitica</italic>, is thrown into stark relief by the extraordinary case of Diego de Alfaro (d.1639) and its apologia, written in 1644 by the former provincial of the Paraguayan province, Diego de Boroa (d.1657).² Alfaro—superior of the missions of Guairá in the province of Paraguay—took up arms in 1639 and fought alongside his Guarani faithful against<italic>bandeirantes</italic>(slave raiders) from the Portuguese city of São Paulo; in the gunfight with these slavers, Alfaro was killed. Portuguese and Spanish detractors of the Society alike decried the scandal of a priest under</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Colonial Theodicy and the Jesuit Ascetic Ideal in José de Acosta’s Works on Spanish America</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Green</surname>
                           <given-names>Bryan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter aims to demonstrate the centrality of the problem of theodicy in José de Acosta’s (1540–1600) scientific, ethnographic, and historical writings on Spanish America.¹ Based on Acosta’s experience as the Jesuit provincial of Peru and his active participation in the political and ecclesiastical reforms initiated under the viceroy Francisco de Toledo (1515–82), these works bear witness to the moral evils running rampant among his fellow Spaniards and the concomitant suffering inflicted upon the indigenous population.² While Acosta recognizes the moral evil at the root of Spanish sovereignty, namely greed in the ruthless pursuit of precious metals, his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Purple Silk and Black Cotton:</title>
                     <subtitle>Francisco Cabral and the Negotiation of Jesuit Attire in Japan (1570–73)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>D’Ortia</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda Zampol</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On September 10, 1573, Francisco Cabral (1533–1609), superior of the Jesuit mission in Japan, informed the superior general in Rome (Francisco de Borja [1510–72], who had already died by that time) that the ship of Visitor Gonçalo Álvares (1527–73) had sunk in front of the port of Nagasaki, with immense loss of lives and funds. At least the state of the Japanese mission was finally acceptable:</p>
                     <p>Thanks to God’s goodness, there is no small improvement [in the situation of the mission], especially in the matter of the silks, that the fathers wore, and the other luxuries they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Pedro de Ribadeneyra’s Vida del P. Ignacio de Loyola (1583) and Literary Culture in Early Modern Spain</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roldán-Figueroa</surname>
                           <given-names>Rady</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On June 23, 1584, Fray Luis de Granada (1504–88) wrote a letter to his friend, Pedro de Ribadeneyra (1526–1611), exalting the latter’s literary qualities, including the candor of his prose.¹ Writing from Lisbon, the prolific Dominican was moved to write in a spirit of gratitude and admiration after reading Ribadeneyra’s<italic>Vida del P. Ignacio de Loyola, fundador de la Compañía de Jesus</italic>(1583).² In the letter, he expressed the deepest admiration for Ribadeneyra’s style and clarity. He also commended his Jesuit counterpart for his balanced account of the origins of the Society of Jesus as well as for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>The Distinctiveness of the Society of Jesus’s Mission in Pedro de Ribadeneyra’s Historia ecclesiastica del schisma del reyno de Inglaterra (1588)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weinreich</surname>
                           <given-names>Spencer J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Two more private and particular considerations encouraged me in the work. The first, that I am a Spaniard; the second, that I am a priest of the Society of Jesus.”¹ Such was the explanation offered by the priest and scholar Pedro de Ribadeneyra (1526–1611) for the production of the<italic>Historia eclesiastica del scisma del reyno de Inglaterra</italic>(henceforth, the “<italic>Historia</italic>”), his polemical account of the English Reformation. Troublingly, virtually all scholarship on the<italic>Historia</italic>has concentrated on the former factor, to the detriment of our appreciation of the latter. This chapter, and my larger project of an annotated translation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Discerning Skills:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psychological Insight at the Core of Jesuit Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Casalini</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristiano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ability to examine talents is one of the key features that continue to distinguish the Jesuits in a large number of fields today. The mission statements of many educative institutions run by the Society all around the world, such as schools and universities, insist on the cultivation of students’ skills and talents as a hallmark of their excellence. Yet, this characteristic goes beyond the boundaries of the ministry of education, for it involves many other tenets of the Jesuit identity.</p>
                     <p>The Society adopted this key feature of its program during the first fifty years of the order’s inception, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Distinctive Contours of Jesuit Enlightenment in France</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Due largely to their persecution of more radical strains of Enlightenment that emerged from Diderot’s editorship of the<italic>Encyclopédie</italic>, many historians have too commonly neglected the important contributions of French Jesuit scholars to eighteenth-century culture. The distinctiveness of French Jesuit contributions to scholarship during the century of Enlightenment is the subject of this chapter. This chapter also emphasizes some of the ways in which the radicalization of the eighteenth-century French<italic>siècle de lumières</italic>—specifically its strains of atheism and materialism—were ironically shaped, however accidentally and indeed unintentionally, by debates already well underway among Jesuit intellectuals themselves.¹ Accordingly, this chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>One Century of Science:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Jesuit Journal Brotéria (1902–2002)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Romeiras</surname>
                           <given-names>Francisco Malta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leitão</surname>
                           <given-names>Henrique</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For historians of science, one of the most distinctive features of the Society of Jesus was its dedication to science and scientific education, especially when compared with other religious orders. The Jesuits’ contributions to early modern science have been studied extensively and are now widely known, lending further credence to George Sarton’s (1884–1956) dictum that “one cannot study the history of mathematics in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries without coming across Jesuits at every corner.”¹ Fifty years later, in his book on the history of electricity in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, John Heilbron (1934–) echoed this assertion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w76ttq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
