<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr68m</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Rigor of Things</book-title>
         <subtitle>Conversations with Dan Arbib</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marion</surname>
               <given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gschwandtner</surname>
               <given-names>Christina M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tracy</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823275762</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275786</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823275787</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr68m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In a series of conversations, Jean-Luc Marion reconstructs a career's path in the history of philosophy, theology, and phenomenology. Discussing such concepts as the event, the gift, and the saturated phenomenon, Marion elaborates the rigor displayed by the things themselves. He discusses the major stages of his work and offers his views on the forces that have driven his thought.</p>
         <p>The conversation ranges from Marion's engagement with Descartes, to phenomenology and theology, to Marion's intellectual and biographical backgrounds, concluding with illuminating insights on the state of the Catholic Church today and on Judeo-Christian dialogue. Marion also reflects on the relationship of philosophy to history, theology, aesthetics, and literature. At the same time, the book provides an account of French intellectual life in the late twentieth century.</p>
         <p>In these interviews, Marion's language is more conversational than in his formal writing, but it remains serious and substantive. The book serves as an excellent and comprehensive introduction to Marion's thought and work.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tracy</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is hardly necessary to introduce Professor Jean-Luc Marion to this audience, since he has become a very important interlocutor in North America for over twenty years. However, the occasion of the English translation of these fascinating interviews is a good time to remind ourselves of some of his accomplishments in philosophy, intellectual history, and, more recently, theology.</p>
                     <p>First philosophy. There is no doubt that Jean-Luc Marion is the foremost living phenomenologist. Not only has he continued the great tradition of Husserl, Heidegger, Levinas, Henry, Ricoeur, and others, but Marion has advanced that tradition in major ways, especially through his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TRANSLATOR’S NOTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>My Path</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Jean-Luc Marion, what would you say if you had to summarize in a few comments the meaning of the philosophical work that has prompted you along the course of your career?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>This question already gives rise to a paradox, for one really carries on a philosophical project without knowing what prompts it, or even precisely because one does not know it. In a sense, I have never had the impression that I knew where I was going, and I have never started a philosophical undertaking, such as a book or an article, being sure of where I was going or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Descartes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>You have devoted three large books to Descartes:</italic>On Descartes’ Grey Ontology<italic>in 1975</italic>, On Descartes’ White Theology<italic>in 1981, and</italic>On Descartes’ Metaphysical Prism<italic>in 1986. To this we should add several dozen articles gathered together in</italic>Cartesian Questions I<italic>and</italic>II<italic>(a third volume is planned) and a final book</italic>, On Descartes’ Passive Thought.¹<italic>Until recently you directed the Centre d’études cartésiennes [Center for Cartesian Studies], and you retired from the Sorbonne while you were holding the chair for the history of modern philosophy. Why Descartes? What brought you to this author?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>First of all, a point deserves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>You completed your great cycle on Descartes with</italic>On Descartes’ Metaphysical Prism<italic>in 1986 [published in English in 1999]. In 1989 you published</italic>Reduction and Givenness<italic>[published in English in 1998], which is a collection of essays on Husserl’s and Heidegger’s phenomenology</italic>.¹<italic>In a sense, this book has produced paradoxical results. Although it claimed to be an erudite study in the history of Husserl’s and Heidegger’s phenomenology, it gave rise to important reactions, as if you had hit upon something absolutely central that could not but elicit reservations from several phenomenologists. What led you to phenomenology after your work on</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Idol and Distance<italic>straightaway opens a theological path in your work</italic>.¹<italic>Besides Bernard-Henri Lévy’s request, how did this book come to be?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Idol and Distance</italic>was written very quickly in 1976, although it relied on material already worked out over several years, especially arguments that had been put to the test in articles published in<italic>Résurrection</italic>during the years 1970 through 1973. In this sense, then, it was an occasional book, but it tackled a haunting or even stubborn problem, one that occupied me and many others for years—the question of the “death of God.” I ended up approaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>A Matter of Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>You have said that one can do history of philosophy without doing philosophy at the same time. In what sense can the history of philosophy itself be “philosophizing”?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>That’s a huge question to which I should return in a more explicit manner some day. Without waiting for that, one can at least point out that, while one can easily write a history of philosophy as a simple appendix to the history of ideas (a thing that is entirely possible; many do it), this raises at least one difficulty: When the history of philosophy is turned into the history of<italic>philosophical</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr68m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The World as It Runs—and as It Doesn’t</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>You stayed comparatively discreet in the media for your entire career, until you started appearing in it, especially when you were elected to the Académie française. Was this discretion deliberate, calculated, or completely unintentional?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Did I stay discreet enough? At least I hope so, but hearing journalists or interviewers point this out to me at the start of every published or broadcast interview, I start to doubt it. If there was discretion, it was in fact voluntary because I had the luck (if one can call it that) to engage the media very early, on the occasion of the publication</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
