<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DT39.W53 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Red Sea Region</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Red Sea</book-title>
         <subtitle>In Search of Lost Space</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wick</surname>
               <given-names>Alexis</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780520285910</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520961265</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520961269</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oakland, California</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt19633g6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Red Sea has, from time immemorial, been one of the world's most navigated spaces, in the pursuit of trade, pilgrimage and conquest. Yet this multidimensional history remains largely unrevealed by its successive protagonists. Intrigued by the absence of a holistic portrayal of this body of water and inspired by Fernand Braudel's famous work on the Mediterranean, this book brings alive a dynamic Red Sea world across time, revealing the particular features of a unique historical actor. In capturing this heretofore lost space, it also presents a critical, conceptual history of the sea, leading the reader into the heart of Eurocentrism. The Sea, it is shown, is a vital element of the modern philosophy of history.Alexis Wick is not satisfied with this inclusion of the Red Sea into history and attendant critique of Eurocentrism. Contrapuntally, he explores how the world and the sea were imagined differently before imperial European hegemony. Searching for the lost space of Ottoman visions of the sea,<italic>The Red Sea</italic>makes a deeper argument about the discipline of history and the historian's craft.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTE ON TRANSLATION AND TRANSLITERATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>History at Sea: Space and the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This dictum evokes a famous verse in the Quran, which affirms that “every living thing is made of water” (<italic>wa jaʿalnā min al-māʾi kulla shayʾ in ḥayyin,</italic>21:30); it is implicit in Genesis I, where the earth and the heavens are created by a division of the waters; it forms a basic truth claim in modern astronomical science, so that the mere presence of water on a planet may be a sign of life; it is found in many creation myths and much common sense. Thales, who launched the great adventure of Greek philosophy, also affirmed as much. There is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Place in the Middle:</title>
                     <subtitle>A GEOHISTORY OF THE RED SEA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though it was once an object of great scholarly debate, few people ask any more what is meant by “the Red Sea” or why it is so called. There is scant curiosity regarding the potentialities attached to the name, even though long ago already Marcel Proust most evocatively demonstrated that the name of a place is a convoluted and significant matter.¹</p>
                     <p>The now seemingly established explanation for the origin of the name “Red” (that it derives from the common ancient practice of assigning particular colors to the different cardinal points) is charming in its simplicity,² but it fails to take</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Thalassology alla Turca:</title>
                     <subtitle>SIX THESES ON THE PHILOSOPHY OF HISTORY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AS A MODERN FIELD OF study, Ottoman historiography is unusual, primarily because of its ambivalent relation to that hegemon of hyper-reality, Europe—finding and placing itself both within and without. For much of its existence, the Ottoman Empire was dominated (demographically, economically, politically, ideologically) by its provinces in regions considered now geographically as part of Europe. This is something Ottoman authors oft en remarked upon when discussing the divisions of European geography, which the Well-Protected Domains straddled.</p>
                     <p>Indeed, as mentioned above, the fountainhead of disciplined history, Leopold von Ranke himself, who was explicit in associating history with European identity, included</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Self-Portrait of the Ottoman Red Sea, June 21, 1777</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE APPROACH that sees space, not as the foundational objective setting for the unraveling of time, but rather as a multitude of discursively constituted and lived places and landscapes, each with a poetics, a history, and a sense of its own, this chapter affirms the potentiality of alternative geohistorical compositions, governed by a different grammar than that of objective space and time.¹ If the Red Sea was invented only in the early nineteenth century as a scientific object, and if Ottoman public discourse did not frame the area in terms of that category before the 1850s, then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Scientific Invention of the Red Sea</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE RED SEA WAS CAPTURED textually before any of its shores were subjected to enduring colonial control, though this was executed in the context of a rapidly expanding British dominance over the region in particular, and the globe more largely. Just as the Crown’s navy was gaining greater and greater control of the Indian Ocean, so too did it seek to reinforce its position in the Mediterranean.¹ It was only logical for the connecting Red Sea to be appropriated as well.</p>
                     <p>Clearly printed, easily accessible, and widely reproduced, the<italic>Sailing Directions for the Red Sea</italic>has been heralded since its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Thalassomania:</title>
                     <subtitle>MODERNITY AND THE SEA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FROM THE POINT OF VIEW of modern geography, the world appears clear and simple. This is somewhat paradoxical, since one of the special qualities of modernity is deemed to be complexity (complex societies, complex personality, complex logic, and so forth). But with the advent of modern geography, every schoolchild should know that the world is divided into a set number of landmasses and seas: there are seven continents, just as there are five oceans, and a set number of seas, all made up of salt water, some completely bounded, others almost so.</p>
                     <p>The claims to objectivity of modern geography have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Rigging the Historian’s Craft: FOR AN EPISTEMOLOGY OF COMPOSITION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AT THE HEART OF THIS book is a basic question that has heretofore largely eluded serious attention: How does history make its subject? Clearly, not all subjects are deemed historical at all times—that much has been clear from the beginnings of the discipline. What is required, then, for a particular object to become a proper subject of history? And what are the implications of such constraints for the history that is being written? In other words, what this book explores is the<italic>rigging</italic>involved in the safe sailing of the historian’s<italic>craft</italic>, that is, as per the Merriam-Webster definitions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19633g6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
