<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">CC77.H5 B38 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Archaeology and history</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Classical antiquities</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Classical literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Greek literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Archaeology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Material culture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Traces of the Past</book-title>
         <subtitle>Classics between History and Archaeology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bassi</surname>
               <given-names>Karen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472119929</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472121960</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Karen Bassi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.8785930"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What are we doing when we walk into an archaeological museum or onto an archaeological site? What do the objects and features we encounter in these unique places mean and, more specifically, how do they convey to us something about the beliefs and activities of formerly living humans? In short, how do visible remains and ruins in the present give meaning to the human past? Karen Bassi addresses these questions through detailed close readings of canonical works spanning the archaic to the classical periods of ancient Greek culture, showing how the past is constituted in descriptions of what narrators and characters see in their present context. She introduces the term protoarchaeological to refer to narratives that navigate the gap between linguistic representation and empirical observation-between words and things-in accessing and giving meaning to the past. Such narratives invite readers to view the past as a receding visual field and, in the process, to cross the disciplinary boundaries that divide literature, history, and archaeology.Aimed at classicists, literary scholars, ancient historians, cultural historians, and archaeological theorists, the book combines three areas of research: time as a feature of narrative structure in literary theory; the concept of "the past itself" in the philosophy of history; and the ontological status of material objects in archaeological theory. Each of five central chapters explores how specific protoarchaeological narratives-from the fate of Zeus' stone in Hesiod's Theogony to the contest between words and objects in Aristophanes' Frogs-both expose and attempt to bridge this gap. Throughout, the book serves as a response to Herodotus' task in writing the Histories, namely, to ensure that "the past deeds of men do not fade with time."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Seeing the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What are we doing when we walk into an archaeological museum or onto an archaeological site? For what or at what are we looking? What do the objects and features we encounter in these unique spaces mean? More specifically, how do they convey to us something about the beliefs and activities of formerly living humans? The answers to these questions may seem all too obvious; they also depend on what “we” I am talking about. Professional archaeologists or art historians, for example, have very specific ways of looking at and talking about their objects of study. But the particulars of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Landscape of the Past in Hesiod’s Theogony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As succinctly expressed in its opening line, “Let us begin to sing” ἀρχώμεθ᾿ ἀείδειν, 1)), Hesiod’s<italic>Theogony</italic>is about the beginning of time as the motivation for the beginning of poetic production.² The question before us is how the visible or material world is part of the poem’s temporal environment. In general, scholarly attention paid to material or visible objects in archaic poetry has taken two routes. On the one hand, they are the source of aesthetic effects in ecphrastic passages, with the Shield of Achilles in the Iliad taking pride of place.³ On the other hand, they are marshaled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Hypothetical Past and the Achaean Wall in the Iliad</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to John Camp, walls are the “most enduring evidence of antiquity surviving in the landscape today.”² As features in the built environment, the remains of walls delimit the lives of ancient humans in both time and space; they give substance to the past. Perhaps it is not surprising that the prominence of walls as archaeological features is shared by their prominence as narrative plot devices. They stand out (as it were) in both contexts. It might even be said that walls occupy a unique position as both signifiers of cultural production and structures within narrative. Between their existence as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Blinded by Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Past “As If ” in the Odyssey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters have focused on the temporal significance of visible objects and monumental features in the poetic landscape of the Greek past. At several points along the way, the discussion has also included encounters with human eyewitnesses: Hesiod’s vision of the Muses on Helicon, Pausanias’ sighting of the stone in Delphi, and Strabo’s assessment of the existence of the Achaean wall in Troy. In this chapter, I discuss the formative role of Odysseus as an eyewitness to his own past and as a figure who occupies an intermediary position between the two principal claimants to knowing the past and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>“Up to My Time”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fading of the Past in Herodotus’ Histories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explores the role of visible evidence for the past in Herodotus’<italic>Histories</italic>, exemplified in the fate of the offerings of the Lydian kings in the Lydian logos. The argument is focused on the temporal, ontological, and epistemological variables at work in the relationship between the oracles given to the Lydian kings and the offerings they inspire. Expressed in terms of a specific temporo-linguistic feature in the<italic>Histories</italic>—namely, Herodotus’ descriptions of objects that exist up to his own time (ἐπ᾿ ἐμεῦ, μέχρις ἐμέο</p>
                     <p>etc.)—this relationship has to do with how visible phenomena in the present are marshaled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Tragedy Vanishes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Past in Aristophanes’ Frogs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last forty years have seen the emergence of scholarship that attempts to read Attic drama as a visual medium, that is, to understand the extant dramatic texts in the context of Athens’ physical environment, as live performance texts, or in their relationship to the visual arts. Drawing on a variety of disciplines and methodologies, this work demonstrates that the interplay between verbal sign and visual referent in dramatic texts presents a particular challenge to interpretation.² Insofar as the dramatic text refers simultaneously to prior and future phenomena—that is, to the plot and (in principle) to the play in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapters, I have defined protoarchaeological narratives as those in which the past is conceptualized in a negotiation between empirical observation and linguistic representation in a variety of ancient Greek genres. I have also suggested that reading—both as a conceptual category and as a practice—functions within these narratives as an acknowledgment that the past is constituted in what can no longer be seen. To return again to Herodotus’ metaphor, reading refers to the past as a congeries of narrativized objects and events that fades with time. In this epilogue, I explore the ontological and epistemological implications</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index Locorum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Greek Terms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.8785930.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
