<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmsm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BH39.B795 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Art</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>On the Anarchy of Poetry and Philosophy</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Guide for the Unruly</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BRUNS</surname>
               <given-names>GERALD L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823226320</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275113</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c84gmm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Marcel Duchamp once asked whether it is possible to make something that is not a work of art. This question returns over and over in modernist culture, where there are no longer any authoritative criteria for what can be identified (or excluded) as a work of art. As William Carlos Williams says, A poem can be made of anything,even newspaper clippings.At this point, art turns into philosophy, all art is now conceptual art, and the manifesto becomes the distinctive genre of modernism. This book takes seriously this transformation of art into philosophy, focusing upon the systematic interest that so many European philosophers take in modernism. Among the philosophers Gerald Bruns discusses are Theodor W. Adorno, Maurice Blanchot, Arthur Danto, Stanley Cavell, Hans-Georg Gadamer, Michel Foucault, Gilles Deleuze and Felix Guattari, Jacques Derrida, Jean-Franois Lyotard, Jean-Luc Nancy, Philippe Lacoue-Labarthe, and Emmanuel Levinas.As Bruns demonstrates, the difficulty of much modern and contemporary poetry can be summarized in the idea that a poem is made of words, not of any of the things that we use words to produce: meanings, concepts, propositions, narratives, or expressions of feeling. Many modernist poets have argued that in poetry language is no longer a form of mediation but a reality to be explored and experienced in its own right. But what sort of experience, philosophically, might this be? The problem of the materiality or hermetic character of poetic language inevitably leads to questions of how philosophy itself is to be written and what sort of communitydefines the work of art-or, for that matter, the work of philosophy.In this provocative study, Bruns answers that the culture of modernism is a kind of anarchist community, where the work of art is apt to be as much an event or experience-or, indeed, an alternative form of life-as a formal object. In modern writing, philosophy and poetry fold into one another. In this book, Bruns helps us to see how.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations for Frequently Cited Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruns</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Modernisms—Literary and Otherwise:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Complexity</italic>. In section 3 of<italic>Sein und Zeit</italic>(1927), on “The Ontological Priority of the Question of Being,” Martin Heidegger writes:</p>
                     <p>The real “movement” of the sciences takes place when their basic concepts undergo a more or less radical revision which is transparent to itself. The level which a science has reached is determined by how far it is<italic>capable</italic>of a crisis in its basic concepts. In such immanent crises the very relationship between positively investigative inquiry and those things [<italic>Sachen</italic>] that are under interrogation comes to a point where it begins to totter. Among the various disciplines everywhere</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Ancients and Moderns:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gadamer’s Aesthetic Theory and the Poetry of Paul Celan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Play of the Artwork</italic>. Possibly there is a no more unlikely, or maybe even unwanted, commentator on modernism than Hans-Georg Gadamer, a classical philologist, distinguished Plato scholar, and author of<italic>Wahrheit und Methode</italic>(<italic>Truth and Method</italic>) (1960), the monumental articulation of philosophical hermeneutics, one of whose central chapters concerns the normative character of the “classical” or “eminent” text. (WM. 269–75/TM. 285–90). Nevertheless, it happens that Gadamer is also an accomplished art historian who thinks that the claim of the modernist work (one of Duchamp’s Readymades, for example) is every bit as compelling as that of the classical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Foucault’s Modernism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language, Poetry, and the Experience of Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Modernism Once More</italic>. Fredric Jameson has usefully proposed that we think of modernism not as a period concept but, more loosely, as a “narrative category” in which topics like nineteenth-century realism, self-reflexive language, and the impersonality of the artist get articulated and rearticulated in multifarious ways.¹ It is certainly the case that modernism is often defined more clearly by examples than by theories—serial music, cubism, nonlinear or fragmentary texts like Stein’s<italic>Tender Buttons</italic>(or Wittgenstein’s<italic>Tractatus</italic>), as well as avant-garde groups like the Surrealists whose aim was often less to produce works of art than to develop new forms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Poetic Communities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ecstasy</italic>. Scholarly tradition pictures Hesiod, like Homer before him, as a great pedagogue.¹ The poet is in charge of a vast encyclopedia concerning gods and heroes (and also, in Hesiod’s particular case, everyday life). But from Hesiod we also learn that poetry itself is not a kind of learning but a species of ecstasy. No one studies to be a poet. No one asks to be such a thing. One is, for no reason, summoned out of one’s house and exposed to a kind of transcendence. Exactly what kind of transcendence is not always clear. One can imagine preferring the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Francis Ponge on the Rue de la Chaussée d’Antin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Artspace</italic>. What becomes of things in art? This is still the question of questions in aesthetic theory, which has understood from the beginning of modernism that the terms “nonrepresentational,” “nonmimetic,” or “abstract,” however much they may capture something of what the experience of nontraditional works of art is like, have little application to twentieth-century art and literature. Modern art is filled with things. A cubist collage is made of real newspaper clippings, and so is a poem by William Carlos Williams. The method of modern poetry is, manifestly, “quotation, commentary, pastische,” as if the poem had become a space for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Senses of Augustine:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Some of Lyotard’s Remains</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Pagan</italic>. At the time of his death in 1998 the French philosopher Jean-François Lyotard had begun writing what was to have been a substantial work on Augustine’s<italic>Confessions</italic>. In the event he has left us only fragments—notes, paragraphs,<italic>envois</italic>, sketches, and two lectures stitched together to form a kind of monograph called “La Confession d’Augustin”:<italic>the</italic>confession, referring, as we shall see, to Augustine’s confession of his love for God. Like all of Lyotard’s productions, this posthumous assembly leaves us guessing as to what kind of writing it is supposed to be. In fact Lyotard was never much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Anarchic Temporality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Writing, Friendship, and the Ontology of the Work of Art in Maurice Blanchot’s Poetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Poetry as Unhappy Consciousness</italic>. It is well known that in Maurice Blanchot’s early criticism writing appears to be less a productive activity than a self-reflexive movement. For example, at the outset of “Littérature et la à la mort” (1947– 48) he remarks that literature begins when it becomes a question for itself (PF. 293/WF. 300–301). What sort of question, exactly? Evidently not Jean-Paul Sartre’s “What is literature?’’ which like all “what is . . . ?” questions carries a demand for justification. Inquiring after the nature of a thing is a way of asking why there is such a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Concepts of Art and Poetry in Emmanuel Levinas’s Writings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emmanuel Levinas’s writings are rich in comments and reflections on art, poetry, and the relations between poetry and ethical theory.¹ Of particular importance is the question of language, because there appears to be a kind of symmetry between language as an ethical relation and the language of poetry, both of which expose us to regions of subjectivity or existence on the hither (anarchic) side of cognition and being. The ethical and the poetic are evidently species of saying (<italic>le Dire</italic>) in contrast to the propositional character of the said (<italic>le Dit</italic>), yet neither one is translatable into the other, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gmm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
