<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnn8d8</collection-id>
      <volume>91</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GT3283.A2B73 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Funeral rites and ceremonies</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Burial</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memorials</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Chinese</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Inscriptions, Chinese</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Qin dynasty, 221–207 B.C.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Han dynasty, 202 B.C.–220 A.D.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Public Memory in Early China</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brashier</surname>
               <given-names>K. E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674492035</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684170753</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684170753</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dnnb3k"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In early imperial China, the dead were remembered by stereotyping them, by relating them to the existing public memory and not by vaunting what made each person individually distinct and extraordinary in his or her lifetime. Their posthumous names were chosen from a limited predetermined pool; their descriptors were derived from set phrases in the classical tradition; and their identities were explicitly categorized as being like this cultural hero or that sage official in antiquity. In other words, postmortem remembrance was a process of pouring new ancestors into prefabricated molds or stamping them with rigid cookie cutters. Public Memory in Early China is an examination of this pouring and stamping process. After surveying ways in which learning in the early imperial period relied upon memorization and recitation, K. E. Brashier treats three definitive parameters of identity—name, age, and kinship—as ways of negotiating a person’s relative position within the collective consciousness. He then examines both the tangible and intangible media responsible for keeping that defined identity welded into the infrastructure of Han public memory.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables and Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conventions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Han memorial culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2004, during the rushed archeological work prior to the planned flooding of the Three Gorges region on the Yangzi River, excavators discovered a stele dated 173 ce and dedicated to a local prefect who had otherwise disappeared from history (Figure 1). In language common for such gravestones from the later years of the Han dynasty (202 bce–220 ce), the two-meter-high slab lavishly praised the administration of this minor official, named Jing Yun 景雲 (d. 103 ce). It describes how the local populace wept at his death “as if mourning for a parent” (如喪考妣), how they set aside their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PART I</label>
                     <title>Names as positioning the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the texts committed to memory in early China, the famous “Shengmin” 生民 (Birth of our people) in the<italic>Songs canon</italic>recounts the life of Houji 后稷, progenitor of a lineage that would one day give rise to the Zhou dynasty. It begins by describing how his mother, Jiang Yuan 姜嫄, sought to abandon him despite his miraculous birth, that desertion scene depicted as follows:</p>
                     <p>While infant abandonment was not uncommon in early China, Houji’s fate was by no means sealed, and the poem moves on to praise his developing horticultural prowess as in the following lines:</p>
                     <p>At this point,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PART II</label>
                     <title>Age as positioning the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Confucius in the<italic>Analects</italic>briefly tracks a person’s physical and emotional well-being through changes to his blood and<italic>qi</italic>, and in Part I, we saw Wang Chong and others in the Han taking that blood and<italic>qi</italic>one step further, at death, with the former transforming into earth and the latter dissipating into the air.</p>
                     <p>The physical decrepitude to be suffered by the elderly was indeed a readily acknowledged fact of life in the minds of Han writers and thinkers, even though efforts were made to stave off the biological inevitability. For example, one might endeavor to forestall the decay</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PART III</label>
                     <title>Kinship as positioning the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing at the end of the Han era, Cao Zhi 曹植 (192–232) lamented the death of his daughter with the following “Jinhu aici” 金瓠哀辭 (“Mournful lyrics for Jinhu”):</p>
                     <p>金瓠，予之首女，雖未能言，固已授色知心矣！生十九旬而夭折，乃作此辭。辭曰﹕</p>
                     <p>Jinhu was my firstborn daughter, and although she wasn’t able to talk yet, she could already let us know what was on her mind through her expressions.¹ She died an untimely death after living only one hundred and ninety days, and so I wrote these lyrics:</p>
                     <p>Able to smile and connect with those around her, Jinhu had earned her name and had already begun to weave herself into the relationship</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PART IV</label>
                     <title>The tangible tools of positioning the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After tracing their ancestry up into the very stars themselves, Liu Min’s descendants on the same cemetery stele then envisioned their new ancestor as reduced to something schematic and enduring:</p>
                     <p>Just as Xunzi, the<italic>Ritual records</italic>, Yang Xiong, and others described the community-building function of mourning (see Section 13), here Liu Min’s descendants would regularly gather to remember him with music and food. His tombstone records that they were to perpetuate his<italic>xiang</italic>像 or “schema,” and the tombstone itself, with its inscribed biography and ancestral hymn, would play a role in that preservation process.</p>
                     <p>The tombstone is of course</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>PART V</label>
                     <title>The intangible tools of positioning the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The line between remembering one’s own ancestor and remembering a public hero is only lightly drawn and, over the course of the Han, was often entirely erased. As seen in Part II, early eulogists consciously rubbed out that line, explicitly contending that mourning was not the monopoly of the family but was also a public matter. The recently discovered Jing Yun stele offers one of the longest and most evocative images of public mourning for their local prefect, and it makes no apologies for borrowing the sentiments of ancestral remembrance:</p>
                     <p>如喪考妣，三載泣怛，追勿八音，百姓流淚，魂靈既載，農夫惻結，行路撫涕，織婦喑咽，吏民懷慕。戶有祠祭，煙火相望，四時不絕，深野曠澤，哀聲忉切，追歌遺風，嘆績億世，刻石紀號，永永不滅，烏呼哀哉，烏呼哀哉！</p>
                     <p>It was as if mourning for a parent, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Here is where the Earl of Shao rested”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>366</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like a Western obituary, the Jing Yun stele begins by offering the names of the deceased—personal, courtesy, and surname—his office, and then the date of his death, the last given as a particular day in the summer of 103 ce, the precision of which is rather surprising given that this stele was erected seventy years later.¹ Unlike a Western obituary (and unlike most other Han stelae), it then provides us with hardly any other personal information about Jing Yun such as his education, his service history, his age at death, and his surviving relatives. Here the Western obituary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>481</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb3k.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>512</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
