<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ4416.B37 1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dante Alighieri, 1265–1321. Divina commedia</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dante Alighieri, 1265–1321</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dante Alighieri, 1265–1321</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Undivine Comedy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Detheologizing Dante</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BAROLINI</surname>
               <given-names>TEODOLINDA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1992</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691015286</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691015287</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400820764</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1992</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7rvnj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Accepting Dante's prophetic truth claims on their own terms, Teodolinda Barolini proposes a "detheologized" reading as a global new approach to the<italic>Divine Comedy</italic>. Not aimed at excising theological concerns from Dante, this approach instead attempts to break out of the hermeneutic guidelines that Dante structured into his poem and that have resulted in theologized readings whose outcomes have been overdetermined by the poet. By detheologizing, the reader can emerge from this poet's hall of mirrors and discover the narrative techniques that enabled Dante to forge a true fiction. Foregrounding the formal exigencies that Dante masked as ideology, Barolini moves from the problems of beginning to those of closure, focusing always on the narrative journey. Her investigation--which treats such topics as the visionary and the poet, the One and the many, narrative and time--reveals some of the transgressive paths trodden by a master of mimesis, some of the ways in which Dante's poetic adventuring is indeed, according to his own lights, Ulyssean.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="368"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDITIONS AND ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>DETHEOLOGIZING DANTE:</title>
                     <subtitle>REALISM, RECEPTION, AND THE RESOURCES OF NARRATIVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his capital and underutilized “Dante profeta,” published in 1941, Bruno Nardi threw down a critical gauntlet and challenged us to look at the<italic>Commedia</italic>not through a glass darkly but face to face.¹ He begins where all such discussions must begin, with the<italic>Commedia’s</italic>most overtly prophetic moments, its political prophecies; situating them within the context of Joachimism and Franciscan spiritualism, he moves to a discussion of medieval attitudes toward prophecy, dreams, and divination. Calling to our attention Albert the Great’s teaching that some people “sognano il vero, e, a differenza di altri, hanno visioni veraci, talchè non di</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>INFERNAL INCIPITS:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE POETICS OF THE NEW</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>commedia</italic>, perhaps more than any other text ever written, consciously seeks to imitate life, the conditions of human existence. Not surprisingly, then, the narrative journey begins with the problem of beginnings.¹ Dante’s beginning, “Nel mezzo del cammin di nostra vita” (“In the middle of the path of our life”), evokes biblical and classical precedents for not beginning at the beginning. As Frank Kermode reminds us, “Men, like poets, rush ‘into the middest,’<italic>in medias res</italic>, when they are born; they also die<italic>in mediis rebus</italic>.”² This is to say that we exist in time, which, according to Aistotle, “is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>ULYSSES, GERYON, AND THE AERONAUTICS OF NARRATIVE TRANSITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ulysses is as fundamental to the<italic>Commedia</italic>as the voyage theme that he incarnates and dramatizes, as irrepressible as the trope whose most living embodiment within the poem he is. He is linked to the poem’s metaphorization of desire as flight, a metaphor whose origin is the celebrated verse from Ulysses’ oration, in which the adventurer indicates the extent of the enthusiasm he had solicited from his aged crew by saying “de’ remi facemmo ali al folle volo” (“of our oars we made wings for the mad flight” [<italic>Inf</italic>.26.125]).¹ Ulysses and his surrogates, other failed flyers like Phaeton and Icarus,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>NARRATIVE AND STYLE IN LOWER HELL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introduced by the complex transition of cantos 16 and 17,<italic>Inferno</italic>18 constitutes an emphatic new beginning situated at the canticle’s midpoint, at its narrative “mezzo del cammin.” “Luogo è in inferno detto Malebolge” (“There is a place in hell called Malebolge”) begins the canto, with a verse that is crisply informative, explicitly introductory, and patently devoted to differentiation:¹ this is a new place, a new locus. Following the<italic>descriptio loci</italic>heralded by the opening “Luogo è,”² the narrator’s focus shifts to the travelers. In two apparently very simple tercets, he activates the poetics of the new, founded on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>PURGATORY AS PARADIGM:</title>
                     <subtitle>TRAVELING THE NEW AND NEVER-BEFORE-TRAVELED PATH OF THIS LIFE/POEM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The narrative of the<italic>Commedia</italic>is a line intersected by other lines; it is a “vedere interciso da novo obietto,” a seeing interrupted by new things, the<italic>novi obietti or cose nove</italic>that do not trouble angels. It is a voyage intersected by other voyages; each time the pilgrim meets a soul, his lifeline intersects another lifeline. In hell he encounters failed voyages, journeys that have ended in failure. Ulysses’ special stature within the poem derives in no small measure from the fact that his lifeline concludes with a literal voyage that has literally failed, so that he, alone among</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>RE-PRESENTING WHAT GOD PRESENTED:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE ARACHNEAN ART OF THE TERRACE OF PRIDE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Representatation becomes an issue for the<italic>Commedia</italic>most overtly on purgatory’s terrace of pride, where the pilgrim encounters a series of marble engravings that are rendered ecphrastically by the poet, one form of representation thus representing another. This chapter will explore the implications of that encounter, viewed as an authorial meditation on the principles of mimesis as they apply to Dante and to his art. As traditionally constituted, the principles of mimesis are here immediately violated; instead of art being inferior to nature, the art of the first terrace is such that it puts nature to shame: “non pur Policleto,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>NONFALSE ERRORS AND THE TRUE DREAMS OF THE EVANGELIST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the time of Drythelm to the time of Charles the Fat, living voyagers traveled to the hereafter, leaving their bodies behind on earth to be returned to at journey’s end. These journeys were considered to be ‘real’ by the men of the Middle Ages, even if they depicted them as ‘dreams’ (<italic>somnia</italic>).” So writes the historian Jacques Le Goff, in words that provide a context for Dante’s experience.¹ Dante believed that his journey was, in some essential sense, real. But Dante differs from other medieval visionaries in at least one fundamental respect, namely, the immensity of his poetic gift:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>PROBLEMS IN PARADISE:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MIMESIS OF TIME AND THE PARADOX OF PIÙ E MENO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We turn now to the<italic>Paradiso</italic>and to the problems of recounting the unrecountable. Due to our habit of conflating the<italic>Commedia’s</italic>form with its content, the exegetical tradition has produced a theologized reading of the third canticle that portrays it as cloyingly serene (no doubt a factor in its undeserved reputation as boring). In recent years, the old critical commonplace of a serene and problem-free third canticle has been given a metapoetic twist; we hear now about the difficulties of writing the<italic>Inferno</italic>, difficulties that presumably lessen as the poem proceeds. As indicated earlier, such readings unacceptably theologize the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>THE HEAVEN OF THE SUN AS A MEDITATION ON NARRATIVE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The thematic project of the heaven of the sun is a replay, in the key of wisdom, of what Dante seeks to represent and promote throughout the<italic>Paradiso</italic>: a paradise where difference is blended into the one enough to achieve peace and harmony, but not enough to lose what makes it itself, what makes it different. Such a paradoxical project requires from the poet a perpetual balancing, as at one moment he emphasizes the unity of paradise and at another he emphasizes the hierarchy that differentiates—and disunifes—that unity. In the heaven of the sun the balancing that underlies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>THE SACRED POEM IS FORCED TO JUMP:</title>
                     <subtitle>CLOSURE AND THE POETICS OF ENJAMBMENT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN ANSWER TO Cacciaguida’s exhortation to sound forth his will and his desire, the pilgrim responds by explaining the diegetic problemsÐ problems of disequality and differenceÐthat beset all mortals:</p>
                     <p>L’affetto e ’l senno,</p>
                     <p>come la prima<italic>equalità</italic>v’apparse,</p>
                     <p>d’<italic>un peso</italic>per ciascun di voi si fenno,</p>
                     <p>però che ’l sol che v’allumò e arse,</p>
                     <p>col caldo e con la luce è sì<italic>iguali,</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>che tutte<italic>simiglianze</italic>sono scarce.</p>
                     <p>Ma voglia e argomento ne’ mortali,</p>
                     <p>per la cagion ch’a voi è manifesta,</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>diversamente</italic>son pennuti in ali;</p>
                     <p>ond’io, che son mortal, mi sento in questa</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>disagguaglianza,</italic>e però non ringrazio</p>
                     <p>se</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>TRANSITION: HOW CANTOS BEGIN AND END</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rvnj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
