<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DC33.7.F728 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">National characteristics, French</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The French Exception</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Godin</surname>
               <given-names>Emmanuel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Chafer</surname>
               <given-names>Tony</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782387169</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782387161</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Emmanuel Godin</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Tony Chafer</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btbw43"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The notion of French exceptionalism is deeply embedded in the nation's self-image and in a range of political and academic discourses. Recently, the debate about whether France really is "exceptional" has acquired a critical edge. Against the background of introspection about the nature of "national identity," some proclaim "normalisation" and the end of French exceptionalism, while others point out to the continuing evidence that France remains distinctive at a number of levels, from popular culture to public policy. This book explores the notion of French exceptionalism, places it in its European context, examines its history and evaluate its continuing relevance in a range of fields from politics and public policy to popular culture and sport.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="274"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book emerges from the Annual Conference of the Association for the Study of Modern and Contemporary France (ASMCF) on the theme ‘La France Exceptionnelle? Comparisons and Intercultural Perspectives’, held at the University of Portsmouth in September 2001. Some of the chapters of the present book emerge from papers given at the conference, others have been specially written for it.</p>
                     <p>One of the founders of the Association for the Study of Modern and Contemporary France, Eric Cahm, served as executive editor of its journal<italic>Modern and Contemporary France</italic>for a number of years. Eric was an enthusiastic francophile and a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godin</surname>
                           <given-names>Emmanuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chafer</surname>
                           <given-names>Tony</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the summer of 2003, a medical doctor in the Grenoble region pinned on the door of his surgery waiting room a large and colourful poster that warned his patients of a great danger: statistics clearly showed that young French children were becoming as obese as their American counterparts. Various unappealing photos of hamburgers, chocolate bars and fizzy drinks showed that the excessive consumption of junk food was primarily responsible for this worrying trend. Of course, similar concerns are regularly expressed in the British and American press, usually with an exhortation to review the menus that schools serve to children.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>France and Exceptionalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hewlett</surname>
                           <given-names>Nick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone with more than a passing scholarly interest in things French will have encountered the notion that France is different from other countries.¹ We might disagree about the usefulness of this idea, we might think it is inaccurate or even trivial, but we have all been exposed to the view that important aspects of French society, French politics, French thought, French language and French culture are strikingly unique. From newspaper articles to the most serious historiography of the French Revolution, via an almost endless array of journal articles, textbooks, journalistic potboilers, and now websites, we find arguments and approaches whose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Exceptionalism and Universalism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Uneasy Alliance in the French-speaking World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Majumdar</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The notion of French exceptionalism is at the heart of French political discourse and culture. Yet it sits in an uneasy alliance with another concept, equally central to the dominant French republican ideology – that of universalism. This chapter explores the contradictions constituting the couplet exceptionalism/universalism, with particular reference to discourses articulating relations between France and its present and former colonies. It will look at the evolution of these discourses, as well as examine contemporary shifts and modifications in relation to what is known as the francophone world.</p>
                     <p>The notion of French exceptionalism has developed on the basis of a fundamental</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Elusive French Exception</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Collard</surname>
                           <given-names>Sue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What exactly is the French exception? What, if anything, makes the French claim to exceptionalism more convincing than others such as the American, the German or the British (Lipset 1996; Adams and van Minnen 1994; Madsen 1998; Gauzy 1998; Colley 1992)? Are all nations not in some respect exceptional? Here my approach is not to seek the answers through a scholarly demonstration of the ways in which French history, politics and culture have combined to produce a particular set of events and traditions that are allegedly different from those of any other country, or by means of a comparative study</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>French Communism:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Exceptional Orthodoxy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bell</surname>
                           <given-names>David S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>French exceptionalism in politics comes down in many respects to French ‘political culture’. ‘Political culture’ is used here to mean the orientation that people have towards politics and their expectations of political action. However, political culture is not a passive given. Political culture is inherited from the past but it is adapted and built on by political institutions which in this way help shape a society’s attitudes to politics. In the case of the French Communist Party (Parti communiste français: PCF), it successfully picked up and used aspects of a pre-existing political culture but it also added its own components.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Does it Make Sense to Treat the Front National as a ‘French Exception’?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godin</surname>
                           <given-names>Emmanuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is exceptional about the French extreme right today? Pascal Perrineau (1997: 10–11) suggests that what distinguishes the Front National (FN) from previous French extreme-right parties or movements is the strength and longevity of its electoral success. From<italic>boulangisme</italic>in the late nineteenth century to the rise of the Leagues in the interwar period, from the Poujadist wave of the 1950s to the defence of French Algeria in the mid-1960s, the French extreme right’s electoral success had always been as intense as it was ephemeral. Conversely, since its first successes in local and European elections in the early 1980s,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>The French Administrative Exception:</title>
                     <subtitle>Change and Resistance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stevens</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In attempting to categorise administrative systems Edward Page (1995: 280) assigned the French system to a group onto itself. France is often regarded as being a particularly striking example, indeed the epitome, of a ‘Napoleonic’ or continental model, its features memorably summarised by Vincent Wright: ‘[s]tatist, powerful, hierarchically structured, ubiquitous, uniform, depoliticised, instrumental, expert and tightly controlled... a model attractive to tidy minds in untidy countries’ (1994b: 116). Pierre (1995) sees it as constituting one of the two globally dominant models, the other being the ‘Anglo-Saxon’ model. Sabino Cassese (Cassese 1987: 12) on the other hand, identifies three models: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>French Industrial Relations – Still Exceptional?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parsons</surname>
                           <given-names>Nick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1990s, there was much debate among observers of the ‘normalisation’ of French industrial relations (Freyssinet 1993; Ruysseveldt and Visser 1996; Goetschy 1998). Broadly, the argument is that there has been a shift from an under-institutionalised system in which state intervention was needed to mediate a more or less naked class conflict between capital and labour to one based upon regular decentralised compromise bargaining between ‘social partners’. From this perspective, the system of labour regulation in France – the ‘rules of the game’ by which wages and working conditions are established – is coming to resemble more closely that of other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>The French Socialists, Dirigisme and the Troubled Europeanisation of Employment Policy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clift</surname>
                           <given-names>Ben</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The case for French exceptionalism in the field of state-economy relations centres on the distinctive French State tradition of<italic>dirigisme</italic>.<italic>Dirigisme</italic>has been succinctly defined as ‘a set of interventionist policies and directive policy-making processes’ (Schmidt 1997: 229). Traditions of state direction of, and intervention in, economic activity in France have a long heritage, traceable at least as far back as Jean-Baptiste Colbert, minister under Louis XIV between 1661 and 1683. His bent for state interventionism in economic affairs reached a zenith when, in 1666, he issued a<italic>règlement</italic>to the effect that the fabrics of Dijon and Selangey were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>French Foreign and Defence Policy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Exceptional in Methods and Rhetoric?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bryant</surname>
                           <given-names>Janet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines the notion of exceptionalism in the context of French foreign and defence policy in the Fifth Republic. The idea that France is exceptional in this area of policy has been characterised by the plethora of adjectives such as different, unusual, unconventional, distinctive and sometimes even maverick, that are often used when describing French actions. To what extent does it really make sense to talk about French exceptionalism in foreign and defence policy? Might it be argued, rather, that this term is particularly difficult to apply to an area of ‘high’ policy where every state will be seeking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>Presidential Debates in France:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Example of Americanisation?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perry</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheila</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The election of the president by universal suffrage was introduced in France by referendum in 1962; France held its first such election in 1965 and its first televised presidential debate in 1974. Televised debates became a regular feature of the second round of the presidential election until 2002, when the unprecedented success of the extreme right-wing candidate Jean-Marie Le Pen in getting through to the second round of voting led Jacques Chirac to refuse to take part. This chapter will examine the origins, format and interpretation of these debates, and compare these with similar debates held elsewhere, to establish to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>The Myth of Exceptionalism?</title>
                     <subtitle>French Television in a West European Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kuhn</surname>
                           <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early summer of 2001 the French terrestrial television channel M6 broadcast a programme that attracted large audience ratings, especially among young viewers.<italic>Loft Story</italic>was the French version of Big<italic>Brother</italic>, the reality show which had originated in the Netherlands, and the format for which had then been imported into the U. K. to become one of the most talked about programmes of 2000. M6 had taken a proven format, tweaked it for its domestic market and then sat back to watch the rise in audience figures, which was helped no doubt by the attendant blaze of controversial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>Cultural exception(s) in French Cinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rollet</surname>
                           <given-names>Brigitte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are few areas in which the idea of a possible French exception has asserted itself to such an extent as in the field of culture, and it is actually hardly surprising that the term ‘cultural exception’ has come to be associated with France, or a certain idea of France. The issue came to the forefront during the 1993 round of GATT (General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade) negotiations, when France insisted on removing cultural products from the negotiations, on the grounds that ‘culture is not just another commodity’. In so doing, the French representatives may have compounded France’s bad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 13</label>
                     <title>Sport and Politics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Another French Exception</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mignon</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In France, sport is characterised by strong intervention by both the state and local authorities. It is one of the manifestations of the famous French exception, which is embedded in a historic continuity that begins in the years following the war of 1870 and continues through the Popular Front, the Vichy regime and the Republics since 1947. What began as material and financial support has come to define sport as the state’s field of competence. The reasons for this intervention are no different from those of other countries which, depending on the period, may be concern for the physical and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 14</label>
                     <title>French Intellectuals:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Legendary Exception</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kelly</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This nuanced denial of the French ‘intellectual exception’ is a graceful way of accepting a compliment. It is true that foreign commentators have often remarked on the extraordinary place of intellectuals in France. Theodore Zeldin, for example, describes them as ‘a small group that have cast a magic spell on the way the French are perceived by themselves and by foreigners’ (Zeldin 1983: 398). The result is a glorious legend that France has always been the privileged homeland of the intellectual. It is echoed in many of the scholarly studies that have been undertaken in recent years. And it figures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw43.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
