<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Being Human, Becoming Human</book-title>
         <subtitle>Dietrich Bonhoeffer and Social Thought</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
               <given-names>Jens</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gregor</surname>
               <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227680278</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227900260</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Witf &amp; Stock Publishers</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgfb5g"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book assembles a distinguished and international group of scholars to examine Bonhoeffer's understanding of human sociality. Vital reading for Bonhoeffer scholars as well as for those invested in theological debates regarding the social nature of human being, the essays in this volume examine Bonhoeffer's rich resources for thinking about what it means to be human, to be the church, to be a disciple, and to be ethically responsible in our contemporary world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="250"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays in this volume demonstrate Bonhoeffer’s significance for reflecting on the social and political dimensions of our contemporary world, which is grappling with questions of social identity and religion. As the title indicates, these essays on Bonhoeffer’s social thought are motivated by an anthropological concern: When we consider the rapid scientific advances of genetics and globally recurring human atrocities, does it not become apparent that human dignity requires a transcendent reference point? Yet as a generation justly suspicious of easy metaphysical assumptions, we also ask how any one concept of human dignity can offer the kind of transcendence and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Dietrich Bonhoeffer as Christian Humanist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Gruchy</surname>
                           <given-names>John W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1966 Kenneth Kaunda, then President of Zambia, published a book entitled<italic>A Humanist in Africa</italic>. He spoke of a humanist revolution then spreading across Africa that aimed at restoring the dignity and national pride of the peoples of the continent, who, for so long, had been dehumanized by the forces of slavery and colonialism. Kaunda wrote as an African, deeply rooted in its culture and tradition, but he also wrote as a Christian, the product of a missionary education. The humanism of which he spoke was not the secular humanism of the West, which he rejected; it was Christian,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Being Human, Becoming Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s Christological Humanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
                           <given-names>Jens</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John de Gruchy’s work, both in his essay in this volume and in previous publications,¹ already suggests that Bonhoeffer’s theology is best characterized as a Christian humanism. De Gruchy seeks to recover Christian humanism as an alternative cultural stance to scientific fundamentalism on the one hand and to religious fundamentalism on the other,² especially when the latter conflates religion and nationalism.³ Let me say from the outset that I fundamentally agree with de Gruchy’s desire to affirm a humanist identity for Christians and that Bonhoeffer is indeed a rich resource for doing so. As the title of my contribution suggests,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Bonhoeffer’s Theology and Economic Humanism:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Exploration in Interdisciplinary Sociality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frick</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The aim of this essay is to examine Bonhoeffer’s theology vis-à-vis economics. Admittedly, at first glance, this may appear as a rather farfetched idea, since Bonhoeffer was neither trained nor known as an economist and has left us no systematic treatment of his thought on that subject. Yet, there is the curious fact that Bonhoeffer’s entire adult life unfolded within an inexorable economic downward spiral. The height of that spiral was for Bonhoeffer in all probability the granting of his doctoral degree in theology in 1927. The bourgeois élan of the Bonhoeffer family, embedded as it was in intellectual elitism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Sociality, Discipleship, and Worldly Theology in Bonhoeffer’s Christian Humanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Green</surname>
                           <given-names>Clifford J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A striking phenomenon of the vast secondary literature about Dietrich Bonhoeffer is that so little of it tries to address his theology as a whole. What are its fundamental patterns of thought? What are their enduring characteristics? What are new developments? What drives its movement? When we look at Bonhoeffer’s older contemporaries in Protestant theology in the twentieth century—Barth and Tillich, for example—there is a fairly broad consensus about their work read as a whole. There is no such consensus about Bonhoeffer. Indeed, while early interpreters were bold to advance theses about the nature of Bonhoeffer’s theology as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Community Turned Inside Out:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s Concept of the Church and of Humanity Reconsidered</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nielsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Kirsten Busch</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The backbone of Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s theology is Christology. If one sees Bonhoeffer’s writings as the attempt to unfold, in a contemporary context, the meaning of believing and confessing the lordship of Jesus Christ, undoubtedly one has a good grasp of the core intention of his theology.</p>
                     <p>But it must be added that more specifically Bonhoeffer—without separating the person of Christ from the work of Christ—lets Christology take its point of departure in soteriology. Paul’s words in 2 Corinthians that God reconciled us to himself through Christ and gave us the ministry of reconciliation (2 Cor 5: 18–19)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Narrow Path:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sociality, Ecclesiology, and the Polyphony of Life in the Thought of Dietrich Bonhoeffer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harvey</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dietrich Bonhoeffer concludes the preface to<italic>Discipleship</italic>with a comment which, though in its immediate setting refers to the decision of the Confessing Church to resist incorporation into the Reich Church, sets the appropriate context for assessing the contribution of his theology to the question of sociality: “Today it seems so difficult to walk with certainty the narrow path of the church’s decision and yet remain wide open to Christ’s love for all people, and in God’s patience, mercy and loving-kindness (Titus 3:4) for the weak and godless. Still, both must remain together, or else we will follow merely human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Christological Presuppositions of Discipleship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yoder</surname>
                           <given-names>John H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The body of teaching and practice among the earliest Anabaptists that we have come to call “discipleship” had at least three kinds of rootage, of unequal genetic immediacy. There was the heritage of late-medieval Jesus-legalism,² which had been espoused most widely in Franciscan and Waldensian forms, most recently and firmly among the Czech Brethren. Here the accent lay upon determining the status of Jesus’s teachings, especially in the Sermon on the Mount, with the clear understanding that, if they have the status of law, they then are to be obeyed.³ A direct and causal linkage of this tradition with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Following-After and Becoming Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Study of Bonhoeffer and Kierkegaard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gregor</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According Jürgen Moltmann, the notion of discipleship is “a Cinderella of Protestantism.” For a long time it was a lowly and despised stepsister. In the established churches it was considered an excess of the pietist fringe, that is, “the ‘voluntary’ groups on the left wing of the Reformation the people who were notoriously slandered as ‘enthusiasts’, ‘fanatics’, ‘do-gooders’ or ‘radicals.’”¹ At the same time, it also threatened to contaminate the gospel with the works-righteousness of the medieval<italic>imitatio Christi</italic>. One of Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s many achievements, Moltmann proposes, was to make it possible to mention discipleship in polite society.² Bonhoeffer gave</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Con-Formation with Jesus Christ:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bonhoeffer, Social Location, and Embodiment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dahill</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What do we learn from Dietrich Bonhoeffer about being and becoming human? That question animating this volume of essays pushes deep into Christian anthropology, ecclesiology, social analysis, and Christology—that is to say, it invites us into the territory of the<italic>body</italic>. To assert that the questions at the heart of Bonhoeffer’s thinking and witness are inherently matters of reflective Christian<italic>embodiment</italic>in the world may seem so clear as not to warrant comment; obviously humans are constituted as bodies, and anything we might say about our humanity and life together in the world must take account of that fact.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Responding to Human Reality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Responsibility and Responsiveness in Bonhoeffer’s Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nissen</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulrik Becker</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A central motif in the ethics of the Danish theologian and philosopher K. E. Løgstrup is the mutual trust between persons encountering each other, giving rise to an ethical demand that is universal. Løgstrup has a phenomenological starting point, describing an ontological structure according to which human beings are delivered over into each other’s hands, thereby raising an ethical demand. In every encounter with another human being there is an ethical demand requiring care for the other.² For Løgstrup this is a universal demand and therefore not something unique to the Christian tradition. Therefore, Løgstrup also argues that there is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfb5g.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
