<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN453.L63 2000</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Creative ability</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Cross-cultural studies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Culture</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social change</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Locating Cultural Creativity</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Liep</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745317021</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849641012</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LONDON; STERLING, VIRGINIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Liep</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18fs9q6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The contributors to this volume reexamine the interconnectedness of culture and creativity in an increasingly hybrid world. They argue that while many of the old certainties about high culture and artistic canons may now be disintegrating, culture and creativity themselves are still very much a reflection of social processes involving power and the control of resources. Case studies include youth subcultures in Europe; experimental theatre derived from the Brazilian candomblé dance; the role of memory in mythology among the Pukapukan of Polynesia; the evolution of football and polo in Argentina; gender relations in Algerian raï music; the notion of authenticity in artistic movements in Zanzibar; traditional and modern practices of the Lio in Indonesia; and kula exchange and social movements in the Trobriand Islands in the Pacific.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liep</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>May 1995 was the fiftieth anniversary of the liberation of Denmark from German occupation during the Second World War. The Ministry of Culture had set aside generous funds for celebratory manifestations. By far the most costly and provocative project to be approved was a gigantic installation by a young artist who proposed illuminating the entire western coastline of Denmark with a single laser beam relayed from hill to hill. This performance on the midnight of peace was to continue along the German coast and thus demonstrate friendly cooperation across the border. The artist herself explained the installation as a re-creation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>CREATIVE ARGUMENTS OF IMAGES IN CULTURE, AND THE CHARNEL HOUSE OF CONVENTIONALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fernandez</surname>
                           <given-names>James W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin with two important modern philosophers, Wittgenstein and Rorty, as a context for more grounded anthropological discussion. These philosophers are both intensely interested in language (and particularly figurative language) and sympathetic to the anthropological project.² I refer to the project dating at least back to Vico which understands culture as something reconstructed, largely out of the building materials of language, from that which is long given.</p>
                     <p>Wittgenstein, conversing on aesthetics, shows understanding of the compensatory – perhaps revitalizing – interest moderns take in ‘creativity’ (Wittgenstein 1966:8 quoted in Lurie 1991). For him as for Spengler and for Vico before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>OTHELLO’S DANCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>CULTURAL CREATIVITY AND HUMAN AGENCY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hastrup</surname>
                           <given-names>Kirsten</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In anthropology, the notion of creativity has received renewed attention in recent years. Partly in response to the general historicization of the subject matter which took place during the 1980s, anthropologists have turned towards the processes of change inherent in any society. Cultural creativity is investigated as an ever-emergent feature in the world (Wagner 1981), and it is generally acknowledged that the ‘healthy perpetuation of cultural traditions requires invention as well as rote repetition’ (Rosaldo et al. 1993:5).</p>
                     <p>One could not agree more, yet there is still a slight feeling of an inherently marginal positioning of the creative element in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE IRON CAGE OF CREATIVITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN EXPLORATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Friedman</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Creativity has become something of a slogan among latter-day Birmingham cultural sociologists and their more seasoned allies, the cultural studies crowd. There has been a clear move from the study of working-class culture to the aesthetics of everyday life. While Birmingham certainly flirted with abstract structural Marxism, their interests lay more in the direction of the concrete, since they, unlike many Marxist sociologists, were trying to gain a purchase on reality in the street, so to speak – although one may have reservations about the nature of their ethnography, which, except for some of the research reports, was explicitly focused</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>WONDERING ABOUT WUTU</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Borofsky</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How does one locate ‘cultural creativity’? Where does one search? Just trying to define the phrase – so one has a clear sense of what one is after – is enough to muddle the process. Regarding culture, for example, Hatch notes: ‘Even though the term has been discussed in countless books and articles, there is still a large degree of uncertainty in its use – anthropologists employ the notion in fundamentally different ways’ (1973:1). Likewise, ambiguity surrounds creativity. My dictionary equates creativity with inventiveness, bringing something new into being, originating. (As Friedman suggests in this volume, novelty seems central to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>CELEBRATING CREATIVITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>ON THE SLANTING OF A CONCEPT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Löfgren</surname>
                           <given-names>Orvar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some years ago I did a study of the moral economy of the Swedish Christmas (Löfgren 1993). Wading through interviews, life histories, newspaper clippings and other mass-media products it seemed to me that one of the most important virtues of the modern Christmas was creativity: the ability to design your own personalized version of it.</p>
                     <p>There was a great seriousness surrounding this basic notion. Both in the individual interviews and in the mass-media advice there emerged a heavy stress on the importance of producing something authentic and genuine, of reworking and elaborating existing traditions. For many people, a homemade object</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>THE CONSTRUCTION OF AUTHENTICITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CASE OF SUBCULTURES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lindner</surname>
                           <given-names>Rolf</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The traditional dilemma of anthropology as an account of the culturally different is contained in the postulate of authenticity which, explicitly or implicitly, underlies it. In this context the word ‘postulate’ should be taken quite literally: a moral demand is made of the group being investigated, that it keep as far away as possible from worldly influence, whether of an economic, social or cultural nature. Renato Rosaldo (1989) has drawn attention to the fact that for anthropologists, if they adhere to the classic norms, the groups possessing the most ‘culture’ are those that are in themselves coherent and homogeneous, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>NATIONALISM, FOOTBALL AND POLO:</title>
                     <subtitle>TRADITION AND CREOLIZATION IN THE MAKING OF MODERN ARGENTINA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Archetti</surname>
                           <given-names>Eduardo P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the end of the nineteenth century and through the first three decades of the twentieth century, Argentina became integrated into the global scene of massive world commodity exchange, vast international migrations, rapid urbanization, new images of urban consumption, world sports competitions and circulation of mass cultural products. Between 1890 and 1914, Argentina became one of the great immigrant nations in the modern world. Buenos Aires grew dramatically from 286,000 inhabitants in 1880 to 1,576,000 in 1914. In 1914 almost half of the population of Buenos Aires were aliens. Spanish and Italian immigrants constituted the bulk of the immigration. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>THE ‘PLAYING’ OF MUSIC IN A STATE OF CRISIS:</title>
                     <subtitle>GENDER AND RAÏ MUSIC IN ALGERIA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schade-Poulsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this contribution I assume that ‘true’ creativity involves the making of novelties. It is not the outcome of a quasi-divine inspiration found in certain artistic geniuses: ‘the ones that create, that draw something out of nothing’ (cf. Robert 1978). Rather, creativity means forming, giving shape to something; it is the outcome of combinations of new potentialities or new combinations of existing resources.</p>
                     <p>Creativity is closely linked to processes of appropriation. Novelties are nothing unless<italic>accepted</italic>and<italic>worked</italic>on as social facts. A ‘social contract’ has to be established between the creators and their surroundings in order to generate a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>CREATIVE COMMODITIZATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SOCIAL LIFE OF PHARMACEUTICALS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whyte</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan Reynolds</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the dark daysof 1985, when Uganda wass still gripped by political insecurity and a sense of acute deterioration and loss, a group of experts published a collection of articles documenting the breakdown of health services in the country (Dodge and Wiebe 1985). The dean of the medical faculty at Makerere University wrote a foreword to the volume, in which he bravely hoped for a better future: Ugandans would build a new health system on the principle of people’s participation. In the intervening decade this has indeed happened, though not asthe experts would have wished. Uganda, like many African countries,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>ESCAPING CULTURES:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE PARADOX OF CULTURAL CREATIVITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parkin</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I take the paradox to be globally widespread. Consumers or, more commonly, spectators of others’ consumerism, see commodities replaced one after another by new ones. Yet, despite being new, each such commodity may sometimes be regarded as representing tradition and as having originated from inside the society rather than having been imported or affected by external influences. For example, local artists and craftsmen may think they know what foreign tourists want, but in fact find that their art works are bought by local people as much as and even more than by outsiders. This unexpected outcome is not always something</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>RECONTEXTUALIZING TRADITION:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘RELIGION’, ‘STATE’ AND ‘TRADITION’ AS COEXISTING MODES OF SOCIALITY AMONG THE NORTHERN LIO OF INDONESIA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Howell</surname>
                           <given-names>Signe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following independence in 1949, the new nation state of Indonesia faced the formidable task of uniting a population scattered over several thousand islands and consisting of several hundred distinct cultural groupings – each with its own language and cultural practices. The new motto became ‘unity through diversity’ and the national charter emphasized democracy, social justice and the belief in ‘the unique Godhead’. Indonesian law recognizes five monotheistic world religions and has made the adherence to one of these a legal requirement. Moreover, Indonesian (<italic>bahasa Indonesia</italic>) was declared the national language, to be employed in schools everywhere and as the language</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>KULA AND KABISAWALI:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONTEXTS OF CREATIVITY IN THE TROBRIAND ISLANDS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liep</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some 25 years ago I wrote a popular article about the<italic>kula</italic>exchange system for a Danish magazine and needed some illustrations. I therefore asked the American anthropologist Jerry Leach, who had worked in the Trobriands in the early 1970s, for a selection of photographs. Among those he forwarded was one taken in 1973 showing baskets of highly decorated kula armshells on a platform outside a house built of local materials on the main island, Kiriwina. The scene would have been redolent of the ‘kula tradition’ had it not, unfortunately, been marred by incongruous intrusions of modernity. It was bad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs9q6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
