<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Dealing with Dictators</book-title>
         <subtitle>The United States, Hungary, and East Central Europe, 1942-1989</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BORHI</surname>
               <given-names>LÁSZLÓ</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>TRANSLATED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VINCZ</surname>
               <given-names>JASON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253019394</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253019479</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253019478</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>László Borhi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cg4n1q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Dealing with Dictators explores America's Cold War efforts to make the dictatorships of Eastern Europe less tyrannical and more responsive to the country's international interests. During this period, US policies were a mix of economic and psychological warfare, subversion, cultural and economic penetration, and coercive diplomacy. Through careful examination of American and Hungarian sources, László Borhi assesses why some policies toward Hungary achieved their goals while others were not successful. When George H. W. Bush exclaimed to Mikhail Gorbachev on the day the Soviet Union collapsed, "Together we liberated Eastern Europe and unified Germany," he was hardly doing justice to the complicated history of the era. The story of the process by which the transition from Soviet satellite to independent state occurred in Hungary sheds light on the dynamics of systemic change in international politics at the end of the Cold War.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="562"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book on the impact of one country on the other. At first sight the selection of this topic may seem a bit odd in light of the fact that it describes the relationship of two geographically distant countries: the United States, the most powerful state of the times, and Hungary, a weak client state in the middle of Europe. It is the history of how the framers of American policy sought to exploit this small but strategically well-located state to further America’s strategic interests and how Hungarians, caught in the net of aggressors, first Germany, then the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Peace Overtures, the Allies, and the Holocaust, 1942–1945</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a forgotten episode of World War II, the United States and Great Britain chose to provoke a German invasion of Hungary (and Romania) in order to “spread the Germans thin” in Western Europe and facilitate the Allied landing in France in 1944. This decision appears to have been made without concern for the last remaining Jewish community in Europe, then numbering 825,000 people, or for Hungarian democratic elements. Allied planners expected that the Germans would need ten to fifteen divisions to occupy Hungary, troops that would thus be rendered unavailable for the fighting in Normandy. No calculation seems to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Cuius Regio, Eius Religio:</title>
                     <subtitle>The United States and the Soviet Seizure of Power</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historians have taken for granted that the Cold War originated at least partly in the fatal discord between the Soviet Union and the United States over the future of Eastern Europe. Scholars also tend to have narrowed the debate to the timing of and motivations behind the introduction of Stalinist regimes in Eastern Europe, generally focusing on whether the Sovietization of Eastern Europe was the predetermined result of Soviet foreign policy or a reaction to American assertiveness. This chapter will suggest that American policies had little or no influence on the course of events in Hungary. There is no evidence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Rollback</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1948 saw a basic shift in American policymakers’ attitudes toward Soviet control of European territory. The idea of peaceful cooperation, nurtured up to then by many British and American politicians and diplomats, was shattered. The last Eastern European democracy, Czechoslovakia, had been amalgamated into the Soviet camp and closed off, although, almost miraculously, Finland was released from Moscow’s grasp. Washington no longer saw Soviet control as a stabilizing factor in Eastern Europe. Instead, the restoration of independent states and the rollback of Soviet military power became the prerequisites of a secure and lasting continental peace. The goal thenceforth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>1956:</title>
                     <subtitle>Self-Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On October 23, 1956, Hungary exploded. Although it is hard to pinpoint why one country remains docile under tyrannical rule while another revolts, historians have dedicated years of research to identifying the specific factors that led to the only armed uprising against Soviet rule. Because virtually all segments of Hungarian society had suffered various forms of repression, unrest was not confined to the capital city. Centrally engineered “circular social mobility” failed to satisfy even the social groups whose aspirations the regime had privileged.¹ Grievances included foreign military occupation, state terror that sometimes exceeded even the limits of Soviet tolerance, serious</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Reprisals and Bridge Building</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The failure of the 1956 revolution shattered the notion that the European status quo could be changed without the consent of the Soviet Union. Washington was forced to take a hard look at the European situation, and over the course of a decade they concluded that there was nothing they could do to reverse the continental division. The calculation that Europe would remain divided for the foreseeable future was not based solely on the United States’s inability to influence the power structure behind the Iron Curtain. The domestic and foreign policies of communist states like Poland, Romania, and Czechoslovakia also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Dilemmas of External Transformation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>American observers noticed that the communist regimes in Eastern Europe were becoming increasingly autonomous. They were beginning to assert that their national interests were not always identical with the Soviets’. Signs that they were heading toward more independence from Moscow made the European status quo acceptable to the United States, if not necessarily desirable. Some went as far as to argue that the Soviet occupation had produced an unprecedented stability in a former cockpit of continental hostilities. Soviet hegemony thus seemed preferable to an unchecked flow of unbridled nationalism. And while nationalism might have been part of the antidote to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“The Status Quo Is Not So Bad”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Détente</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is hard to disagree with historian Geraint Hughes’ assessment that “throughout the late 1960s, Britain and other Western powers were above all concerned that the status quo in Europe should be upheld.”¹ The European status quo would be sanctioned by an unlikely candidate. Richard Nixon had been known for his uncompromising anticommunist stance, but as president he espoused an unabashed realism. He and Henry Kissinger formed a tandem that would redefine American Cold War politics and treat the division of Europe as if it were permanent. Stability was to prevail at the expense of the independence of old nation-states.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Nixon, Carter, and the Kádár Regime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At last, the international constellation favored normalization. On August 5, 1971, Brezhnev received a personal letter from Nixon in which the president asked Brezhnev to cooperate in answering the “large questions.” Brezhnev proposed a summit,¹ and this was the point at which American policy toward Eastern Europe turned decisively toward accepting the permanence of Soviet control. Nixon traveled to Warsaw, where he declared his understanding of the predicament of Poland’s geopolitical environment. He also told the new Hungarian ambassador that he attributed Hungary’s “relationship to its neighbors” to the country’s “historical and geographical” attributes.² Károly Szabó was thrilled by Nixon’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>“Love Toward Kádár”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reagan and the Myth of Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even though the United States had finally accepted the division of the continent on a permanent basis – and was not particularly secretive about having done so – the years of détente were coming to an end. Each side was accusing the other of violating the terms of the SALT I treaty. The Soviet Union may have been exploiting loopholes in the agreement to build superiority in the field of strategic nuclear missiles.¹ In fact, confidence between the two superpowers or indeed the two military alliances had never really taken hold. Security, as Churchill once put it, remained the “sturdy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>1989:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Together We Liberated Eastern Europe”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>364</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The day the Soviet Union collapsed, George H. W. Bush penned a personal note to his friend Mikhail Gorbachev in which he immodestly declared, “Together we liberated Eastern Europe and unified Germany.”¹ Did this bold claim do justice to the complicated history of the transition from the Cold War to the reunification of Europe, the restoration of multiparty democracy, and national independence in Eastern Europe? The answer to this question is not only a matter of historical truth. The clarification of the process of transition will shed light on the dynamics of systemic change in international politics at the end</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>434</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is striking about U.S. policy toward Hungary – and more broadly speaking, toward East Central Europe – is that at certain junctures it exerted a profound influence on events and sometimes none at all. The ability of American foreign policy to leave its mark on the region depended to a large extent on the willingness of the countries there to engage themselves with the United States.</p>
                     <p>Washington faced hard choices in East Central Europe. In World War II an opportunity presented itself to exploit the satellites’ eagerness to break with Hitler in order to help the Allied war effort.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>443</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>527</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>541</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n1q.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>549</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
