<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vbx</collection-id>
      <volume>32</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Literatures of the French Pacific</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reconfiguring Hybridity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RAMSAY</surname>
               <given-names>RAYLENE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SMYTH</surname>
               <given-names>EDMUND</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FORSDICK</surname>
               <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781781380376</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781385883</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Raylene Ramsay</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18kr78q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Hybridity theory, the creative dissemination and restless to-and-fro of Homi Bhabha’s Third Space or of Stuart Hall’s politics of difference, for example, has opened up understandings of what may be produced in the spaces of cultural contact. This book argues that the particularity of the forms of mixing in the literatures of the French Pacific country of New Caledonia contest and complexify the characterisations of hybrid cultural exchange. From the accounts of European discovery by the first explorers and translations of the stories of oral tradition, to the writings of settler, déporté, convict, indentured labourer and their descendants, and contemporary indigenous (Kanak) literatures, these texts inscribe Oceanian or Pacific difference within and against colonial contexts. In a context of present strategic positioning around a unique postcolonial proposal of common destiny, however, mutual cultural transformation is not unbounded. The local cannot escape coexistence with the global, yet Oceanian literatures maintain and foreground a powerful sense of ancestral origins, of an original engendering. The spiral going forward continually remembers and cycles back distinctively to an enduring core. In their turn, the Pacific stories of unjust deportation or heroic settlement are founded on exile and loss. On the other hand, both the desire for, and fears of, cultural return reflected in such hybrid literary figures as Déwé Gorodé’s graveyard of ancestral canoes and Pierre Gope’s chefferie internally corrupted in response to the solicitations of Western commodity culture, or Claudine Jacques’ lizard of irrational violence, will need to be addressed in any working out of a common destiny for Kanaky-New Caledonia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pacific literatures in French are little known. In French scholarship, as in French libraries and bookshops, this region of the world has tended to be tacked on to Asia (a category also referred to as Asia-Pacific) in a concession to what is largely absent or imagined as vast and empty. The colonial fracture of the Pacific region into French-speaking and English-speaking countries has continued into the present with the result that the literatures of the French-speaking Pacific that include the indigenous and settler literatures of New Caledonia, French Polynesia, and the now independent Vanuatu have also been virtually unstudied in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Behind the Accounts of First Encounter and the Tales of Oral Tradition:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Kanak-New Caledonian Texts as Palimpsest</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The earliest accounts of the ‘discovery’ of New Caledonia were published in Europe in 1777 from journals written by members of James Cook’s expedition and, later, from the French expedition led by Bruny d’Entrecasteaux.¹ The first European to bear witness to contact with the indigenous peoples, Captain James Cook weighed anchor in Balade in September 1774 and remained in that north-east coast location for eight days. Some nineteen years later, d’Entrecasteaux’s ship used Cook’s accounts to navigate its way through the break in the reef into the same harbour, where his party was to spend three weeks. Like the English</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Writing (In) the Language(s) of the Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translation as Third Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sites of translation from indigenous to European languages, considered in this chapter as further and particular spaces of writing and reading hybridity between cultures, derive from different periods of New Caledonian post-contact history. They also come from different areas of an archipelago that includes the main island of<italic>Grande Terre</italic>, the Isle of Pines and Belep, to the south and to the north respectively, and the Loyalty Islands – Maré, Lifou, and Ouvéa. New Caledonian history is distinctive in that the main island’s geography has resulted in the division of the indigenous peoples into separate language groups, from valley</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Histories of Exile and Home:</title>
                     <subtitle>Strategic Hybridity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters looked at two different kinds of hybrid texts that have resulted from European-Kanak contact: the texts of the European explorers in the eighteenth century and the translations into French of texts of oral tradition in the nineteenth, twentieth, and twenty-first centuries. The present chapter extends the examination of the hybridity of New Caledonian culture(s), their mix of differences and commonalities, by considering the respective approaches to a trope present in the work of every group of writers, from the colonial period to the postcolonial present. This is the theme of exile, or living in-between the lost home,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Locating the First Man in the (Hi)stories of Kanaky:</title>
                     <subtitle>Internal Kanak Hybridities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most of the histories examined in the last chapter reconstruct origins and memory with present socio-political ends in mind. All derive from nostalgia for a past and present home, and seek to establish roots and legitimacy by reconstituting a New Caledonian history that guarantees their community its own place, cultural specificity, and centrality. The dialectic between literature and history, between European and New Caledonian homes, refashions the sense of history in these texts: a (hi)story that is more about a distinctive (group), a political message, and an ethical vision of the future than a faithful reproduction of a past society</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Paradoxical Pathways of the First Kanak Woman Writer:</title>
                     <subtitle>Déwé Gorodé’s Parti Pris of Indigeneity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The two previous chapters have tracked the differences in the shared rewriting of history and of the importance of home in contemporary New Caledonian literatures, in settler literatures (to be considered more fully in later chapters), but most particularly in the three major Kanak versions of the story of the first ancestor, Kanaké/Kënâké. Very different perspectives – political, feminist, and mythico-poetical – are at work within the third spaces constructed by these Kanak rewritings of origin. Each writer, I argued, attempts to connect to a lost or buried Kanak cultural core through his/her exploration and reconstruction of history in necessary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Hybrid Within:</title>
                     <subtitle>The First Kanak Novel, L’Épave [The Wreck], and the Cannibal Ogre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite Gorodé’s resolute centring and valuing of an indigenous vision of the world,<italic>L’Épave</italic>[The Wreck] stands apart from the work of other Pacific writers, not the least for its mordant image of the ancestral canoe become a wreck. This canoe, solidified, metamorphosed into a black rock in the shape of a prow in the tribe’s canoe graveyard, a metonym of the wreckage that strews the novel, is the site of the violation of barely pubescent girls, over generations, by the cannibal ogre-ancestor.</p>
                     <p>The functioning of the canoe and its proliferating avatars as a synecdoche for incest in Gorodé’s first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Cross-cultural Readings of ‘Le Maître de Koné’ [The Master of Koné]:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intertextuality as Hybridity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present chapter investigates in greater depth the nature and effects of the third spaces created in New Caledonia in the encounters between Kanak and<italic>Caldoche</italic>(Caledonian) cultures; a mixing given various labels including<italic>métissage</italic>and, to use the term coined by Nicolas Kurtovitch, ‘interfaces’. Principally concerned with ‘intertexts’, that is, texts shared between cultures, whether borrowed, mimicked, appropriated, re-configured or re-possessed, the chapter will follow the mixed fortunes of the sharing of the story of ‘Le Maître de Koné’ [The Master of [the Land of] Koné]. The consideration of ‘interfaces’ has been narrowed principally to two linked themes central</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Writing Métissage in New Caledonian Non-Kanak Literatures:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Colonial to Postcolonial Hybridities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the nineteenth-century novels set in New Caledonia,<italic>métissage</italic>, as the process and outcome of racial mixing, was most particularly associated with women characters, and largely characterized by sexual permissiveness and biological degeneration. The earliest written literature in New Caledonia was, for the most part, produced by Metropolitan French people passing through. Louise Michel, considered in Chapters 1 and 2, spent eight years in the country’s penitentiary system, leaving New Caledonia after the general amnesty to rejoin her ailing mother in France. Jacques and Marie Nervat came to the colony a decade later, where they lived from 1898 to 1902.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>A Multicultural Future (Destin Commun) for New Caledonia?:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Métissage to Hybridities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a reflection on the manifestations of multiculturalism in postcolonial literature, Sylvie André presents the phenomenon of cultural mixing as a victory over both the colonial will to assimilate and an inevitably unequal separate development. However, as she asks, to what degree must its constitutive elements be fused for a mixed society to consider itself multicultural? Does this require a shared ideological foundation, or is the acceptance of difference or so-called ‘diversity’ sufficient? (2002: 5). English-speaking Canada might consider itself a multicultural country but Quebec, despite thirty years of political coexistence, might well not. Laurence Cros expresses these differences in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Summing Up</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>344</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The various studies of this book have revealed the presence of multiple and shifting hybridities, at all levels of the work of recovery and reconstruction underway in all communities, if to varying degrees of transculturality. Accounts of first contacts on beaches with savages were shown to be largely a product of European Enlightenment thinking, the circulation of European ships and texts. Translation of the texts of oral tradition was an early locus of production of a hybrid new cultural entity, different nonetheless in degrees of transformation in the publications of the red virgin, the missionary-ethnographer, and the contemporary ethnographer. To</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr78q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
