<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JA71.B5345 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Patriotic Elaborations</book-title>
         <subtitle>Essays in Practical Philosophy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BLATTBERG</surname>
               <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773534919</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773576636</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt8054j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Blattberg's is a genuinely original philosophical voice. The essays collected here discuss how to re-conceive the political spectrum, where "deliberative deomocrats" go wrong, why human rights language is tragically counterproductive, how nationalism is not really secular, how many nations should share a single state, a new approach to the Arab-Israeli conflict, and why Canada might have something to teach about the "war on terror." We also learn about the right way to deny a role to principles in ethics, how to distinguish between the good and the beautiful, the way humor works, the rabbinic nature of modernism, the difference between good, bad, great, and evil, why Plato's dialogues are not really dialogues, and why most philosophers are actually artists.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="392"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>C. B.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Political Philosophies and Political Ideologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to proffer a schema. I’m going to present, one at a time, four contemporary political philosophies – I call them neutralism, postmodernism, pluralism, and patriotism¹ – and then show how they relate to political ideologies, such as liberalism, conservatism, socialism, feminism, green ideology, nationalism, fascism, and so on. This will involve more than just advancing a particular typology, however, for in so doing I shall also be putting forth an argument: namely that, given a proper understanding of the relation between philosophy and ideology, postmodernism is superior to neutralism, pluralism to postmodernism, and patriotism to pluralism, making the patriot’s approach</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Patriotic, Not Deliberative, Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both those who defend what I call a patriotic politics and those in favour of a deliberative conception of democracy call on us to try to respond to conflict with conversation rather than just negotiation or bargaining.² And since conversation aims for reconciliation, for realizing the common good, while the compromises of negotiation take us no further than accommodation, both patriots and deliberative democrats can claim an inheritance from the classical republican tradition.³ To classical republicans, negotiation is the mark of a corrupt polity dominated by factions, this being how they would conceive of the politics advocated by contemporary pluralist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Ironic Tragedy of Human Rights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the 1948 United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights, the idea of human rights came into its own on the world stage. More than anything, the Declaration was a response to the Holocaust, to both its perpetrators and the failure of the rest of the world adequately to come to the aid of its victims. Since that year, however, we have seen many more cases of mass murder. Think of China, Bali, Cambodia, Ethiopia, Guatemala, the former Yugoslavia, Rwanda, and now Darfur. Of course, one could always claim that such horrors would have been even more frequent if not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Secular Nationhood?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Importance of Language in the Life of Nations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholars of nationhood have neglected the artists. It is not that they have failed to recognize the sometimes essential role of national artists; rather, it is that they have not given them their due<italic>qua</italic>artists, by which I mean as individuals who engage in a specifically creative process. I want to claim that among the prime sources of both the origins and persistence of nations and nationalism has been an aesthetically contingent one: if not for artists having been inspired to create nations, there would be none, and if not for nations’ continual receptivity to their artists’ creations, an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Federalism and Multinationalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even those who accept that a single country can serve as a home for more than one nation are often led astray by the venerable nationstate model of what a country is or should be. Consider what has become a virtual axiom among scholars of nations and nationalism, namely that nationalists’ concern for self-determination invariably leads to a desire for sovereignty, for the complete control over a state. When applied to multinational federations, the axiom supports the assumption that the members of the minority nations will, at the very least, favour decentralization. Here, for example, is Will Kymlicka:</p>
                     <p>As a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Going Rabin One Further</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are three ways of responding to conflict: conversation, negotiation, and violence. Of course, violence tends, at the end of the day, to be the basis of war, while the other two, being modes of dialogue, are constitutive of politics. But whereas the politics of negotiation aims for accommodation, for resolving conflict through the making of trade-offs and concessions, those who converse strive instead for genuine understanding, for learning from each other and progressively transforming their positions so that they can be not compromised but integrated, reconciled. That is why only conversation is a matter of trying to “convince” people</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Canada, Terror, and the Minimal Global Ethic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his final book,<italic>Justice Is Conflict</italic>, the pluralist political philosopher Sir Stuart Hampshire makes the fundamental point – commonsensical to all except some philosophers – that when faced with conflict, those involved should be willing to compromise. Hampshire’s book begins with the assumption that conflicts are driven by often incommensurable values and that justice requires us to respond to them with an adversarial form of rationality. Faced with a conflict, in other words, we should aim to reach a balanced accommodation with our enemies, and this means negotiating with them in good faith. To Hampshire, this conception of justice is universal,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>From Moderate to Extreme Holism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jonathan Dancy has described his<italic>Ethics without Principles</italic>as the culmination of twenty-five years of work, and indeed it is a major statement by a leading contemporary moral philosopher. Dancy’s basic aim is to provide an alternative to those mainstream, principlesbased approaches to ethics, which is why a great deal of his energy in this and previous works has been devoted to criticizing that mainstream. My critique here, however, is different in that it comes from “the other side,” so to speak, for I wish to argue that Dancy’s alternative does not take us far enough.</p>
                     <p>Central to my argument</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>What’s Wrong with Hypergoods</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles Taylor fails to distinguish enough between art and ethics. Whereas Kant sharply separates the two domains and Hegel brings them close together, subordinating both to his concept of unified philosophical knowledge,¹ Taylor treads an ambiguous path between their positions. Like them, he recognizes that creativity is a unique capacity, that “aesthetic excellence doesn’t just amount to spiritual or moral depth.”² Yet Kant would not be able to accept Taylor’s conception of interpretation as an activity central not only to art criticism but also to ethics, and Hegel would balk at Taylor’s implication that philosophy cannot be said to encompass</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>On the Minimal Global Ethic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where do values come from? I’m tempted to say “the stork” and leave it at that, but perhaps a wiser tack would be to narrow the question somewhat and ask about the origins of those values or goods expressed by what I want to call the “minimal global ethic.” The ethic consists of a set of prohibitions, present in all of the world’s cultures, that speak against such utterly base acts as murder, torture, slavery, and other forms of gross cruelty. Those philosophers who have recognized the ethic have been careful to emphasize its minimalism, which is to say that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Good, Bad, Great, Evil</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a diversity of goods in the world: the various kinds of liberty (political, national, and individual), equality, welfare, happiness, friendship, beauty, family, pleasure, and so on. We come to adopt these goods as we grow up, forming and reforming the unique wholes that constitute our identities. These we realize throughout our lives as we participate in practices, which are but the expression of our goods. More often than not, we carry those practices out prereflectively, habitually, expressing goods that are so closely integrated and harmonious with each other that we are barely aware that they are there. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Opponents vs Adversaries in Plato’s Phaedo</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How are we to understand the philosophy presented in Plato’s dialogues? To be sure, this is not a question about the philosophy that Plato himself affirmed, which is a matter of perhaps interminable controversy. But it is a question that has generated numerous answers in its own right. For the most part, they can be divided into two groups.</p>
                     <p>One reads the dialogues as defending a “theoretical” philosophy, which can be understood either doctrinally or as a way of life. Thus the neo-Platonists through to the modern unitarians claim that the dialogues contain a unified set of doctrines, metaphysical to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Loving Wisdom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hubris or chutzpah? The successful philosopher, it seems, must have a bit of both. For despite the number of rival conceptions of philosophy on offer today, almost everyone recognizes that to philosophize, even when the results of doing so mean that one ends up rejecting philosophy, involves making claims of the greatest scope and generality. Whether these are understood to be universally or more locally relevant is, of course, one of the central issues at stake in the contemporary debates. But even those who emphasize philosophy’s limitations tend to do so with reference to<italic>all</italic>philosophy and philosophers, everywhere. That,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8054j.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
