<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125vm0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">kear16102</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL473.R45 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">God</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Death of God</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and culture</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kearney, Richard</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Interviews</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reimagining the Sacred</book-title>
         <subtitle>Richard Kearney Debates God with James Wood, Catherine Keller, Charles Taylor, Julia Kristeva, Gianni Vattimo, Simon Critchley, Jean-Luc Marion, John Caputo, David Tracey, Jens Zimmermann, and Merold Westphal</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kearney</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
               <given-names>Jens</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231540889</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231540884</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/kear16102"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Contemporary conversations about religion and culture are framed by two reductive definitions of secularity. In one, multiple faiths and nonfaiths coexist free from a dominant belief in God. In the other, we deny the sacred altogether and exclude religion from rational thought and behavior. But is there a third way for those who wish to rediscover the sacred in a skeptical society? What kind of faith, if any, can be proclaimed after the ravages of the Holocaust and the many religion-based terrors since?</p>
         <p>Richard Kearney explores these questions with a host of philosophers known for their inclusive, forward-thinking work on the intersection of secularism, politics, and religion. An interreligious dialogue that refuses to paper over religious difference, these conversations locate the sacred within secular society and affirm a positive role for religion in human reflection and action. Drawing on his own philosophical formulations, literary analysis, and personal interreligious experiences, Kearney develops through these engagements a basic gesture of hospitality for approaching the question of God. His work facilitates a fresh encounter with our best-known voices in continental philosophy and their views on issues of importance to all spiritually minded individuals and skeptics: how to reconcile God's goodness with human evil, how to believe in both God and natural science, how to talk about God without indulging in fundamentalist rhetoric, and how to balance God's sovereignty with God's love.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kearney</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ZIMMERMANN</surname>
                           <given-names>JENS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Richard Kearney is one of the most creative and insightful voices of the so-called theological turn in continental philosophy. His imaginative and constructive application of hermeneutic philosophy to postmodern debates about religion and culture characterizes Kearney’s mature work, contained in the trilogy of publications titled Philosophy at the Limit: On Stories,<italic>The God Who May Be</italic>, and<italic>Strangers, Gods and Monsters</italic>. With these works, Kearney established himself as one of the greatest contemporary philosophical mediators of traditional concepts that define our humanity, such as narrative identity, practical wisdom, hospitality, and perceptions of God. Unlike many postmodern treatments of religion that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>God After God:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Anatheist Attempt to Reimagine God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEARNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I hope it may be useful for the reader to preface this series of dialogues by offering a summary of what I mean by<italic>anatheism</italic>and the need to reimagine the sacred.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ana-</italic>is a prefix defined in the<italic>Shorter Oxford English Dictionary</italic>as, “Up in space or time; back again, anew.” So understood, the term supports the deeper and broader sense of “after” contained in the expression “God after God.” The poet Gerard Manley Hopkins describes the moment of imaginative creation as “aftering, seconding, over and overing.”¹ He speaks of poetic epiphany, accordingly, as a retrieval of past experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Imagination, Anatheism, and the Sacred</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wood</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Wood is a well-known English literary critic, essayist, and novelist. His career as an increasingly influential writer includes positions as the<italic>Guardian</italic>’s chief literary critic (1991– 1994), senior editor of the<italic>New Republic</italic>, staff writer at the<italic>New Yorker</italic>, and professor at Harvard University. After publishing several volumes of essays, Wood has also written a theological novel,<italic>The Book Against God</italic>(2004). Not unlike his novel’s main character, who struggles with his religious background, Wood, an atheist convert from evangelicalism, finds in literature a middle ground between belief and unbelief. Good literature, he argues in<italic>The Broken Estate</italic>, not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Beyond the Impossible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keller</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Catherine Keller is professor of constructive theology at Drew University in Madison, New Jersey. She is a process theologian with wide-ranging theoretical interests, encompassing feminist theology, ecotheology, and poststructuralist and postcolonial theory. In her highly original and influential theological works—most notably<italic>Face of the Deep, From a Broken Web</italic>, and<italic>On the Mystery</italic>—she has sought to develop the relational potential of a theology of becoming. Her books reconfigure ancient symbols of divinity for the sake of a planetary conviviality—a life together, across vast webs of difference. Her latest book,<italic>Cloud of the Impossible</italic>(2014), explores the relation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Transcendent Humanism in a Secular Age</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Taylor</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Canadian philosopher Charles Taylor, one of the finest intellectual commentators on Western culture and religion, has written widely on political philosophy, theories of social science, and the history of philosophy. He is best known for his narrative account of modernity’s cultural origins and potential futures in<italic>Sources of the Self: The Making of Modern Identity</italic>(1989), and, most recently,<italic>A Secular Age</italic>(2007). Especially in the last book, Taylor has shown that modernity’s rejection of religion is itself based on an assumed logic of history, or what he calls a “subtraction narrative”—the story that human progress in any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>New Humanism and the Need to Believe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kristeva</surname>
                           <given-names>Julia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Julia Kristeva is a Bulgarian-French philosopher, literary critic, psychoanalyst, sociologist, feminist, and cultural theorist. Her most recent work on “post-Christian humanism” overlaps significantly with Richard Kearney’s anatheism. Kristeva defines this humanism, with Nietzsche, as “a process of permanent refoundation.”¹ According to Kristeva, European culture is undergoing an unprecedented existential crisis concerning the definition of what it means to be human. We no longer know, “What is a man? What is a woman?” In her view, this crisis calls on the human sciences and humanism to reenvision human structures by creating new languages in literature and the creative arts for a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Anatheism, Nihilism, and Weak Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Critchley</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Italian philosopher and politician Gianni Vattimo is best known for his concept of “weak thought” (<italic>pensiero debole</italic>). Weak thought is Vattimo’s term for his hermeneutic ontology: human existence and perception are interpretive all the way down. In his most recent work, Vattimo has argued for a “hermeneutic communism,” a communism stripped of grand metaphysical assumptions that seeks to stem the tide of capitalism by working on concrete issues—in particular, historical communities. While Vattimo derives his thinking from Nietzsche, Heidegger, and Gadamer, in the works<italic>Belief</italic>(1999) and<italic>After Christianity</italic>(2002) he has also articulated weak thought in terms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>What’s God? “A Shout in the Street”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Critchley</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Simon Critchley is a British philosopher and public intellectual who is now Hans Jonas Professor of Philosophy at The New School for Social Research in New York. Critchley’s interdisciplinary research interests range from continental philosophy, literature, and psychoanalysis to ethics and political theory. After his first major book,<italic>The Ethics of Deconstruction</italic>, on Levinas and Derrida, Critchley published an essay collection on literature, death, and ethics, entitled<italic>Very Little . . . Almost Nothing</italic>, in which he first articulated what he called “atheist transcendence,” a theme that returns in his most recent work,<italic>The Faith of the Faithless</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Critchley’s basic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Death of the Death of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-Luc Marion is arguably the most original and creative living French philosopher in the phenomenological tradition. He is also the foremost proponent of the theological turn in phenomenology, who has argued consistently that phenomenology is open to transcendence and thus, by implication, that a phenomenology of religion is a legitimate philosophical task. In his essays collected as<italic>Le visible et le révélé</italic>(2005), Marion shows how revelation can register in phenomenology as “donation” through “saturated phenomena.”</p>
                     <p>The idea of “donation” builds on Husserl’s and Heidegger’s solution to the Cartesian segregation of the mind from the external world and the resulting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Anatheism and Radical Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Dialogue with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caputo</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John Caputo is an American philosopher of religion with particular expertise in phenomenology, hermeneutics, and deconstruction. He is widely known for developing Derrida’s deconstruction into “radical hermeneutics,” a philosophy that subverts any essentialist claims and resists arresting the play of interpretation.¹ This radical hermeneutics is closely aligned with Caputo’s interest in theopoetics, a term that is variously defined by practitioners but that entails the notion that both God and life are best described poetically rather than rationalistically. Theopoetics, at least in Caputo’s radical hermeneutics, and also in Kearney’s anatheism, has connotations of<italic>poiein</italic>, of making or remaking God through our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Theism, Atheism, Anatheism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <role content-type="author">A Panel Discussion with</role>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tracy</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Westphal</surname>
                           <given-names>Merold</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
                           <given-names>Jens</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following conversation, Richard Kearney’s book<italic>Anatheism</italic>is engaged by one theologian and two theologically inclined philosophers. David Tracy is a well-known Roman Catholic theologian at the University of Chicago Divinity School, who has written important works on hermeneutics and theology (<italic>The Analogical Imagination: Christian Theology and the Culture of Pluralism</italic>and<italic>On Naming the Present: Reflections on God, Hermeneutics, and Church</italic>) and has contributed immensely to interfaith dialogue. In much of his work, Tracy argues for a hermeneutic faith and recovers the incomprehensible God of the mystics, a God who reveals himself in weakness and suffering. Tracy shares</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>In Guise of a Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEARNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thank you for these questions. Rather than respond to each individually, let me try grouping the main points under a few recurring headings: the challenge of the new hermeneutics, power and sovereignty, the key questions of<italic>perichoresis</italic>and kenosis.</p>
                     <p>I will start with a few words on hermeneutics—or what David Tracy calls the “new hermeneutics.” I begin<italic>Anatheism</italic>with a question that Paul Ricoeur asked me when I first attended his seminar in Paris, in 1977. He went around the room and asked each new student, “D’où parlez-vous?” Where do you speak from? Where do you come from? This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Artist’s Note on Cover Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GALLAGHER</surname>
                           <given-names>SHEILA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Pneuma Hostis</italic>is a flaming halo created out of gold-leafed cigarette butts. It is a maze-mandala in the form of a commercial Lasco fan, modeled on the one installed in my studio window in Boston to clear the smoke and toxic fumes from my work space. The butts and the fan blades come together in the shape of a gold host, where inhalation and exhalation, life and death, health and illness, the addict and the saint share the same space.</p>
                     <p>The cover image points to a crossing of the sacred and the profane. This is a central insight of Richard</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">kear16102.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
