<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR428.B66W35 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Books and reading in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Early modern, 1500–1700</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romances, English</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Immaterial Book</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reading and Romance in Early Modern England</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wall-Randell</surname>
               <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472118779</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472029143</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ANN ARBOR</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.4765277"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In romances-Renaissance England's version of the fantasy novel-characters often discover books that turn out to be magical or prophetic, and to offer insights into their readers' selves.<italic>The Immaterial Book</italic>examines scenes of reading in important romance texts across genres: Spenser's<italic>Faerie Queene,</italic>Shakespeare's<italic>Cymbeline</italic>and<italic>The Tempest,</italic>Wroth's<italic>Urania,</italic>and Cervantes'<italic>Don Quixote</italic>. It offers a response to "material book studies" by calling for a new focus on imaginary or "immaterial" books and argues that early modern romance authors, rather than replicating contemporary reading practices within their texts, are reviving ancient and medieval ideas of the book as a conceptual framework, which they use to investigate urgent, new ideas about the self and the self-conscious mind.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="183"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The scene: a hero in an early modern romance is on a journey. The stakes are high; at one point, the prospects for future happiness seemed enormous, and perhaps success is still within reach, but nothing is certain. Along the way, there have been disappointments, delays, and reversals, suffering and doubt. But now the hero finds himself (or herself) in some extraordinary setting—perhaps he enters an ancient library; or has a vision, while in prison, of long-lost parents and descending gods; or discovers an enchanted theater—and he chances upon a book. Opening the book, which may be enormous,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>“Antiquities, Which No Body Can Know”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spenser’s Books and the Romance of the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Amid the most basic premises of<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>as a literary project, among the necessary preconditions of its creation, lies an idea about books: the assumption that books are a powerful medium for transmitting knowledge. “The generall end therefore of all the booke is to fashion a gentleman or noble person in virtuous and gentle discipline,” Spenser says, in the most remembered line of his “Letter to Ralegh,” testifying to a belief that a book, taken in “generall”—that is, both with respect to the class or genre to which it belongs and also as a whole—could make</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Dreaming of the Book in Cymbeline</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Near the end of<italic>Cymbeline</italic>, in a burst of thunder and lightning, the Roman god Jupiter descends, a literal<italic>deus ex machina,</italic>to begin the turn of the play from tragedy to comedy.¹ He presents the despairing Posthumus, who is languishing in prison and wishing for death, with a book that offers a riddling prophecy of a happy ending for Posthumus himself and for the British nation. The giving of the book marks the pivotal moment between what one editor of the play has called “four and a half acts of bad faith, cruelty, violence, and revenge”² and a final</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>“Volumes That I Prize”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Spaces of the Book and the Mind in The Tempest</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Tempest</italic>is a play explicitly shaped by books but in which no book explicitly appears. As several critics have recently noticed, while Prospero’s book is central to the action of Shakespeare’s play, it remains a collection of references, an immaterial presence, not an object.<italic>The Tempest</italic>is “a play about the power of books that refuses to make a spectacle of the book,” as James Kearney puts it; in Paul Yachnin’s formulation, “there are no books in this most bookish of plays.”¹ It is not clear what conventions for the use of books as props were in operation on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>“A Booke Layd By, New Lookt On”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Romance of Reading in Urania and Don Quixote</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early modern romance is a Janus-faced genre. It looks nostalgically backward, to the medieval past and the tales that accrete around English and Continental chivalric heroes: Arthur, Amadis, Guy, Bevis, Roland. At the same time, it pushes the leading edge in generic experimentation, engendering radically new forms, hybrid species such as tragicomic drama, and developing the mode that would ultimately dominate fiction making, the long prose narrative, which became the novel. Evidence that early seventeenth-century English readers themselves regarded romance as participating in such a duality of past and present, traditionalism and modernity, is present in the language of early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I proposed in chapter 4, the sealed book in the enchanted theater in Wroth’s<italic>Urania</italic>calls to mind the book with seven seals in Revelation, perhaps the most book-filled portion of the Bible. There, St. John observes God holding the Book of Truth: “And I sawe in the right hand of him that sate upon the throne, a Boke written within, and on the backeside, sealed with seven seales.”¹ Christ appears as a slain lamb and begins to open the seals, releasing more visions and voices with each stage of opening, so that all the images and admonitions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.4765277.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
