<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1035.P46 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and history</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Persistent Forms: Explorations in Historical Poetics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kliger</surname>
               <given-names>Ilya</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Maslov</surname>
               <given-names>Boris</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITORS</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823264858</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823264889</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18kr6cs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since the mid-1980s, attempts to think history and literature together have produced much exciting work in the humanities. Indeed, some form of historicism can be said to inform most of the current scholarship in literary studies, including work in poetics, yet much of this scholarship remains undertheorized. Envisioning a revitalized and more expansive historicism, this volume builds on the tradition of Historical Poetics, pioneered by Alexander Veselovsky (1838-1906) and developed in various fruitful directions by the Russian Formalists, Mikhail Bakhtin, and Olga Freidenberg. The volume includes previously untranslated texts of some of the major scholars in this critical tradition, as well as original contributions which place that tradition in dialogue with other thinkers who have approached literature in a globally comparatist and evolutionary-historical spirit. The contributors seek to challenge and complement a historicism that stresses proximate sociopolitical contexts through an engagement with the longue duree of literary forms and institutions. In particular, Historical Poetics aims to uncover deep-historical stratifications and asynchronicities, in which formal solutions may display elective affinities with other, chronologically distant solutions to analogous social and political problems. By recovering the traditional nexus of philology and history, Persistent Forms seeks to reinvigorate poetics as a theoretical discipline that would respond to such critical and intellectual developments as Marxism, New Historicism, the study of world literature, practices of distant reading, and a renewed attention to ritual, oral poetics, and genre.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAYOT</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One day someone will look back at the last few de cades of U.S. literary criticism and remark on the strange trajectory of the category of the “universal.” Beginning with the reaction against structuralism, that person will observe a strong conceptual and rhetorical preference for multiplicity, diversity, and smallness across the major categories of the field. Among the many examples of this trend we can include the antagonism toward “grand narratives,” the postcolonial emphasis on hybridity, the resistance to Marxist models of totality (synonymous, briefly, with totalization) or to masculine models of desire seen in French feminism and queer theory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kliger</surname>
                           <given-names>Ilya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maslov</surname>
                           <given-names>Boris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introducing Historical Poetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>History, Experience, Form</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KLIGER</surname>
                           <given-names>ILYA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MASLOV</surname>
                           <given-names>BORIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theory vs. history; form vs. content; artistry vs. ideology; close reading vs. contextualization: these dichotomies are intrinsic to the way literary scholars have come to think of their subject, especially within the—now globally influential—U.S. academy. This volume explores a critical tradition, known as Historical Poetics, that offers a way of negotiating between these familiar oppositions, blending literary theory, history of poetic forms, cultural history, philosophy of history, and (often less overtly) philosophical aesthetics. In the following chapters, this exploration is undertaken on four different fronts—new translations that make available important theoretical work from the past, contributions to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>From the Introduction to Historical Poetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Questions and Answers (1894)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VESELOVSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>ALEXANDER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary history is reminiscent of a geo graphical zone that international law has consecrated as<italic>res nullius,</italic>where the historian of culture and the aesthetician, the erudite antiquarian and the researcher of social ideas all come to hunt. Each carries away what he can, according to his abilities and views; the goods or the quarry display the same tag, but their contents are far from identical. There is no agreement about a common standard, for otherwise we would not return so insistently to the question: What is the history of lit erature?³ One of the views to which I am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Alexander Veselovsky’s Historical Poetics vs. Cultural Poetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering the Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SOMOFF</surname>
                           <given-names>VICTORIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a lecture entitled “From the Introduction to Historical Poetics,” Alexander Veselovsky makes an unusually casual reference, with no precise attribution, to a certain “erudite German [who] has dedicated a special monograph to a single poetic formula, tracing it from popular song to new manifestations in refined literature:<italic>Wenn ich ein Vöglein wär!</italic>There are many formulas like this.”¹ Here the word “formula” stands for any preexisting pattern of verbal expression, from apparently dead meta phors of everyday language (e.g.,<italic>the sun rises</italic>) to artistic topoi, motifs, and plots. Once created, formulas carry on and endure, albeit in a multitude</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Historicist Hermeneutics and Contestatory Ritual Poetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Encounter Between Pindaric Epinikion and Attic Tragedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KURKE</surname>
                           <given-names>LESLIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The challenge of this volume is to think about different models and methods for “literary history” or the historicist reading of literary forms. I contribute to this enterprise as a representative of “New Historicism” or “Cultural Poetics,” and in that capacity, I have been thinking about the similarities and differences between New Historicism and the Russian tradition of “Historical Poetics,” and the usefulness, for the material I work on, of the latter. Both methods reject aestheticism, old-fashioned psychologizing of the author, and literary biography. And both insist on starting from the linguistic structure of the text as a formal system</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Metapragmatics, Toposforschung, Marxist Stylistics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Extensions of Veselovsky’s Historical Poetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MASLOV</surname>
                           <given-names>BORIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alexander Veselovsky’s versatile body of work is notably hard to synthesize, and the method as well as the conceptual apparatus he refined over the years, yet never fully explicated, does not lend itself easily to either systematic summary or piecemeal extraction. It is in part for this reason that Veselovsky’s legacy proved of no direct use to the totalizing twentieth-century theories of literature, such as Structuralism of the French or Soviet varieties, or to the more recent transnational literarycritical practice, whose volatile methodological eclecticism favors the propagation of isolated conceptual moves and argumentative schemata. For Veselovsky’s is an approach that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Oresteia in the Odyssey (1946)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FREIDENBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>OLGA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of Agamemnon is told in the<italic>Odyssey</italic>twelve times. First it is recounted by Zeus (1.29). In spite of the prophecy, Aegisthus married the spouse of the Atrides, whom he then murdered upon his return home; Aegisthus neglected the gods’ advice and Orestes’ revenge—and had to pay for everything. Athena is more succinct (1.298). She only reminds [Telemachus] of the glory of Orestes, who killed the deceitful “father- slayer.” Nestor (3.197) at first only mentions the return of the Atrides, the murder, and Orestes’ revenge. In almost the same words, Athena again speaks about the same events</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Innovation Disguised as Tradition:</title>
                     <subtitle>Commentary and the Genesis of Art Forms</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRAGINSKAYA</surname>
                           <given-names>NINA V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For millennia, in a wide variety of different cultures, connected or not, commentary has been an unquestioned and indeed the most respected form of studying a text. We might think of such traditions as Neoplatonism, Confucianism, Mishna and the Talmud, Christian exegesis, Indian, Arabic, and other traditions of commentary. It is only in recent years, however, that commentary has become<italic>a problem in and of itself.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The European tradition of commentary has been reliant upon an unspoken consensus about what commentary is; this consensus has been passed down from teacher to student, based in a robust, albeit implicit understanding of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>A Remnant Poetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Excavating the Chronotope of the Kurgan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KUNICHIKA</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One needed to know little about Vshchizh, a settlement located in the southeast of Russia. It was situated on the right bank of the Desna river; the nearest city was Briansk; it was razed by Mongols sometime in the thirteenth century; and not far from it was a complex of kurgans, or burial mounds, which archaeologists had begun excavating in the 1840s.¹ These were some of the few facts recorded in the entry “Vshchizh” in the 1896 Brokgauz-Efron encyclopedia, which designated it an “insignificant settlement.”² Although condemned to insignificance, Vshchizh does possess some value for Russian literary history because two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>On “Genre Memory” in Bakhtin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KLIGER</surname>
                           <given-names>ILYA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of “genre memory,” proposed by Mikhail Bakhtin in the second edition of his book on Dostoevsky from 1963, names one of the most vivid and enigmatic figurations of literary-historical continuity we have. It is of course not the first attempt to think such continuity within the Russian tradition. Almost one hundred years before Bakhtin coined the term, Alexander Veselovsky, the founder of Historical Poetics as a paradigm within literary scholarship, wondered whether “each new poetic epoch [does] not work on images bequeathed from antiquity, being of necessity constrained by their boundaries.”¹ Veselovsky would go on to refine and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>The Age of Sensibility (1904)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VESELOVSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>ALEXANDER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the first third of the eighteenth century, a new style begins to install itself in European literatures. Wherever it was engendered, it was preceded by a corresponding mood<italic>[nastroenie]</italic>of the social psyche, a reflection of the recently accomplished social revolution. This is what happened in England, which explains England’s leading role in the ensuing currents of European thought, the influence of its didactic comedy and its<italic>comédie larmoyante,</italic>its novelists, whom Diderot and Rousseau indulged in reading. This influence had an uneven impact, depending on how well prepared, in a given society, the soil was to receive the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Against Ornament:</title>
                     <subtitle>O. M. Freidenberg’s Concept of Metaphor in Ancient and Modern Contexts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay on historical poetics will comprise two parts: historical and poetic. To put it another way, I will attempt to offer a theoretical examination and then a practical explication, the former dealing with the concept of metaphor as developed and employed by the sadly neglected Soviet-era philologist and theoretician Olga Mikhailovna Freidenberg, the latter centered on the poetry of Pindar. The goal is to see how Freidenberg’s work might still be of relevance and usefulness, not just in relation to more recent theories of metaphor, but also as a heuristic device in the study of archaic Greek poetry, one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Breakfast at Dawn:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alexander Veselovsky and the Poetics of Psychological Biography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VINITSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>ILYA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the authors of the introduction to this volume observe, one of the goals of Veselovsky’s historical poetics dealt with uncovering “the ways in which literary practices constitute[d] historical experience by perpetuating conceptual, emotional, and behavioral schemata across space and time.”³ In this context, the ill-famed “age of Sensibility” in Russia⁴ presented a special interest for Veselovsky. In his classical book on Vasily Zhukovsky’s life and work, eloquently subtitled<italic>The Poetry of Sentiment and of the “Heart’s Imagination”</italic>(1903; published in 1904), the scholar posed an intriguing question of how the Western literary modes of sentimentality were absorbed by a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>From the Prehistory of Russian Novel Theory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alexander Veselovsky and Fyodor Dostoevsky on the Modern Novel’s Roots in Folklore and Legend</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOLLAND</surname>
                           <given-names>KATE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholarly work on the subject of Alexander Veselovsky rarely, if ever, deals with the fact that the philologist and folklorist was an exact contemporary of the great Russian novelists Dostoevsky, Turgenev, and Tolstoy, and that most of his philological work was done in the period of the generic hegemony of the Russian novel. At first sight this omission seems understandable; in his own scholarly work Veselovsky was more interested in examining archaic drama and medieval legends than the works of his own contemporaries. Yet like his more internationally renowned successor, Mikhail Bakhtin, Veselovsky used the medium of genre as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Satire (1940), for the Literary Encyclopedia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAKHTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>MIKHAIL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1. The word “satire” denotes three phenomena:</p>
                     <p>1) a specific, small- scale lyrico- epic genre that formed and developed on Roman soil (Naevius, Ennius, Lucilius, Horace, Persius, Juvenal) and was resurrected in modern times by the neoclassicists (the satires of Mathurin Régnier, Boileau, Kantemir et al.).</p>
                     <p>2) another, less well- defined, mixed (mainly prose), purely dialogical genre that appeared in the Hellenistic epoch in the form of the philosophical diatribe (Bion [of Borysthenes], Teles [of Megala]) was reformed and standardized by the Cynic Menippus (third century B.C.E.), and was named in his honor “Menippean satire.” We find later exemplars of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 14</label>
                     <title>Columbus’s Egg, or the Structure of the Novella (1973)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GASPAROV</surname>
                           <given-names>MIKHAIL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of Columbus’s egg (the degree of its unreliability does not concern us here) is usually told as follows. At a dinner table Columbus challenges his esteemed companions to make an egg stand on its sharp end. They make an attempt at this, rotating the egg in this and that way, all to no avail. Then Columbus takes the egg, gently taps its sharp end against the table, and makes the egg stand. “What, was it allowed to break the egg?” asked the disappointed onlookers. “Who said it wasn’t allowed?” Columbus replied.</p>
                     <p>The structure of this ruse is clear.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 15</label>
                     <title>On the Eve of Epic:</title>
                     <subtitle>Did the Chryses Episode in Iliad I Begin Its Life as a Separate Homeric Hymn?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FARAONE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bakhtin famously argued that in his day the novel was a young “genrein-the-making” that easily absorbed other genres, both the literary (e.g., epic and tragedy) and the mundane (e.g., epistle and legal transcript). In the larger project from which this essay is excerpted, I examine how orally composed Homeric epic (as we find it inscribed in the<italic>Iliad</italic>and<italic>Odyssey</italic>) likewise absorbed both the form and content of other, shorter hexametrical genres, especially those performed in clearly defined ritual contexts, as, for example, hymns, oracles and incantations. In what follows I argue that a good deal of the first book</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 16</label>
                     <title>Schematics and Models of Genre:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bakhtin and Soviet Satire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BIRD</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alexander Veselovsky, one of the earliest proponents of Historical Poetics, once shared an alarmingly pessimistic view of the kind and quality of knowledge produced by the literary scholarship of his day:</p>
                     <p>The history of lit erature is reminiscent of a geographical strip which international legislation has sanctioned [<italic>osviatilo</italic>] as<italic>res nullius</italic>, where the historian of culture and aes the ti cian, the erudite and the researcher of social ideas, all venture to hunt. Each bears forth from it what he can, according to his capabilities and views, with the same label on the goods or kill [<italic>dobycha</italic>], although it be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FURTHER READINGS IN HISTORICAL POETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>463</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr6cs.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
