<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Onslaught against Innocence</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LaCocque</surname>
               <given-names>André</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173190</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903346</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>André LaCocque</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf49n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While in Genesis 2-11 the Yahwist confronts the issue of evil through a sequence of stories on the progressive deterioration of the divine-human relationship, in Genesis 4 he describes the initial slaughter of one human being by another as fratricidal. This book provides a close reading of J's story by using literary criticism and psychological criticism, and shows that the biblical author has more than an "archaeological" design. His characters - including God, Adam, Eve, Cain, and Abel, plus minor character - are paradigmatic, as they allow J to proceed with a fine analytical feel for the nature of evil as performed by "homo" as "homini lupus." No imaginative "mimesis" of evil has ever been recounted with such an economy of means and such depth of psychological insight.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="188"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a companion volume to<italic>The Trial of Innocence: Adam, Eve, and the Yahwist</italic>.¹ It prolongs my essay on the dialectic anthropology according to J in Gen 2:4—4:1. Each book stands on its own, however, and can be read independently.</p>
                     <p>Here again, because the story of Cain and Abel is so well and so universally known, as is the tale of Adam and Eve, there can hardly be a first “reading” of it. Even our first encounter with the text is already a “rereading.” There is nothing to lament about for, as Gary Saul Morson states, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>The Anthropological Dimension</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jstates that Cain offered the fruit of his fare to God. Abel did the same with the product of his shepherding. From the very beginning of his narrative composition, J has displayed a striking preoccupation with the human work. Does it mean originally the opposite of rest and enjoyment? J’s first answer comes with the myth of Adam and Eve, and it is a resounding No. In the Garden of Eden, the human enjoyable activity was work (see Gen 2: 15). But, while the origin of work is devoid of pain and anxiety, it is transformed after the human transgression</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>The Theological Dimension</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kinship relations belong to the sacred—this point is emphasized in our narrative by God’s constant presence and concern for domestic affairs, which are elevated thereby to a superior level. And this deserves all our attention, for the natural brotherly kinship is transcended. It receives a special divine confirmation and is the object of a special divine care. J, who had already stressed the oneness of husband and wife in Genesis 2–3, now shows the sacredness of the family ties. Cain’s fratricide will not just be unnatural, but blasphemous. A crime against nature is a grievous thing, but a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>The Psychological Dimension</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the first time in the Bible, blood is mentioned, as well as its virtue of epitomizing life that belongs to God (4:10; see 9:4–6). Let us start with a philological note: although the singular “blood” (<italic>dam</italic>) may only at times refer to blood shed by violence (see Num 35:33), the plural<italic>damim</italic>, as we have it here in Gen 4: 10, is more specifically blood spilled or blood-guilt (see Num 35:27; Exod 22:1). The expression “man of blood” (‘iš damim) designates a murderer (see 2 Sam 16:7, 8; Ps 5:7) and “city of blood” (‘iš damim) designates a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Genealogy and Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>George A. Barton, in his article “A Sumerian Source of the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of Genesis,”¹ argues that we can trace the list of names in Genesis 4–5 to a Sumerian tablet of Nippur, held at the University Museum in Philadelphia. Barton’s lists, set in parallel, of the documents from Akkad and the Bible are particularly interesting.¹ They would show the derivation of the name “Abel” from Etana the shepherd, who went to heaven, and of the name “Cain” from Pilikam, which means “with intelligence to build.”³</p>
                     <p>But even if Barton were right, the “Sumerian source” appears rather</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf49n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
