<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16xwbwn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Eco</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Anthology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Capozzi</surname>
               <given-names>Rocco</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253332752</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253112828</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253112826</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz0xk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>[READING ECO is a timely indication] of the fruitfulness of perceiving Eco as the same in his metamorphoses. [It also testifies] to a certain price that Eco and his readers must/may pay for the enormous pleasure and intellectual stimulus of being Eco and being with Eco." -The Comparatist</p>
         <p>Umberto Eco is, quite simply, a genius. He is a renowned medievalist, philosopher, novelist, a popular journalist, and linguist. He is as warm and witty as he is learned-and quite probably the best-known academic and novelist in the world today. The goal of this anthology is to examine his ideas of literary semiotics and interpretation as evidenced both in his scholarly work and in his fiction.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="512"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sebeok</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the peak of Summer in 1981, I land in Rome from overseas. For the first time, I glimpse<italic>Il nome della rosa</italic>, by my long-time friend and semiotic comrade-in-arms, Umberto Eco, published a few months earlier, displayed wherever books are sold. I buy a copy–“Naturalmente, un manoscritto”–prove the resonance of its Old Testament beginnings, then continue browsing at my hotel, wide-eyed from jet lag, late into the night. I finish reading the novel during sleepless times to follow in the course of a dozen train-rides up and down Italy and nights in hotels, until I reach “stat</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Capozzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Rocco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.1</label>
                     <title>Semiotics and the Philosophy of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eco</surname>
                           <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many disciplines–such as linguistics or iconography or musicology–that are concerned with different semiotic systems, of which they represent the rules of functioning. We will call these disciplines<italic>grammars</italic>. In this sense Italian linguistics is a grammar, as is the study of gestural languages, or as it can be the study of different types of road signals. Any theory of signs that assumed to be a general or universal grammar would be a grammar in the above sense in so far as it takes into account only these rules that are allegedly at work in every sign-system,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.2</label>
                     <title>Innovation and Repetition:</title>
                     <subtitle>Between Modern and Post-Modern Aesthetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eco</surname>
                           <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is not by chance that modern aesthetics and modern theories of art (and I mean by “modern” those born with Mannerism, developed through Romanticism, and provocatively restated by the early-twentieth-century avant-gardes) have frequently identified the artistic message with metaphor. Metaphor (the new and inventive one, not the worn-out catachresis) is a way to designate something by the name of something else, thus presenting that something in an unexpected way. The modern criterion for recognizing the artistic value was<italic>novelty</italic>, high information. The pleasurable repetition of an already known pattern was considered, by modern theories of art, typical of Crafts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.3</label>
                     <title>Two Problems in Textual Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eco</surname>
                           <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The two sections below are two further elaborations of the theory of the interpretation of narrative texts presented in<italic>The Role of the Reader</italic>(1979) and then developed further in<italic>Lector in Fabula</italic>(1979).</p>
                     <p>For the convenience of the reader, I am presenting here the table of levels of textual cooperation (published in<italic>Role</italic>14). In the box on discursive structures I did not sufficiently develop the voice “chosen of the isotopies,” since the concept of isotopy was there understood as used in Greimas’ semiotics. As to the deeper intensional levels, in<italic>The Role of the Reader</italic>I have developed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.4</label>
                     <title>Universe Of The Mind.</title>
                     <subtitle>A Semiotic Theory Of Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eco</surname>
                           <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the course of his intellectual career, Yuri M. Lotman has applied his mind to a wide range of disciplines: aesthetics, poetics, semiotic theory, the history of culture, mythology, and cinema, in addition to the principle themes of the history of Russian literature of which he is Professor at the University of Tartu in Estonia. His works range from the analysis of cultural phenomena such as blue jeans, and observations on demonology, through readings of poetic texts and consideration of the problems of interpretation, to references to mathematics and biology. However, even readers unfamiliar with the entire range of Lotman’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.5</label>
                     <title>An Author and his Interpreters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eco</surname>
                           <given-names>Umberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have repeatedly tried, in the course of the last 15 years, not to speak about my novels. First of all I decided not to answer silly questions and once I made a list of 12 stupid questions for which I have already provided 12 stupid answers. I remember that the first question was “Why did you choose this tide?” and the answer was “Because Pinocchio and Snow White were already copyrighted”.</p>
                     <p>Then I think that a narrator, as well as a poet, should never provide interpretations of his own work. A text is a machine conceived for eliciting interpretations.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.1</label>
                     <title>The Open Work in Theory and Practice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Seed</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reviewing the early works of George Eliot in 1866 Henry James reflected on the possibility of foreshadowing later events in narratives without every describing them. This possibility leads James to make the following statement about the composition of novels: “In every novel the work is divided between the writer and the reader; but the writer makes the reader very much as he makes his characters. When he makes him ill, that is, makes him different, he does no work; the writer does all. When he makes him well, that is, makes him interested, then the reader does quite half the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.2</label>
                     <title>Looking back on A Theory of Semiotics:</title>
                     <subtitle>One Small Step for Philosophy, One Giant Leap for the Doctrine of Signs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deely</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1976, Umberto Eco’s<italic>Trattato di semiotica generale</italic>, published by Bompiani the year before, appeared in the English translation of David Osmond-Smith¹ under the title<italic>A Theory of Semiotics</italic>. This volume was the first in the Advances in Semiotics series begun with the Indiana University Press under the editorship of Thomas A. Sebeok. The series now exceeds forty-six volumes, and the<italic>Theory of Semiotics</italic>has appeared in perhaps as many languages as the series has volumes. A general study heretofore pursued mostly by writers of solitary genius (such as John Poinsot in the seventeenth century and Charles Peirce in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.3</label>
                     <title>The Themata of Eco’s Semiotics of Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Doležel</surname>
                           <given-names>Lubomir</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a key passage of<italic>The Book of Laughter and Forgetting</italic>Milan Kundera poses the question why the mature Beethoven “committed his most beautiful meditations” to the form of variations. At first glance, variations might appear to be “the most superficial of forms, … a work suited for a lacemaker rat her than a Beethoven”. But when the son-writer deciphers the unfinished gesture of his dying father-musicologist, he comes to understand that the form of variations is a voyage “into the infinite internal variety which is hidden in every thing”. The variation technique, a tenacious pursuit of certain themata with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.4</label>
                     <title>Toward Interpretation Semiotics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petrilli</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The mid 1970s onward have been decisive years in Italian semiotics considering both the development in general sign theory as well as the flourishing of the various specific semiotics. In fact, these years mark a transition from decodification semiotics, which was influenced either directly or indirectly by Saussurean linguistics, to interpretation semiotics, largely a derivation of the Peircean-Morrisian tradition. Two books by Umberto Eco–A<italic>Theory of Semiotics</italic>of 1975 and<italic>Semiotics and the Philosophy of Language</italic>of 1984–may be viewed as expressions of this transition. Indeed, Eco’s<italic>A Theory of Semiotics</italic>may be taken as the point of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.5</label>
                     <title>Openness, Eco, and the End of Another Millennium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rauch</surname>
                           <given-names>Irmengard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The origin and nature of language as an object of human curiosity is entering its third millenium of study in the Western world. Discussion of this premier semiotic system, language, has ever been suspended in a tension between historiographically so-called Analogists and Anomalists (cf. Colson 1919), be they from among, e.g., the Greek Ancients or from among, e.g., the contemporary Cognitivists. Whether to understand the nature of language as natural or conventional, rule driven or usage bound, regular or irregular and the myriad proximate and distal implications deriving from these Western metaphysical bifurcations remains thus an unabated subliminal, if not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.6</label>
                     <title>Eco, Peirce, and the Necessity of Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tejera</surname>
                           <given-names>Victorino</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At a time when the lines between literary theory, literary criticism, and literature have been deliberately blurred by so many critics and theorists–it is good to have a book on the problems of contemporary text theory from the learned littérateur and semeiotician Umberto Eco¹. The essays that make up his book, he tells us, “study … the dialectics between the rights of texts and the rights of their interpreters;” they also seek to “stress the limits of the act of interpretation.” He finds that, having “advocated an active role of the interpreter in the reading of texts … with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.7</label>
                     <title>Semiotics and Deconstruction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buczynska-Garewicz</surname>
                           <given-names>Hanna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Semiotics and deconstruction deal with the question of text, its meaning and interpretation. They both are significant and influential contemporary theories of meaning. However, the sense of meaning and interpretation provided by them is very different. They are contradictory rather then complementary theories. Semiotics is general theory of signs which intends to clarify signs and to “make our ideas clear”, while deconstruction stresses the notion of “indecidability” of meaning and intends to refutation of logocentrism. If the rational analysis is still the main method of semiotics, certainly deconstruction focuses on the limits of reason and opens avenue for irrationalism. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.8</label>
                     <title>The Interpretant in Literary Semiotics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Riffaterre</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is an attempt at adapting Peirce’s semiotic model to the analysis of literary texts. It could not have been written without Umberto Eco’s seminal contributions to semiotics and to the theory of interpretation.</p>
                     <p>Semantic and formal constant features of literature can be identified that may help define a literary kind of sign. Intertextuality¹ offers an effective model for the understanding of the relationships between these features. No definition of a specialized literary sign can have any validity, however, unless it can be integrated in a general theory of signs. I propose therefore to test poetics against semiotics by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.9</label>
                     <title>On Truth and Lying:</title>
                     <subtitle>Umberto Eco and Algirdas Julien Greimas</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perron</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Debbèche</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fellow travelers and long term acquaintances, Umberto Eco and Algirdas Julien Greimas’ friendship and collaboration date from the beginning of the 1960s. Indeed, they both published a chapter in the seminal volume,<italic>Communications 8, L’analyse structurale du récit</italic>, edited by Roland Barthes, along with Claude Bremond, Christian Metz, Tzvetan Todorov and Gérard Genette, to name but the most prominent of the contributors who were to have a major impact on the shaping of theory and methodology in the social sciences and the humanities. Greimas’ contribution, “Eléments pour une théorie de l’interprétation mythique,” consisted in working out the descriptive procedures for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.10</label>
                     <title>Eco and Dramatology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kevelson</surname>
                           <given-names>Roberta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That Eco makes frequent recourse to narrative fiction is not surprising since the semiotician and the author of fictive narrative are two of the most public faces he presents to us who adore and admire him from whatever portion of himself he gives freely and with great gusto. But what is a surprising fact, to use Peirce’s notable term for that which comes to us from experience and shakes us out of old habit into new play, is Eco’s occasional mention of the dramatic text as representing through the work of so me twentieth-century playwrights a prototype of the indeterminacy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.11</label>
                     <title>Esoteric Conspiracies and the Interpretative Strategy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Longoni</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present critical debate focuses on the role of the interpreter who can be seen shifting between two extremes, dangerously near the edge of the deconstructionist whirl or firmly anchored to the objectivity of the text.</p>
                     <p>In this debate the literary theories interlace with the philosophical ones, and criticism is in danger of getting lost in the labyrinth of its numerous and divergent tracks, which can lead to the unique and absolute textual truth or, in the opposite direction, to the never-ending replacement of meanings.</p>
                     <p>The predominant question is: does there exist a legitimate interpretation and therefore a watershed which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.12</label>
                     <title>Interpretation and Overinterpretation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Rights of Texts, Readers and Implied Authors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Capozzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Rocco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sensational “success story”¹ of Umberto Eco’s first internationally acclaimed best-seller novel<italic>The Name of the Rose</italic>(1980), followed by<italic>Foucault’s Pendulum</italic>(1988) and<italic>The Island of the Day Before</italic>(1995), has been accompanied by an increasing amount of attention given to the author’s writings on interpretation vis-à-vis his views on semiotics, textual analysis, narratology, postmodernism, and reader response theories. In North America, Eco’s role among contemporary theorists of literary criticism became noticeable after the publication of<italic>A Theory of Semiotics</italic>(1975; 1976) and<italic>The Role of the Reader</italic>(1979). Today, after the appearance of<italic>Semiotics and the Philosophy of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.1</label>
                     <title>Gaudy Rose:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eco and Narcissism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Lauretis</surname>
                           <given-names>Teresa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What’s in a name? asks Juliet, who is a woman and knows the tide, the ebb and flow, the pull of the real. Eco answers her question simply, yet implicating the whole of philosophy and the vicissitudes of Western epistemology: everything and nothing.<italic>Stat rosa pristina nomine. Nomina nuda tenemus</italic>(<italic>Rose</italic>503). But Juliet’s, of course, was a rhetorical question, and Eco’s answer is not what she wants. We leave Juliet at the balcony unfulfilled, as she must be, and go on to scene two.</p>
                     <p>Imagine now Adam and Eve in the garden of Eden, naked, without guilt and (naturally,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.2</label>
                     <title>The Mirrored World:</title>
                     <subtitle>Form and Ideology in Umberto Eco’s The Name of the Rose</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Richter</surname>
                           <given-names>David H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Devoted scanners of the<italic>New York Times</italic>lists of best-selling books were probably mystified in the summer of 1983 by the apparition at the top of the fiction charts of<italic>The Name of the Rose</italic>, a first novel by Umberto Eco. Eco might have been a household word to semioticians and structuralist critics of narrative, but his name meant nothing to the general public. The popularity of his novel must have had a great deal to do with its being a mystery novel; neither of Eco’s later novels has done as well. But despite its superficial genre,<italic>The Name of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.3</label>
                     <title>Give Me Another Horse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sebeok</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There hangs in London’s National Portrait Gallery a 1926 cartoon by Bernard Partridge, depicting Sir Arthur Conan Doyle as “the slave of his creation, Sherlock Holmes.</p>
                     <p>Because “The Adventure of the Lion’s Mane” (Doyle 1967:776-89), first published in the same year, 1926, represents a singularly radical stylistic experiment on the part of its author, then age 67, this, of all his mysteries, surely became one the most intriguing in the entire Sherlock Holmes corpus of 56 short stories: for Holmes, then living in retirement in his Sussex home, necessarily conducts his investigation there in the absence of Watson. As the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.4</label>
                     <title>Interpretation, Overinterpretation, Paranoid Interpretation and Foucault’s Pendulum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bondanella</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only a very naive reader of<italic>Il pendolo di Foucault</italic>(1988,<italic>Foucault’s Pendulum</italic>) would not presume that Umberto Eco’s second novel can be enriched by reference to Eco’s theoretical works on narrative theory, semiotics, and popular culture. But the most important clue to Eco’s thinking while he composed this difficult work is infrequently cited by his critics. It is a theoretical introduction to a collection of Italian essays on esoteric interpretations of Dante from the nineteenth century–<italic>L’idea deforme: interpretazioni esoteriche di Dante</italic>(1989,<italic>The Distorted Idea: Esoteric Interpretations of Dante</italic>)–research carried out by Eco’s students in a seminar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.5</label>
                     <title>Bellydancing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gender, Silence, and the Women of Foucault’s Pendulum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coletti</surname>
                           <given-names>Theresa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>300</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shortly after the European puhlication of Umherto Eco’s second novel, the noted historian Jacques Le Goff wrote an essay in which he argued that<italic>Foucault’s Pendulum</italic>, despite the modernity of its historical setting, was as profoundly anchored in the Middle Ages as its predecessor,<italic>The Name of the Rose</italic>.¹ Detailing the many ways that Eco’s novels represent their complicated debts to medieval discourses, ideas, and social practices, Le Goff observed a decisively medieval quality in their respective figurations of gender: “The Middle Ages was an epoch of men … the novels of Umberto Eco are men’s novels. This is clear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.6</label>
                     <title>Irony-clad Foucault</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hutcheon</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In certain critical circles, from the moment the tide of Umberto Eco’s second novel was announced, the speculation began.<italic>The Name of the Rose</italic>had been chock full of more semiotic theories than most competent readers could ever hope to discern. Did this mean that the more helpfully named<italic>Foucault’s Pendulum</italic>would come complete with long discourses on sexuality, knowledge, and power? It was true that Eco had not often mentioned Michel Foucault by name in his theoretical work before this, but the tide was certainly directive, was it not? Then we began to read the novel. And—only then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.7</label>
                     <title>The Swing of the ‘Pendulum’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eco’s Novels</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zamora</surname>
                           <given-names>Lois Parkinson</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>328</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Umberto Eco is a phenomenon. The range of his erudition, the centrality of his influence in a number of academic disciplines and discourses, the originality, insight, diversity and sheer volume of his writings defy comparison among his contemporaries. So does the size of his audience.<italic>The Name of the Rose</italic>, written in the popular narrative mode of the analytical detective story, made Umberto Eco a household word in the U.S., Europe, and Latin America. The novel seemed effortlessly to breach the usually impenetrable line between elite and mass culture in this country - a feat achieved by only a few</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.8</label>
                     <title>“Whose ‘Excess of Wonder’ Is It Anyway?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Umberto Eco’s Tangle of Hermetic and Pragmatic Semiosis in The Island of the Day Before”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bouchard</surname>
                           <given-names>Norma</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To the reader unacquainted with Eco’s work,¹<italic>The Island of the Day Before</italic>is likely to be read as an historical-cum romance novel relating the adventures of a seventeenth-century man–Roberto de La Griva–reconstructed by an anonymous narrator from his letters and unfinished novel. Following an arrest in Paris, Roberto is offered a chance for freedom by the Cardinal Mazarin if he agrees to go on a mission to uncover the British attempt to find the “<italic>punto fijo</italic>;” the fixed point to measure the longitudes which was sought by European navigators till Harrison’s invention of the maritime chronometer. Roberto</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.9</label>
                     <title>‘Dove’ is the Dove?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miranda</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>362</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this paper is not a reference to Stein’s “a rose is a rose is a rose” as Stein was playing with the multiple connotations of the word “rose” in the “encyclopedia.” My tide plays with homophony because “dove”–which in English means “where”–in 1talian stands for “colomba,” and in Umberto Eco’s<italic>The Island of the Day Before</italic>, the “dove” stands for different significations, such as an oracular bird of unusual color, a symbol of “the day before,” a 17th-century emblem, an enigma to be solved, and, possibly, the key to this<italic>roman à clef. The Island</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.10</label>
                     <title>Intertextuality, Metaphors, and Metafiction as Cognitive Strategies in The Island of the Day Before</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Capozzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Rocco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Island of the Day Before</italic>(1995) is Umberto Eco’s third encyclopedic postmodern collage and essay-novel which focuses, among many other things, on the practice of semiosis, on palimpsests, on meta-narrativity, and on the connection between “knowledge and power.”¹ Capitalizing on three most significant heterogeneous historical eras, the XIVth and XVIIth Centuries (two extraordinary periods of history marked by revolutionary transformations in all sectors of society),² and the XXth Century (an era exemplified by frequent changes and by so called postmodern pastiches and recyclings of every cultural phenomenon from the past) Eco’s trilogy³ illustrates how man’s eternal quest for knowledge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.1</label>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.2</label>
                     <title>Integrated Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>440</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0xk.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.3</label>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>473</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
