<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P301.5.M48D66 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Metaphor</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Donoghue</surname>
               <given-names>Denis</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674430662</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780674419483</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Denis Donoghue</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt6wps2d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Metaphor supposes that an ordinary word could have been used, but instead something unexpected appears. The point of a metaphor is to enrich experience by bringing different associations to mind, by giving something a different life. The prophetic character of metaphor, Denis Donoghue says, changes the world by changing our sense of it.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>a</italic>metaphor, according to I. A. Richards, is “a shift, a carrying over of a word from its normal use to a new use.”¹ That definition is good enough: the root meaning is to transfer a word from one place to another: μεταϕερειη. It supposes that there is an ordinary word that could have been used but hasn’t been: instead, another word is used that drives the statement in an unexpected direction. Richards calls the ordinary or expected word the<italic>tenor</italic>—whether it’s spoken or not—and the unexpected one the<italic>vehicle</italic>. The metaphor is the whole episode, tenor and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>figures of speech, figures of thought: I was suffused with metaphors and other figures before I knew there were such things. When I was a boy, growing up in Warrenpoint, County Down, Northern Ireland, from about 1932 to 1942, I attended evening devotions with my mother at our local Catholic Church, St. Peter’s. My father and my brother Tim accompanied us to Mass on Sundays, but they did not extend their observance beyond that duty. My father was a straightforward Catholic, but he was not devout. Tim was sullen as if on principle, but even in his most truculent moods</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>After Aristotle</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>i find in Gustav Stern’s<italic>Meaning and Change of Meaning with Special Reference to the English Language</italic>(1931) definitions of simile and metaphor that are more elaborate than Richards’s. “A simile consists in the formal and avowed comparison of one thing to another.” A metaphor is “a figure of speech in which (1) the enhancement is the result of a fusion between two disparate notions,<italic>i.e.,</italic>there is no essential identity between the two referents involved; and (2) the relation between the two referents is not expressed.”¹ “Fusion” is not helpful, it sets up a new problem by being itself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>No Resemblance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mrs. Riordan’s Protestant neighbors were justified in asking, of the Litany of the Blessed Virgin, “How could a woman be a tower of ivory or a house of gold,” but they were wrong to assume that the question was decisive.¹ They had read too many nineteenth-century realist novels. Empson’s understanding of language was more generous. Commenting on two lines from Arthur Waley’s Chinese translations—</p>
                     <p>Swiftly the years, beyond recall.</p>
                     <p>Solemn the stillness of this spring morning—</p>
                     <p>he remarked:</p>
                     <p>Lacking rhyme, metre, and any overt device such as comparison, these lines are what we should normally call poetry only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“It Ensures That Nothing Goes without a Name”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The second chapter of<italic>Genesis</italic>reports that God brought “every beast of the field, and every fowl of the air” to Adam “to see what he would call them.” “Whatsoever Adam called every living creature, that was the name thereof.” Presumably the name gave official reference to each thing, according to its kind. Pointing to a particular thing, Adam declared it to be, I assume, an animal and, as a particular instance among animals, a cow. Figures of speech and figures of thought were not required; the name covered everything, literally, that needed to be said. Anything in the world</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Not Quite against Metaphor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On December 6, 1921, Franz Kafka, reading to himself a short sentence from a light-hearted letter he had recently written to his friend Robert Klopstock—“Ich wärme mich daran in diesem traurigen Winter (During this dreary winter I warm myself from this)”¹—commented in his diary (I repeat):</p>
                     <p>Metaphors are one among many things that make me despair of writing. Writing’s lack of independence of the world, its dependence on the maid who tends the fire, on the cat warming itself by the stove; it is even dependent on the poor old human being warming himself by the stove. All</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Motive for Metaphor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>the strongest motive for metaphor known to me is conveyed by Quintilian in a glowing passage:</p>
                     <p>[Metaphor] is both a gift which Nature herself confers on us, and which is therefore used even by uneducated persons and unconsciously, and at the same time so attractive and elegant that it shines by its own light however splendid its context. So long as it is correctly employed, it cannot be vulgar or mean or unpleasing. It also adds to the resources of language by exchanges or borrowings to supply its deficiencies, and (hardest task of all) it ensures that nothing goes without</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wps2d.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
