<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kw28s4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr6tw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sexual Disorientations</book-title>
         <subtitle>Queer Temporalities, Affects, Theologies</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BRINTNALL</surname>
               <given-names>KENT L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MARCHAL</surname>
               <given-names>JOSEPH A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MOORE</surname>
               <given-names>STEPHEN D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITORS</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823277520</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823277544</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823277542</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr6tw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Sexual Disorientations brings some of the most recent and significant works of queer theory into conversation with the overlapping fields of biblical, theological and religious studies to explore the deep theological resonances of questions about the social and cultural construction of time, memory, and futurity. Apocalyptic, eschatological and apophatic languages, frameworks, and orientations pervade both queer theorizing and theologizing about time, affect, history and desire. The volume fosters a more explicit engagement between theories of queer temporality and affectivity and religious texts and discourses.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>Queer Disorientations: Four Turns and a Twist</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOORE</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRINTNALL</surname>
                           <given-names>KENT L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARCHAL</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It’s about time. This book is principally about time—queer time, to be precise. But it’s also about time that a book on queer theologies tackled queer temporalities, together with queer affects.¹ Like the colloquium out of which it emerged, this volume seeks to engage with certain field-reorienting—and field-disorienting—inflections of queer theory whose origins lie in the midto late 1990s but which have been oddly underremarked even by those in the theological disciplines most invested in all matters queer. The literature by biblical scholars, theologians, and church historians that has been assembled incrementally under the patchwork queer banner</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How Soon Is (This Apocalypse) Now?</title>
                     <subtitle>Queer Velocities after a Corinthian Already and a Pauline Not Yet</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARCHAL</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These times justify impatience. Is it the end? Or was<italic>that</italic>the end? Well, when exactly do you mean?¹ Has it already taken too long? If so, in which ways and in what directions have these ends or these pauses turned us, even dragged us? Ultimately, why should those of us who want (at least some) things to change care? One way to address such questions, such<italic>feelings</italic>, about time is to attend to a range of strange temporalities bubbling up out of an ancient letter and more recent missives in queer studies. The downright eschatological mood of late in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Unbinding Imperial Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Chrononormativity and Paul’s Letter to the Romans</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOKE</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The empire binds time. The idea of time being bound by institutions of power (ancient or modern) to have a normalizing effect, of course, comes from Elizabeth Freeman. She identifies such a binding as chrononormativity, “the use of time to organize individual human bodies toward maximum productivity.”¹ Under a modern capitalist system, for example, a normal “workday” is arranged (including “free” time) in such a way that workers produce more labor, and thus capital, for their employers. Chrononormativity, therefore, produces the most benefit for those at the top of the socioeconomic hierarchy.</p>
                     <p>Chrononormativity’s effectiveness derives especially from its routinization of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Futures Outside:</title>
                     <subtitle>Apocalyptic Epilogue Unveiled as Africana Queer Prologue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOMAS</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIC A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth passed away …</p>
                     <p>revelation 21:1</p>
                     <p>This essay examines the epilogue of Revelation (22:8–21)¹ as an intervention for new imaginations of, and actions toward, a new heaven and a new earth that can be realized now in the present. It names the ways that Revelation (and therefore the Bible) is used as a means to make outsiders of queer people and proposes that the author/narrator John is not the only one who can be filled with the spirit on the Lord(e)’s day</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Our Book of Revelation … Prescribes Our Fate and Releases Us from It”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Scriptural Disorientations in Cherríe Moraga’s The Last Generation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HIDALGO</surname>
                           <given-names>JACQUELINE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Invoking a range of religious intonations, Cherríe Moraga frames her essay collection,<italic>The Last Generation: Prose and Poetry</italic>(1993), as “a prayer” even though she “no longer remember[s] how to pray.”¹ She writes in a moment of temporal convergence as she reflects upon the five hundred years since Christopher Columbus arrived in the Americas.² She reminds readers of the “catastrophic consequence” of this advent, a catastrophe that still ripples through the early 1990s. The essays in the collection, all written between 1990 and 1993, respond to varying local and international crises: “the Gulf War, the collapse of the Soviet Union,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Queer Persistence:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Death, History, and Longing for Endings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOTROSITS</surname>
                           <given-names>MAIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The one thing we thought we knew for sure about infection with HIV—that it is invariably fatal—has become, in recent years, ever more uncertain,” writes Tim Dean in 2008, in an essay called “Bareback Time.”¹ Noting the changing timeline for HIV (at least for some populations) in the wake of new and very welcome medical treatments, Dean explores the anxiety experienced by some gay men as a result of the uncertainties around HIV positivity: “A sexual life story whose conclusion gay men dreaded but quickly came to know by heart has morphed, without sufficient warning, into a drama</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Who Weeps for the Sodomite?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRINTNALL</surname>
                           <given-names>KENT L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the possible exception of Lot and his daughters, it seems virtually no one in the history of the West has obeyed the injunction not to look back on the fiery devastation rained down on the Cities of the Plain. Although gendered injustice most certainly appears to have played a role in the punishment meted out to Lot’s wife, when one begins to rack up the shame, terror, anger, and hate experienced by those who have tried to discern—or think they understand—what happened in Sodom and Gomorrah, and to whom, and why, it may be that no one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“They Had No Rest from This Torment”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Encountering the Apocalypse of Peter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PERRY</surname>
                           <given-names>BROCK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“At one point, Rev. Lovejoy described Hell in so much detail that Mrs. Addison, a dignified lady with yellow feathers in her yellow hat, burst into tears and ran right out of the church. A bunch of people, including me, followed her with their eyes, guessing why she thought she was going to Hell.”¹ So recalls Gary Gray, the black protagonist of James Hannaham’s novel<italic>God Says No</italic>, of his visit to the A.M.E. Zion Church of Charleston, South Carolina—his home church—during Thanksgiving break of his freshman year of college. Gary, a devout Christian since he was a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Excess and the Enactment of Queer Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Futurity, Failure, and Formation in Feminist Theologies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DANIELS</surname>
                           <given-names>BRANDY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Anglican theologian Sarah Coakley is a particularly notable, if provocative, figure in feminist theology, a discourse often at odds with traditional systematic theology—either in perception or by its own avowal. A central endeavor in Coakley’s scholarship has been to rethink this complicated, often fraught, relationship between feminism and systematics via a turn to contemplative prayer.¹ In her acclaimed collection of essays titled<italic>Powers and Submissions</italic>, for instance, Coakley challenges feminist theologians to rethink their skepticism toward submission and proposes a Christian feminism grounded on a “fundamental and practiced dependency<italic>on God</italic>,” arguing this dependency as a “fulcrum from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Madness of Holy Saturday:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bipolar Temporality and the Queerdom of Heaven on Earth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is there an end to capitalism? As in, “Does capitalism have an end time, an apocalyptic thrust—the apex of which we might be nearing?”<italic>And</italic>as in, “Does capitalism have an end goal, a telos toward which it strives?” Further, what does it mean to live in the<italic>time</italic>of twenty-first-century neoliberalism? As in what are the “signs” (mores, theologies, affects) of our time?<italic>And</italic>as in under what constructs of temporality do we labor? Questions of ends, times, and End Times have been at the forefront of contemporary political theologies. For instance, in<italic>The Theology of Money</italic>, Philip</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Entrepreneur and the Big Drag:</title>
                     <subtitle>Risky Affirmation in Capital’s Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TONSTAD</surname>
                           <given-names>LINN MARIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The current socioeconomic order exerts immense pressure to convince us that significant change is impossible: We can practice amelioration—but not desired transformation—as we participate in the forced march toward willing acquiescence to the logic of economic rationality. Not a contradiction—this order is particularly insidious in its ability to orient our desires from the inside, as it were, so that our experiences of risk and futility turn into opportunities for self-realization, as we’ll see.</p>
                     <p>Two different strategies naturalize the current order, increasing the power of both. One insists there is no alternative; any attempt to create one is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Queer Structures of Religious Feeling:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Time Is Now?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PELLEGRINI</surname>
                           <given-names>ANN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Freud’s hostility toward religion and his, at best, condescension toward the religious are by now so well known as to have become part of the obviousness of the secular modern—and of classical psychoanalysis as secular discourse par excellence. For the Freud of<italic>The Future of an Illusion</italic>(1927), religion is akin to an obsessional neurosis of childhood; just as children may be hoped (and helped) to outgrow their neuroses, so too might humankind overcome the obsessional neurosis that is religion.¹ A few sentences later in the same text, Freud is even less sparing, and religion approaches the level of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>More Than a Feeling:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Queer Notion of Survivance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHNEIDER</surname>
                           <given-names>LAUREL C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>New thinking in queer temporalities and affects outside of the (temporally, affectively charged) field of religion constitutes a challenge and invitation to stretch queer thinking in theology yet again, and further. Although feminist, womanist, process, and other theorists in religion and theology have been working around the fuzzy borders and stubborn impasses that fleshy experiences—bodies and histories of bodies—present, queerly inflected affect theory expands these moves into a complex materialism.¹ Affect theory’s approach to embodiment in terms of the deeply constitutive dynamics of temporality, proximity, touch, and even elemental gravitation provides a conceptual framework that helpfully limits any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Remember—When?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MACKENDRICK</surname>
                           <given-names>KARMEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Surely my memory is where you dwell,” Augustine famously writes in his<italic>Confessions</italic>, addressing the puzzling, immaterial God for whom “there can be no question of place.” We might hope to resolve the puzzle by replacing the “where” of memory with a “when,” but chronologically, too, God turns out to be not quite placeable. Augustine argues that one way that we can be sure that we<italic>remember</italic>God is that we all seek the happiness God brings, even though we have not yet found it in this life: How else could we know about it?¹ It must be that we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>Queer Enfleshment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUBENSTEIN</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY-JANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On numerous occasions, I have had the chance to respond to Karmen MacKendrick’s challenging and beautiful work, or to respond to her response to something I have written (often under the influence of her challenging and beautiful work). In the face of this complex and perennial entanglement, I admit to feeling both prideful and indulgent. Steeped in such sinful affect, I would like to think for a nonlinear moment within some of the possibilities MacKendrick’s thinking opens, most recently in the preceding essay “Remember—When?” for something like a queer-incarnational apophasis.</p>
                     <p>Mashing up the inexhaustible<italic>Confessions</italic>of Saint Augustine with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>In Search of Queer Theology Lost</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JORDAN</surname>
                           <given-names>MARK D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Time-and-again [<italic>longtemps</italic>] we have endured, and today suffer still, a Victorian regime.”¹ You recall the opening of Foucault’s<italic>History of Sexuality</italic>. With its first word, the short book alludes to the beginning of Proust’s<italic>In Search of Lost Time</italic>, that torrent of written memories about loves, their captivating intensities and evaporating fulfillments.</p>
                     <p>Foucault declares an interest in how languages applied to sexed bodies mark time while pretending to be timeless.<italic>History of Sexuality</italic>is not a history of sex, as you know, but a narrative of the invasive fictions that “explain” bodies in order to manage them from birth to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>To Mark Jordan’s “In Search of Queer Theology Lost”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KELLER</surname>
                           <given-names>CATHERINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In Search of Queer Theology Lost” opens by way of the opening of<italic>The History of Sexuality</italic>I, in which Foucault plays on the opening of Proust’s<italic>In Search of Lost Time</italic>. So we should not be surprised when Mark Jordan lets us know, many pages later, that “everything I have written so far is prologue to a (new) narrative I meant to write.” If his writing has been eluding his intention, queer theology, hey, theology tout court, may have to follow him on this prolegomenal peregrination. “Time-and-again.”</p>
                     <p>Finding the way will be hard to distinguish from getting lost. We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FREEMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ELIZABETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Episcopal Church, there is a Sunday school curriculum called Godly Play. Based on Montessori principles, the curriculum involves an adult telling a Bible story, parable, or “liturgical action” story, using small fi gurines and symbolic objects to make the story pictorial and compelling to children ages three through ten. The very first story the children hear, “The Circle of the Church Year,” is about time.¹</p>
                     <p>“Time,” the teller asks in this story. “What is time? Some people say that time is in a line, but I wonder what that would look like?” (26). The storyteller pulls a length</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr6tw.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
