<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>God and the Gawain-Poet</book-title>
         <subtitle>Theology and Genre in Pearl, Cleanness, Patience and Sir Gawain and the Green Knight</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hatt</surname>
               <given-names>Cecilia A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781843844198</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782045984</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk; Rochester, NY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cecilia A. Hatt</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt17mvk2t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Pearl, Cleanness, Patience and Sir Gawain and the Green Knight are accomplished examples of four different literary genres and represent some of the finest poetry in Middle English. They are, by turns, fast and funny, powerfully dramatic, gentle and ironic, telling of painful bereavement and the terror of victims of disaster and violence, as well as the comic bewilderment of people entangled in alarmingly mysterious situations. The anonymous poet's evident delight in the pleasures and artistry of courtly life has led some readers to suggest that he was a gifted but complacent frequenter of courts, his attention dedicated to the wealthy and his sympathies to the powerful, and moreover, that his poems pay the merest lipservice to religious observance. God and the Gawain-poet argues that, on the contrary, the poet's wide-ranging engagement with all human life explicitly acknowledges all material creation as God's gift, revelling in its physicality, in bodily senses and movement and the ways a community celebrates itself. Dr Hatt shows how, in exhorting readers to recognize and respond to the narrative of divine gift, he appears as an energetic Christian poet and a humane and compassionate observer. Cecilia Hatt gained her D.Phil from Oxford University.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VIII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>X</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Signposts on the trail of the Gawain-poet</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The now well-established critical consensus that the four poems of British Library MS Cotton Nero A.x, Art.3 are the work of the same person is derived in part from the recurrence in them of particular motifs and preoccupations which to that extent draws them together. We shall go further, suggesting that what we call the<italic>oeuvre</italic>of the<italic>Gawain</italic>-poet presents us with a coherent religious vision, deliberately explicated according to a particular order and within a particular social context. In order to answer the questions that the Cotton poems have raised, and to account for our various reactions to them,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Pearl, the jeweller’s dream</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may be that the author of MS Cotton Nero A.x Art.3 had it in mind to compose a series of poems based on the Beatitudes of Matt.5:3–10.<italic>Patience</italic>and<italic>Cleanness</italic>are explicitly so based and<italic>Pearl</italic>, it has been suggested, could be an examination of ‘Blessed are they that mourn, for they shall be comforted’.¹ If this is so, any referring of<italic>Pearl</italic>to the<italic>consolatio</italic>tradition must be conducted with the caveat that Pearl does not offer consolation to the bereaved: this most clear-sighted of poets is concerned only to make the protagonist look hard at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The difficulty of Cleanness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although<italic>Pearl</italic>is the first poem in its section of MS Cotton Nero, and the first to be discussed in this study, there is a general assumption that<italic>Cleanness</italic>was actually the first of the four poems to be composed.¹ The main reason for this may be that<italic>Cleanness</italic>initially strikes the reader as a less polished production than the others, uneven in its structure and inconsistent in its message.<italic>Cleanness</italic>is nevertheless a very powerful and impressive poem. It contains exciting scenes of cataclysmic disaster, vivid passages of descriptive chronicle, direct and earthy expressions of humorous contempt, a lovingly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Patience and the Book of Jonah</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Patience</italic>is the second of the Beatitude-poems in this collection and is on the face of it as different from<italic>Cleanness</italic>as could be. It is short, brisk and funny. In<italic>Patience</italic>, as in<italic>Cleanness</italic>, God observes the wickedness of human beings and sends a prophet to rebuke them, but instead of destroying them in the whirlwind he has threatened, he relents and forgives the repentant Ninevites. It is not God who is stern and unforgiving, but the reluctant prophet, Jonah. The Biblical book of Jonah gives<italic>Jonah</italic>this character, but in<italic>Patience</italic>it is shown to be ridiculous as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Sir Gawain and the Green Knight:</title>
                     <subtitle>an alternative romance?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his article ‘Template Criticism:<italic>Sir Gawain and the Green Knight’</italic>, John Halverson attacks the critics who apply a single idea to the interpretation of<italic>SGGK</italic>and try to make everything in the poem fit into it:</p>
                     <p>once the template is imposed, it becomes tyrannical. It not only excludes other interpretations and clouds perception, but also sends the interpreter off into a multiplication of detailed identifications often so far-fetched that they arouse the amusement or scorn of all except other believers. It demands that everything be reduced to a single set of terms.¹</p>
                     <p>One knows, of course, exactly what he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>some biographical and contextual speculations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>232</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvk2t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>250</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
