<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h0b18</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX830.1962V373 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vatican Council (2nd: 1962-1965)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Church history</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Vatican II</book-title>
         <subtitle>Expériences canadiennes – Canadian experiences</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Attridge</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Clifford</surname>
               <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Routhier</surname>
               <given-names>Gilles</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9782760319530</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">2760319539</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Les Presses de l'Université d'Ottawa</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ch77hx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Le deuxième concile du Vatican (1961-1965) fut l'un des événements religieux les plus importants du vingtième siècle. Au Canada, il coïncida avec une période de changements culturels et sociétaux sans précédent, entraînant chez les évêques catholiques canadiens un réexamen de la place et de la mission de l'Église dans le monde. Pendant quatre ans, les évêques catholiques canadiens se réunirent avec leurs collègues de partout dans le monde pour réfléchir aux questions urgentes qui se posaient à l'Église et en débattre. Ce livre bilingue étudie l'interprétation et la réception de Vatican II au Canada, analysant diverses questions, dont le rôle des médias, les réactions des autres chrétiens, les contributions des participants canadiens, l'impact du Concile sur la pratique religieuse et sa contribution à la progression du dialogue interreligieux.</p>
         <p>The Second Vatican Council (1961-1965) was one of the most significant religious events of the twentieth-century. In Canada, it was part of a moment of unprecedented cultural and societal change, causing Canadian Catholics to reexamine the church's place and mission in the world. For four years, Canadian Catholic bishops met with their peers from around the globe to reflect on and debate the pressing issues facing the church. This bilingual volume explores the interpretation and reception of Vatican II in Canada, looking at many issues including the role of the media, the reactions of other Christians, the contributions of Canadian participants, the council's impact on religious practice and its contribution to the growth of inter-religious dialogue.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="568"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Remerciements / Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Attridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifford</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Routhier</surname>
                           <given-names>Gilles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction (Français)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Le concile Vatican II est reconnu comme l’événement religieux qui a eu le plus grand retentissement au XX<sup>e</sup>siècle. Vu à l’échelle du Canada, son importance n’est pas moindre. En effet, non seulement c’était la première fois qu’un nombre significatif d’évêques canadiens participait à un concile oecuménique, mais ce concile s’est tenu au moment où la société canadienne entrait dans une période de grande mutation, où l’Église catholique du Canada était appelée à une transformation sans précédent et à trouver une nouvelle manière de se situer dans cette culture et cette société en évolution. Cette Église, dont la pierre de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction (English)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Attridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifford</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Routhier</surname>
                           <given-names>Gilles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Second Vatican Council (1962–65) is recognized as the most significant religious event of the twentieth century, having a global influence. Its importance is no less significant when viewed from a Canadian perspective. In fact, this was the first time that a substantial number of Canadian bishops took part in an ecumenical council. Moreover, the Second Vatican Council was held at a moment when Canadian society was beginning to undergo a period of profound change, at a time when the Catholic Church in Canada was called to an unprecedented transformation due to its changing place within this evolving culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reporting the Revolution:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Western Catholic Reporter and Post-Vatican II Reform</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cuplinskas</surname>
                           <given-names>Indre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Half a year after the closing of the Second Vatican Council, on April 19, 1966, the board of advisors of the weekly newspaper the<italic>Western Catholic Reporter</italic>met in the chancery office boardroom of the Archdiocese of Edmonton. The secretary recorded the following discussion:</p>
                     <p>Father Mueller … stated that he had talked to two priests who were very vehement. These priests considered the paper too ambiguous. One priest stated that in their opinion the paper was not faithful to Catholic teaching. Both stated that if they were in control of [it,] something would be done about the format of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Le concile Vatican II dans la région de la Beauce:</title>
                     <subtitle>une fenêtre sur Rome à travers l’Éclaireur-Progrès</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pelchat</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nous disposons déjà, sur la couverture de presse de Vatican II, d’un bon nombre d’études qui nous éclairent sur la diffusion des idées et la réception des enseignements ou des décisions du concile¹. Cependant, les études réalisées sur la couverture de l’événement conciliaire par des publications hebdomadaires en région sont beaucoup plus rares. Dans ce dernier cas, le regard porté sur l’événement, dans la durée, révèle une attention plus particulière à certains thèmes, dans les limites d’une population précise, possédant ses caractéristiques propres. L’importance du journalisme hebdomadaire en regard de la diffusion des idées auprès d’une population régionale ne saurait</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Deux événements reliés au concile dans les médias québécois:</title>
                     <subtitle>« Foi et Constitution » à Montréal (1963) et Paul VI à L’onu (1965)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pagé</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>C’est toujours par l’image médiatique que les faits religieux d’une société rejoignent le grand public, qu’il s’agisse de la population chrétienne active en Église ou de la population québécoise toutes sensibilités religieuses confondues. Au début des années soixante, la composition socio-démographique du Québec évolue rapidement, et la culture religieuse se modifie au rythme de la culture publique commune. Il est pertinent de jeter un regard critique sur deux événements qui ont constitué à cette époque des moments exceptionnels par rapport à l’activité régulière de la vie de l’Église au Québec. Ces deux faits médiatiques représentent des ruptures dans l’image collective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canadian Presbyterians and Vatican II:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Silent Revolution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Stuart</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only one solution was offered—forget him. The romance needed to end. As the article in the 1958 denominational magazine the<italic>Presbyterian Record</italic>put it: “He is not the one and only person in this world who could fill your life with love. You could find somebody else to love and be loved by.”¹ In the imagined scenario, it is a Presbyterian girl—intriguingly named “Mary”—who faced this dilemma. The reason for such a drastic proclamation is simple. The boy (“John”) is Roman Catholic. This would be a “mixed marriage.” In the world of pre–Vatican II Presbyterianism this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reaction to Vatican II in The United Church of Canada</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Young</surname>
                           <given-names>John H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fall of 1954, The United Church of Canada’s Commission on the Christian Faith published a sixty-four-page booklet entitled<italic>What’s the Difference? Protestant and Roman Catholic Beliefs Compared</italic>. While the commission hoped “that this booklet will lead to a better understanding of both Protestantism and Roman Catholicism”¹ and asserted that “every attempt has been made to avoid an adverse and prejudiced attitude and to be fair and just in every judgment expressed,”² the document’s doctrinal comparisons were certainly not designed to encourage the membership to visit a neighbourhood Roman Catholic parish. Not quite ten years later, in the winter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Hold onto Your Hats”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Vatican II and Aggiornamento in the Anglican Church of Canada</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hayes</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Second Ecumenical Council of the Vatican had a profound impact on Canadian Anglicans in two general ways: it changed their ecumenical landscape forever, and it helped guide farreaching changes in their denominational identity. As for the change in ecumenical landscape, Vatican II led Anglicans and Roman Catholics in Canada to cordial and close relationships with surprising speed. Within ten years of the opening session of Vatican II, the Canadian arms of the two communions were co-operating in such ventures as dialogue groups, local collaborations of various kinds, the Toronto School of Theology, and inter-church coalitions for social justice. As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Growing Awareness Regarding Vatican II in Canadian Theological Monographs and Journals (1959–1969)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fahey</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On October 28, 1958, the College of Cardinals in conclave elected as Pope Angelo Giuseppe Roncalli, Patriarch of Venice, who assumed the name of John XXIII. Some three months later, on January 25, 1959, following a liturgy celebrated in Rome’s basilica St. Paul Outside the Walls, the reigning Pope met with a small group of cardinals in the adjacent Benedictine monastery, and, totally unexpectedly, announced his resolve to hold a double celebration for the Roman Catholic Church. Speaking in Italian he promised a “<italic>duplice celebrazione: di un Sinodo Diocesano per l’Urbe, e di un Concilio Ecumenico per la Chiesa universale</italic>.”¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Inspiration after Dei Verbum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spatafora</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fiftieth anniversary of the calling of the Second Vatican Council by Pope John XXIII is an appropriate occasion to assess its impact on the Church and on its theology. This article will examine the developments in the Church’s doctrine of inspiration since the council and will focus principally on the contribution of a Canadian exegete, Walter Vogels.¹ The study will begin with an overview of the origins and development of the concept of inspired Scripture up to Vatican II, followed by a brief presentation of the Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation,<italic>Dei Verbum</italic>’s treatment of inspiration, and a brief</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cardinal Paul-Émile Léger and the Establishment of the Mixed Commissionon Revelation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schelkens</surname>
                           <given-names>Karim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This article investigates the role of one of Canada’s most prominent voices at the Second Vatican Council, that of Cardinal Paul-Émile Léger, from material found in several archival collections.² In recent years, several publications have already documented Léger’s conciliar activities, making clear that Léger was—in the context of Vatican II—omnipresent.³ Therefore, this contribution simply cannot study the full scope of Léger’s actions, let alone the entire story of his involvement in the council’s revelation debate, on which it will focus. On that debate too, much research has already been conducted. It remains a<italic>communis opinio</italic>among Vatican II</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Lesser of Two Evils?</title>
                     <subtitle>Archbishop Philip Pocock, Vatican II, and the Birth Control Controversy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meehan</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the afternoon of Wednesday, October 21, 1964, during the third session of the Second Vatican Council, Philip Pocock, the coadjutor archbishop of Toronto, was enjoying a rare moment of personal time. He was getting a haircut. He later recalled that tumultuous afternoon, sitting in the barbershop of the Hotel de la Ville on the Via Sistina, ten minutes from the Vatican: “That barbershop had a telephone in every chair. The telephone rang and it was for me. I was talking to some reporter in Toronto while the barber was clipping my hair around the back.”¹ The call, from a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Council Diary of Metropolitan Maxim Hermaniuk and Turning Points in the History of the Catholic Church:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Interpretation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Galadza</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Allow me to begin on a note of thanks to the organizers of the conference upon which this collection is based. If not for the conference I would have remained ignorant of certain important moments in the history of my own Church, the Ukrainian Catholic.¹ Before outlining how I plan to structure my analysis of the Council Diaries of Metropolitan Archbishop Maxim Hermaniuk, allow me to share some facts that illustrate this ignorance, and then, more importantly, suggest the significance of this lack of knowledge. I do so only to indicate that in some parts of the Church “the state</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canada’s Ukrainian Catholics and Vatican II:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Guide for the Future or Struggling with the Past?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tataryn</surname>
                           <given-names>Myroslaw</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the reception of Vatican II by Ukrainian Catholics in Canada is a particularly vexing one because it is not a welltrodden path and has eluded critical inquiry. Thus it remains a question that will involve not just academic study but also personal bias or, more diplomatically put, context. The current author, for example, does not come to the study as a researcher of Vatican II but rather as someone who has been perplexed by the difference in religious cultures among Ukrainian Catholics in eastern and western Canada. One of the main differences in these cultures relates to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Experimenting Creatively with Being Church in the Modern World:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Social Affairs Commission of the Canadian Conference of Catholic Bishops, 1965–1984</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baltutis</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Promulgated on the last day of the Second Vatican Council, December 7, 1965, “The Pastoral Constitution on the Church in the Modern World”² articulated the council fathers’ desire that religion should not only affect a Catholic’s private life but it should also influence their cultural, social, and political engagement with the world. Beginning with the principle that all human beings have an herent dignity since they were created in the image of God,³<italic>Gaudium et Spes</italic>(the constitution’s Latin title) argued that humans can only attain their full potential by participating in community.⁴ In promoting the common good of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Le synode extraordinaire de 1985:</title>
                     <subtitle>l’expérience canadienne</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Racine</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Le 25 janvier 1985, en la fête de la Conversion de Paul, lors de l’octave de prière pour l’unité des chrétiens, Jean-Paul II annonce la tenue d’un synode extraordinaire des évêques qui sera célébré du 25 novembre au 8 décembre de l’année en cours. Il y convoque les patriarches, quelques évêques des Églises orientales et les présidents de toutes les conférences épiscopales. Il affirme:</p>
                     <p>Le but de cette initiative est non seulement de commémorer le concile Vatican II vingt ans après sa clôture, mais aussi et surtout de:</p>
                     <p>Revivre en quelque manière cette atmosphère extraordinaire de communion ecclésiale qui caractérise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Marcel Bélanger:</title>
                     <subtitle>itinéraire d’un expert canadien à Vatican II</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roy</surname>
                           <given-names>Philippe J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marcel Bélanger¹ naquit à Valleyfield le 6 novembre 1908. Fils d’Alfred Bélanger, entrepreneur, et de Florida Desjardins, il fit ses études primaires dans sa ville natale entre 1914 et 1920, et ses études secondaires au Collège de Valleyfield, où il obtint un baccalauréat ès arts en 1928. Cette année-là, il entra au noviciat des Oblats de Marie Immaculée de Ville-La-Salle. Après sa profession, le 2 août 1929, il poursuivit ses études au Scolasticat Saint-Joseph, à Ottawa, jusqu’en 1932. Entre-temps, en 1930, il avait obtenu une licence en philosophie et, en 1932, un baccalauréat en théologie. Lorsqu’il eut prononcé ses voeux</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“A Great Historic Day”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Conciliar Diaries of Metropolitan Maxim Hermaniuk</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Skira</surname>
                           <given-names>Jaroslav Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>322</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay will broadly examine some of the late Metropolitan Maxim Hermaniuk (1911–96) of Winnipeg’s contributions to the preparatory stages and sessions of the Second Vatican Council¹ through his comments on his experiences on the Preparatory Theological Commission, the Secretariat for Christian Unity, and in actual council debates. This research is largely based on selected passages of his unpublished council diaries and his work on two conciliar pastoral letters of the Synod of the Ukrainian Catholic Bishops.² In these diaries the late metropolitan dealt with a number of themes, such as relations with the Orthodox churches, interreligious dialogue, sobornicity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Canadian Anglican at Vatican II:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Activity of Eugene R. Fairweather</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Attridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is difficult to imagine how Eugene Fairweather must have felt when he received the letter from England the week before Christmas in 1963. Signed by Canon John R. Satterthwaite, secretary to the Archbishop of Canterbury, Michael Ramsey, the letter asked Fairweather if he would be “willing to be appointed one of the three Anglican Observers for the next session” of the Vatican Council in Rome.¹ “The Archbishop,” its author wrote, “is keen to send observers who are theologically-minded, and I know he would be grateful if you were able to consider going.”² According to Satterthwaite, this invitation was still</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Vatican Council II:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Turning Point in the Church’s History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baum</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>360</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After the Second Vatican Council (1962–65), Catholic theologians discussed among themselves how to interpret the doctrinal evolution that had taken place. They all felt that in response to the conditions of modernity, the Church, in fidelity to the Gospel, had reinterpreted its teaching in a certain discontinuity with the past. During a discussion at the board of directors of the review<italic>Concilium</italic>, Hans Küng made a brilliant suggestion that became the topic of a learned symposium in 1984¹ and has subsequently been widely accepted in the field of religious studies.</p>
                     <p>The Swiss theologian adapted for his use in theology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Théologiens à Vatican II.</title>
                     <subtitle>Notes et carnets, témoins de l’expérience vécue à la Commission doctrinale</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Laberge</surname>
                           <given-names>Léo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>378</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Les sessions de Vatican II nous renvoient aux années 1962-1965. L’annonce du concile et sa préparation, par ailleurs, incluent les années 1960-1962. Si les participants directs ont disparu pour la plupart, la mémoire du concile se retrouve dans une multitude de documents tant officiels que privés, parmi lesquels les notes personnelles des Pères du concile et des autres participants, tels les théologiens et les conseillers des évêques, qui deviennent accessibles dans des archives ici et là dans le monde, tout particulièrement en Europe et en Amérique.</p>
                     <p>On dispose, bien sûr, des 23 volumes des<italic>Acta et Documenta Concilio Œumenico Vaticano</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The St. Lawrence Flows into Lake Ontario:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tides of Liturgical Renewal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dias</surname>
                           <given-names>Darren J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The liturgical renewal movement in Canada in the years prior to Vatican II seemed to flow from the French-language Church to the English-language Church. This movement is evident in the Canadian Dominican province in the 1950s and 1960s. The Province of St. Dominic of Canada was the foundation of the Paris province (France) principally present in French-speaking Canada. Its ties to the Frenchspeaking Dominicans in Europe were most evident in its program of study: in 1950, 15 per cent of Canadian students were pursuing advanced degrees in centres such as Le Huy, Louvain, and the Saulchoir, where they were immersed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La réception de Vatican II dans la formation catéchétique au Québec</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brodeur</surname>
                           <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>436</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cette recherche s’inscrit dans l’œuvre novatrice entreprise depuis quelques années par Gilles Routhier autour de l’herméneutique relative à l’événement et aux productions de Vatican II. L’angle de travail privilégié ici traite des apports de Vatican II sur le développement de la catéchèse et, de manière plus précise, sur ce qui touche à la formation d’une nouvelle génération de catéchètes. Cette étude contient d’emblée de nombreuses vertus, car elle concerne à la fois la façon de concevoir la mission première de l’Église, la formulation des contenus théologiques, les aspects anthropologiques, sociologiques et psychologiques inhérents aux personnes destinataires des activités catéchétiques et</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious Education:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Dogma to Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Power</surname>
                           <given-names>Myrtle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van den Hengel</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>448</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Approaches to religious education had begun to change in the Western Church long before the Second Vatican Council gathered in 1962. The heritage of the famous Roman Catechism of the Council of Trent, with its various national editions and its memorization method of question and answer, endured generally until the 1960s, but voices for transformation had been gathering strength decades earlier.¹</p>
                     <p>There were various reasons for the transformation of the catechetical method. One reason stands out as a powerful driving force behind the catechetical movement. By the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the massive reshaping of the religious landscape</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imaging Perfectae Caritatis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Viewing the Consecrated Life through the Mother House Museums of Canadian Women Religious</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacDonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Heidi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>476</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1960s some 60,000 Canadian women belonged to 183 congregations and orders. These congregations were diverse in historical roots and governance. Some were provinces of international communities; others were indigenous Canadian foundations. Regardless of their origins or orientations, Vatican II marked a significant event in their history. While many of the council’s documents both directly and indirectly impacted on their identities and caused some to question the very nature of the vowed life (e.g., the Dogmatic Constitution on the Church [<italic>Lumen Gentium</italic>] in its call to holiness of all the faithful), this essay will focus on the response of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Spiritual Journey of Alice Trudeau, MO, in the Postconciliar Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruno-Jofré</surname>
                           <given-names>Rosa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>495</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alice Trudeau entered the Missionary Oblate Sisters of the Sacred Heart and Mary Immaculate in Saint-Boniface, Manitoba, in 1953 when the congregation’s spirituality and culture still had to come to terms with late modernity.¹ The sisters had started to experience an increasing contradiction between their own culture, their own universe, and the world around them, even at the religious level. The journey of Alice Trudeau as a religious was largely defined by her early years as a daughter in a large Franco-Manitoban Catholic family, her personal experience as an orphan, her losses, her experience with Catholic Action, and the drastic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Vatican II and the Changing Mission of the Catholic Women’s League of Canada</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jardine</surname>
                           <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>515</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>English-speaking Canadian lay Roman Catholic women have had a long and vital role in creating community and parish life in the twentieth century.¹ In 1891 Pope Leo XIII’s encyclical Rerum Novarum was issued in response to societal pressures. As a result, opportunities for lay people, particularly women, to minister in the Church were greatly increased. While the call to personal piety as a way of seeking grace and building the Church was still emphasized, working in the world with and for other people was encouraged. Both Pope Pius X and Pope Pius XI issued calls to the laity to become</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La question de la liberté religieuse au Québec à l’heure du concile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Routhier</surname>
                           <given-names>Gilles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>525</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’origine de cette étude se trouve dans une lettre envoyée par Philippe Delhaye à André Laurentin, à l’été 1965. Delhaye, qui n’avait pas obtenu de poste à Louvain et qui, de ce fait, avait dû s’expatrier à Lille et à Montréal, enseignait alors à temps partiel au nouvel Institut de sciences religieuses à l’Université de Montréal. Ses contacts avec les milieux montréalais lui avaient valu d’être nommé, à la demande du cardinal Léger,<italic>peritus</italic>au concile en 1962.</p>
                     <p>À l’été 1965, à la suite d’une conférence sur la liberté religieuse qu’il donnait à Montréal, il écrivait à André Laurentin, également</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anglican–Roman Catholic Dialogue in Canada:</title>
                     <subtitle>Receiving Unitatis Redintegratio</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifford</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>543</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the principal motives in calling the Second Vatican Council, as signified in John XXIII’s decision to announce it in the Week of Prayer for Christian Unity on January 25, 1959, was the restoration of Christian unity. The council made the Catholic Church’s full commitment to ecumenism explicit in its Decree on Ecumenism (<italic>Unitatis Redintegratio</italic>).¹ Among the many practical ways that this engagement in the search for the full visible unity of the divided churches was to be carried out, the decree set out the conditions for the establishment of formal commissions of “dialogue between competent experts from different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Collaborateurs et Collaboratrices / Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>559</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77hx.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
