<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Turns of Event</book-title>
         <subtitle>Nineteenth-Century American Literary Studies in Motion</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Blum</surname>
               <given-names>Hester</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780812247985</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812292657</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0812292650</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19rmcdc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>American literary studies has undergone a series of field redefinitions over the past two decades that have been consistently described as "turns," whether transnational, hemispheric, postnational, spatial, temporal, postsecular, aesthetic, or affective. In<italic>Turns of Event</italic>, Hester Blum and a splendid roster of contributors explore the conditions that have produced such movements. Offering an overview of the state of the study of nineteenth-century American literature, Blum contends that the field's propensity to turn, to reinvent itself constantly without dissolution, is one of its greatest strengths.</p>
         <p>The essays in the volume's first half, "Provocations," trace the theoretical and methodological development and institutional emergence of certain turns, as well as providing calls to arms. The geopolitically oriented turns toward the transnational, hemispheric, and oceanic (whether Atlantic, Caribbean, Pacific, or archipelagic in focus) have held a certain prevalence in American studies in recent years, and the second half of this volume presents a series of scholarly essays that exemplify these subfields.</p>
         <p>Taken together, these essays survey the field of American literary studies as it moves beyond new historicism as its primary methodology and evolves in light of ideological, conceptual, and material considerations. There is much at stake in these movements: the consequences and opportunities range from citational and evidentiary practices to canon expansion, resource allocation, and institutional futurity.</p>
         <p>Contributors:Monique Allewaert, Ralph Bauer, Hester Blum, Martin Brückner, Michelle Burnham, Christopher Castiglia, Sean X. Goudie, Meredith L. McGill, Geoffrey Sanborn</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="200"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>Academic Positioning Systems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLUM</surname>
                           <given-names>HESTER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of the Americas in relation to the West begins with a turn: a wrong turn, as the story is commonly told. Christopher Columbus, the Genoan sailing in search of Cathay on behalf of Spain, encountered unexpected islands that he mistook for the Indies. This landfall came after he decided against returning to Europe when the voyage had proceeded farther than his frightened sailors had thought navigationally possible. In the parlance of quips about his “failure to ask for directions” (as Michelle Burnham glosses it in her contribution to this volume), Columbus took an errant turn, mistaking the Americas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Turn It Up:</title>
                     <subtitle>Affects, Structures of Feeling, and Face-to-Face Education</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANBORN</surname>
                           <given-names>GEOFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will begin with two accounts of beginnings. The first is from Elizabeth Grosz’s<italic>The Nick of Time: Politics, Evolution, and the Untimely</italic>:</p>
                     <p>In the beginning, if it makes any sense to talk of a beginning, there were differences, in all likelihood chemical differences, variations in compounds, in different geographical and climatological contexts. These chemical differences, under some unknown and perhaps unknowable conditions, were transformed or transformed themselves into simple organic proteins, whose structure provided some means of reproduction. Life “began.”¹</p>
                     <p>The second is from<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>:</p>
                     <p>The lights grow brighter as the earth lurches away from the sun</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Literary History, Book History, and Media Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McGILL</surname>
                           <given-names>MEREDITH L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My title places in apposition three fields of study that possess rich areas of overlap, but that have carved out separate domains for themselves, often defining their object of study by contrast with one another. Some of the differences between and among Literary History, Book History, and Media Studies can be clarified by considering these disciplines’ midtwentieth-century precursors. If this essay were written fifty years ago, my title might refer to Literary Criticism, Bibliography, and Communications, and we would, I think, rest assured that these were very different areas of study, requiring sharply different kinds of training. In the contemporary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Cartographic Turn and American Literary Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Of Maps, Mappings, and the Limits of Metaphor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRÜCKNER</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A survey of literary studies reveals a relatively sudden and now widespread fascination with all things cartographic. According to the<italic>MLA International Bibliography</italic>, published essay and book titles using the word “map” and its variants increased exponentially over the past forty years. Before 1990, a total of 503 titles used the terms “map” or “mapping.” After 1990, the enthusiasm for using “ map” as the defining label grew by a factor of three (Figure 3.1). Between 2001 and 2010 the search term “map*” identified over 1,400 titles in books, essays, collections, and dissertations. A fifth of these titles—281 to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Twists and Turns</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CASTIGLIA</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is possible that the reason so many “turns” can be claiming to change the field is, ironically, because they are not really changing much at all, but instead shifting the same methodologies and attitudes from one object (or “ideology”) to another. One sign that this might be the case is the increasing number of critics wondering about the contemporary viability of “critique,” shorthand for the righteous digging around in a text for hidden displacements of the social struggles that evade all but the politically savvy and serious critic. Critiques of critique might lead us to wonder whether what we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Of Turns and Paradigm Shifts:</title>
                     <subtitle>Humanities, Science, and Transnational American Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAUER</surname>
                           <given-names>RALPH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Shelley Fisher Fishkin publicized the phrase “transnational turn” in her 2004 presidential address to the american Studies association, she noted that her remarks were occasioned by many recent books and articles published during the 1990s and early 2000s that challenged the “national<italic>paradigm</italic>of the United States as a clearly bordered geographical and political space”—books and articles by border theorists such as Gloria anzaldúa, critics of american Empire such as amy Kaplan, and Inter-americanist literary historians such as José David Saldívar.¹ More recently, Paul Jay, in<italic>Global Matters</italic>(2010), has celebrated the “transnational turn” that literary studies have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>The Geopolitics and Tropologies of the American Turn</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALLEWAERT</surname>
                           <given-names>MONIQUE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A turn suggests a change in direction that might be rendered as a curved line that stops short of a full circling.<italic>A turn</italic>does not entail a completed action in time, as the governing metaphor of<italic>revolution</italic>used by older Americanist scholarship tended to suggest . Figuring the turn as a curved line gives it a geometry, which implies at least an abstract temporality and spatiality but does not anchor the turn in a specific geography. And while it offers the possibility of movement, which implies temporality, it implies no teleology. In short, the metaphor of the turn evokes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>The Caribbean Turn in C19 American Literary Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOUDIE</surname>
                           <given-names>SEAN X.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1992 was the quincentennial anniversary of the moment when Columbus’s ill-fated voyage to the Indies took an unplanned West Indian turn. The anniversary of the year when the Caribbean became the original site in the hemisphere of Native American genocide, of the enslavement of captured Africans and their descendants, and of European colonialism and settlement coincides with, and bears an indirect relation to, what this essay argues was a Caribbean turn in nineteenth-century American literary and cultural studies. While no single anniversary or critic or event, we shall see, is responsible for generating such a turn, this chapter’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Oceanic Turns and American Literary History in Global Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BURNHAM</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An unusual map titled “Atlantic Ocean, Toscanelli, 1474” appeared in J. G. Bartholomew’s 1911<italic>Literary and Historical Atlas of America</italic>. This composite map superimposes onto a modern cartography of the Atlantic world Toscanelli’s premodern map of that same space. The earlier 1474 map was drawn, of course, without any knowledge of the existence of the Americas, and the effects of combining pre-Columbian with post-Columbian geography are both fascinating and disorienting. The large island of Japan (then called Cipangu) hovers over the western half of Mexico, the enormous landmass identified as Cathay (or Northern China) swallows the Aleutians and shoulders its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rmcdc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
