<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vtp</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Science Fiction Double Feature</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Science Fiction Film as Cult Text</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>TELOTTE</surname>
               <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DUCHOVNAY</surname>
               <given-names>GERALD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781781381830</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781384640</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Liverpool University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6btc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Critical discussion of cult cinema has often noted its tendency to straddle or ignore boundaries, to pull together different sets of conventions, narrative formulas, or character types for the almost surreal pleasure to be found in their sudden juxtapositions or narrative combination. With its own boundary-blurring nature—as both science and fiction, reality and fantasy—science fiction has played a key role in such cinematic cult formation. This volume examines that largely unexplored relationship, looking at how the sf film’s own double nature neatly matches up with a persistent double vision common to the cult film. It does so by bringing together an international array of scholars to address key questions about the intersections of sf and cult cinema: how different genre elements, directors, and stars contribute to cult formation; what role fan activities, including “con" participation, play in cult development; and how the occulted or “bad" sf cult film works. The volume pursues these questions by addressing a variety of such sf cult works, including Robot Monster (1953), Zardoz (1974), A Boy and His Dog (1975), Tetsuo: The Iron Man (1989), Space Truckers (1996), Ghost in the Shell 2 (2004), and Iron Sky (2012). What these essays afford is a revealing vision of both the sf aspects of much cult film activity and the cultish aspects of the whole sf genre.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Science Fiction Double Feature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Telotte</surname>
                           <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most well-known, and certainly the most frequently discussed cult film,<italic>The Rocky Horror Picture Show</italic>(1975), opens with an arresting image, a close-up of bright red lips mouthing the film’s theme song, “Science Fiction Double Feature.” Both image and song have become practically iconic—emblems of the cult film, signs of its generally transgressive, sometimes campy nature, celebrations of the way such films, in contrast to most traditional Hollywood cinema, seem to directly address their audience, even, as Timothy Corrigan allusively puts it, placing them “oddly inscribed” within the film text (34). While<italic>Rocky Horror</italic>—the film—no longer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>From “Multiverse” to “Abramsverse”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Blade Runner, Star Trek, Multiplicity, and the Authorizing of Cult/SF Worlds</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hills</surname>
                           <given-names>Matt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When theorizing how a cinematic cult status develops, we should bear in mind that there may be more than one kind of media cult, and also more than one way for audiences to meaningfully approach films and franchises as cults. Prior research has emphasized different<italic>types</italic>of cult texts, whether by distinguishing “the midnight movie from the classical cult film” (Telotte, “Beyond” 10), “residual” from “emergent” audience valorizations (see my own “Realising the Cult Blockbuster”), or transgressive cult movies from “cult blockbusters” (Mathijs and Sexton 214). Some writers have explicitly identified branches of cult movies: “One … branch of cult</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The Coy Cult Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Man Who Wasn’t There as Noir SF</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bould</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many attempts to define cult movies and to describe their appeal are characterized by notions of doubleness, contradiction, and introjection. For example, J. P. Telotte finds in the “etymological underpinnings of ‘cult’” (14) a complex of potential meanings pointing to a dialectical impulse to possess and to be possessed, to express selfhood through surrendering to an external other. Thus, he suggests, the cult movie transgresses norms, enabling the cultist “to fashion a statement of difference” (14), even as it establishes “a stable ground from which to make that assertion, a ground<italic>within</italic>the very boundaries” that are being transgressed (15).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>“It’s Alive!”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Splattering of SF Films</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abbott</surname>
                           <given-names>Stacey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 1970s represent one of the great transitional periods for Hollywood, producing an increasingly independent and confrontational approach to cinema in terms of both narrative content and aesthetic display. Film-makers sought to break violently with film-making conventions by reimaging genre tropes through a more visceral and realistic style, challenging audiences with graphic, nihilistic, and often brutal imagery. Thus, John Carpenter, director of<italic>The Thing</italic>(1982), confesses that he “wanted something savage to happen. I don’t believe I could do that now. I don’t believe they’d let me do that,” while David Cronenberg explains that he “wanted to blow other people’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Sean Connery Reconfigured:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Bond to Cult Science Fiction Figure</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duchovnay</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While histories of cinema, especially US cinema, typically discuss the development of the star system, only in recent decades has much attention been paid to actors as performers, and still less attention is given to actors as cult performers. As Wade Jennings observes, compared to regular stardom, “Cult stardom is a relatively recent phenomenon,” and one that, “over time … can emerge as a quite different phenomenon” (90). Exploring the discourses related to this “different phenomenon,” Matt Hills notes how, “across their lifetime, some cult stars become hemmed in by their most famous roles (where a specific character has taken</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>The Cult Film as Affective Technology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anime and Oshii Mamoru’s Innocence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Orbaugh</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharalyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oshii Mamoru’s animated<italic>Ghost in the Shell 2: Innocence</italic>(2004, hereafter<italic>Innocence</italic>) is indisputably an sf film, but does it constitute a cult film as well? Is it a cult film for all audiences, or only those outside Japan, fascinated by the world of anime? Perhaps we might better ask: can an animated film for adults, created within Japan for a Japanese audience, be considered anything<italic>but</italic>cult when it circulates in a non-Japanese context?¹ This essay will explore these questions en route to a consideration of the connections between the “cult” elements of the film and the science fiction-esque</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Whedon, Browncoats, and the Big Damn Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Unified Meta-Myth of Firefly and Serenity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilcox</surname>
                           <given-names>Rhonda V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of<italic>Firefly</italic>’s death and rebirth is fairly well known; indeed, for some, the story has gained the status of myth, a myth that they are “living in.” The television series was created by Joss Whedon, famous for the success of<italic>Buffy the Vampire Slayer</italic>(1997–2003), which ran for seven years, and the spin-off<italic>Angel</italic>(1999–2004), which ran for five. The Fox network ran<italic>Firefly</italic>for just three months: September 20, 2002 to December 20, 2002. Yet the fans and the series’ makers refused to let it die. Organized expressions of fan interest, such as postcard campaigns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Iron Sky’s War Bonds:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cult SF Cinema and Crowdsourcing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tryon</surname>
                           <given-names>Chuck</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In February 2012, after six years of planning, fundraising, and production, the sf film<italic>Iron Sky</italic>premiered at the Berlin Film Festival. Although<italic>Iron Sky</italic>featured a provocative plot—one in which Nazis who had been hiding on the dark side of the moon return to earth in the year 2018—along with a couple of familiar international stars, including German actor Udo Kier, and a soundtrack by the Slovenian avant-garde band Laibach, the film was discussed most frequently because of its unusual production history, which involved the contributions of thousands of fans and followers who donated time and money</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Transnational Interactions:</title>
                     <subtitle>District 9, or Apaches in Johannesburg</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tatsumi</surname>
                           <given-names>Takayuki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2009, several friends recommended that I see<italic>District 9</italic>, a new film produced by Peter Jackson and directed by the hitherto unknown Neill Blomkamp. They knew that since I was something of a missionary for cyberpunk and avant-pop texts, I would appreciate this film, an unlikely export from South Africa that had quickly attracted a cult following. They were right. Blomkamp’s ideas and shocking images immediately reminded me of Shinya Tsukamoto’s cyberpunk Tetsuo films (<italic>Tetsuo: The Iron Man</italic>, 1988, and<italic>Tetsuo II: Body Hammer</italic>, 1992) which had inspired me to write my first book,<italic>Full Metal Apache</italic>(2006). However,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>A Donut for Tom Paris:</title>
                     <subtitle>Identity and Belonging at European SF/Fantasy Conventions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lamerichs</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicolle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Decades ago, fans were usually adults who had the economic and social liberty of going to conventions or clubs. Recently, the discourse on fandom has become entwined with that on new media audiences, who are not only portrayed as younger, but also seen as especially exemplary of fandom in terms of their online activity. As a result of the increase in online participatory culture, criticism has followed suit, often focusing more on the “online” than the “offline” dimensions of fandom. However, concerts, conventions, movie theaters, and fan clubs remain relevant sites where media fandom is performed today, and these venues</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Robot Monster and the “Watchable … Terrible” Cult/SF Film</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Telotte</surname>
                           <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Lincoln Geraghty reminds us, early 1950s sf cinema, typified by films like<italic>The Day the Earth Stood Still</italic>(1951),<italic>The Thing</italic>(1951),<italic>Invaders from Mars</italic>(1953), and<italic>War of the Worlds</italic>(1953), was often marked by a rather serious tone and effect, presenting “America and the world in the grip of emergencies … that jeopardized the future of the [human] race” (23). Despite their sometimes strange monsters and strained plots, the “emergency” visions in these films urged audiences to contemplate the trajectory of their newly atomic-driven world, to reconsider the tense and potentially destructive relations between nations, or, simply,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Science Fiction and the Cult of Ed Wood:</title>
                     <subtitle>Glen or Glenda?, Bride of the Monster, and Plan 9 from Outer Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hill</surname>
                           <given-names>Rodney F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a body of work, the films of Edward D. Wood, Jr., virtually defy classification. Wood’s career output included exploitation films, short subjects, industrial films, commercials, pornography, and unproduced screenplays, as well as various forays into sf. Yet even at an individual level, several of Wood’s best-known films elude our grasp in terms of genre:<italic>Bride of the Monster</italic>(aka,<italic>Bride of the Atom</italic>, 1955) freely traverses the borders between sf and horror; and recent criticism has noted the avant-garde qualities evident in Wood’s sf opus<italic>Plan 9 from Outer Space</italic>(1956, released 1959), as well as the exploitation film</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Visual Pleasure, the Cult, and Paracinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vint</surname>
                           <given-names>Sherryl</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cult and sf are both categories that suggest a skewed perspective on reality. Jeffrey Sconce uses the term “paracinema” to denote this different perspective, as he describes cult and other kinds of “bad” cinema that are often appreciated, ironically, for their deviation from—perhaps resistance to—dominant aesthetic codes. Sconce maintains that the resulting celebration of such “trash” is a rejection of the hegemony of academic film criticism, championing the trashy as “a final textual frontier that exists beyond the colonizing powers of the academy, and thus serves as a staging ground for strategic raids on legitimate culture and its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>“Lack of Respect, Wrong Attitude, Failure to Obey Authority”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dark Star, A Boy and His Dog, and New Wave Cult SF</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Latham</surname>
                           <given-names>Rob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stanley Kubrick’s 1968 film<italic>2001: A Space Odyssey</italic>was a<italic>cause célèbre</italic>within the sf genre, dividing Old Guard fans, who deplored the film-maker’s purported contempt for reason and scientific inquiry, from younger fans aligned with contemporary counterculture, who embraced its trippy imagery, its fusion of science and mysticism, and its tone of apocalyptic transcendence. At the time of its release,<italic>2001</italic>became a kind of litmus test of fan sentiment towards the New Wave movement, a rising sf avant-garde that sought to remake a genre traditionally inclined towards technocratic scientism and conservative narrative style into a more experimental, counterculturally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Capitalism, Camp, and Cult SF:</title>
                     <subtitle>Space Truckers as Satire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Booker</surname>
                           <given-names>M. Keith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Set in worlds that are different from our own and often featuring civilizations and customs (or even species) that are different from our own, sf is<italic>the</italic>genre of difference. And sf fans, with a long history of fandom that dates back to the letters columns in the pulps of the 1930s, tend to be regarded as a sort of subculture, different from the mainstream, though alike in their difference and in their common interest in sf. In like fashion, cult films and other cult objects achieve their cult status both because they are different from the perceived norm in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Bubba Ho-tep and the Seriously Silly Cult Film</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weinstock</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By looking at the example of Don Coscarelli’s unapologetically silly 2002 film,<italic>Bubba Ho-tep</italic>, I want to propose that we consider sf, fantasy, and indeed cult films of all stripes as both literal and figurative “strange attractors.” Excluding perhaps what J. P. Telotte refers to as “classical” cult films in<italic>The Cult Film Experience</italic>—mainstream Hollywood films such as<italic>Casablanca</italic>(Michael Curtiz, 1942) that have inspired fiercely loyal fan followings—cult films typically are works that foreground their thematic, structural, and/or aesthetic deviation from loosely defined Hollywood norms. They<italic>literally</italic>attract due to their strangeness. Borrowing from chaos theory, however,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Select Cult/SF Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Select Cult SF Filmography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6btc.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
