<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p95w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN5499.N5 A334 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Press and politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Nigeria</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Government and the press</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Nigeria</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nigeria</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Press coverage</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nationalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Press coverage</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Nigeria</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Nation as Grand Narrative</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Nigerian Press and the Politics of Meaning</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Adebanwi</surname>
               <given-names>Wale</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781580465557</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782047629</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wale Adebanwi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt1r69zcb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Nation as Grand Narrative offers a methodical analysis of how relations of domination and subordination are conveyed through media narratives of nationhood. Using the typical postcolonial state of Nigeria as a template and engaging with disciplines ranging from media studies, political science, and social theory to historical sociology and hermeneutics, Wale Adebanwi examines how the nation as grand narrative provides a critical interpretive lens through which competition among ethnic, ethnoregional, and ethnoreligious groups can be analyzed. Adebanwi illustrates how meaning is connected to power through ideology in the struggles enacted on the pages of the print media over diverse issues including federalism, democracy and democratization, religion, majority-minority ethnic relations, space and territoriality, self-determination, and threat of secession. Nation as Grand Narrative will trigger further critical reflections on the articulation of relations of domination in the context of postcolonial grand narratives. Wale Adebanwi is associate professor of African American and African studies, University of California-Davis, and a visiting professor at the Institute of Social and Economic Research (ISER), Rhodes University, Grahamstown, South Africa.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="406"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adebanwi</surname>
                           <given-names>Wale</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Nation as Grand Narrative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1953 a political crisis threatened to break up colonial Nigeria and terminate the possibility of common political independence for the country. This crisis was partly instigated, elaborately reported, and, ultimately, profoundly shaped by newspaper narratives. Anthony Enahoro, the anticolonial activist and leading member of the Action Group, one of the major political parties in late colonial Nigeria, whose motion at the federal parliament provoked this crisis, had been a journalist most of his adult life. Enahoro became the editor of the<italic>Southern Nigerian Defender</italic>at age twenty-one in 1944. He was later the editor of<italic>Comet</italic>, associate editor of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Interpretive Theory, Narrative, and the Politics of Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The social sciences have been concerned for many decades with fundamental questions concerning the nature of social life and its investigation. Whereas some of these concerns, and the debates they have generated, have been geared toward resolving ontological and epistemological dilemmas, others have focused on methodological challenges of the process of social enquiry.¹ This concern forms my examination of the hermeneutical analysis of social phenomenon such as the narratives about the idea and practices of the “nation.” Using interpretive theory, or hermeneutics, this chapter explores how interpreting ideology as “meaning in the service of power” illuminates the analysis of media</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>In Search of a Grand Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Press and the Ethno-Regional Struggle for Political Independence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the decade leading up to Nigeria’s independence, the three major ethno-regional blocs in the country, the eastern region, the northern region, and the western region, organized essentially around the three major political parties, the National Council for Nigeria and the Cameroons (NCNC) the Northern People’s Congress (NPC), and the Action Group (AG), respectively. The struggle to define the character and logic of the emergent state and imagined grand nation by the many ethnic nationalities of the regions, through the leveraging of group interests within the larger context, was evident in the major newspapers that represented each of these major</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Hegemony and Ethno-Spatial Politics:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Nationalizing” the Capital City in the Late-Colonial Era</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines the narratives surrounding the structure, nature, and dynamics of the spatial struggle for hegemony over a city that was seen by some “gladiators” as the social and political—perhaps also economic—equivalent of the whole of Nigeria. One of the leading nationalists of that era, H. O. Davies, captured this sentiment when he said that Lagos contained “the genius of the country.”¹ Obafemi Awolowo, also a leading activists of that era, but an Ibadan resident in the same Western region, accused the nationalists in Lagos of seeing the city as “the alpha and omega of political sagacity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Paper Soldiers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narratives of Nationhood and Federalism in Pre–Civil War Nigeria</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Narratives of conflict between antagonistic or competing communities compel the construction of simplistic binaries: good versus evil, truth versus falsehood, progress versus regression, and freedom versus oppression.¹ In reporting ethnic conflicts, the media, particularly those representing interested parties, rarely present “a coherent political analysis.”² Yet media narratives can precipitate and exacerbate conflict. Daya Kishan Thussu and Des Freedman identify the media in the context of the communication of conflict as a “battleground.”³ Regarding the contemporary world, saturated with the media’s reporting of conflict, Simon Cottle argues that the media-conflict interface needs to be understood through the perspective of “mediatized conflict.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Representing the Nation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Electoral Crisis and the Collapse of the Third Republic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is Nigeria? A mere geographical expression or potentially a nation? And on what basis can the people who constitute it make claims on the polity? As members of different communities (ethnic or ethno-regional) or as individual rights-bearing citizens? Chapter 1 discussed the debate in Africa on whether the question of identity or that of democratic freedom should constitute the foundation for understanding belongingness within multicultural polities in Africa. This debate is mirrored in the questions above. Whereas scholars like Brendan Boyce argue that reconciling the issue of “identity redefinition” in the context of the historical limitations and opportunities in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The “Fought” Republic:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Press, Ethno-Religious Conflicts, and Democratic Ethos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 6 considered the relationship between identity politics and democracy in Africa and the challenge of reconciling democratic freedom with the limitations and opportunities of ethnic or ethnonationalist (and also faith-based) claims. This chapter analyzes democratic and identitarian narratives reflecting antagonistic and competing claims within the Nigerian national space and the dangers that these represent for national democratic life in Nigeria.</p>
                     <p>Nigeria’s Fourth Republic, which commenced on May 29, 1999, almost six years after the Third Republic was aborted, provided yet another opportunity for ethno-regional and religious identities to engage in simultaneous contests for supremacy or accommodation within a democratic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Narratives, Territoriality, and Majority-Minority Ethnic Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I concentrate on how the symbolic manifestation of territoriality is used to structure other manifestations. I describe this symbolic manifestation as<italic>discursive territoriality</italic>, one in which the media become resources “through which power is exercised to produce—or disrupt—systemic regularity.”¹ Discursive territoriality is a dimension of spatial politics, one in which the material and emotional dimensions of space are harnessed in the narratives and discourses of power, which then align particular people firmly, and sometimes also exclusively, to particular territories and privilege their claims to the material benefits of—and emotional attachment to—such spaces.</p>
                     <p>Discursive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Narratives, Oil, and the Spatial Politics of Marginal Identities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The debate on the place of minority ethnic groups in Nigeria preceded the independence of the Nigerian state. However, by the 1940s and 1950s, it was evident that ethnicity in general and the struggle for the accommodation of the many ethnic nations within Nigeria would pose a major challenge to the process of nation-building. It was precisely at this point, particularly during the June 1957 London Conference on the Nigerian (Independence) Constitution, that the three dominant ethnic groups were struggling to gain advantage over one another and that ethnic minorities made it clear they would not be “pacified by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Beyond Grand Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Narratives make “meaningful totality” out of a myriad of events.¹ Therefore they play a very important role in the struggle for control and full participation in whatever is constituted as a “totality”—particularly a political totality expressive in ethnic or ethno-national boundaries. In constructing a meaningful totality out of the mess of political life, narratives invite other narratives to validate or invalidate them. Therefore, no single narrative is adequate in representing the political world. As Campbell asserts, “only through the clash of competing narratives are we likely to assemble justifiable knowledge.”² Indeed, although they present a more meaningful and coherent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r69zcb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
