<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B981.P55 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Canadian</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Philosophical Apprenticeships</book-title>
         <subtitle>Contemporary Continental Philosophy in Canada</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lampert</surname>
               <given-names>Jay</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Robinson</surname>
               <given-names>Jason</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776618012</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776618016</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpgcw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Philosophical Apprenticeships</italic>gathers fresh and innovative essays written by the next generation of Canada's philosophers on the work of prominent Canadian philosophers currently researching topics in continental philosophy. The authors--doctoral students studying at Canadian universities--have studied with, worked with, or been deeply influenced by these philosophers. Their essays present, discuss, and develop the work of their mentors, addressing issues such as time, art, politics, hermeneutics, and phenomenology. The result is a volume that introduces the reader to the work of current Canadian philosophers and to that of their successors, who will soon be making their own contributions to Canadian continental philosophy.Includes articles by Gabriel Malenfant on Bettina Bergo, Saulius Geniusas on Gary Madison, John Marshall on Samuel Mallin, François Doyon on Claude Piché, Stephanie Zubcic on Jennifer Bates, Alexandra Morrison on Graeme Nicholson, Scott Marratto on John Russon, and Jill Gilbert on John Burbridge.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="152"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Simultaneity and Delay:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lampert’s Already and Not Yet of Now</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robinson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jason</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The nature of time has been an irresistible mystery for philosophers for thousands of years. The same is no less true today, although questions of time have changed dramatically under the influence of physicists such as Newton and Einstein, and the hegemony of the natural sciences. For instance, most no longer think of time in terms of the Ancient Greeks’ cyclical time, modelled on the periodical rhythms of nature, or Christian eschatological time (rectilinear historical time), with its actual though postponed Kingdom in the present age (both fulfilled and fulfilling). While elements of both persist—such as the association of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Faire sens du sensé ou Bergo et la sortie de soi par l’arrivée de l’autre</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Malenfant</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Si l’autre brusque ma pensée, s’il interrompt l’idée que je me fais–interruption de l’activité même de toute création de concept–, c’est qu’il brise la tâche incessante que l’intentionnalité prend à bras le corps, soit celle de la connaissance. Néanmoins, l’épistémie faite du monde par un épicentre subjectif semblait, jusqu’à Lévinas, englober l’autre (dans le cartésianisme ou par l’intersubjectivité husserlienne, notamment). Après tout, l’autre est justement du monde et, à ce titre, il peut être, comme la pierre, objet pour un sujet. Mais la plupart, sinon la totalité, des raisonnements religieux et éthiques des traditions confessionnelles et philosophiques ont</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Madison and Hermeneutic Intentionality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Consciousness, Language, Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geniusas</surname>
                           <given-names>Saulius</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following remarks on the concept of intentionality will follow the path traversed by Gary Madison, the person who introduced me to phenomenology. By inquiring into intentionality I aim to account for at least some of the central features of Madison’s phenomenological hermeneutics. I share Madison’s conviction that the fruitful future of phenomenology and hermeneutics to a large degree depends upon the continuing dialogue between them. My aim here is to explore some reasons that will help in substantiating this claim. My interpretation, besides addressing Madison’s published texts, will also focus on a number of conference presentations, lectures, seminars, and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Mallin and Philip Glass’s “The Grid”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marshall</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Arguably one of the most difficult tasks of philosophy is to grasp where we are today. While undoubtedly this has something to do with the usual biases of the day, in that philosophers are as surely bound by mundane prejudices as everyone else, it also seems to derive from a factor peculiar to philosophy. It is no accident that philosophers have long dealt with the question of the good life. Philosophers have always wanted to leave the cave. Whether or not one fashions the departure in grand metaphysical terms, one can maintain, with fairly adequate justification, that a defining characteristic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Piché:</title>
                     <subtitle>la méthode phénoménologique du jeune Heidegger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Doyon</surname>
                           <given-names>François</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Il y a certainement autant de conceptions de la phénoménologie qu’il y a de phénoménologues. Plus encore, la conception de la plupart des phénoménologues varie tout au long de leur recherche, se modifi ant aux tournants de leurs chemins de pensée. Aussi est-il impossible de donner une défi nition univoque de la phénoménologie et d’assigner au mouvement phénoménologique une quelconque unité doctrinale. En effet, comme l’a montré Claude Piché¹, depuis Lambert, le concept de phénoménologie n’a cessé d’évoluer. Au départ science de l’apparence, la phénoménologie a fini par devenir, chez Heidegger, la science de ce qui n’apparaît pas à première</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Mediating Play:</title>
                     <subtitle>Analyzing Jennifer Bates’s “Interplay” with Hegel, Shakespeare, and Morality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zubcic</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper concerns an important and prominent theme in Hegelian study: the power of mediation to unite diverse voices in dark times. I begin with my interpretation of Hegel’s phenomenological subjectivity of “self-consciousness.” According to my reading of his<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>, his dialogical project gives significant emphasis to the idea that mediation acts as a dialogical process of representational “interplay.” I briefly discuss the historical and conceptual origin of this idea as it pertains to Hegelian thought. The central aim of this paper is to account for the role of imagination epistemologically as it relates to moral action. Exploring</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Nicholson:</title>
                     <subtitle>Through Self-loathing to Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morrison</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his contribution to a collection honouring his fellow Heidegger scholar William J. Richardson, Graeme Nicholson explains why the preposition “through” governs the title of his essay “Through Phenomenology to Concealment.”¹ Nicholson explains his choice by describing how Heidegger persuaded Richardson to change the subtitle of his book, which initially read<italic>Heidegger: From Phenomenology to Thought</italic>, but which came to read<italic>Through Phenomenology to Thought.²</italic>As Nicholson points out, this seemingly minor alteration “helped to shape a whole generation’s reading of Heidegger.”³ The preposition “through” emphasizes that phenomenology is not left behind, that it is not simply a passes through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Russon’s Pharmacy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Desire, Philosophy, and the Ambiguity of “Mental Health”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marratto</surname>
                           <given-names>Scott</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his book<italic>Human Experience: Philosophy, Neurosis, and the Elements of Everyday Life</italic>(2003), John Russon explores some of the major themes of contemporary European philosophy, such as time, embodiment, and language, and does so in the clear, engaging, and conceptually precise manner that I, as one of his grateful students, have come to recognize as the hallmark of his teaching style. In fact,<italic>Human Experience</italic>is a book written in the “voice” of a teacher, and in a manner that exemplifies Russon’s philosophy of education. Its argument unfolds in such a way to lead the reader through what seems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Contingency as Pedagogy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Burbidge on Hegel and Contingency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                           <given-names>Jill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John Burbidge is one of the foremost scholars of Hegel in the English-speaking world. He has helped to bring Hegel into the twenty-first century, and has overturned many preconceived notions about Hegel’s philosophy. My attempt in this paper is to illustrate the originality of Burbidge’s thought by appealing to his most recent book,<italic>Hegel’s Systematic Contingency</italic>, which gathers articles written over the course of his philosophical career.</p>
                     <p>In this book Burbidge offers two primary theses. The first of these emphasizes that contingency is necessary in Hegel’s philosophy, and, more specifically, that it is critical to systematic thought. Burbidge’s second thesis,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpgcw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
