<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh4pf</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PA4037.A5W75 1997</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Homer</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Epic poetry, Greek</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Epic poetry, Medieval</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Comparative</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greek and medieval</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Comparative</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Medieval and Greek</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral interpretation of poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Written communication</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">formulaic analysis</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral tradition</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral tradition</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Written Voices, Spoken Signs</book-title>
         <subtitle>Tradition, Performance, and the Epic Text</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BAKKER</surname>
               <given-names>EGBERT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KAHANE</surname>
               <given-names>AHUVIA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674962606</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780674020467</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x0fd2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Written Voices, Spoken Signs</italic>is a stimulating introduction to new perspectives on Homer and other traditional epics. Taking advantage of recent research on language and social exchange, the nine essays in this volume focus on performance and audience reception of oral poetry.</p>
         <p>These innovative essays by leading scholars of Homer, oral poetics, and epic invite us to rethink some key concepts for an understanding of traditional epic poetry. Egbert Bakker examines the epic performer's use of time and tense in recounting a past that is alive. Tackling the question of full-length performance of the monumental<italic>Iliad</italic>, Andrew Ford considers the extent to which the work was perceived as a coherent whole in the archaic age. John Miles Foley addresses questions about spoken signs and the process of reference in epic discourse, and Ahuvia Kahane studies rhythm as a semantic factor in the Homeric performance. Richard Martin suggests a new range of performance functions for the Homeric simile. And Gregory Nagy establishes the importance of one feature of epic language, the ellipsis. These six essays centered on Homer engage with fundamental issues that are addressed by three essays primarily concerned with medieval epic: those by Franz BÃƒÂ¤uml on the concept of fact; by Wulf Oesterreicher on types of orality; and by Ursula Schaefer on written and spoken media. In their Introduction the editors highlight the underlying approach and viewpoints of this collaborative volume.Reviews of this book:"Despite its wide range of topics and approaches, the volume has a clear thematic focus. All contributors seek to leave behind the more formal concerns of past generations of scholars and aim instead at an understanding of orality as that which is (conceptually or actually) close, immediate, or performed. In their joint search for the new picture, classicists, linguists, and medievalists discover a range of different 'oralities'."</p>
         <p>--J. Haubold,<italic>Classical Review</italic>
         </p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boedeker</surname>
                           <given-names>Deborah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Raaflaub</surname>
                           <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Center for Hellenic Studies, located on a wooded campus in Washington, D.C., is a privately endowed residential research institute affiliated with Harvard University. At its core is a specialized library devoted to ancient Greek literature, history, philosophy, and related fields. Each academic year the Center offers ten Junior Fellowships to an international group of Hellenists in the earlier stages of their careers, as well as a Summer Session for postdoctoral scholars who need ready access to a strong research library. In addition, the Center has recently begun an annual Colloquium series.</p>
                     <p>The CHS Colloquia are devoted to examining significant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAKKER</surname>
                           <given-names>EGBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAHANE</surname>
                           <given-names>AHUVIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A little more than two generations ago Milman Parry argued for the oral nature of Homeric verse. Parry’s work started an intense debate that has irrevocably changed Homeric studies and that has provided valuable impulses for a wide variety of other disciplines.¹ In the last several years the study of oral poetry has itself received considerable impulse and has undergone a dramatic increase in the variety of approaches and points of view.</p>
                     <p>At the heart of Parry’s original thesis was the notion of “formula,”² a term that has since been modified, extended, reapplied, reused, and rejected.³ Although disagreement among scholars</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Storytelling in the Future:</title>
                     <subtitle>Truth, Time, and Tense in Homeric Epic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question whether the Greek epic tradition is a matter of truth or of fiction remains a central issue in Homeric scholarship, and any answer to it betrays one’s stance with regard to a host of other issues, such as text, tradition, and authorship. Opinions are divided as to whether the Homeric rendition of the heroic past is wholly traditional and so “objective,” or allows of fictional, “original” admixture by an individual poet. What is less often asked is whether the notion of truth itself, in the sense of an acknowledged correspondence between a statement and a state of affairs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Writing the Emperor’s Clothes On:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literacy and the Production of Facts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BÄUML</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANZ H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I shall propose the hypothesis that the development of literacy in the Middle Ages went hand in hand with the growing belief in the existence of “facts” as independent entities. Moreover, I shall maintain that this notion of “facts” is dependent on literacy and cannot arise in an oral culture, and I shall argue this using examples from medieval sources. Though I do not necessarily subscribe to a theory of two different “mentalities,” one “oral” and one “literate,” I do contend that the tools with which one thinks affect one’s thinking, that the way in which one thinks has its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Traditional Signs and Homeric Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FOLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN MILES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present contribution will focus on the roots of Homeric epic in an ancient Greek oral tradition, exploring Homeric art not as a literary triumph over that heritage but as the direct product of its unique, empowering agency. That is, it will consider how the bard and his tradition employed a dedicated medium for expression to achieve a more-than-literary art.¹ Our exordium for the exercise is the unassuming word<italic>sēma</italic>—not as in the contemporary linguistic and literary approach called “ semiotics” but as a trope and a term in the native poetics of ancient Greek epic poetry. To indicate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Inland Ship:</title>
                     <subtitle>Problems in the Performance and Reception of Homeric Epic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The time seems to be passing when the Parry-Lord theory that Homer’s epics were composed in oral performances was thought to be incompatible with the high artistic quality of our<italic>Iliad</italic>and Odyssey. Recent studies of oral formulaic language, as represented elsewhere in this volume, have shown it to be capable of many subtly expressive effects and structural patternings.¹ But if we are approaching a time when it will make little difference whether the Homeric poems were composed orally or not (Martin 1989: 1), another, and older, question becomes more pressing: how could such large-scale poems as the Homeric epics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Hexameter Progression and the Homeric Hero’s Solitary State</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAHANE</surname>
                           <given-names>AHUVIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The poetry of Homer as we have it today is a highly<italic>textualized</italic>verbal artifact. In other words, we come into immediate contact with the<italic>Iliad</italic>and<italic>Odyssey</italic>as fixed sets of graphic symbols that are independent of any particular performance event, rather than as time-bound sequences of sounds that are unique to their performance context. Many aspects of this<italic>text</italic>are indeed unchanging regardless of whether we speak out, or hear the poems, or read them silently. At the same time, we are increasingly aware of what we might call the<italic>nontextual</italic>aspects of Homer, that is, of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Similes and Performance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The linguist Michel Bréal, better known as a semanticist than Homerist, had been a teacher of Antoine Meillet, the great comparatist who succeeded him in the chair in comparative grammar of the Collège de France.¹ Bréal’s little book<italic>Pour mieux connaître Homère</italic>is actually cited once by Meillet’s student Milman Parry in<italic>L’Épithète traditionnelle,</italic>to the effect that the fixed epithet provides not only a rest to the singer but also a pause for the audience.² It is not his view on the formula, however, that seems to me an appropriate introduction to this paper, but rather Bréal’s remarks on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Ellipsis in Homer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NAGY</surname>
                           <given-names>GREGORY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This preparation concentrates on four questions: (1) What is ellipsis? (2) How does ellipsis work in Homeric song-making? (3) How does ellipsis typify Homeric song-making? (4) How does Homeric song-making use ellipsis to typify itself?</p>
                     <p>In the dictionary of Liddell and Scott, the verb<italic>elleipō</italic>is defined as (1) leave in, leave behind; (2) leave out, leave undone; (3) fall short, fail.¹ The abstract noun<italic>elleipsis,</italic>derived from this verb, designates a “leaving out” of something, as we see from the use of the word in a grammatical sense: in Athenaeus 644b, for example, the term<italic>elleipsis</italic>is applied to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Types of Orality in Text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OESTERREICHER</surname>
                           <given-names>WULF</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The subject of the following article is orality in text. Although this term may seem paradoxical at first, the formulation reflects a fundamental distinction, which is discussed at some length in the first part of the article. In the second part, some examples from the field of Romance philology are given to show not only the applicability but also the importance of this distinction and the concepts associated with it. In the main part of my argument, a typology of orality in written texts is presented. This typology is illustrated by Latin documents, because these are easily accessible and generally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>The Medial Approach:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Paradigm Shift in the Philologies?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHAEFER</surname>
                           <given-names>URSULA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their introductory essay to a collection of articles by Eric H. Havelock, Aleida and Jan Assmann speak of “the new paradigm ‘Communication and Media.’”¹ Assmann and Assmann credit Eric Havelock with having given to the formula From Mythos to Logos the empirical basis of media science:² “The new idea which Havelock has elaborated on and varied in all of his works is that of the media dependence of thinking. Sense [<italic>Sinn</italic>], experience, reality—these are all variables of the media that we avail ourselves of. Anything that may be known, thought and said about the world is only knowable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0fd2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
