<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">RC480.8.H44 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychotherapist and patient</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychotherapy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Helping behavior</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Counseling</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Education</subject>
         <subject>Psychology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Helping Relationship</book-title>
         <subtitle>Healing and Change in Community Context</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Meier</surname>
               <given-names>Augustine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rovers</surname>
               <given-names>Martin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776619354</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776619357</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ch77tk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The increased use of and emphasis on managed care, manualized treatment protocols, evidence-based treatments and quick treatments have marginalized the role of the helping relationship in the helping professions. This shift has sparked a debate within the helping professions over whether the helping relationship or technique is primarily responsible for healing and change.<italic>The Helping Relationship</italic>weighs in on this debate, arguing that healing and change always take place within the context of relationships and that the relationship is more important than the technique. While recognizing the value of techniques, the authors valorize the helping relationship, considering it in unconventional contexts, such as formal education, supervision, and faith communities to show its flexibility and efficacy. This alternative approach adds a new perspective on the helping relationship debate, shedding new light on the roles of relationship and technique in the healing process.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Helping Others in Religious, Cultural, and Psychological Contexts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier</surname>
                           <given-names>Augustine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rovers</surname>
                           <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many stories of how people have come together to help others who have endured unexpected disasters and tragedies or suffer from some of life’s pains, losses, and traumas. During the flood in Manitoba, volunteers from all across Canada came to the aid of inundated Manitobans. Hurricane Katrina (2005) marshalled help from all over the world. When a young Saskatchewan farmer died from cancer, his relatives and neighbours organized themselves to take off his harvest. Following the Columbine High School Massacre (1999), counsellors were sent to the school to help the returning students grieve the loss of their friends.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I</label>
                     <title>The Therapeutic Relationship and Techniques:</title>
                     <subtitle>How Clients Bring about Desired Changes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier</surname>
                           <given-names>Augustine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twenty-first century is indeed an exciting time in which to live because of the many technological advances that pervade all segments of our society. Information technology allows us in seconds to connect to and communicate with people regardless of where they live. Technology has opened the door to outerspace exploration and has advanced medical diagnostic and surgical procedures. One stands in awe in the face of all these advances and humbly ponders whether the best is yet to come.</p>
                     <p>Fascinated by the technological advances in medicine, communication, and outerspace exploration, psychotherapists and psychotherapy researchers ponder whether there are techniques</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>II</label>
                     <title>The Fate of the Helping Relationship in the Age of Manualized Treatments:</title>
                     <subtitle>Evidence-Based Practice and Time-Limited Psychotherapies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schöttler</surname>
                           <given-names>Tricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the gloomy tone of the title of this chapter, the aims of this discussion are ultimately benevolent: to highlight the crucial importance of the helping relationship, a proven medium of client change; to outline the current trends in psychotherapy research and training as they relate to the recognition, or lack thereof, of the role of this crucial factor; to speculate on the possible future of the helping relationship within this current social/political/economic climate; and to offer some alternative paths that might serve to counteract what seems to me and many others to be a growing trend toward ultimately divesting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III</label>
                     <title>Transference and Countertransference Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier</surname>
                           <given-names>Augustine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the past decade, there has been increased interest in the theoretical construct of countertransference. Attempts have been made to broaden its meaning to include all of the therapist’s feelings toward the client, in therapy and beyond therapy, and not to limit its meaning to the expression of the therapist’s unconscious and conflicted feelings as a reaction to a client’s transference. To better appreciate this trend, it is essential to revisit the concept of countertransference and to ascertain its original meaning, see how it has evolved over time, and consider the factors that have contributed to its modification.</p>
                     <p>The primary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV</label>
                     <title>Working with Transference and Countertransference in Psychotherapy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Briscoe-Dimock</surname>
                           <given-names>Shelley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of “alliance” is rooted in psychoanalysis and Freud, who viewed the alliance as the connection between client and therapist (Horvath, 2001). Although there is no precise definition of alliance, the concept has been a topic of theoretical and empirical interest for the past quarter-century, particularly in counselling and supervision.</p>
                     <p>A review of the professional literature on the helping relationship and specifically the therapeutic alliance has consistently shown a positive relationship between client-therapist alliance and therapeutic outcome (Lambert &amp; Barley 2001). Indeed, most therapists would agree that a positive alliance is critical to the therapeutic process. Decades of research suggest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>V</label>
                     <title>Working through the Transference of an Unresolved Separation/Individuation Pattern:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study Using Theme-Analysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier</surname>
                           <given-names>Augustine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boivin</surname>
                           <given-names>Micheline</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier</surname>
                           <given-names>Molisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A primary developmental task for a child is to become emotionally bonded with a significant caregiver (e.g., mother) and then, in due course, to separate from her and to individuate and become his or her own person (Mahler, Pine, &amp; Bergman, 1975). A failure to achieve this developmental task may mark the person’s relational pattern in that he or she may develop a fear of getting close to people or of feeling abandoned when pushed to pursue independence. A person with this pattern can also alternate between getting close to and taking distance from a significant person. This relational pattern—referred</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VI</label>
                     <title>The Medical Model of Psychotherapy:</title>
                     <subtitle>In Historical Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dimock</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One usually goes to a doctor when one is sick. Th at has been true for time immemorial. Hua T’o was, according to the annals of the later Han Dynasty, an excellent Chinese surgeon who practised around 220 AD. He possibly used opium dissolved in wine as his anaesthetic. Western medicine was introduced to China in the early 17<sup>th</sup>century, while Emperors Fu Hsi, Shen Nung, and Huang Ti were said to have founded the art of healing long before. Tao—the method of maintaining harmony between this world and the beyond—was subdivided into heaven, earth, and man. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VII</label>
                     <title>The Helping Relationship:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Context for Learning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lund</surname>
                           <given-names>Kristine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These common presenting issues elicit a variety of therapeutic responses, such as solution focused, cognitive behavioural, or psychoanalytic theory, to address unresolved issues from childhood or family of origin patterns that are influencing the client’s current relationships. More recently, therapists have looked at client issues from a systemic perspective, especially narrative and constructionist, and in particular have worked to build on client strengths to address current concerns.</p>
                     <p>What if counselling is simply about learning? What if the presenting concerns that clients bring to counselling are more about opportunities for learning than about indications of dysfunction, pathology, or problems to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VIII</label>
                     <title>Mentoring:</title>
                     <subtitle>Educating for Mental Growth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ste-Marie</surname>
                           <given-names>Lorraine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mentoring is generally understood as a relationship between two people aimed at enabling a wide range of learning, experimentation, and development. Although mentoring is becoming increasingly recognized as a significant aspect of both personal and professional development today, the mentoring-type relationship has existed in all of human history. This is well exemplified in the characters of Mentor and his mentee, Telemachus, in the ancient Greek story of<italic>The Odyssey</italic>(Daloz, 1999, p. 17). In the past 25 years, there has been an increase in the use of formal mentoring programs in the workplace as well as in academic and professional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IX</label>
                     <title>The Helping Relationship in CPE Supervision</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cutting</surname>
                           <given-names>Marsha</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word<italic>ezer</italic>(“helper”) in its various forms is widely used in the Hebrew Bible—120 times, to be exact. If we examine the passages where<italic>ezer</italic>is used, we find that a helper keeps one from being alone and can be a partner (Genesis 2:18), the powerless have particular need of a helper (Job 29:12), God is appealed to as a helper (Psalm 30:10), and God delivers those who have no helper (Psalm 72:12). Also, if God opposes you, you won’t prevail, even with help (Jeremiah 47:1–7), people are foolish to put faith in helpers who oppose God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>X</label>
                     <title>The Pastorate as Helping Relationship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morrison</surname>
                           <given-names>Bradley T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Spiritual care is rapidly replacing pastoral care in institutional settings. While the assumptions of spiritual counselling may be a better fit for hospitals, nursing homes, and counselling centres, the pastoral paradigm remains the better fit for congregational care. This chapter argues that the pastoral paradigm provides a productive framework for addressing developments in the field of pastoral care and congregational ministry. The chapter correlates the psychotherapy outcome research of the common factors model with features of the pastoral paradigm to identify the ways in which the pastoral paradigm leverages the relational and communal dimensions of congregational life. The pastorate is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77tk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
