<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B946 .L97 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, American</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803–1882</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Migration and Mobility in the Modern Age</book-title>
         <subtitle>Refugees, Travelers, and Traffickers in Europe and Eurasia</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WALKE</surname>
               <given-names>ANIKA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MUSEKAMP</surname>
               <given-names>JAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SVOBODNY</surname>
               <given-names>NICOLE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253024763</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253025081</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253025087</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt20060x8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Combining methodological and theoretical approaches to migration and mobility studies with detailed analyses of historical, cultural, or social phenomena, the works collected here provide an interdisciplinary perspective on how migrations and mobility altered identities and affected images of the "other." From walkways to railroads to airports, the history of travel provides a context for considering the people and events that have shaped Central and Eastern Europe and Russia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walke</surname>
                           <given-names>Anika</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>SINCE THE FALL of the Iron Curtain in the late 1980s, the movement of people is a central topic of concern, among the citizenry, among politicians, and among scholars in Central and Eastern Europe (CEE) and the former Soviet Union. The intense debate about people’s ability to move and the transfer of goods and ideas and about ways to deal with unregulated migration reflects a complex web of movements and their assigned meanings. Recent scholarship on the movement of people in this region largely uses and expands on sociological and political science frameworks, focusing on pressing problems of integration and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Paris—St. Petersburg:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shrinking Spaces in the Nineteenth Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Musekamp</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 1789, THE AUTHOR of this account, famous Russian writer and historian Nikolai Mikhailovich Karamzin, went on an extended study tour of Western Europe.² Starting at Tver’ in the Russian Empire, he traveled first to St. Petersburg, then to Königsberg (Kaliningrad) in East Prussia, then to Berlin and France, and, finally, to England. In 1791–1792, he published his<italic>Letters of a Russian Traveler</italic>(<italic>Pis’ma russkogo puteshestvennika</italic>) . Karamzin did not base his literary work on actual letters but rather on notes taken during his trip.³ While scholars widely regard these “letters” as a model for contemporary Russian travel accounts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>“A Main Station at One’s Front Door”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bicycles, Automobiles, and Early Adopters’ Dreams of Personal Mobility in Poland, 1885–1939</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wood</surname>
                           <given-names>Nathaniel D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 1899, THE VARSOVIAN civil engineer Emil Sokal wrote, “In the West, they maintain that time is money; here it seems that time still has little value, yet there will come a time of change when rapid locomotion will prove extremely valuable, just as it allegedly already is abroad, except that the automobile will become an extraordinary advantage for us by replacing in many instances the railway with a main station at one’s front door.”¹ Sokal’s enthusiasm for the automobile was much like the famed writer Bolesiaw Prus’s fervor for the bicycle eight years earlier, when he gushed that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Walking with a Tolstoyan Dancer:</title>
                     <subtitle>Physical and Psychic Mobility in Vaslav Nijinsky’s Diary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Svobodny</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicole</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ON JANUARY 19, 1919, Vaslav Nijinsky, the Polish-Russian internationally acclaimed dancer, gave a solo recital for about two hundred people at the Suvretta House Hotel in St. Moritz, Switzerland. His wife, Romola, recalls how Nijinsky came out in plain practice clothes, picked up a chair, and sat down in front of the audience. The audience waited, ill at ease but full of expectation, while Nijinsky sat perfectly still. Everyone waited like this for about half an hour. Eventually Nijinsky took out a few rolls of black and white velvet cloth and made a big cross the length of the room.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Russian Resorts and European Leisure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Railroad Vacations, “Native” Sites, and the Making of a Russian (Post) Colonial Identity in Manchuria, 1920s–1930s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hsu</surname>
                           <given-names>Chia Yin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AN ENGLISH-LANGUAGE HANDBOOK of North Manchuria published in 1924 by the Chinese Eastern Railway (CER), the region’s central land transportation network, ran a full-page advertisement for the railway’s “health resorts.” The CER was constructed in the Chinese territory of Manchuria by the imperial Russian state and completed in 1903. As the final stretch of the Siberian Railroad, it linked European Russia to the Pacific Ocean. The advertised resorts were located at various CER train stations and shared their names: Chalantun, Imienpo, Fularki, Hingan, Laosiaokow and Echo. The page offered scenic images of the resorts and descriptions of their surroundings. Chalantun</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Dynamic Bohemians:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Russian Artistic Circle in Paris (Russkii Artisticheskii Kruzhok v Parizhe)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Winestein</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE PERIOD FROM 1870 to 1930 was the heyday of visual artistic exchange between France and Russia, during which countless Russian and later Soviet artists traveled to Paris to visit, study, create, advance their careers, and simply live. They naturally gravitated toward creative compatriots—other artists, poets and writers, musicians, scholars and scientists—but sometimes also turned to political émigrés, revolutionaries, or alternatively diplomats and other representatives of Russian officialdom. The informal networks and structured organizations that emerged not only connected the artists with other Russians in Paris but helped them interact and even integrate into the broader French art</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Sex at the Border:</title>
                     <subtitle>Trafficking as a Migration Problem in Partitioned Poland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stauter-Halsted</surname>
                           <given-names>Keely</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE TURN OF the twentieth century was a time of nearly constant human movement out of Eastern Europe. A huge portion of the population of the Polish lands left home during the decades leading up to World War I, with some 8 percent of ethnic Poles crossing international boundaries for seasonal or long-term work.¹ This heightened mobility brought with it chaos, corruption, and anxiety about the fate of loved ones across the sea.² Those left behind reserved special concern for the fortunes of single women traveling abroad on their own.³ Families worried about the vulnerabilities young women suffered during the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Evacuation as Migration:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Soviet Experience during the Great Patriotic War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Siegelbaum</surname>
                           <given-names>Lewis H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moch</surname>
                           <given-names>Leslie Page</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WE LIVE IN an age when large undertakings by states are likely to inspire suspicion if not outright hostility, when the fruits of previous state endeavors wither for lack of commitment to their continuation, and when corporate and other private enterprises reap the whirlwind of profit and power from state retrenchment. The only exceptions to these trends might be war and disaster relief, though states increasingly are privatizing and outsourcing war making, and their relief efforts often take second place to those of nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) or international bodies.</p>
                     <p>In this respect, perhaps more than any other, the Soviet Union</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Far From Home:</title>
                     <subtitle>Soviet and Non-Soviet Railway Workers’ Experiences during the Construction of the Baikal-Amur Mainline Railway (BAM), 1974–1984</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ward</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS CHAPTER EXPLORES the efforts of the Soviet administration, particularly members of the Komsomol (the USSR Young Communist League) and the USSR Ministry of Transport Construction, to complete the Baikal-Amur Mainline Railway (BAM) by propagandizing the mainline among the peoples of the Soviet Union’s allies and through the use of foreign labor in the area in which the railway was being constructed, which is known as the BAM Zone.⁴ In the eyes of the project’s managers, this accomplishment would serve as a catalyst in increasing trade between the European USSR and the Pacific Rim, particularly with Japan, and thus help</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Traumatic Mobility:</title>
                     <subtitle>Motivating Collective Authorship in Siberian Narratives of Polish Exiles from the Inter-revolutionary Epoch (1832–1862)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blake</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE VARIOUS LABELS<italic>deportees</italic>,<italic>exiles</italic>, and<italic>Sybiracy</italic>(Siberians) do not adequately express the violent and traumatic dislocation experienced by generations of nineteenth-century Polish revolutionaries, when they were arrested, imprisoned in citadels, and forced to march, often in shackles, across vast expanses of the Russian Empire as part of the process of being relocated to prisons and fortresses in a land governed by officials speaking another tongue.¹ Polish exiles from the<italic>epoka miêdzypowstaniowa</italic>(inter-revolutionary epoch), sentenced between the 1830–1831 November Uprising and the 1863 January Uprising in the Congress Kingdom of Poland, comprised a particularly mobile group of<italic>Sybiracy</italic>, since</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Technology, the City, and the Body:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bergelson and Shklovsky in Berlin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Murav</surname>
                           <given-names>Harriet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FOR VIKTOR SHKLOVSKY, the Russian-language Formalist writer and critic, and for David Bergelson, the Yiddish prose author, the city of Berlin, the place of their temporary exile in the 1920s, presented a fascinating spectacle of city life and technological sophistication, as well as the horrific traces of World War I. Both refer to the so-called broken men, veterans who had suffered severe and dramatically visible bodily disfigurement. In the “postscript” to<italic>Zoo, or Letters Not about Love</italic>(written and published in Berlin), Shklovsky notes that the “streets are filled with terribly subdued cripples.”¹ The protagonist of Bergelson’s “Among Refugees,” a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Andrzej Stasiuk and the Myth of the Literary Gastarbajter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gasyna</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Andrzej Stasiuk, born in 1960 in Warsaw, ranks among postcommunist Poland’s most successful cultural exports. His novels and his persona have achieved cult status both in Poland and elsewhere, especially in Ukraine and the Balkans. Despite only one reading tour of North America, in 2010, Stasiuk is a relatively familiar name in the United States, specifically in academia. Indeed, no syllabus for a college course on postcommunist European fiction would be complete without at least one work by Stasiuk on it—most often, the novel<italic>Tales of Galicia</italic>or collections of essays/stories such as<italic>Fado or My Europe</italic>are included.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Journeys of Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Soviet Jew to German Writer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wanner</surname>
                           <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>SINCE THE TURN of the millennium, a striking new phenomenon has appeared on the German literary scene: Soviet-born native speakers of Russian who immigrated to Germany and write fiction in German for a German audience. As a country that used to define itself in ethnically homogeneous terms, Germany has only belatedly and reluctantly come to acknowledge its status as a destination for immigrants. While narratives of immigration have long been at the core of America’s cultural mythology, no comparable tradition exists in Germany aside from the relatively recent phenomena of<italic>Gastarbeiterliteratur</italic>(<italic>guest worker literature</italic>) and Turkish-German literature. Russian speakers have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060x8.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
