<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT453.G69 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jesus Christ</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Crucifixion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Philosophical Anthropology of the Cross</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Cruciform Self</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gregor</surname>
               <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253006714</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253007049</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253007046</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Brian E. Gregor</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzjvj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What does the cross, both as a historical event and a symbol of religious discourse, tell us about human beings? In this provocative book, Brian Gregor draws together a hermeneutics of the self-through Heidegger, Gadamer, Ricoeur, and Taylor-and a theology of the cross-through Luther, Kierkegaard, Bonhoeffer, and Jüngel-to envision a phenomenology of the cruciform self. The result is a bold and original view of what philosophical anthropology could look like if it took the scandal of the cross seriously instead of reducing it into general philosophical concepts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="278"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Philosophy, the Cross, and Human Being</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Justifying religious faith through thinking consciousness: this is arguably the highest aspiration of the philosophy of religion. Whether this aspiration is itself justifiable, however, is another question. Can religious faith be grasped and grounded, so that its content is justified by the necessity of the philosophical concept? Does religious faith have its telos in philosophical consummation? Or does there remain some residual opacity that philosophy cannot penetrate, some otherness that philosophy cannot reconcile within its own conceptual scheme? How should philosophy approach a reality that claims to be an irresolvable scandal for philosophical thinking?</p>
                     <p>This book explores that question with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutics of the Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Book XI of his<italic>Confessions</italic>, Augustine records his perplexity over the nature of time. What is it? We talk about it all the time in our everyday conversations, as if we know what it is. “What then is time? Provided that no one asks me, I know. If I want to explain it to an inquirer, I do not know.”¹ Something similar is true about the self: in late modern Western culture, we talk about selves—and “the self”—all the time. In the natural attitude the idea of the self seems fairly unproblematic, yet if we stop and ask</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Faith, Substance, and the Cross</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we discussed Charles Taylor’s claim that human beings are self-interpreting animals. As we saw, self-interpretation is a matter of strong evaluation, a second-order evaluation of oneself. Are my desires, goals, and commitments good? Am I living the way I should? Is it good that I “am”? We evaluate ourselves, in this strong sense, within a horizon of significance—i.e., a set of background assumptions regarding what is good, meaningful, and valuable. Moreover, this strong evaluation takes place before some authority. The category of “existence before” is therefore essential to becoming a self. I experience myself as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Incurved Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this chapter is to work out two related claims regarding how to think about the fallen self, i.e., the self in sin. First, following on the relational ontology we sketched in the previous chapter, we need to think about sin relationally rather than in terms of substance and accidents. Second, in order to understand sin, we need recourse to figurative discourse. Taking Ricoeur as a point of departure, in the first section we will see why reflection on sin and evil requires a hermeneutics of figurative discourse. Sin and evil cannot be explained, but must be described.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Anthropological Question</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who am I? This is the question of the human being seeking self-understanding. It is also a question the incurved self cannot ultimately answer, because it seeks to answer this question itself through reflection on its own possibilities and acts. In order for the self to be put into the truth about itself, it must be addressed by a word from outside of itself. This external word constitutes the self and opens it toward the future. Following our discussion in chapter 4, we can distinguish between two different ways of relating to the future: (1) According to a conditional word,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Concreteness and Continuity of Faith</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 5 we saw how the self is constituted through the address of an external word, which gives the self its point of unity (<italic>Einheitspunkt</italic>). But if the self is constituted in the event of being addressed, how does the self have continuity from moment to moment? Does this event have any concrete extension in the life of the self, or does this account lead in the direction of an actualistic or punctual (<italic>Pünktlich</italic>) self?</p>
                     <p>Charles Taylor uses the term “punctual self” to describe the highly influential modern assumption that the self is pointlike in nature, with no extension</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Capable Human Being as a Penultimate Good</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 6 we saw that the cruciform self is not a punctual self. In this chapter I demonstrate the sense in which the cruciform self is a capable self, since capability is one of the central themes of philosophical anthropology. On Ricoeur’s definition, capability is a power or potentiality that the self is able to exercise—most basically, “the power to cause something to happen.”¹ So our question is this: What place do human agency and the power to act have in the life of faith? What does the word of the cross mean for our understanding of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Call to Responsibility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a result of the preceding chapter, we can see how the category of the penultimate allows us to affirm human capability yet also discern the limits of human capability and avoid a synergistic confusion of divine and human agency. The ultimate word is pronounced from beyond the self and its immanent possibilities and capacities, but within the horizon of the penultimate the self is<italic>homo capax</italic>. We can therefore identify the capacities that Ricoeur discusses in his phenomenology of<italic>l’homme capable</italic>—speaking, acting, narrating, and assuming responsibility—as penultimate capacities. If time permitted it would be worthwhile to examine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Reflexivity, Intentionality, and Self-Understanding</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 7 we saw how the category of the penultimate allows for a critical affirmation of human capability. This chapter employs a similar strategy regarding self-reflexivity and self-understanding, showing that the for-itself has a proper penultimate status in the life of faith and that the cruciform self is a self-interpreting animal. It is necessary to make this argument given our interpretation of sin as incurvature, which might seem to reinforce the Romantic-idealist interpretation of the fall as a<italic>felix culpa</italic>, a condition for the possibility of self-consciousness. Moreover, Bonhoeffer’s claim that the intentionality of faith is an<italic>actus directus</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Religion within the Limits of the Penultimate?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen how the cruciform self fits and conflicts with a number of themes of philosophical anthropology, such that we can understand the sense in which the cruciform self is also a<italic>homo capax</italic>, a responsible self, and a self-reflexive, self-interpreting animal. In this final chapter we will see whether we should think of the cruciform self as a<italic>homo religiosus</italic>. Once again we will bring Ricoeur and Bonhoeffer into dialogue. Religion, and the sacred, is a significant aspect of Ricoeur’s philosophical anthropology, since he argues that religion plays a pivotal role in the convergence of human capability and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzjvj.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
