<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Returning to Reality</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christian Platonism for our Times</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tyson</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893859</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843540</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul Tyson</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdwbb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Could it be that we have lost touch with some basic human realities in our day of high-tech efficiency, frenetic competition, and ceaseless consumption? Have we turned from the moral, the spiritual, and even the physical realities that make our lives meaningful? These are metaphysical questions -questions about the nature of reality- but they are not abstract questions. These are very down to earth questions that concern power and the collective frameworks of belief and action governing our daily lives. This book is an introduction to the history, theory, and application of Christian metaphysics. Yet this book is not just an introduction, it is also a passionately argued call for a profound change in the contemporary Christian mind. Paul Tyson argues that as Western culture’s Christian Platonist understanding of reality was replaced by modern pragmatic realism, we turned not just from one outlook on reality to another, but away from reality itself. This book seeks to show that if we can recover this ancient Christian outlook on reality, reframed for our day, then we will be able to recover a way of life that is in harmony with human and divine truth.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="228"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Everyone does metaphysics. Whenever we endeavor to understand the nature of reality we are doing metaphysics. Such an enterprise is not an abstract mind game—to the contrary, nothing could be more mundane, more practical than our operational understanding of reality. Even so, no operational understanding of reality is simply pragmatic; every time we plan or perform any activity in what we take to be a realistic manner, we do so by putting our confidence in a set of deeply held beliefs about the nature of reality itself.</p>
                     <p>As integral with realistic action as our metaphysical beliefs are, most of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Two Views of Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emma, my two-year-old daughter, has quite an astonishing understanding of reality. She is now adept at talking, but she does not just talk to her family and friends, she also talks to the cat, she talks to her breakfast, she talks to the flowers. And as far as she is concerned, her breakfast and the flowers talk back to her. It seems that she inhabits a cosmos that is intelligibly animate in its own right and where she is in rich communicative fellowship with, well, everything. And it is not just people, animals, and things she talks to. When we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Christian Platonism of Lewis and Tolkien</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If you go to Oxford today you can pop into a little pub and sit down in the room where Lewis and Tolkien and a few other likeminded friends used to have a pint and chat late into the night about what they were most seriously concerned with: imaginative stories. In our very down-to-earth times it may seem strange, even eccentric, for this bunch of English academics to take imagination so seriously, but, as we shall later unpack, imagination is indeed a very serious matter. What they were doing was seeking to clothe the Christian vision of reality, which they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bridge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Part Two I will defend the metaphysical vitality of Christian Platonism from the strident antagonism this reality vision receives from the conceptual reflexes of modern philosophy and theology. The outlooks on truth, meaning, and power that are native to the modern world find it compellingly obvious that Christian Platonism is—thankfully—long obsolete, was always intellectually impossible, and remains theologically corrupting.</p>
                     <p>In order to clear the ground for Christian Platonism to engage fairly with the deep disdain it receives from the dominant reality outlook of modernity, we will have to get right down into the “subconscious” of the mindset</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Mythos of Modernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In one of Shakespeare’s famous plays there is a scene in which some of Hamlet’s former schoolfellows flatter him about his breadth of mind. Hamlet’s response shows that he is well aware of the dark political subtext to this flattery, but his response also demonstrates precisely the kind of conceptual expansiveness he ironically denies. Refusing the compliment that Denmark is “too narrow for [his] mind” Hamlet says, “O God, I could be bounded in a nutshell and count myself a king of infinite space.”¹</p>
                     <p>Here we touch on one of the reasons why Shakespeare’s plays have such enduring power. Shakespeare,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Platonist Ideas in the New Testament</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter sketches a short outline of how some important statements in the New Testament align with one of the central ideas about the nature of reality found in Plato’s dialogues. In order to do this I will be “proof texting” both the New Testament and Plato. Whilst I hope this chapter will prove to be a useful contribution to the argument of this book, I am very aware that this exercise has some very clear limits and is fraught with perils.</p>
                     <p>The first reason why proof texting is of limited value here is that Christian Platonism is not actually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>How Christian is Christian Platonism?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even though there is no shortage of sympathy between the New Testament and some central Platonist ideas, modern Western Christians often find the idea of Christian Platonism immediately suspect. Much of this suspicion is more the product of the distinctive epistemic and metaphysical incompatibilities that exist between modernity and Christian Platonism than it is a function of a carefully supported negative evaluation of how Christian Platonism came into being and what it actually entails. In what follows we will now do some historical spadework to dispel ignorance around how Christian Platonism arose and what its distinctive features as<italic>Christian</italic>Platonism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>So What Went Wrong?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At this point in the book I think we have done enough background digging to realize that the deep-seated antipathy that modern Western philosophy and theology reflexively has towards Christian Platonism may well tell us more about modernity and nineteenth-century progressivism than it tells us about Christian Platonism. Further, I hope that it is clear that we can now no longer simply<italic>assume</italic>that Christian Platonism is obviously a bad and dead idea that is a travesty to both philosophy and theology. However, I would not be writing this book if it was not broadly assumed by academics and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Is Modern Truth, without Wisdom, Believable?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I will critique the modern notion of truth and endeavor to show that the Christian Platonist approach to truth is by no means an unreasonable or intrinsically dated alternative.</p>
                     <p>The Latin word<italic>modernus</italic>is derived from<italic>modo</italic>, meaning “just now.” What distinguishes a modernist from some other type of thinker is not simply that they are here in the “just now”—for everyone is contemporary with their own day—but that they do not take authorities from the past too seriously. That is, if the knowledge of some past sage is no longer “up to date,” then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Returning to Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past three days two of my daughters have been at a music camp. We live on the eastern coast of Australia in the beautiful sub-tropical city of Brisbane, and at this music camp Aurora and Claire have been playing their violins with four hundred other primary-school aged music students from state schools in the northern suburbs. This evening we had a two-hour concert where the children displayed their achievements to over a thousand admiring parents and relatives. They played music in two string orchestras and three stage bands, but the highlight was the massed choir at the end.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwbb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
