<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Imagining the Arabs</book-title>
         <subtitle>Arab Identity and the Rise of Islam</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Webb</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474408264</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474408271</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1474408273</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Peter Webb</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1bh2j7h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Investigating the core questions about Arab identity and history, this book tackles the time-honoured stereotypes that depict Arabs as ancient Arabian Bedouin, and reveals the stories to be a myth: tales told by Muslims to recreate the past to explain the meaning of Islam and its origins.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="416"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Note on the Text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A book about the history of the Arab people strikes its path into seemingly well-worn ground. There is nearly a millennium-worth of Arabic literature and a several century-strong tradition of European writing that portrays the Arabs as Arabia’s original population, an array of ancient Bedouin tribes roaming vast expanses of solemn sand-sea until the dawn of the seventh century when Islam’s rise stirred them from their long Arabian subsistence into a wave of rapid conquest and settlement across the Middle East that laid the ground for today’s Arab World. This familiar story has persuaded many, and the sum of much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Imagining Ancient Arabs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sources and Controversies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The evidence about pre-Islamic Arabian populations emanates from two perspectives: (1) the writings of peoples from outside Arabia who, across the 1,500 years from the Assyrians in the ninth century BCE to Islam’s rise in the seventh century CE, recorded many stories about Arabians, and (2) voices from within the Arabian Peninsula itself, preserved in inscriptions from as early as the eighth century BCE. Both bodies of sources contain numerous and intriguing references to an array of ancient peoples whose names resemble ‘Arab’, and it may seem logical enough that Arab history can be written by synthesising the material, but,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Pre-Islamic ‘Arabless-ness’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Arabian Identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The analysis thus far presents the spectre of an ‘Arabless’ pre-Islamic Arabia which may appear an extreme reaction to the familiar notion of Arabs in Antiquity, but we pose these radical challenges as there is a need to provoke critical questioning of the idea of Arabness and the timeworn practice of labelling peoples ‘Arab’ without considering how they related to senses of Arab community. An array of groups inhabited pre-Islamic Arabia and some of their descendants would come to identify themselves as Arabs, but outsiders’ evidence and anachronistic paradigms about ‘original Arab characteristics’ have not been able to give a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Arabness from the Qur’an to an Ethnos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The novel appearance of<italic>al-ʿarab</italic>in Umayyad-era poetry as a term of self-reference points decisively to the period when ideas of Arab communal consciousness gained wide acceptance to articulate a shared identity, but the verses alone do not explain why early Muslims during the later first/seventh century chose the name ‘Arab’ to identify themselves. The word<italic>al-ʿarab</italic>appeared as an understood byword for the large collective – but where did early Muslims find the word and why did it become their ethnonym? These questions are important because peoples’ choice to identify as ‘Arabs’ would not have been idle: Arabness replaced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Interpreting Arabs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Defining their Name and Constructing their Family</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When third/ninth-century Iraqi writers began their efforts to gather the many pieces into which memories of Islam’s rise had scattered, they imagined that Islam’s first believers all constituted a unified community of Arabs, and they set about assembling narratives of Islam’s rise into an Arab story. The sum of their writings had the seminal result of creating the impression that pre-Islamic Arabia was inhabited by ‘Arabs’. Akin to the construction of communal identities across the world, the Muslim-era writings obscured the Arab community’s origins in early Islam and cast Arabness back into a deep, ancient pre-history, cobbling memories of tribes,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Arabs as a People and Arabness as an Idea:</title>
                     <subtitle>750–900 CE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far, we have traced the sociopolitical drivers of Arab ethnogenesis to the second/eighth century, and we found that the exceptional conditions of early Islam fostered a new idea of ‘Arab community’ as a means for Conquerors to uphold their elite status once the initial burst of conquests had passed. The Conquerors’ towns (<italic>al-amṣār</italic>) bear striking parallels to the conditions which catalyse ethnogenesis, but the process of creating shared consciousness of Arab community was nonetheless uneven as a consequence of various obstacles impeding the capacity of Arabness to reconcile the Conquerors into one integrated family. Power struggles, regional rivalries and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Philologists, ‘Bedouinisation’ and the ‘Archetypal Arab’ after the Mid-Third/Ninth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the face of assimilation and the seismic changes in the political structure which deprived Arab groups of their status in third/ninth-century Iraq, it is remarkable that scholarly interest in ancient<italic>Arabica</italic>paradoxically blossomed after the mid-third/ninth century. Despite urban Iraqi society’s abandonment of Arab tribal affiliations (<italic>nisba</italic>) and the severance of urban Iraq from desert Arabia in the wake of the escalating Qarāmiṭa crisis and the collapse of Hajj traffic, Iraqi writers produced an unprecedented outpouring of literature about Arabness and Arab history, resulting in what today constitute the ‘primary sources’ about pre-Islamic Arabia. When reading these sources, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imagining and Reimagining the Arabs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conclusions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>352</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By unfastening Arab identity from conventional cultural stereotypes, Bedouinism and ancient pre-Islamic Arabian bloodlines, this book sought to reveal the complexities and changing nature of historic Arab identity. The book was intended as an invitation to begin rethinking Arabness afresh, and by highlighting the shortcomings inherent in the static, monolithic manner in which historical Arab communities have often been discussed, our analysis sought to reappraise historic Arabness as an ethnicity, tracking its evolution and contextualising its development with close attention to the sociopolitical and ‘cultural stuff’ factors that sustain ethnogenesis.</p>
                     <p>Taking stock, ethnogenesis and Max Weber’s ideas seem to do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2j7h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
