<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn31v7</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Deleuze's Literary Clinic</book-title>
         <subtitle>Criticism and the Politics of Symptoms</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tynan</surname>
               <given-names>Aidan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748650552</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748650569</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748650563</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Aidan Tynan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt3fgstk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first study of Deleuze's critical and clinical projectAidan Tynan addresses Deleuze's assertion that 'literature is an enterprise of health' and shows how a concern of health and illness was a characteristic of his philosophy as a whole, from his earliest works to his groundbreaking collaborations with Guattari, to his final, enigmatic statements on 'life'.He explains why alcoholism, anorexia, manic depression and schizophrenia are key concepts in Deleuze's literary theory, and shows how, with the turn to schizoanalysis, literature takes on a crucial political and ethical role in helping us to diagnose our present pathologies and articulate the possibilities of a health to come.Key FeaturesThe first book length study of Deleuze's critical and clinical project and the conceptualisations of health and illness he developed over the course of his careerUses the idea of the literary clinic to unify Deleuze's literary theory with the political critique he developed with Guattari, and argues in this way for a distinctively Deleuzian critical practiceDraws on Deleuze conceptualisations of health and illness to reassess his relationship to key thinkers such as Spinoza, Marx, Nietzsche, Freud and Melanie Klein and literary figures such as Melville F. Scott Fitzgerald, Kafka, Beckett and Artaud</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="200"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Symptomatology to Schizoanalysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book centres on Deleuze’s understanding of literature as ‘an enterprise of health’ and of literary criticism’s links to aspects of pathology and clinical practice, especially as these latter come under scrutiny in Deleuze and Guattari’s ‘schizoanalysis’ project (CC 3). The relation between literature and health is argued for most explicitly by Deleuze in his last published book,<italic>Essays Critical and Clinical</italic>. It is here that he lays out the principal hypothesis of a clinical criticism: certain authors have a weak health, but literature, by gaining a perspective on sickness, is capable of transforming this weakness into a creative power.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Case of Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Deleuze, all thinking begins in a kind of pathos. This is because thinking must be distinguished from knowledge or mental activity in general: remembering, sensing, imagining and so on. These modes of cognition remain at the purely empirical level of recognisable objects. Thought, however, goes beyond the limits of the recognisable and thus needs to be grasped in a way which distinguishes it from our day-to-day cognition of the world.¹ In other words, thought goes beyond the given differences which allow us to recognise the objects of our experience, and in turn leads towards a realm in which differences</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Paradox of the Body and the Genesis of Form and Content</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary clinic suggests a profound linkage between biophilosophy and literature. In the biophilosophical tradition of hylomorphism which includes Aristotle and Kant equally, life is isolated from the material it animates, since, as Toscano explains, life ‘cannot organize itself, it can only organize matter’ (Toscano 2006: 36). From the hylomorphic point of view, a self-organising life would be unintelligible, since the forms which organise matter would be indistinguishable from matter itself. Life is thus properly speaking ‘immaterial’ and immortal, the pure formal movement of the concept, while matter is mere lifeless receptivity. Deleuze is critical of this position,¹ and it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Symptoms, Repetition and the Productive Death Instinct</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary clinical procedure as a creative practice works via repetition, but there is always a chance that the procedure will fail and the repetition will remain unproductive. While failure and success are not to be judged from the point of view of conscious intent, as this would imply a transcendent judgment rather than an immanent evaluation, their effects are nevertheless quite real. The prospect of psychological disintegration, manifesting itself in the worst cases in schizophrenic illness, is, in Deleuze’s conception of writing, an ever-present threat. However, the very reality of this threat offers salvation from it. Failure and success</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Identity of the Critical and the Clinical</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a note devoted to the critical and the clinical in<italic>Dialogues</italic>Deleuze writes that ‘<italic>criticism</italic>and<italic>the clinic</italic>ought strictly to be identical’ (D 89). The identity of the critical and the clinical expresses a more general turn in Deleuze’s philosophy towards a pragmatic, diagrammatic or cartographic theory of language which attempts to articulate a relationship between literature and the socio-political critique of power. Pragmatics does not replace but rather subsumes what Deleuze calls the ‘generative’, which we have discussed in terms of the psychosexual genesis of material bodies and immaterial signs, and the ‘transformational’, which we have discussed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The People to Come</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From his early work on Masoch, Deleuze associated health with an engagement with issues of group subjectivity and collective life. The literary clinic grasps the author’s position not as a particular and personal case of a wider social and collective generality, but precisely as a<italic>problematic</italic>intersection of the personal and the collective in which the author can be viewed as a singularity capturing both personal and collective forces at once. If Masoch or Kafka suffered their own conditions at some private or personal level, it was the procedures of their literary activity that allowed a transmutation – what we have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has presented a reconstruction of Deleuze’s critical and clinical project, arguing that this must be grasped as incomplete in terms of Deleuze’s own writings on the subject, but that it appears as a coherent set of concepts when read alongside the rest of his work. As a result, it has been necessary for me to present Deleuze’s literary clinic in terms of the developments informing the early and middle sections of his career, while at the same time insisting that the methodological principles of immanent critique have remained consistent throughout. If literary criticism and questions of health and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgstk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
