<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4zc0g</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BP173.6.R6813 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ummah (Islam)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Lebanon</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sunnites</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Lebanon</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Islam and state</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Lebanon</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Sunni Tragedy in the Middle East</book-title>
         <subtitle>Northern Lebanon from al-Qaeda to ISIS</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rougier</surname>
               <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400873579</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400873576</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pk86v9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Northern Lebanon is a land in turmoil. Long under the sway of the Assad regime in Syria, it is now a magnet for Sunni Muslim jihadists inspired by anti-Western and anti-Shi'a worldviews.<italic>The Sunni Tragedy in the Middle East</italic>describes in harrowing detail the struggle led by an active minority of jihadist militants, some claiming allegiance to ISIS, to seize control of Islam and impose its rule over the region's Sunni Arab population.</p>
         <p>Bernard Rougier introduces us to men with links to the mujahidin in Afghanistan, the Sunni resistance in Iraq, al-Qaeda, and ISIS. He describes how they aspire to replace North Lebanon's Sunni elites, who have been attacked and discredited by neighboring powers and jihadists alike, and explains how they have successfully positioned themselves as the local Sunni population's most credible defender against powerful external enemies-such as Iran and the Shi'a militia group Hezbollah. He sheds new light on the methods and actions of the jihadists, their internal debates, and their evolving political agenda over the past decade.</p>
         <p>This riveting book is based on more than a decade of research, more than one hundred in-depth interviews with players at all levels, and Rougier's extraordinary access to original source material. Written by one of the world's leading experts on jihadism,<italic>The Sunni Tragedy in the Middle East</italic>provides timely insight into the social, political, and religious life of this dangerous and strategically critical region of the Middle East.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book aims to explain how and why jihadism wove its way into a Sunni social fabric in the throes of a leadership crisis. It shows how this new phenomenon is both exploiting and provoking a deep crisis of authority within Sunni Islam. The setting is the predominantly Sunni Muslim city of Tripoli, Lebanon’s second largest city, with a population of 350,000 inhabitants. Yet the story also encompasses other parts of North Lebanon, as well as western Syria, especially since the outbreak of the Syrian crisis in 2011.</p>
                     <p>When Lebanon’s civil war ended in 1990, the country’s north fell under</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>North Lebanon in Bilad al-Sham</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The city of Tripoli began to decline in the mid-nineteenth century.¹ In less than a hundred years, it had become the “always less” city—less economic activity due to the growth of the port of Beirut, less prestige with the loss of its status as an Ottoman provincial capital, and less regional influence following the creation of Greater Lebanon in 1920. With the French mandate, Tripoli experienced the same phenomenon as did<italic>Bilad al-Sham</italic>in general—a weakening of power through territorial amputation and a loss of influence. Its marginalization was complete when its hinterland was appended to Syria and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Defending an Imagined Umma:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Path to Terrorism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout 2002 and 2003, Lebanon experienced a wave of terrorist attacks directed at American fast-food restaurants and a supermarket belonging to a British chain. Six successful bombings occurred in Tripoli and on the coastal road between Beirut and Tripoli. The last attack, carried out on April 5, 2003, was carefully crafted to maximize casualties. Its target was the McDonald’s restaurant at the entrance of the Dora neighborhood, in the eastern suburbs of Beirut, and it was timed for a Saturday afternoon, when the restaurant would be at its busiest. The first charge, planted in the bathroom, was calculated to provoke</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Anti-Syrian Movement:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rebuilding a Political Scene</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Former prime Minister Rafiq al-Hariri’s assassination on February 14, 2005, sparked both international pressure and local pro-sovereignty protests, forcing Syrian troops from Lebanon in April. This series of events profoundly transformed Sunni Islamism in North Lebanon.¹ For the first time, the Future Movement (Rafiq al-Hariri’s political party) could extend its political influence to the north of the country, a move that was not possible under the Syrian occupation. Salafi sheikhs with much to gain from the Syrian forces’ scheduled departure also threw their support behind the Future Movement. They hoped in particular to benefit electorally from public reaction to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Syrian Regime Reacts:</title>
                     <subtitle>Building Up a Jihadi Network</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fatah al-Islam proclaimed its existence from the Palestinian camp of Nahr al-Bared on November 26, 2006. This announcement profoundly changed the political situation that had existed in North Lebanon since the departure of Syrian troops in April 2005. From the beginning, this jihadi group outlined a series of rather grandiose objectives aimed at winning international, Arab, and local Lebanese public opinion over to its cause. It would struggle against the West and its local allies, conduct jihad for the liberation of Palestine, and destroy all those who opposed these glorious purposes. Alongside an intense public relations campaign—featuring press conferences,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Jihad and Resistance in North Lebanon:</title>
                     <subtitle>The History of Fatah al-Islam</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the Lebanese civil war was drawing to a close, various Salafi groups began incorporating the country’s Palestinian camps into their religious networks. That they were so quickly successful bears witness to the failure of the PLO’s political socialization tools within the camp. Several factors explain this dynamic. First, Salafism offered a new intellectual horizon to its partisans, allowing those who had not personally experienced the Palestinian nationalist struggle to look beyond their geographical, legal, and political restrictions as “Palestinian refugees” in Lebanon. Salafism offered a new religious identity and new possibilities for action severed from a Palestinian cause that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The Failure to Create a Lasting Support Base for the Syrian Insurrection</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To pro-independence Sunni elites in Lebanon, the Syrian uprising presented a unique chance to right the unfavorable domestic position in which they had found themselves ever since Hezbollah became the country’s main political and military force in the 1990s. Sa‘ad al-Hariri, whose father was assassinated by Hezbollah’s operational apparatus, would benefit greatly were the Syrian regime to fall. Potentially, it could be his path back into power and a way for Lebanon to ditch the Syrian-Iranian military agenda. In 2011, at the beginning of what was then called the “Syrian revolution,” many in Lebanon and abroad thought the time was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the fall of al-Qusayr in June 2013 and the Syrian regime’s reconquest of Homs, the Syrian region of Qalamoun, to the northeast of the Anti-Lebanon Mountain Range, has taken on strategic importance for belligerents in both camps. For the regime, “pacification” of Qalamoun is a prerequisite to securing the highway between Damascus and Homs and destroying any form of threat coming from Lebanon. Hezbollah also considers that groups active in the region planned the attacks that struck the southern suburb. After losing the battle of al-Qusayr, thousands of Syrian rebels defending Homs withdrew into this mountainous area, seeking to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has examined why it was so difficult to build a Sunni political community in this part of the Middle East. According to John Dewey, building a political community requires setting up mechanisms for deliberation that allow its members to identify collective interests and define a shared response to a number of threats. It cannot emerge without freedom of access to data that directly concerns its political affairs: “inquiry” moves a group from apathy to political action.</p>
                     <p>Syria’s withdrawal from Lebanon following Rafiq al-Hariri’s assassination facilitated the affirmation, within the Sunni milieu, of a political community defined by a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Maps</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86v9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
