<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Poetic Language</book-title>
         <subtitle>Theory and Practice from the Renaissance to the Present</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jones</surname>
               <given-names>Tom</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748656189</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748656189</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Tom Jones</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b4vx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first study of poetic language from a historical and philosophical perspective</p>
         <p>In a series of 12 chapters, exemplary poems - by Walter Ralegh, John Milton,William Cowper, William Wordsworth, Gerard Manley Hopkins, Wallace Stevens, Ezra Pound, Frank O'Hara, Robert Creeley, W. S. Graham, Tom Raworth, Denise Riley and Thomas A. Clark - are read alongside theoretical discussions of poetic language.</p>
         <p>The discussions provide a jargon-free account of a wide range of historical and contemporary schools of thought about poetic language, and an organised, coherent critique of those schools (including analytical philosophy, cognitive poetics, structuralism and post-structuralism). Via close readings of whole poems from 1600 to the present readers are taken through a wide range of modernist, experimental and innovative poetries. Paired chapters within a chronological structure allow lecturers and students to approach the material in a variety of ways (by individual chapters, paired historical periods) that are appropriate to different courses.</p>
         <p>Key Features:</p>
         <p>Surveys a variety of linguistic and philosophical approaches to poetic language: analytical, cognitive, post-structuralist, pragmaticProvides readings of complete poems and places those readings within the wider context of each poet's workCombines theory and practiceIncludes a Glossary of Terms, Biographical Notes on Poets and Suggested Further Reading and Further Reading (by Theoretical School)</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How to Use this Book</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The argument of this book is that poems encourage their readers to experience language as a dual-aspect phenomenon, as something known and understood in two different ways simultaneously. Poems make the language in which they are made appear contingent, and necessary, at once: they make their writers and readers feel a justness or truth in the poem’s language, at the same time as making those writers and readers question just how that part of the poem’s language (a rhyme, an image, the weight on a syllable, and so on) could produce the reactions it produces. The language in poems seems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Figure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Walter Ralegh</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Walter Ralegh’s ‘Farewell to False Love’ is a poem of eighteen lines and around twenty metaphors describing the nature of false love. False love is an ‘oracle of lies’, ‘A way of error, a temple full of treason’, ‘a nest of deep deceit’, ‘A fortress’, ‘A siren song’, ‘A ranging cloud that runs before the wind, / A substance like the shadow of the sun’. The metaphorical elaboration of the nature of false love is, by the end of the poem, reduced to comparisons that are themselves only approximate (like) to ephemeral and insubstantial things (shadows). When Thomas Heneage replies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Selection:</title>
                     <subtitle>William Cowper</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapter suggested that some poetic choices of figure can question the boundary between figurative and literal meaning. This chapter will explore a comparable phenomenon within the vocabulary of poetry more broadly considered. Even when poets are not being metaphorical, they still make choices of vocabulary, they still engage in acts of selection. One of the great pleasures poetry sometimes offers is exhilarating correctness, the use of exactly the right form of words. There are also pleasures, or interesting effects, at least, associated with incorrect or peculiar or unsettling choices of words. This chapter will ask what such effects</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Measure:</title>
                     <subtitle>William Wordsworth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter follows on from the last by offering an account of the differences between Wordsworth and Coleridge’s thinking on poetic diction and measure. Wordsworth’s well-known objections to poetic diction were made just before the death of Cowper, whose work Wordsworth read and admired. Wordsworth understands poetic diction as a strictly delimited and historically sanctioned set of words found frequently in poetry and infrequently in prose, and therefore an artificial deformation of language, like metre and rhyme. Unlike those deformations, however, poetic diction is unpredictable:</p>
                     <p>the distinction [from prose] of rhyme and metre is regular and uniform, and not, like</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Equivalence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gerard Manley Hopkins</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poetry can be a reflection upon what it is to be the kind of being that uses language, a reflection upon how humanity is characterised by being linguistic. This reflection, in the form it takes in several of the poems read in this book, is critical, in as much as it emanates from a crisis, a deeply unnerving realisation about the nature of being a language-using being. This unnerving realisation, I suggest, is the realisation that the language people use, and which can feel to its users so deeply intertwined with the natures of the objects it refers to, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Spirit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wallace Stevens</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most of the ways in which poetic language is said to be poetic that are discussed in this book are more or less superficially or formally evident in the language, either in its metre, syntax, figurative constructions, phonological repetitions or elsewhere. This and the following chapter on Frank O’Hara focus on arguments suggesting that a force behind, and not immediately evident in, language is the source of its poeticalness. Such arguments beg the question: if the spirit (force, charge, drive) that manifests itself in poetic language is a poetic spirit, and is identifiable only in and through that language, can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Spirit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frank O’Hara</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The tradition I sketched in the run-up to my discussion of ‘The Idea of Order at Key West’, that of identifying a spark or charge in poetic language, is sometimes manifested in psychologistic forms in the twentieth century: the energy expressing itself in poetic language is not that of a divine ordering spirit, nor the character of a people, nor a latent ‘chemical’ power in the language itself, but in the psyche of the poet concerned. The surrealist and poet André Breton thought this way. Adopting the language of the poet-critic Pierre Reverdy, who said that one ‘creates … a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Measure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robert Creeley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the twentieth century, American poets, whether ‘formalist’ or ‘experimental’ are found relating poetic measure to the rhythmic structure of life. Howard Nemerov thinks that patterns in verse ‘seem to represent the world itself in its either pious or stupid comings and goings, its regular recurrences and rhythmical repetitions, cosmic in the heavens, terrene in the tides, physiological in the beating of the heart’.¹ And William Carlos Williams urges poets to make experiments that ‘will be directed toward the discovery of a new measure, I repeat, a new measure by which may be ordered our poems as well as our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Deviance:</title>
                     <subtitle>W. S. Graham</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Picking up on the discussion of identity and difference in ‘Measure: William Wordsworth’, this chapter focuses on deviance, a related topic. In order for a phrase to be deviant, it must be different from a more ordinary way of saying something similar or of employing the same construction. A similitude within dissimilitude is required here, as, if one were to see no resemblance between the ordinary and the deviant phrase, they would stand in no relation to each other at all, the one would not be recognised as a deviant form of the other (I shall go on to qualify</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Figure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tom Raworth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Metaphor, as will already be evident from ‘Figure: Walter Ralegh’, has been thought characteristic of poetic language. A recent book on the subject states that ‘metaphor has always been, and still is, the main device of poetry’.¹ Several important accounts of metaphor have been offered from diverse quarters in recent decades, and I want to engage with three of them in this chapter: the cognitive account of metaphor as conceptual mapping; Donald Davidson’s insistence that the meaning of a metaphor is just its literal meaning; Paul de Man’s argument that knowledge about the operations of the mind has the structure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Selection:</title>
                     <subtitle>Denise Riley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My main concerns in this chapter are the restrictions placed upon the selection of words that make up poems, whether these restrictions are more personal or social (if that distinction makes sense), and how selection for poems relates to selectional procedures in language more generally. In relation to this last topic I consider selection in the work of the generative linguist Noam Chomsky. Whilst generative grammar and modern logic understand selection as an operation pertaining to particular terms in an individual’s lexicon, following, or refusing to follow, certain rules, other theorists of literary language have focused on the selection of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Equivalence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thomas A. Clark</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas A. Clark’s<italic>The Path to the Sea</italic>contains several poems, or sequences of poems, most of which were published separately as pamphlets. Clark’s poems reflect on and are also made by perceptions of an environment, one that is given scale and significance by the quotidian yet metaphysically rich act of walking. This interest in walking, in measuring the environment by human and poetic modes of perception, places Clark close to other poets who figure in this book, such as Wordsworth and Creeley. These are long-standing concerns for Clark: earlier sequences such as ‘Through White Villages’ and ‘From Sea to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Deviance: Robert Creeley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early in the introduction to this book I quoted the Czech structuralist Jan Mukařovský’s itemisation of the supposed distinguishing formal features of poetic language, which came to the conclusion that, ‘finally, not even<italic>individuality</italic>, the emphasized uniqueness of linguistic expression, characterizes poetic language in general’.¹ Whilst originality or uniqueness might characterise some instances of poetic language, only function will identify all instances. But some kind of qualification may be made to Mukařovský’s assertion. It might not be the emphasised uniqueness of expression that makes the deployment of (for want of better terminology) a highly conventional phrase poetic, precisely because the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Further Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Poets</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b4vx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
