<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Degrees of Givenness</book-title>
         <subtitle>On Saturation in Jean-Luc Marion</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GSCHWANDTNER</surname>
               <given-names>CHRISTINA M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253014191</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253014283</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025301428X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Christina M. Gschwandtner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz4t7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The philosophical work of Jean-Luc Marion has opened new ways of speaking about religious convictions and experiences. In this exploration of Marion's philosophy and theology, Christina M. Gschwandtner presents a comprehensive and critical analysis of the ideas of saturated phenomena and the phenomenology of givenness. She claims that these phenomena do not always appear in the excessive mode that Marion describes and suggests instead that we consider degrees of saturation. Gschwandtner covers major themes in Marion's work-the historical event, art, nature, love, gift and sacrifice, prayer, and the Eucharist. She works within the phenomenology of givenness, but suggests that Marion himself has not considered important aspects of his philosophy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS OF WORKS BY JEAN-LUC MARION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Givenness, Saturated Phenomena, Negative Certainties, and Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the subtitle of<italic>Being Given</italic>indicates, Marion’s philosophy can be defined as a “phenomenology of givenness.” The term “givenness” featured already in his earlier preparatory work<italic>Reduction and Givenness</italic>where he first developed the notion of a “third reduction” to givenness. “Givenness” translates the French donation, which ostensibly translates the German term<italic>Gegebenheit,</italic>which is an important Husserlian term also used by Heidegger, as Marion contends in a more recent essay on that topic (RoG, 35–49; FP, 45–58). This translation of Gegebenheit with<italic>donation</italic>and givenness is not uncontroversial, and Marion has been challenged on this.¹ The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Historical Events and Historical Research</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marion uses the term “event” in two different but closely connected senses in his work, especially in his presentation in<italic>Being Given.</italic>On the one hand, he speaks of the event as a characteristic of all given phenomena: phenomena give themselves as events, they are “being given.” He develops this in §17 of<italic>Being Given</italic>as the fifth characteristic of<italic>all</italic>phenomena alongside anamorphosis, arrival, incident, and fait accompli. Most prominently, however, the event is<italic>one type</italic>of saturated phenomenon, namely the phenomenon saturated according to quantity. The phenomenon of the historical or cultural event gives “too much” information, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Art and the Artist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marion has written fairly extensively on art, although this topic has not been discussed much in the secondary literature on his work.¹ One of his early works,<italic>The Crossing of the Visible,</italic>is an extended reflection on the status of the image in art and contemporary culture. In his later writings, the work of art occupies a central place as the second type of saturated phenomenon, saturated according to quality. A “mediocre” Dutch painting and the practice of anamorphosis employed in painting is an element of the discussion of the given phenomenon in general in Being Given, and the chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Nature and Flesh</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Instead of examining a phenomenon that Marion already depicts as saturated, this chapter focuses on one he does not discuss. I will suggest that nature and various nonhuman beings can appear to us as saturated phenomena, both on Marion’s own terms and in the sense in which I have argued in respect to the first two types of phenomena examined: as displaying degrees and requiring hermeneutic context. Hence this chapter is not specifically about Marion’s discussion of the third saturated phenomenon, that of the human flesh. Yet, as we see later in this chapter, there might be some connections between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Love and Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The lover “declares his love as one declares war” (EP, 79; PE, 129). So insists Marion repeatedly in his investigation into the nature of the erotic phenomenon. War, of course, is here “only” a metaphor illustrating the absolute commitment of the lover. Yet the fact that this analogy is used several times throughout<italic>The Erotic Phenomenon</italic>seems to indicate that it is not insignificant. Rather, it points to a problematic aspect of Marion’s treatment of eros, namely the extreme—if not almost militant—character of this love. And the careful reader finds the connotations of absoluteness exacerbated by another subtheme,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Gift and Sacrifice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marion is maybe most well-known as a philosopher of the gift. Already in a widely read article, titled “Sketch of a Phenomenological Concept of the Gift,” he attempted to illuminate the topic of the gift.¹ His major phenomenological work,<italic>Being Given,</italic>explores phenomenology as fundamentally about “givenness” and includes an entire section titled “The Gift” (part 2). He engaged in extensive debates with Jacques Derrida on the gift and economy, especially in the highly publicized debate of the 1997 conference “ Religion and Postmodernism I: God, the Gift, and Postmodernism.”² In the English-speaking world, this debate (somewhat unfortunately) dominated the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Prayer and Sainthood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prayer is a fairly prominent topic in Marion’s writings, although it is not a concern addressed much by the secondary literature on his work.¹ Already the early distinction between idol and icon in<italic>God without Being</italic>is to a large extent about prayer or worship, about the human approach to the divine that can be expressed in idolatrous adoration or authentic prayer before an icon. The former is idolatrous for Marion because it becomes an invisible mirror that returns entirely upon the self, while the other is authentic because it is emptied of self and exposed to the divine gaze.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Eucharist and Sacrament</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marion has explored sacraments and especially the Eucharist throughout his work, beginning with his rather controversial treatment in<italic>God without Being</italic>and culminating with two accounts in<italic>Le croire pour le voir.</italic>Why is the Eucharist so important for Marion? On the one hand, it is obviously a central liturgical rite that particularly defines Christian identity. It is therefore especially significant for a phenomenology that seeks to explore religious experience. One might say that the Eucharist is Christian religious experience par excellence. On the other hand, the Eucharist is believed to be a central place of<italic>God’s</italic>self-revelation. The Eucharist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this book I have examined Marion’s proposal of saturated phenomena and argued that Marion focuses too exclusively on their absolute excess and almost complete lack of context. I have suggested, instead, that phenomena are given in degrees of saturation and not only in the two or three degrees Marion indicates, poverty and saturation, but instead in a whole variety and range of degrees. Phenomena are more or less saturated in many different ways, fitting not along a narrow spectrum, but occupying a wide field of diversity of appearance or givenness. Focusing entirely on absolute and total givenness, excessive saturation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz4t7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
