<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Religion: Beyond a Concept</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>de VRIES</surname>
               <given-names>HENT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823227242</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823259984</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5chhf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What do we talk about when we talk about religion? Is it an array of empirical facts about historical human civilizations? Or is religion what is in essence unpredictable-perhaps the very emergence of the new? In what ways are the legacies of religion-its powers, words, things, and gestures-reconfiguring themselves as the elementary forms of life in the twenty-first century?Given the Latin roots of the word religion and its historical Christian uses, what sense, if any, does it make to talk about religionin other traditions? Where might we look for common elements that would enable us to do so? Has religion as an overarching concept lost all its currency, or does it ineluctably return-sometimes in unexpected ways-the moment we attempt to do without it? This book explores the difficulties and double binds that arise when we ask What is religion? Offering a marvelously rich and diverse array of perspectives, it begins the task of rethinking religionand religious studiesin a contemporary world. Opening essays on the question What is religion?are followed by clusters exploring the relationships among religion, theology, and philosophy and the links between religion, politics, and law. Pedagogy is the focus of the following section. Religion is then examined in particular contexts, from classical times to the present Pentacostal revival, leading into an especially rich set of essays on religion, materiality, and mediatization. The final section grapples with the ever-changing forms that religionis taking, such as spirituality movements and responses to the ecological crisis.Featuring the work of leading scholars from a wide array of disciplines, traditions, and cultures, Religion: Beyond a Concept will help set the agenda for religious studies for years to come. It is the first of five volumes in a collection entitled The Future of the Religious Past, the fruit of a major international research initiative funded by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="1000"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Vries</surname>
                           <given-names>Hent</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Still “Religion”?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Vries</surname>
                           <given-names>Hent</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Religion” may—or may not—be here to stay. As a “concept” (but which or whose, exactly?), from one perspective it might seem to be losing its received reference (the transcendent, the world beyond, and the life hereafter) and its shared relevance (a unified view of the cosmos and all beings in it; a doctrine of the origin, purpose, and end of all things; an alert, enlightened, or redeemed sense of self; a practice and way of life), if it has not done so already. Yet from another perspective, it continues to claim a prominent role in attempts to understand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Public Religions Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Casanova</surname>
                           <given-names>José</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has now been over a decade since the publication of<italic>Public Religions in the Modern World</italic>, and it can be asserted with some confidence that the thesis first presented there—that we were witnessing a process of “deprivatization” of religion as a relatively global trend—has been amply confirmed.¹ The most important contribution of the book, in my view, however, was not the relatively prescient empirical observation of such a new global trend but the analytical-theoretical and normative challenge to the liberal theory of privatization, namely, the claim that the thesis of the privatization of religion in the modern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Provincializing God?</title>
                     <subtitle>Provocations from an Anthropology of Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lambek</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My title exhibits great hubris: in the literal sense, first of all; then toward theologians and members of established religions; then also perhaps toward the many nonanthropologists in this interdisciplinary audience. But more immediately, it exhibits hubris toward Dipesh Chakrabarty, the title of whose magnificent work<italic>Provincializing Europe</italic>, I have appropriated and transformed.¹ Here are some of the objects intended by the “provincializing” of my title: first, the conceptualization of God as singular, unitary, and supreme, and, even though we can never know His mystery, as someone on the order of a human person, most likely a senior male, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Translating Gods:</title>
                     <subtitle>Religion as a Factor of Cultural (Un)Translatability</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Assmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Babylonians were the first to equate two gods by defining their common functional definition or cosmic manifestation.¹ We may call this method “theological onomasiology.” By “onomasiology” is meant a method that starts from the referent and asks for the word, in opposition to semasiology, which starts from the word and asks for its meaning. Onomasiology is by definition cross-cultural and interlingual. Its aim is to find out how a given unit of meaning is expressed in different languages.</p>
                     <p>The Babylonians very naturally developed their “theological onomasiology” in the context of their general diglossia. Their constant concern for correlating Sumerian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Christian Invention of Judaism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Theodosian Empire and the Rabbinic Refusal of Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boyarin</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It seems highly significant that there is no word in premodern Jewish parlance that means “Judaism.” When the term<italic>Ioudaismos</italic>appears in non-Christian Jewish writing, to my knowledge only in II Maccabees, it doesn’t mean Judaism, the religion, but the entire complex of loyalties and practices that mark off the people of Israel; after that, it is used as the name of the Jewish religion only by writers who do not identify themselves with and by that name at all, until, it would seem, well into the nineteenth century.¹ It might seem, then, that Judaism has not, until some time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Future of the Religious Past</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Taylor</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I start to write this essay, I have great misgivings. Predicting the future is an extremely foolish enterprise. Historians and social scientists know this well, and refrain from it entirely. And although philosophers haven’t got much of a reputation for accuracy to lose, it still seems somewhat foolhardy.</p>
                     <p>But I still my fears by telling myself that what I’m actually going to do is give an account of the vectors of religious development up to the present (itself a high-risk, accident-prone enterprise), from which some very tentative guesses might be made about their continuation or alteration in the future.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religion as Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reference to Tradition and the Constitution of a Heritage of Belief in Modern Societies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hervieu-Léger</surname>
                           <given-names>Danièle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farhat</surname>
                           <given-names>John A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until the end of the 1960s, the sociology of religion was governed by one principal objective: namely, that of illuminating and analyzing the structural connection between the rise of modernity and the cultural and social repression of religion. The readings of the founding fathers of the discipline, dominant up to that time, furnished the theoretical underpinnings for this program: Marx, Durkheim, and Weber have certainly developed radically different approaches to the structures and functions of society, but each has, in his own way, contributed to establishing that the process of rationalization characterizing the advance of modernity is identical to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>If This Be Magic . . . :</title>
                     <subtitle>Excursions into Contemporary Hindu Lives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Das</surname>
                           <given-names>Veena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his commentaries on a series of papers on “Indian Religion,” the distinguished philosopher of religion and Indologist Alexander Piatigorski theorizes that, despite the widely accepted notion that the emergence of the anthropology of religion as a science was historically connected with a widespread cultural rejection of religious belief, anthropology remains, from the point of view of an external observer, “an epiphenomenon of Christian culture.” This is evident, Piatigorski argues, in the way in which concepts such as “religion,” “magic,” “god,” or “myth” are deployed in scholarly texts. He further claims that, despite the assumption of their universal applicability, all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Metaphysics and Phenomenology:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Relief for Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of God certainly does not begin with metaphysics. But it seems—or at least it managed to appear—that, since metaphysics was coming to an end, being completed, and disappearing, the question of God was also coming to a close. Throughout the past century, everything happened as if the question of God would have to make common cause, whether positively or negatively, with the destiny of metaphysics. Everything also happened as if, in order to keep the question of God open so as to permit a “rational worship” of him (Rom. 12:1), it was absolutely necessary to stick</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What No One Else Can Do in My Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Conversation with Emmanuel Levinas</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Levinas</surname>
                           <given-names>Emmanuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Guwy</surname>
                           <given-names>France</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FRANCE GUWY: Mr. Levinas, to begin with a rather foolish question: Is one born a philosopher, or does one become one?</p>
                     <p>EMMANUEL LEVINAS: Well, you don’t claim the name<italic>philosopher</italic>the way you do a profession. To hear someone say “I’m a philosopher” or “I’m a poet” always shocks me. It’s not my style. In the word<italic>philosophy</italic>there is already the impossibility of possessing wisdom; it already implies taking a step back before the word of the wise man. The philosopher is a person who loves wisdom. It is the beginning of an interest in certain questions, certain books.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abraham, the Other</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Derrida</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anidjar</surname>
                           <given-names>Gil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a citation. “I could think of another Abraham for myself.” One could translate it slightly differently. For the word<italic>think</italic>, one could substitute “imagine” or “conceive”: “Ich könnte mir einen anderen Abraham denken”; “I could, for myself, aside within myself [<italic>à part en moi</italic>], as for myself, imagine, conceive the fiction of another Abraham.”</p>
                     <p>The sentence comes to us from a brief parable, two short pages, by Kafka.¹ It bears as a title only a name: “Abraham,” precisely. “Ich könnte mir einen anderen Abraham denken.” And further: “Aber ein anderer Abraham”; “But yet another Abraham.”</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Perhaps,</italic>perhaps then,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From French Algeria to Jerusalem:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Itinerary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Atlan</surname>
                           <given-names>Henri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I grew up in Algeria before and during the Second World War, at a time when Algeria was part of France. Approximately one million French people had been living there for several generations, next to eight to nine million Arab and Berber people, who were treated as second-class citizens. The fifty to one hundred thousand indigenous Jews were granted French citizenship collectively by a special law at the end of the nineteenth century. Thanks to this law, my father and mother were already born French. This was highly appreciated not only because of the rights granted by French citizenship but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nature as Religious Force in Eriugena and Emerson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Otten</surname>
                           <given-names>Willemien</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From its earliest beginnings, Christianity has had trouble finding a proper role for nature. While the ancient concept of<italic>natura</italic>contained strong overtones of a mythological kind, linking natural generation not only with demiurgic guidance, as in Plato’s<italic>Timaeus</italic>, but also with sexual desire, as in Plato’s<italic>Symposium</italic>, in the later Neoplatonism of Proclus and others such mythological aspects were muted as philosophically stratified forms of organic emanation. The cosmos should above all present traits of rational adornment, it seemed, as the order of nature could only survive by repressing its more animal-like instinctual impulses. On a microcosmic scale, human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Inheriting the Wound:</title>
                     <subtitle>Religion and Philosophy in Stanley Cavell</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Szafraniec</surname>
                           <given-names>Asja</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary philosophy has many times disavowed any relationship with religion, yet it remains strangely committed to a distinctly religious vocabulary. Stanley Cavell’s work bears traces of such problematic engagement with religion, entwined as it is in the vocabulary of faith, sacrifice, redemption, incarnation, conversion, and confession. While Cavell’s engagement with religion is not of a straightforwardly affirmative kind, we can’t call it straightforwardly dismissive, either. Rather, we could perhaps speak about a transformation, a “transfiguration” (to use his own vocabulary) of religion taking place in his work.</p>
                     <p>The question of the function of this commitment is especially urgent, since Cavell,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Deconstruction of Monotheism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nancy</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Luc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Malenfant</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>380</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>TheWest can no longer be called theWest on the basis of the movement through which it saw extended to the entire world the form of what might have appeared, up until recently, as its specific profile. This form contains both techno-science and the general determinations of democracy and law, as well as a certain type of discourse and modes of argument, accompanied by a certain type of representation—understood in a broad sense of the term (e. g., that of the cinema and the entirety of post-rock and post-pop music). In this way, the West no longer acknowledges itself as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>After Theism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adriaanse</surname>
                           <given-names>H. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The conviction underlying the present essay is that theism in its traditional form has lost its credibility. Convictions, it is sometimes argued, are the sort of things you have or you don’t have. I think this is not quite right; reasons can be brought forward even for convictions, though these reasons cannot be considered as the premises from which the conviction necessarily follows as a conclusion. I shall mention three of the reasons for abandoning theism.</p>
                     <p>By theism in its traditional form, I understand something not very different from what R. Swinburne understands by it in his book<italic>The Coherence</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Teaching Religious Facts in Secular Schools</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Debray</surname>
                           <given-names>Régis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ginsburg</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A truly secular school must give each student access to an understanding of the world. For this reason, it has always been possible to speak of religions in the schools of the Republic, insofar as they are facts of civilization. Contrary to a tenacious prejudice, the content of our schools’ curricula attests to this, and has long done so.</p>
                     <p>While respecting<italic>laïcité</italic>, a principle of harmony, teachers give the knowledge of religions its fair place in the teaching of their disciplines. History, philosophy, literature, the plastic arts, music . . . here we can rightfully call upon the humanities.</p>
                     <p>Without</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Secularization:</title>
                     <subtitle>Notes Toward a Genealogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bremmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>432</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his fascinating but not always easy to follow study “What Might an Anthropology of Secularism Look Like?” Talal Asad embarks on an important quest, namely, to determine the nature of the secular. He takes it that the secular is “a concept that brings together certain behaviors, knowledges, and sensibilities in modern life.” Moreover, he stresses that “the secular is neither singular in origin nor stable in its historical identity, although it works through a series of particular oppositions.” In fact, Asad takes the view “that ‘the religious’ and the ‘secular’ are not essentially fixed categories.” He also assumes “that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>An Alternative View of Christianity:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Troeltschean Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Molendijk</surname>
                           <given-names>Arie L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>438</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Despite the efforts of doubters, sceptics and adversaries, the most influential general account of religion in modern Europe, and in the modern world, remains the theory of secularisation.”¹ Notwithstanding its obvious shortcomings, secularization is still the reigning paradigm when the fate of religion in modernity is discussed. This raises the question of why secularization theory is so persistent. The foremost answer is that it is the master narrative by which many of us have learned to perceive religion in the modern world, the paradigm that shapes our view of religion. Moreover, it fits in all too well with the very</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>As Close as a Scholar Can Get:</title>
                     <subtitle>Exploring a One-Field Approach to the Study of Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Droogers</surname>
                           <given-names>André</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>448</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among all the phenomena that scholars study, religion occupies an exceptional position because as a form of knowledge it is commonly presented as the opposite of science. Religion, as we now use the term, is a relatively recent construct, formed explictitly in contrast to science. When in modernity science came into a dominant position, religion was categorized in accordance with its nonscientific nature, given that the transcendental reality to which it refers is not open to empirical verification. That nonempirical reality could not be accepted as a causal factor in explaining religion. As a consequence, theories of religion refer primarily</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Religion” in Public Debates:</title>
                     <subtitle>Who Defines, for What Purposes?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Drees</surname>
                           <given-names>Willem B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>464</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A question central to this volume is “What is religion?” In this essay I want to focus on a related question, namely: “Who is to say what religion is?” That is, who defines what is to be considered as fitting the concept “religion”? I also think it useful to consider a related question: “What purposes are served by using the concept in a particular way?” I’ll discuss this in two steps. The first section will deal with the question “What is religion?” as an academic question. However, I hope to make clear that the academic question, as a quest for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Field of Religion and Ecology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Addressing the Environmental Crisis and Challenging Faiths</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Watling</surname>
                           <given-names>Tony</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>473</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is concerned with “religion and ecology,” or religious environmentalism. It analyzes how religious traditions are used to understand and interact with the environment and environmental issues, suggesting ways of relating to these that are different from and possibly less destructive and ecologically harmful than those of the modern secular worldview. It argues that religious traditions may thereby be gaining new private and public relevance, while perhaps also being changed in the process, becoming more environmentally friendly and ecumenical. The article ethnographically and qualitatively analyzes a “field of religion and ecology” comprising ecologically minded academics and representatives of various</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Politics of Love and Its Enemies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nirenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>491</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Theology and the Political</italic>, the latest volume in Slavoj Žižek’s series SIC, comes with an introduction by the Archbishop of Canterbury, Rowan Williams. Within its brief compass, the archbishop’s introduction outlines two views of meaningful action. The first understands meaningful action as assertion, existing only where “a particular will has imprinted its agenda on the ‘external’ world”; the second insists that “meaningful action is action that is capable of contributing to a system of communication, to symbolic exchange.” The first “pervades so much of modernity and . . . postmodernity,” including “popular liberal and pluralist thought,” and ”raises a a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious Indifference:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Nature of Medieval Christianity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pranger</surname>
                           <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More often than not, we can read as nonreligious written and visual medieval sources that at first sight seem replete with religion, specifi-cally, Christianity. How can this be so? If we want to avoid the anachronistic opposition between religious and nonreligious, we could rephrase this question: Why does the religious element often manifest itself as intrinsically indifferent?¹ Not only does this “indifference” apply to the obvious cases of logic and semantics, and, more generally, to scholastic sources, it also underlies texts that are thoroughly devout. Whether we are dealing with the logics of Abelard, Ockham, or Buridan, or with Thomas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Christ at Large:</title>
                     <subtitle>Iconography and Territoriality in Postwar Ambon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>524</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Picture a situation of blindness, invisibility, and uncertainty, where the sense of unseen and faceless danger prevails, where what was once familiar becomes unfamiliar, where everyday appearances hide unknown horrors. This is one way of describing the recent war in Ambon, the capital of the Moluccas in eastern Indonesia. The Malino Peace Agreement in early 2002, following three years of intermittent violence, left a city divided into “Christian” and “Muslim” territories, with up to ten thousand persons killed and close to seven hundred thousand displaced, equaling one-third of a total Moluccan population of 2.1 million, including those fleeing violence on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Renewing Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Charismatic Renewal in a Conservative Reformed Church</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Versteeg</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>550</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Time is an important structure of social life. As an image of life and its phases of growth and decay, it is associated with qualities such as endurance and transformation. As a social construction, time is a narrative through which events and nonevents are ordered in relation to people. Within society, time sets some crucial standards for living. Both individuals and societies try to reproduce themselves and try to keep themselves healthy, sometimes in conflicting ways. They do not always succeed in these efforts, and they sometimes run out of time.</p>
                     <p>Religions create and inhabit their own time to avoid</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Neutralizing Religion; or, What Is the Opposite of “Faith-based”?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                           <given-names>Winnifred Fallers</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>563</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Center for Studies in Criminal Justice at the University of Chicago Law School held a two-day conference in May 2001 entitled “Faith-Based Initiatives and Urban Policy.”¹ The principal focus of the conference was the then relatively new use of private “faith-based” social service agencies in addressing the needs of the urban poor. Could churches replace or supplement government agencies by delivering social services in a more effective manner? Speakers and participants were largely expert in sociology or criminal justice. None were in religious studies, however loosely defined. From time to time, the question would surface as to exactly what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reflections on Blasphemy and Secular Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Asad</surname>
                           <given-names>Talal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>580</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many years now there has been much talk in Euro-America about the threat to free speech, particularly whenever its Muslims have raised the issue of blasphemy in response to some public criticism of Islam. The most recent crisis was the scandal of the Danish cartoons. A decade and a half after the Rushdie affair, the old religious denunciation of “blasphemy” had reared its head again among Muslims in Europe and beyond, seeking to undermine hard-won freedoms. Or so we were told. There were angry protests and some violence on one side, many affirmations of principle and expressions of contempt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Is Liberalism a Religion?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Warner</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>610</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have no interest in answering the question of my title. For most people the obvious answer would be “no.” For Stanley Fish, among others, the answer is “yes.” Dissatisfied with the terms on both sides, I wish to analyze the question itself and the conditions under which it has come to seem meaningful. The point is not to single out Fish, since his basic claim is one that has wide currency, especially in conservative legal circles and among Christian critics of secular law, from Michael McConell and Stephen Carter to Stanley Hauerwas. Nor is it to defend liberal secularism.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Social Democracy and Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Reverse Beakthrough</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Job</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>618</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Someone who knows the history of this building is likely to think it appropriate that a symposium entitled Religion and Politics is being held here in the Koepelkerk, or “domed church,” also known as the Round Lutheran Church. The original church here on the Singel was built in 1671. Since then it has twice been destroyed by fire. The first Lutheran church was built in 1633 at Singel 411, on the corner with the Spui. Most of that building is now used by the University of Amsterdam.</p>
                     <p>Because that church soon became too small for the growing Lutheran community, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Toward a Politics of Singularity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Protection and Projection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weber</surname>
                           <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>626</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1651: England is in the midst of civil war. Cromwell has defeated the Royalists and is preparing to assume the title “Great Protector.” Thomas Hobbes begins the concluding paragraph of his treatise<italic>Leviathan, of the Matter, Forme, &amp; Power of a Common-Wealth Ecclesiasticall and Civill</italic>with the following resumé of the work:</p>
                     <p>And thus I have brought to an end my Discourse of Civil and Ecclesiastical Government, occasioned by the disorders of the present time, without partiality, without application, and without other design than to set before men’s eyes the mutual relation between<italic>protection and obedience</italic>; of which the condition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Troubles with Materiality:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ghost of Fetishism in the Nineteenth Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Masuzawa</surname>
                           <given-names>Tomoko</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>647</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Upon hearing the standard disciplinary history of the science of religion (<italic>Religionswissenschaft</italic>),¹ one might get the impression that, by the second half of the nineteenth century, talk of fetishism should have been all but dead. By then, “fetishism” as a particular type or form of religious belief and practice was supposedly no longer a viable or respectable category in debating the origin, evolution, or morphology of religion. Thus we read in the Victorian chapter of this history about the rise—and usually also the fall—of various theories concerning the origin of religion, such as Edward B. Tylor’s animism theory,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Salvation by Electricity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stolow</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>668</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether looking at matters of invention and design, of distribution and ownership, or of reception and use, histories of technology are typically framed within one of two metanarratives: the optimistic or the dystopian. In the former, technologies are seen as benign instruments that fulfill the needs, intentions, and desires of their human users. An extreme form of such technophilia can be found in the pages of the American magazine<italic>Wired</italic>and among techno-gurus such as Nicholas Negroponte, who wax poetic about an imminent world populated by therapeutic Barbie dolls, self-cleaning shirts, driverless cars, and a range of devices enabling immediate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cybergnosis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Technology, Religion, and the Secular</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aupers</surname>
                           <given-names>Stef</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Houtman</surname>
                           <given-names>Dick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pels</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>687</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus spoke Timothy Leary, one of the most prominent spokesmen of the spiritual counterculture in the 1960s and 1970s, who converted from “psychedelia” to “cyberdelia” in the 1990s.² Together with computer scientist Eric Gullichsen, Leary considered the emerging realm of cyberspace—first imagined by William Gibson in his 1984<italic>Neuromancer</italic>and popularized by the personal computer and the Internet—an “experience” of a “quantum universe” of digital information. Since the world is held hostage by “white, menopausal men,” the young “cyberpunks,” “electro-shamans,” and “modern alchemists” have a duty to turn this experience into personal transmutation by means of “the ecstasy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious Sensations:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Media, Aesthetics, and Power Matter in the Study of Contemporary Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Birgit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>704</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether we like it or not, religion appears to be of the utmost importance in the early twenty-first century. The idea that the public relevance of religion would decline with modernization and development, yielding a disenchanted world, has been contradicted by actual developments, from the manifestation of so-called political Islam to the rise of Pentecostal-charismatic movements propagating the Gospel of Prosperity, from wars that mobilize religious convictions to acts of terror in the name of God, from contests over blasphemous representations and sacrilege on the part of Muslims and Christians to the deep entanglement of religion and entertainment, from accusations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Can Television Mediate Religious Experience?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Theology of Joan of Arcadia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zito</surname>
                           <given-names>Angela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>724</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>American prime-time television has recently seen a number of programs that deal with spiritual issues from various perspectives.¹ These wildly successful primetime dramas have included the much-older<italic>Highway to Heaven</italic>and its successor<italic>Touched by an Angel</italic>(both featuring angels on earthly missions among ordinary people),<italic>Buffy, the Vampire Slayer</italic>, popular among young people for its heroine who secretly fights against evil spirits, and science-fiction shows like<italic>The X-files</italic>, which had the FBI investigating strange phenomena from alien spaceships to extrasensory perception.² These shows raise interesting questions about “theology and its publics” in the U. S. context. What form does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A “Sense of Possibility”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robert Musil, Meister Eckhart, and the “Culture of Film”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Largier</surname>
                           <given-names>Niklaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>739</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The—at least slightly—enigmatic title of this essay begs for some preliminary explanation. As is well known, Robert Musil plays in the very title of his novel<italic>Der Mann ohne Eigenschaften (The Man Without Qualities</italic>) on an expression coined by the medieval German mystic and philosopher Eckhart von Hochheim. In many of his sermons, Eckhart speaks of man “without qualities [<italic>âne eigenschaften</italic>],”¹ thus fashioning a term and a concept for a religious ideal that embodies specific aspects of detachment, freedom, and salvation. Musil’s references to Eckhart in his great, unfinished novel do not end with the allusion in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Intimate Exteriorities:</title>
                     <subtitle>Inventing Religion Through Music</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Maas</surname>
                           <given-names>Sander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>750</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is not a rare phenomenon today to find a concert hall—that bourgeois temple of the cult of Art—filled with religious music. This may not seem surprising, since soon after its invention in the eighteenth century the concert hall became a location for the performance of religious repertoires. The times have changed, however, and the position of religion today can hardly be compared with the one it occupied centuries ago. The presence of religion in classical music performances today is mostly historical in character, such as, for instance, when Handel’s oratorios are played, or Mozart’s<italic>Requiem</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Much less</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Death in the Image:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Post-Religious Life of Christian Images</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alexandrova</surname>
                           <given-names>Alena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>772</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A number of group and solo exhibitions offer evidence that both curators and visual artists are increasingly interested in the controversial issue of religion and its role in the contemporary art scene.¹ Artworks that deal with or refer to religious themes and motifs constitute a very heterogeneous group. They have in common the fact that they do not function in religious contexts and cannot be described as “religious art.” Instead, these artworks are<italic>about</italic>religion and its practices, concepts, ideas, and images in the sense that they thematize its continued cultural relevance. Curators and artists interested in religious themes are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Spirituality in Modern Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van der Veer</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>789</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In December 1911, Wassily Kandinsky published his<italic>Über das Geistige in der Kunst (Concerning the Spiritual in Art</italic>). The book’s main purpose was to arouse a capacity to experience the spiritual in material and abstract things, for Kandinsky believed this capacity enables experiences that in the future would be absolutely necessary and unending. Kandinsky emphasizes that he is not creating a rational theory, but that as an artist he is interested in experiences that are partially unconscious. One of the formative experiences he describes in his book<italic>Rückblicke (Glances Back</italic>) is his encounter at a French exhibition with Monet’s<italic>Haystack</italic>:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Sacralization of the Self:</title>
                     <subtitle>Relocating the Sacred on the Ruins of Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aupers</surname>
                           <given-names>Stef</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Houtman</surname>
                           <given-names>Dick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>798</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no doubt that the new buzzword in the contemporary religious landscape is “spirituality.” Indeed, entering “spiritual or spirituality” in the Internet search engine Google produces no fewer than 84 million hits—more than “catholic or catholicism” (73 million), much more than “protestant or protestantism” (16 million), and not many fewer than “islam or islamic or muslim” (121 million). Those 84 million hits even exceed the numbers found for “porno or porn” (31 million) and do not fall far short of those for popular search terms such as “soccer” (109 million), “sex” (189 million), and “football” (221 million).</p>
                     <p>What</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Horizontal Transcendence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Irigaray’s Religion after Ontotheology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Halsema</surname>
                           <given-names>Annemie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>813</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“No tradition can claim to possess the religious truth of humanity,” writes Luce Irigaray in<italic>Key Writings</italic>.¹ In the Christian tradition, God too often is perceived as a fixed entity that is absolutely transcendent. Instead, we need a God who would be an inspiration to develop ourselves fully and to live fully our relation to the other, to others, and to the world around us. Even though Irigaray is critical of the Western religious tradition,² in her recent work she more and more understands religion as an indispensable and valuable dimension of human life.</p>
                     <p>Irigaray does not stand alone in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religion and the Time of Creation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Placing “the Human” in Techno-scientific and Theological Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carlson</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>826</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of “religion” today often seems most urgent wherever the “human” in its “life” or “nature” appears to grow unstable conceptually and/or to fall under threat existentially. Such instability and threat come into play very notably in the context of recent scientific and technological developments where any number of categories long operative in conceptions of the human—intelligence and agency, birth and death, natural life, and so on—prove increasingly difficult to delimit because open to various forms of manipulation, simulation, or transformation. In reading the daily newspaper in the United States, for example, one quickly gets the sense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>843</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chhf.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>999</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
