<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ffjp1x</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD450.P47238 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Philosophy and Anthropology</book-title>
         <subtitle>Border Crossing and Transformations</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Giri</surname>
               <given-names>Ananta Kumar</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Clammer</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780857285126</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780857280817</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Anthem Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LONDON; NEW YORK; DELHI</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ananta Kumar Giri</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>John Clammer</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gxpchs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Philosophy and Anthropology: Border Crossings and Transformations is an innovative and original collection of essays exploring the relationships between philosophy and anthropology – historically and presently – and the theoretical and practical issues concerning their dialogue.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="380"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>PHILOSOPHY AND ANTHROPOLOGY IN DIALOGUES AND CONVERSATIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clammer</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giri</surname>
                           <given-names>Ananta Kumar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy and anthropology have long been intellectual companions. In European continental philosophy in particular, the boundaries between the two disciplines have always been very porous. One thinks at once of the largely German project to construct a philosophy of man and of human’s place in nature (a project broadly known as philosophical anthropology), the constant border crossings between anthropology and philosophy of notable individuals such as Paul Cassirer and Martin Heidegger, and the importation into British analytical philosophy by way of Ludwig Wittgenstein of concerns that can only be called anthropological. Although from the other side of the disciplinary boundary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>THE PROJECT OF PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clammer</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The notion of a philosophical anthropology has almost entirely dropped out of contemporary intellectual discourse, both in philosophy and in anthropology. Among the few places where it is alive as an active concept or form of intellectual inquiry is in Christian (mainly Roman Catholic) theology. There are reasons for this absence, which we will shortly elaborate on, but the virtual disappearance of the idea of a philosophical anthropology is an unfortunate one, as it is potentially a notion that can not only provide a bridge between anthropology and philosophy – linked as we shall see by many common concerns – but also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>THE SELF-PRESERVATION OF MAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>REMARKS ON THE RELATION BETWEEN MODERNITY AND PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lysemose</surname>
                           <given-names>Kasper</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It would probably be too bold a statement to say that philosophical anthropology is the philosophy of modernity. There is, however, an important and close relation between the two. It is the aim of this article to draw attention to this relation.² This will be done by examining the following hypothesis: the tertium<italic>comparationis</italic>between philosophical anthropology and modernity is to be found in the principle of self-preservation.</p>
                     <p>The idea that philosophical anthropology is a movement with a particular close connection to modernity is not new. It has been stressed by the German philosopher Odo Marquard in his<italic>Schwierigkeiten mit</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>WHITHER MODERNITY?</title>
                     <subtitle>HYBRIDIZATION, POSTOCCIDENTALISM, POSTDEVELOPMENT AND TRANSMODERNITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marquez</surname>
                           <given-names>Ivan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Western philosophy has had a long engagement with the philosophicalanthropological issue of the nature of and prospects for humanity. Aristotle, for instance, placed humans within a functional, organic, cosmic totality, where the part–whole relation between humans and the rest of nature ascribed the<italic>telos</italic>and proper flourishing of humans. Many seventeenth-century philosophers – rationalists like Descartes, materialists like Hobbes and empiricists like Locke – defined humans as rational, self-interested and atomistic. With eighteenthcentury French Enlightenment thought – especially the idea of progress in the work of de Saint-Pierre, Turgot, Voltaire, d’Holbach, Helvetius and Condorcet – and nineteenth-century German idealism, especially Hegel, human nature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY AND PHILOSOPHY IN ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brezina</surname>
                           <given-names>Vaclav</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who are we as human beings? In what sense are we part of nature (like plants and animals) and in what sense are we different? What is our place in the world? Is there a common meaning to life or is there a series of culturally based meanings? Is there such a thing as meaning of life?</p>
                     <p>It is probably fair to say that some of the most exciting (as well as challenging) questions are those directly related to the human condition (see the examples above). In today’s globalized and warming world, in which an unprecedented opportunity to come together</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>THE ENGAGEMENT OF PHILOSOPHY AND ANTHROPOLOGY IN THE INTERPRETIVE TURN AND BEYOND:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARDS AN ANTHROPOLOGY OF THE CONTEMPORARY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kämpf</surname>
                           <given-names>Heike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most interesting and fruitful anthropological discussions of philosophy occurred within the so-called ‘interpretive turn’ in anthropology. This turn was inspired by philosophy and initiated a reconsideration of philosophical concepts. In particular, the reconsideration of the hermeneutic notion of ‘ understanding’ led to new anthropological readings of the works of Martin Heidegger, Hans-Georg Gadamer and Paul Ricoeur. At the same time this anthropological discussion had its impact on philosophy. On the one hand, hermeneutic and analytic philosophy came closer together while questioning the possibilities of understanding alien cultures: Peter Winch and Richard Rorty dealt with the problem of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>MEDIATION THROUGH COGNITIVE DYNAMICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY AND THE CONFLICTS OF OUR TIME</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strydom</surname>
                           <given-names>Piet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the light of a heightened sense of contingency and vulnerability, a pronounced uncertainty has set in since the late twentieth century about human nature and, hence, the image of the human being. This has been fuelled further by the recognition of the inherent ambiguity of these concepts. Awareness of the precariousness of our assumptions about what human beings are like has not only affected intellectuals, prompting philosophers and social scientists to embark on a searching interrogation, but has also penetrated into the policymaking and the public domain. While philosophers and social scientists may still be able, during the process</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>PHILOSOPHY AS ANTHROPOCENTRISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>LANGUAGE, LIFE AND APORIA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Biswas</surname>
                           <given-names>Prasenjit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Cartesian-Kantian anthropomorphic subject represents a state of continual immanence in terms of its indefinite and infinite possibilities. The linguistic turn takes an anthropocentric form that has been embedded in the Cartesian-Kantian metaphysics of presence. Wittgenstein, especially, takes language as an enactable rule-governed activity, thereby making it immanent to the ‘lived experiences’ of the users of language. Heidegger introduces a comprehensive embeddedness of being in language and viceversa, thereby assigning it a hermeneutical closure. In such anthropomorphic and anthropocentric moves, what is lost is the very ground of reality on which language must act. A project of recovery of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>KANT AND ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giri</surname>
                           <given-names>Ananta Kumar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we explore the challenge of rethinking modernist knowledge by looking at Kant’s conception of anthropology. Kant taught courses in both anthropology and physical geography, and his book<italic>Anthropology from a Pragmatic Point of View</italic>(1798) was published nearly thirty years after his initial engagement with anthropology. While his lectures embodied his crisis of identity as a professional philosopher, thus facilitating a border crossing between philosophy and anthropology,<italic>Anthropology from a Pragmatic Point of View</italic>was far short of his earlier critique of metaphysics. Kant wanted anthropology to play by universal principles, if not be totally subordinate to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>DILTHEY’S THEORY OF KNOWLEDGE AND ITS POTENTIAL FOR ANTHROPOLOGICAL THEORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Šuber</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With some considerable delay, the German philosopher Wilhelm Dilthey (1833–1911) was, in 1986, declared the ‘new anthropological ancestor’ (Bruner 1986, 4). Although he had been acknowledged as having exerted some influence on major figures of anthropology, like Boas and Benedict well before, the recent turn to Dilthey was meant to go far beyond the historical concern. This move contrasts sharply with the result of an examination of the indexes of relevant textbooks on basic anthropological theory, where Dilthey’s name hardly ever appears. What then are the common points of contact between late twentieth-century anthropology and turn-of-the-century German philosophy? In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>MALINOWSKI AND PHILOSOPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Skalník</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bronislaw Malinowski, the founder of modern social anthropology, was a philosopher by way of his tertiary education at Jagiellonian University in Kraków. He was influenced by Friedrich Nietzsche on the one hand and Ernst Mach on the other. At the height of his brilliant career, he enjoyed a lengthy exchange of views with Bertrand Russell. This chapter will explore the place of philosophy in his innovative contribution, with special emphasis on the relationship between philosophy on the one hand and science, religion, culture, civilization, war and state on the other. The tension between Malinowski’s emphasis on empirical research and his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>GROUND, SELF, SIGN:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SEMIOTIC THEORIES OF CHARLES SANDERS PEIRCE AND THEIR APPLICATIONS IN SOCIAL ANTHROPOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kjaerholm</surname>
                           <given-names>Lars</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Far more than a theory of signs, Peirce’s semiotics is also an attempt to summarize ontology as seen in his time and in the Kantian tradition in which he is situated. The concepts of<italic>firstness, secondness</italic>and<italic>thirdness</italic>sum up the forms and conditions under which anything can exist, within the framework of the ontological tradition that Peirce belonged to. Peirce has various ways of defining Firstness. It is ‘what the world was to Adam on the day he opened his eyes, before he had even drawn distinctions, or had become conscious of his own existence’ (1.357). This makes Peirce’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>RICOEUR’S CHALLENGE FOR A TWENTY-FIRST CENTURY ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Taylor</surname>
                           <given-names>Betsy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ricoeur ends his last major book with the above poem (Ricoeur [2000] 2004, 506). This poem is a dance of paradoxes, vividly conjuring up its author and his long life of philosophical labours – a life remarkable for both generous openness and tenacious continuity. In his distinctive mix of solemnity and playfulness, Ricoeur sets up a game of hide and seek in this poem – between text, author and reader, between life and death, between embodiment and disembodiment.</p>
                     <p>The overt paradoxes in this poem concatenate with silent allusions to the aporias central to earlier works. On the one hand, the poem evokes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 13</label>
                     <title>CLIFFORD GEERTZ:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE PHILOSOPHICAL TRANSFORMATION OF ANTHROPOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Saalmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Gernot</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Clifford Geertz (1926–2006) was one of the main figures to build a new kind of anthropology, beginning in the 1960s. In doing so, he borrowed many ideas from philosophy. Although some of his works have been read by philosophers too, the influence of his anthropology on philosophy is negligible. The reception of his thoughts does not conform to the generally accepted significance of his writings, appropriate to their philosophical content. Most often, Geertz is read only superficially and the reading is confined to his two most famous texts – ‘Thick Description’ (1973) and ‘Deep Play: Notes on Balinese Cockfight’ (1972).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 14</label>
                     <title>BAKHTIN’S HERITAGE IN ANTHROPOLOGY:</title>
                     <subtitle>ALTERITY AND DIALOGUE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brocki</surname>
                           <given-names>Marcin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For over thirty years, the development of theory in anthropology has been under heavy influence from literary theory, serving mostly as an inspiration in solving certain problems in the research practice of ethnography. This influence first started with the assimilation of structuralism and semiotics into anthropology, with their concept of culture as a collection of texts interacting with one another. The real interdisciplinary dialogue, however, originated with the discovery, received in the field of ethnography with much suspicion and astonishment, that the practice of anthropology is not only collecting and analysing data, but also ‘producing texts’, and that the textualization</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 15</label>
                     <title>THE PHILOSOPHY OF SLAVOJ ŽIŽEK AND ANTHROPOLOGY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CURRENT SITUATION AND POSSIBLE FUTURES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kjaerholm</surname>
                           <given-names>Lars</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Slovenian philosopher Slavoj Žižek has opened up a discussion of the subject and the self and ideology, which is of great interest to anthropology. In the words of Fabio Vighi and Heiko Feldner, Žižek’s concept of ideology distances itself from all former definitions because:</p>
                     <p>[…] instead of ideology falsifying reality for the sake of pathological interests (power strategies), we start from the assumption that there is no way to access and conceptualize reality which has not already been stained by discourse. The term ideology thus becomes redundant, Žižek argues, for what counts in critical analysis is that every ideological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 16</label>
                     <title>BORDER CROSSINGS BETWEEN ANTHROPOLOGY AND BUDDHIST PHILOSOPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goonatilake</surname>
                           <given-names>Susantha</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter attempts to locate anthropology historically as to its epistemological roots, its critique that occurred after decolonization and its future, as once again the centre of gravity of the world’s economic axis shifts to Asia. The position taken in this chapter is that of standpoint theory, namely that all theoretical as well as empirical statements are bound within a social framework and perspective.</p>
                     <p>Hitherto, in the discussions on the social construction of knowledge, the canvas had either been the small groups within which knowledge is created (for example, in the case of natural sciences in the laboratory, or in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 17</label>
                     <title>‘ANTHROPOLOGY OF PHILOSOPHY’ IN AFRICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE ETHNOGRAPHY OF CRITICAL DISCOURSE AND INTELLECTUAL PRACTICE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kresse</surname>
                           <given-names>Kai</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An anthropological investigation into philosophy can provide us with insights and information about traditions of knowledge and intellectual practice elsewhere in the world, in social contexts very different from our own. The project needs to engage with – and first of all be able to identify – philosophy as part of social discourse, and as a social practice, within any given region. Here, I am carving out one particular approach about how this could work, in relation to the Swahili context and against the background of discussions in African philosophy. Philosophy, as socialized discourse and practice, overlaps with other (more established) areas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 18</label>
                     <title>ALBINOS DO NOT DIE:</title>
                     <subtitle>BELIEF, PHILOSOPHY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Pina-Cabral</surname>
                           <given-names>João</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Mozambique one is often told things about albinos that can hardly be interpreted at face value.¹ These are not, properly speaking, fictionalized narratives of a connected series of events, but rather they are evidence of propositional attitudes pertaining to refer to statements of fact, that is, they are ‘beliefs’. Although they are not told to you as ‘lies’, the fact is that the people who narrate them are often uncertain as to whether they are true. Upon hearing them, I was immediately challenged by the following question: if these beliefs do not meet up with the test of disbelief,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 19</label>
                     <title>ANTHROPOLOGY, DEVELOPMENT AND THE MYTH OF CULTURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Feleppa</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropologists have become increasingly involved as participants on development teams, but their great potential to promote sustainable development is hindered by vestiges of one of cultural anthropology’s founding myths. It is the notion of cultures construed as self-contained symbol systems, conceptually opaque to all but true insiders, with an implied notion of correct translation, which makes it an ‘all or nothing’ matter. This notion is also linked to long-standing concerns in the field with moral relativism, value neutrality and colonialism. As a result, within the community of anthropologists working in development, two somewhat opposed positions have arisen: one holds that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 20</label>
                     <title>NOTIONS OF FRIENDSHIP IN PHILOSOPHICAL AND ANTHROPOLOGICAL THOUGHT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Friese</surname>
                           <given-names>Heidrun</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the Western philosophical tradition, the notion of friendship indicates relations to the<italic>self</italic>, an<italic>other</italic>and the political<italic>community</italic>. It is a practice constituting subjectivity, personal, partial and particularistic bonds, and at the same time it articulates specific moral/ethical expectations of behaviour and universalistic demands.¹ Friendship fosters goodness, reciprocity and generosity, entails mutual trust, solidarity and cooperation. Thus, it creates both social ties and is related to the political order of a community, its ethical prerequisites and the ways in which common matters are negotiated.</p>
                     <p>Given that friendship cross-cuts what is considered as making up the Western subject and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpchs.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                     <subtitle>THE RETURN OF PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dallmayr</surname>
                           <given-names>Fred</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As is well known, and as the editors emphasize, the topic of philosophical anthropology has fallen on hard times in recent decades, to the point that it virtually ceased to occupy the attention of both philosophers and professional anthropologists. This neglect stands in stark contrast to the situation prevailing in Europe in the early and middle part of the last century, which can be described as the heyday of philosophical anthropology.¹ The basic aim of the present volume is to rescue the topic from oblivion, and more specifically to recover the older European legacy while transforming it in the light</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
