<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Beyond Old and New Perspectives on Paul</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reflections on the Work of Douglas Campbell</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tilling</surname>
               <given-names>Chris</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Adams</surname>
               <given-names>Edward</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174630</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902738</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Chris Tilling</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf6fp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In his work 'Deliverance of God' Douglas Campbell presents what Chris Tilling considers a "complete rereading of Paul’s letters that genuinely offers a way beyond problems associated with old and new perspectives. And his resultant picture of Paul’s theology generally, and the Apostle’s soteriology particularly, is beautiful, liberating, consistent, exegetically rigorous, theologically aware and pastorally compelling. It captures, I think, the best of the old perspective, with its concern to speak energetically about the God who saves, and it takes seriously the concerns of the new perspective on Second Temple Judaism. But in remarkable and jarringly elegant ways, it moves beyond them both." This collection of essays is divided into two sections. Part One analyses key aspects of Campbell’s account of the problem confronting readers of Paul. Part Two analyses key aspects of Campbell’s proposed solution to to the current confused state of Pauline interpretation. This book is essential reading for anyone involved in the study of Paul.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="334"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adams</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In december 2011, at King’s College London, was convened a conference critically engaging with Douglas Campbell’s monumental<italic>The Deliverance of God</italic>. a follow-up conference was held in November 2012 at duke divinity school. The present volume arises from papers presented at these gatherings. It is appropriate that the first conference took place at King’s, where Douglas’s work on the project that would lead to Deliverance began in earnest. I was a colleague of his during his time at King’s and witnessed first hand the early birth pangs of the project. It was a great delight to welcome my old friend</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tilling</surname>
                           <given-names>Chris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“<italic>Beyond</italic>old and new perspectives on Paul!” bemused students exclaim. “We are still trying to get our heads around the old and new ones! now there is a<italic>newer</italic>one?” and then there are those students who know a bit more about phrases such as “old perspective” and “new perspective,”¹ and this elite group often already have a personal investment in one or the other. With narrowed eyes, they continue: “so, you’re saying that both the reformation and the new Perspective on Paul have it wrong? And you think you have it right?!”</p>
                     <p>Depending on how early in the day</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Review of Douglas Campbell’s The Deliverance of God from a Theological Perspective</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Torrance</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have been invited to assess Douglas Campbell’s door-stopper of a tome from a theological perspective. Given that this is a work in Pauline scholarship by a leading New Testament scholar, what is the justification for involving a theologian? Clearly, it is because the argumentation of this book is driven by a theological critique of certain key methodological, epistemological, and indeed, ontological suppositions that have functioned to sustain what Campbell calls “justification discourse”—an approach to Pauline interpretation that Campbell argues is outmoded, confused, and ultimately incoherent.</p>
                     <p>So, very briefly, what are the core concerns of this book? The first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Luther and the Deliverance of god</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tomlin</surname>
                           <given-names>Graham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Doug Campbell’s book<italic>The Deliverance of God</italic>promises to be a milestone in Pauline exegesis and interpretation. The conference from which the papers in this book emerged was a lively, fast-moving, and valuable opportunity to scrutinize, examine, and question it from a range of perspectives. The particular aspect this chapter brings to bear is that of historical theology, particularly from the reformation period. as primarily a student of the reformation, i do not consider myself qualified to comment on the exegetical case campbell makes in drawing such a sharp contrast between Paul’s apparent teaching in the early chapters of romans,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Current Crisis:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Capture of Paul’s Gospel by Methodological Arianism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Campbell</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does all that has been said in this volume so far have to do with the reading of Paul and of Romans, most especially of Romans 1–3, and with my arguments in<italic>Deliverance</italic>? Much in every way.</p>
                     <p>It is my contention that Paul, rightly understood, is a clear-sighted and courageous advocate of a revelational gospel—of Athanasianism, so to speak. His advocates in these terms within specialized Pauline circles often denote their approach “apocalyptic” (from the Greek for “revelation”).² But it is also my contention that large parts of Paul’s theological description have been captured by arianism, not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Campbell’s Apocalyptic Gospel and Pauline Athanasianism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tilling</surname>
                           <given-names>Chris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Deliverance of God</italic>Douglas campbell seeks to provide a vision of a revelatory, transformational, unconditional, and liberational Pauline theology, one that, he maintains, stands in stark contrast to readings of Paul influenced by contractual foundationalism.¹ in response to the reviews by me and Michael Gorman,² campbell elucidates his understanding of the contrast involved by speaking of it in terms of the debate between Athanasianism and Arianism. The foundationalist reading is Arian in its basic theological dynamics, and cannot stand together with but is necessarily antagonistic towards Paul’s essentially athanasian gospel. in this chapter i will explore the basic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Arian” Foundationalism or “Athanasian” Apocalypticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Patristic Assessment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Warren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I am in the company of New Testament colleagues they ask what I, as a patrologist, think of Douglas Campbell’s invocation of Athanasius and Arius to characterize the difference between his and previous readings of Romans. In their voice I detect a hint of skepticism. After all, they think of “Athanasian” and “Arian” as theological categories—markers for competing views of the trinity or Christology. What do Arius and Athanasius have to do with issues of theological method or participatory Soteriology that are at the heart of Campbell’s assessment of Romans? This skepticism is understandable given the way the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Connecting the Dots:</title>
                     <subtitle>One Problem, One Text, and the Way Ahead</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Campbell</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The journey to a solution from the problems I outlined in chapter 3 can begin usefully by considering just one concern— Judaism—in relation to a limited text—Galatians 2:15–16.² This consideration can illustrate both why the presence of a fundamentally Arian type of western contractualism in Paul is so problematic, however unnoticed, and what the basic strategy for resolving it is that<italic>Deliverance</italic>is proposing. In what follows, largely for the sake of convenience, I will call the problematic approach “forwardness.”³ in Galatians 2:15–16 Paul states, Ἡμεῖς φύσει Ἰουδαῖοι καὶ οὐκ ἐξ ἐθνῶν ἁμαρτωλοί· [16] εἰδότες δὲ</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A Response to Campbell’s “Connecting the Dots”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hilborn</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Douglas Campbell has produced an ambitious interdisciplinary<italic>tour de force in The Deliverance of God.</italic>Those who, like me, are not new testament specialists but who seek to ensure that their work in other theological fields is informed by contemporary biblical scholarship, will surely appreciate its rich synthesis of systematics, ethics, social theology, and church history with biblical exegesis and hermeneutics.</p>
                     <p>In relation to Campbell’s second paper, chapter 6, I have a number of points to raise—most of them for clarification, but all, I hope, in a spirit of general admiration for what I am sure will be seen</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Legal Mind of American Christianity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bowler</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>American Christians, contrary to popular opinion, have a soft spot for lawyers. When Charles Finney, the leading revivalist of the second Great awakening, described his career change from the law to the gospel as his “retainer from the Lord Jesus Christ to plead his cause” before God, the greater Judge, the crowd must have cooed.¹ Because what they loved about Finney they hated about another of God’s lawyers, John Calvin, who would not have understood what Americans loved about themselves. Their reasonableness. Their self-confidence. Their ability to see a good bargain when they saw it, and what Jesus—through Finney</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Rereading Romans 1–31</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Campbell</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We will begin, in this chapter, by seizing the bull by the horns on the assumptions that we are dealing with a bull and that chapters 1 through 3 of Romans are its horns. These badly need to be blunted by being construed differently or reread.²</p>
                     <p>Despite what some have said, Romans 1–3 is generally read prospectively or forward, setting up a tacitly Arian or foundationalist variant within Paul’s theology more broadly in the form of Western Contractualism, so we need to engage with this text carefully if we are ever to rid Paul of this problem. without a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Beyond Reasonable Hope of Recognition?</title>
                     <subtitle>Prosōpopoeia in Romans 1:18—3:8</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffith-Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By June 1845 Dr. Wiseman was anxious to know whether John Henry Newman would really convert to Rome. Wiseman sent Father Smith, a former pupil of Newman’s who had converted, to Littlemore, “under cover of a simple visit of friendship,” to discover how the land lay. In a cool conversation that never reached matters of substance, Father smith found no clues. So the afternoon ended. But when they re-assembled for dinner, smith noticed that Newman had changed his trousers. It was all that smith needed. He returned post-haste to wiseman. He reported that all was well: Newman clearly no longer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Rereading Romans 1–3 Apocalyptically:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response to Douglas Campbell’s “Rereading Romans 1–3”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>Brittany E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my response to Douglas Campbell’s essay “Rereading Romans 1–3,” I want to begin by way of disclaimer. Overall, I am very sympathetic to Campbell’s reading of Paul. Like Campbell, I read Paul apocalyptically, and I agree that Romans 5–8 lies at the heart of Paul’s apocalyptic soteriology.² Moreover, I also reject what Campbell calls a “prospective” reading of Paul, or what he elsewhere terms “Arianism,” foundationalism, contractualism, and justification discourse. Such readings lead, inter alia, to an individualistic view of salvation in which the gospel is not freely given, but necessitated because of human sinfulness. I applaud</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Rereading Paul’s ΔIKAIO-Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Campbell</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We considered in chapter 9 one way that a destructive foundationalism can be unleashed into our broader accounts of Paul’s thinking about salvation—through a forward construal of the argument in Romans 1–3. This construal will release foundationalism in its own right, in the specific form of course of Western contractualism, although it may form an alliance with a more general commitment on the part of Paul’s interpreter to a fundamentally rationalistic and moralistic, and invariably quite individualizing, anthropology—a conception of the human person that primarily governs itself, which is deeply congenial to modern thought and culture (repeated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Reading Paul’s ΔIKAIO-Language.</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response to Douglas Campbell’s “Rereading Paul’s ΔIKAIO-Language”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hafemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Scott</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theologically, we ought to agree with Campbell’s concern to combat all “Western contractualism,” which is so “congenial to modern thought and culture.”¹ Contrary to Paul’s perspective, such a worldview entails “a fundamentally rationalistic and moralistic, and invariably quite individualizing, anthropology” based on “a conception of the human person that primarily governs itself.”² Campbell is right to reject any anthropology in which “an essentially autonomous individual sets off on a quest for salvation driven and governed by her own conceptions.”³</p>
                     <p>Campbell’s own resistance to such a construct is based on his conviction that this “western contractualism” can be countered once we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Campbell’s Faith:</title>
                     <subtitle>Advancing the Pistis Christou Debate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tilling</surname>
                           <given-names>Chris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Campbell’s work on Paul’s πίστις/πιστεύω language represents some of the most exegetically innovative and insightful work in<italic>Deliverance</italic>. Yet it is also the case that his arguments have not always been understood by his reviewers, and his key exegetical moves have largely been ignored. We will now survey some of his central arguments before briefly considering some potential objections.</p>
                     <p>I have regularly lamented the fact that the hardback version of<italic>Deliverance</italic>was published using endnotes (rather than footnotes), and this has no doubt meant that even those who have read the whole book may not have mustered the willpower to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>The Faith of Jesus Christ:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Evangelical Conundrum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Freeman</surname>
                           <given-names>Curtis W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I was sitting in a Greek exegesis course my sophomore year in college when we came to the construction ἐν πίστει ζῶ τῇ τοῦ υἱοῦ τοῦ θεοῦ (Gal 2: 20). Our professor, Dr. Richard Cutter (of blessed memory), asked me how the genitive should be translated: “was the apostle Paul saying he lived by faith<italic>in</italic>the Son of God (an objective genitive) or the faith<italic>of</italic>the Son of God (a subjective genitive)?” When I answered that it could be translated either way, he pressed me to say Which one I thought was the best translation. A long and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix A:</title>
                     <subtitle>Covenant or Contract? A Study of the Theological Background of Worship in Seventeenth-Century Scotland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Torrance</surname>
                           <given-names>James B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix B:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Contribution of Mcleod Campbell to Scottish Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Torrance</surname>
                           <given-names>James B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6fp.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
