<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GT525.E93 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Clothing and dress</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fashion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Gender identity</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Group identity</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Business</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Exchanging Clothes</book-title>
         <subtitle>Habits of Being II</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GIORCELLI</surname>
               <given-names>CRISTINA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RABINOWITZ</surname>
               <given-names>PAULA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780816678075</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780816680306</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0816680302</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1b7x5h7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Clothing may not make the man (or woman), but it helps. How clothing as a vestige and artifact and as transmitter of identity moves from one use to another, from one fantasy to another fad, from one literary source to another visual one: these are the concerns of the essays in this volume.</p>
         <p>The second in a four-part series charting the social, cultural, and political expression of clothing, dress, and accessories,<italic>Exchanging Clothes</italic>focuses on the concept of transnational "circulation and exchange"-not only the global exchange of material commodities across time and space but also of the ideas, images, colors, and textures related to fashion. Essays examine the parade of heroes past, from Homer and Virgil to Dante and Ariosto, wearing armor or nothing; the social power of a tie or of a safety pin sprung from punk fashion to the red carpet; a Midwestern thrift store, from cheap labor to cheap purchase, as a microcosm of global circulation; and lesbian pulp fiction as how-to-dress manuals.</p>
         <p>Whether looking at Kate Chopin's silk stockings, Nellie Bly's capacious bag, Audrey Hepburn's cross-Atlantic travels, rings in James Merrill's poetry, or feminine ornaments in Algeria, these essays offer an ever-expanding vision of how fashion moves through culture and the economy, reflecting and determining identity at every stage and turn of the transaction.</p>
         <p>Contributors: Nello Barile, IULM U, Milan; Vittoria C. Caratozzolo, Sapienza, U of Rome; Alisia Grace Chase, SUNY, Brockport; Chafika Dib-Marouf, Jules Verne U, Picardie; Anne Hollander; Mariuccia Mandelli (Krizia); Andrea Mariani, Gabriele d'Annunzio U, Chieti-Pescara; Katalin Medvedev, U of Georgia; Laura Montani; Karen Reimer; Cristina Scatamacchia, U of Perugia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Clothing, Dress, Fashion:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Arcade</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>WALKING THE WALK: CIRCULATION AND EXCHANGE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rabinowitz</surname>
                           <given-names>Paula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between May 10 and 14, 2010, Kate Gilmore’s Public Art Fund–sponsored installation<italic>Walk the Walk</italic>was on exhibit in a corner of New York’s Bryant Park. Set behind the New York Public Library on Forty-Second Street, home of Fashion Week and Midtown urban refuge for the hundreds of thousands of office workers in the surrounding buildings, the “hardcore endurance” installation featured seven young women dressed in identical canary-yellow shifts, pink cardigan sweaters (when the weather was cool), and ivory pumps continuously walking in five-hour shifts between 8:30 a.m. and 6:30 p.m. Ms. Gilmore had bought their identical rayon-and-spandex cowl-neck</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>ACCESSORY QUESTIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Montani</surname>
                           <given-names>Laura</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most ancient definition of the word “accessory,” together with the meaning it commonly has in current usage, suggests a unique spatial configuration where center and periphery are confused and intertwined. Anything that is marginal is, indeed, also a pathway required or necessary to get to a given point, a destination, taken to be a hypothetical center.</p>
                     <p>In Italian,<italic>accessorio</italic>, as defined by the Garzanti dictionary, is similar to the English “accessory” but with a few interesting legal twists. “Accessory: that which accompanies or is added to that which is principal; secondary, complementary, marginal. From Medieval Latin<italic>accessorium</italic>, from<italic>accedere</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>KRIZIA AND ACCESSORIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mandelli (Krizia)</surname>
                           <given-names>Mariuccia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my opinion, accessories are small, portable talismans of our well-being. They make up that framework of meaning that we construct about ourselves; they are invaluable indicators of taste, character, style, and behavior. I can understand a lot more about people by looking at their shoes or their watch than the clothes they wear or the things they say. Walter Albini, one of my first assistants who went on to become an almost legendary name in fashion, used to say that accessories are ten times more important than clothes. I agreed then—and I agree now.</p>
                     <p>This is also true</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE DRESS OF THOUGHT</title>
                     <subtitle>CLOTHING AND NUDITY IN HOMER, VIRGIL, DANTE, AND ARIOSTO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hollander</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to look at clothes in the works of Homer, Virgil, Dante, and Ariosto, four great poets who represent a cumulative literary tradition, with a huge influence on centuries of later writing. Each of these writers was essential to the next, and a great deal of later Western literature shows constant evidence of having internalized them all. I’ll be dealing with a few of these poets’ common themes that treat of dress, undress, and armor, with their differences in attitude about clothes, and with real clothes in their time. I will also note how one powerful literary treatment of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>ORBITS OF POWER</title>
                     <subtitle>RINGS IN JAMES MERRILL’S POETRY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mariani</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Merrill agrees with Charles Baudelaire in considering dressing a deeply spiritual act that, through artifice (which opposes the banality of daily reality), demonstrates the soul’s immaterial dimension.¹ His texts abound in elegant skirts, fur coats, sandals, and sunglasses; the poetic “I” describes with morbid satisfaction scarves, pochettes, jewels (tissues, colors, textures) as signals of deeper truths (good or bad taste, tensions and intentions) that contribute to the overall message of the text. This is true even of tights (according to Umberto Eco, the only garment that “the thought abhors”), which can allow for an appreciation of the abstract, purely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>SHEER LUXURY</title>
                     <subtitle>KATE CHOPIN’S “A PAIR OF SILK STOCKINGS”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giorcelli</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That talented, innovative composer and author who was Serge Gainsbourg wrote a beautiful, delicate song titled “Les dessous chics” (“Chic underwear”) in which he twice, in a song dedicated to elegant undergarments, evokes stockings (and once even garters):</p>
                     <p>C’est ne rien dévoiler du tout</p>
                     <p>se dire que lorsqu’on est à bout</p>
                     <p>c’est tabou</p>
                     <p>les dessous chics</p>
                     <p>c’est une jarretelle qui claque</p>
                     <p>dans la tête comme une paire de claques</p>
                     <p>les dessous chics</p>
                     <p>ce sont des contrats résiliés</p>
                     <p>qui comme des bas résilles</p>
                     <p>ont filé</p>
                     <p>…</p>
                     <p>les dessous chics</p>
                     <p>c’est se garder au fond de soi</p>
                     <p>fragile comme un bas de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>TRAVELING LIGHT</title>
                     <subtitle>NELLIE BLY’S ALL-INCLUSIVE BAG</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Scatamacchia</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The American journalist Nellie Bly, whose real name was Elizabeth Cochrane, was fully aware of the importance of clothes. As a reporter, she was the first woman to do undercover investigations, creating a new kind of female sensational journalism. In the course of her reporting for Joseph Pulitzer’s<italic>New York World</italic>, she realized that clothes played a crucial role: they became masks allowing her to hide her true identity and assume a new one that would enable her to expose social abuses and political corruption. Bly was an exception among women journalists of that time, and her work marked a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>LIKE THEIR FIRST PAIR OF HIGH-HEELED SHOES</title>
                     <subtitle>CONTINENTAL ACCESSORIES AND AUDREY HEPBURN’S CINEMATIC COMING OF AGE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chase</surname>
                           <given-names>Alisia Grace</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For nearly two centuries, the idea that the atmosphere of Europe would turn a puritanical American into a passionate American was fairly commonplace. It was also a given, however, that the American taking a trip to the Continent in order to seek sensual and cultural pleasures (often referred to as “the grand tour”) was male.¹ There were definitely flesh-and-blood counterparts to Henry James’s wealthy heiresses and Ernest Hemingway’s bohemian heroines, but these tended to be the exception not the rule, and it wasn’t until the early 1950s that the dream of fulfilling one’s desires while traveling or living abroad finally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>WORD-PROCESSED FOR YOU BY A PROFESSIONAL SEAMSTRESS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reimer</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My embroidered works exploit the tensions between copy and original, object and process, and fine art and domestic craft to examine the relations between beauty, value and meaning. I’m particularly interested in how the amount of manual work invested in an object affects our judgment of which category it fits into and to what degree it possesses those related qualities. These embroidered replicas of fragments and texts range from great books to candy wrappers. Generally speaking, copies are of less value than originals, but when I copy by embroidering, the value of the copy is increased because of the elements</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>SLIPS OF THE TONGUE</title>
                     <subtitle>LESBIAN PULP FICTION AS HOW-TO-DRESS MANUALS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rabinowitz</surname>
                           <given-names>Paula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The department store, site of middle-class female consumer culture since the nineteenth century, demarks a zone in which women not only shop but, in the process of trying on apparel, communally disrobe, sometimes literally together within a huge open space, occasionally under the supervising eye of the saleswoman who monitors the cut and fit of the garments, more often alone before a full-length three-way mirror, producing a solitary portrait. In another part of the modern cityscape, bohemia, female models shed their clothes and pose nude or draped in fabric for life drawing and painting classes in artists’ studios. Each scene</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>A SAFETY PIN FOR ELIZABETH</title>
                     <subtitle>HARD-EDGE ACCESSORIZING FROM PUNK SUBCULTURE TO HIGH FASHION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caratozzolo</surname>
                           <given-names>Vittoria C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>London, May 1994. A radiant Elizabeth Hurley caused an uproar at the premiere of<italic>Four Weddings and a Funeral</italic>, the film starring her boyfriend, Hugh Grant, thanks to the daring black dress she wore, designed by Versace. Soon after, when Hurley’s outfit was splashed across the front pages of the English tabloids, Gianni Versace himself described it in rather blasé terms as a remake of the old, classic punk dress. The tone of his remark surely complies with British understatement but is nonetheless an astonishing reference to his safety-pin dress—a bold sartorial experiment in construction.</p>
                     <p>Twenty years after the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>A KNOT TO UNTIE</title>
                     <subtitle>SOCIAL POWER, FETISHISM, AND COMMUNICATION IN THE SOCIAL HISTORY OF THE TIE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barile</surname>
                           <given-names>Nello</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If fashion is a language, albeit one marked by a low semantic level, then accessories can be taken as special indicators of the meaning of clothing. Idiosyncratically arranged, they are able to create both stable structures and variations on a theme. As a starting point I would like to use Mikhail Bakhtin’s concept of “multiaccentuality” and its appropriation by Stuart Hall, who adopts it as a benchmark for his encoding/decoding model.¹ His analysis of these modes of arrangement reveals decisive turning points in the social history of the tie.² Hidden within this accessory, in fact, is a symbolic potential that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>ORNAMENTS AND FEMININE CLOTHING TRADITION IN ALGERIA; OR, THE IDENTITY QUEST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dib-Marouf</surname>
                           <given-names>Chafika</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within Algerian culture, the semiology of clothing and, more generally, the code of jewelry as it encompasses all aspects of ornamentation constitute a privileged mode of expression. In the feminine universe of Tlemcen,¹ this code marks the events of festivals and ceremonies, and at the same time, delimits moments of daily life, more permissive because more anonymous.² However, even important occasions of ceremony are not rigidly prescriptive because the ritual space permits a wide range of possible choices, whose thresholds are nevertheless defined by rules of avoidance (at the lower limit) and rules of designation or exemplarity (at the upper</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>IT IS A GARAGE SALE AT SAVERS EVERY DAY</title>
                     <subtitle>AN ETHNOGRAPHY OF THE SAVERS THRIFT DEPARTMENT STORE IN MINNEAPOLIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Medvedev</surname>
                           <given-names>Katalin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My biggest difficulty after I moved to Minneapolis a decade ago to attend the University of Minnesota as an older doctoral student was admitting to myself that I was poor. I had exchanged a relatively comfortable life of a college professor in Hungary for the life of an underprivileged foreigner on campus. With my small stipend, I had to ration my meals, stint on my living conditions, and use public transportation. Although I gained a lot of knowledge at the university, my real “schooling” in the United States took place on the Lake Street No. 21 bus and subsequently at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CODA</title>
                     <subtitle>SPEAKING OUT AND SPEAKING UP: THE CIRCULATING POWER OF FASHION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giorcelli</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the West, fashion (in French<italic>mode</italic>, in Italian<italic>moda</italic>) is one of the modes of modernity; in the two languages, the punning contiguity, the etymological kinship, between the two words is significant.<italic>Mode</italic>and<italic>moda</italic>derive from the Latin word<italic>modus</italic>, which has several meanings, among them “way, measure, form, rule, rhythm, temporary state of being.”¹ If one of the imperatives of modernism is Ezra Pound’s exhortation to “make it new!” such a demand strictly coincides with fashion’s “way”: its need for constant change. And if rupture, fluctuation, surprise seem to be the rule of fashion, it is also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x5h7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
