<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX2353.D86 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mothers and sons</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Abandoned children</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Marie de l’Incarnation, mère, 1599–1672</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Martin, Claude, 1619–1696</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Church history</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Cruelest of All Mothers: Marie de l'Incarnation, Motherhood, and Christian Tradition</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dunn</surname>
               <given-names>Mary</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823267217</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823267248</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16nzfwp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In 1631, Marie Guyart stepped over the threshold of the Ursuline convent in Tours, leaving behind her eleven-year-old son, Claude, against the wishes of her family and her own misgivings. Marie concluded, "God was dearer to me than all that. Leaving him therefore in His hands, I bid adieu to him joyfully." Claude organized a band of schoolboys to storm the convent, begging for his mother's return. Eight years later, Marie made her way to Quebec, where over the course of the next thirty-three years she opened the first school for Native American girls, translated catechisms into indigenous languages, and served some eighteen years as superior of the first Ursuline convent in the New World. She would also maintain, over this same period, an extensive and intimate correspondence with the son she had abandoned to serve God. The Cruelest of All Mothers is, fundamentally, an explanation of Marie de l'Incarnation's decision to abandon Claude for religious life. Complicating Marie's own explication of the abandonment as a sacrifice carried out in imitation of Christ and in submission to God's will, the book situates the event against the background of early modern French family life, the marginalization of motherhood in the Christian tradition, and seventeenth-century French Catholic spirituality. Deeply grounded in a set of rich primary sources, The Cruelest of All Mothers offers a rich and complex analysis of the abandonment.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“I received your letter,” wrote Marie de l’Incarnation to her son, Claude, “and everything that was in your packet when I was no longer expecting it.” It was the summer of 1647 and nearly a decade since Marie had left her cloister in Tours, France, to found the first Ursuline convent in the New World. The Quebec in which Marie had settled in 1639 was still, eight years later, underdeveloped, poorly organized, and thinly populated—a struggling outpost pitifully vulnerable to Iroquois attacks. Marie’s mind was not, however, on the state of colonial affairs at this particular moment in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Explication:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representations of the Abandonment in the Relations, the Letters, and the Vie</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It’s hard to describe what it feels like to be told that there’s something wrong with your baby. Bobby and I had been worried for a while about Aggie. She was only four months old, but she wasn’t moving out of the newborn stage at the same pace that our three boys had. She rarely smiled. Her head was wobbly. And she still slept all the time. But I had been told that all babies develop at different rates, that girls are different, that—don’t worry—by six months she’ll blossom. So when Bobby and I brought Aggie in for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Explanation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contextualizing the Abandonment within Seventeenth-Century French Family Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The way Marie tells the story in the<italic>Relations</italic>of 1633 and 1654 and in her letters home to Claude, the abandonment was a sacrifice performed in imitation of Christ and in submission to the unambiguous will of God. Much as Christ himself had pleaded with God to “take this cup from me” (Luke 22:42), so Marie had resisted delivering “the blow of division” that God had commanded her to carry out. Marie’s sacrifice of Claude, much like Christ’s own sacrifice, had been contrary to both natural instinct and human reason. But in the end Marie, much like Christ himself,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Explanation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Marginalization of Motherhood in the Christian Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was in graduate school, I was assigned to read the bestseller<italic>Expecting Adam</italic>, Martha Beck’s memoir about bearing and raising a son with Down syndrome. Beck’s story, as she tells it, is one of “two driven Harvard academics” who find meaning and miracles in the experience of parenting their special-needs child. Fundamentally a narrative of resistance to a coldly rational and achievement-oriented Harvard culture,<italic>Expecting Adam</italic>is the story of parents who, in “allow[ing] their baby to be born … [were] themselves … born, infants in a new world where magic is commonplace, Harvard professors are the slow</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Explanation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maternal Hagiographies and Spiritualities of Abandonment in Seventeenth-Century France</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me return, by way of beginning this chapter, to Anneke Mulder-Bakker’s observation that “‘something happened’ with respect to sanctity and motherhood” in the later Middle Ages.¹ Beginning in the twelfth century, we find the first representations of a quartet of martyred mothers with their children—Felicitas and Symphorosa together with their seven sons, Julita holding her son Quiricius on her lap, and Sophia surrounded by her three children.² It is around the same period that St. Anne, second only to her virgin daughter Mary in maternal fame, began to garner the attention of the Christian faithful. And between the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Motherhood Refigured:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kristeva, Maternal Sacrifice, and the Imitation of Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To his critics, Bourdieu’s understanding of human agency (upon which I have relied to loosely structure my explanation of the abandonment) amounts to nothing more than a sophisticated version of social determinism.¹ Although Bourdieu’s intention had been to articulate a way of thinking about why people do what they do that transcended the reductive binaries of domination and resistance, his critics have consistently accused him of proposing a model of agency that condemns human actors to the reproduction of their own histories. And it is easy to see upon what logical grounds such accusations rest. For Bourdieu, after all, social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword/Afterward</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So, what happened afterward? What became of the abandoned son? We know that Marie went on to enjoy a vibrant mystical life and an active occupation among the indigenous girls of the New World. But what about Claude? How does his story end?</p>
                     <p>After completing his education with the Jesuits of Orléans, Claude went on to become a Benedictine monk in the Congregation of St. Maur. Over the course of his five-decade-long monastic career, Claude held a diversity of administrative positions, serving as prior at various monasteries and eventually as assistant to the superior general of the Maurists. He published</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16nzfwp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
