<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7mr99</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DC397.A33 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1940–1945</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Political Ecumenism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Catholics, Jews, and Protestants in De Gaulle’s Free France, 1940-1945</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ADAMS</surname>
               <given-names>GEOFFREY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773530768</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773576667</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt80x6j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Adams examines the contributions of such major Français libres as René Cassin, Pierre Mendès France, and Jacques Soustelle and explores de Gaulle's troubled relations with Churchill and Roosevelt. The opportunity for Gaullists to offer full membership to the fourth religious family, Algeria's Muslim majority, following the liberation of French North Africa is also considered. In an epilogue, Adams reflects on the impact of Free France's political ecumenism in the postwar era.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chronology of Events</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Free French Leadership:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Politically Ecumenical Coalition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Free French Organization at the End of 1943</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>The Free French Challenge: Reuniting the Two Frances</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When, on 18 June 1940, in the aftermath of France’s defeat and the assumption of power by Marshal Philippe Pétain, Charles de Gaulle appealed to his fellow citizens over the BBC to join him in continuing the fight against Nazi Germany, he initiated a process that would reunite the Two Frances (revolutionary and counter-revolutionary) which had been in open or covert conflict since 1789. And, when men and women of France’s “three religious families,” Jews and Protestants as well as Catholics, who had been involved in this conflict, joined him to fight under a banner on which the Cross of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>1905–1940:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Generation United in War, Divided in Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During 1906, when French Catholics were beginning to absorb the shock created by the Separation law, the nation’s attention was drawn toward the serious external threat posed by Germany, which was openly challenging France’s increasing influence in Morocco. Since their humiliating defeat in 1870, the French had been debating whether to challenge Germany directly on the Rhine, in an effort to regain domination of the Continent, or to compensate for their losses in Europe by expanding their colonial holdings in Asia and North Africa. The appointment in 1912 of General (future Marshal) Hubert Lyautey as<italic>commissaire-résident général</italic>in Morocco provided</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Charles de Gaulle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Devout Catholic, Pragmatic Republican, Political Ecumenist</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While his chief biographers point to the mix of qualities which, against all odds, helped de Gaulle become the saviour of his nation’s honour in 1940, none of them would maintain that the general was a plausible champion of France’s republican or democratic tradition.¹ In any event, those republican patriots ready to continue the battle against fascism following France’s defeat in 1940 would normally have looked for leadership from among the agnostics, Jews, Protestants, and Freemasons who had governed the Third Republic since 1879. As it turned out, such a potential leader existed in the person of the Jew Georges</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The General’s Inner Circle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Christian and Republican</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To the great distress of<italic>Le Connétable,</italic>his 18 June appeal for support was, with a few exceptions, greeted with silence by France’s military, political, socio-economic, and religious elites. The most logical political allies in the struggle against fascism (Paul Reynaud, Léon Blum, and Georges Mandel) opted, for different reasons, to stay in France. With the exception of Admiral Émile Muselier and four-star General Georges Catroux, dismissed from his post as Governor-General of Indo-China by Vichy, none of the nation’s military chiefs were willing to join de Gaulle in rebelling against Marshal Pétain, nor did any of the administrators of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>René Cassin:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jewish Champion of Gaullist Legitimacy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Interestingly enough, one of the first well-known personalities to show up at Free French headquarters was René Cassin, a Jew. Cassin was a law professor at the University of Paris who brought to the cause a rich experience of public service in Geneva as well as France. His arrival and the warm welcome he received from de Gaulle established the general’s indifference to the religious or ethnic background of would-be recruits and his clear willingness to override the evident anti-Semitism in his military entourage. As a jurist, Cassin would develop a persuasive case for the political legitimacy of La France</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Maurice Schumann:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Catholic Voice of La France libre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all those who transmitted the Free French message of defiance, resistance, and hope to those living in Vichy France or in the German-occupied zone, none was more eloquent than the journalist-turned-broadcaster Maurice Schumann. Schumann was born in Paris on 10 April 1911 to upper-middle-class Jewish parents who were so thoroughly assimilated that they felt only the most nominal link to their ancestral faith.¹ Schumann<italic>père</italic>was a successful corset manufacturer; like his wife, he was devoted to the Republic and to the memory of the Revolution which had given it birth. Patriotism came naturally in this environment: Schumann tells</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Ecumenical Money-Managers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pierre Denis, André Diethelm, André Postel-Vinay, Maurice Couve de Murville, and Pierre Mendès France</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The long-term financing of Free France seemed highly problematic in the early summer of 1940. Unlike other Allied forces then in Great Britain – the Dutch, the Czechs, and the Poles, for instance – de Gaulle’s organization began with only the most tenuous political legitimacy, and that status was put in jeopardy when Pétain’s État français charged<italic>Le Connétable</italic>with treason. The obvious solution to this dilemma would have been for de Gaulle to allow his supporters to become part of Britain’s armed forces, in effect turning them into mercenaries. The pride of the general and that of his devoted band of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Jacques Soustelle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Huguenot Rebel Becomes Gaullist Propagandist</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Born in Montpellier on 3 February 1912 to a working-class Catholic father and a Protestant mother, Jacques Soustelle was baptized in the Reformed communion. Although as an adult he drifted away from his childhood faith, Soustelle always saw himself as shaped by the Huguenot tradition. He never forgot early memories of itinerant lay preachers who travelled door-to-door throughout the Protestant heartland in the Cévennes distributing tracts with their message of eternal salvation. In writing about his wartime commitment to Free France, Soustelle recalls taking heart from these sometimes solitary pilgrims:</p>
                     <p>I still remember one of them in particular, so vividly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Blum’s Disciples Become de Gaulle’s Apostles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The presence of a contingent of Jewish Socialists in La France libre was a source of concern to de Gaulle, not because of any personal antipathy (he had great respect for Léon Blum) but because it caused deep resentment among many of the officers who had rallied to his cause and because it offered an easy target to Vichy propagandists, who tried to fix the blame for France’s collapse on Blum’s Popular Front administration (as well as on Jews in general). By contrast, Blum was the object of something close to veneration by the Socialists who showed up at Free</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Pierre Mendès France:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Jewish Radical Joins the Battle</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The strong Jewish presence in the ranks of the Free French was hardly surprising. Jews had been consistent defenders of the republican ideal since 1848. They had participated in the ephemeral government of the Second Republic in 1848, and the quintessentially assimilated Léon Blum had become the first Jewish premier of France in 1936 (albeit, not without infuriating disciples of Maurras). Pierre Mendès France, who played a secondary role in Blum’s Popular Front government, would join La France libre following his escape from Vichy. His presence in General de Gaulle’s wartime organization would be the prelude to a long, mutually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Louis Closon, Jean Moulin, Georges Bidault:</title>
                     <subtitle>Binding the Resistance to de Gaulle</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the resistance to fascism within France gathered momentum beginning in 1942, the Free French in London faced the challenge of trying to bring it under the overall command of General de Gaulle or of letting it develop autonomously, which might lead to a very different representation of the Republic when liberation came, especially if the communist vision of postwar France were to prevail. To further the first option, de Gaulle and his advisors found three remarkable men – Louis Closon, Jean Moulin, and Georges Bidault – who would between them help secure the general’s claim to lead all French forces committed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Simone Weil:</title>
                     <subtitle>Would-Be Martyr to the Free French Cause</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all those drawn to the Gaullist cause, Simone Weil must surely be counted the most spiritually exalted.¹ Born in Paris in 1909 to a determinedly agnostic Alsatian-Jewish father and a mother whose family was only nominally linked to Judaism, Simone developed an early antipathy to the faith of her ancestors and an equally powerful fascination for the Catholic version of Christianity. This spiritual outlook was based partly on an aversion to the Old Testament which she saw to be ethnocentric in focus² and partly on a fascination for Catholic ritual. Visits to the Benedictine abbey at Solesmes at Easter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>André Philip and the Christian Left Commit to Free France</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the longstanding devotion of the vast majority of French Protestants to the Republic and to democratic principles, it is not surprising that a substantial proportion of those who showed up to enrol in La France libre were linked to the Reformed communion.¹ None of these Protestants had a more significant role in shaping wartime Gaullist policy than André Philip, the only practicing Christian among the pre-war leaders of the SFIO.² Before arriving in London, Philip had been active in the internal Resistance. Through his initiative, two more Protestant<italic>résistants</italic>familiar with the French trade-union movement – Albert Guigui and Louis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>De Gaulle’s Protestant Emissaries:</title>
                     <subtitle>René Massigli and André Philip</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the aftermath of his 18 June 1940 appeal over the BBC, Charles de Gaulle expected to rally to his cause key members of France’s military and political elites. Nowhere was the reaction to the general’s challenge more disappointing than among France’s senior diplomats, whose responses ranged in tone from indifferent to openly hostile. As a result, at least during its first year, Free France’s external relations were entrusted to a variety of well-intentioned intellectuals and two men with a background in business.</p>
                     <p>The absence of experienced diplomats at the outset of the Free French saga and the peculiar vulnerability</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Operation “Torch”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jews, Muslims, and the Limits of Political Ecumenism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In sharp contrast to the aims of those who planned it, Operation “Torch,” the American-led assault on the North African coast which began on 8 November 1942, would end up radically enhancing the status and influence of La France combattante.¹ Yet while the liberation of the Maghreb, accomplished with the aid of Jewish Gaullists inside Algiers, was followed by the ascendancy of de Gaulle over his American-backed rivals and the restoration of Jewish rights which Vichy had revoked, it did not deliver to Algeria’s Muslims the political and social emancipation which they hoped for and which progressive Gaullists such as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>From Mystique to Politique:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Emergence of a Gaullist Administration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In London, where he was kept long after the success of Operation “Torch,”<italic>Le Connétable</italic>declared on 2 January 1943 that the interests of France required the creation of “an enlarged provisional central authority based on the principle of national unity, inspired by a fighting spirit and a desire for liberation and guided by the laws of the Republic until the nation is able to make known its will.”¹ This bold demand was seriously challenged at a conference two weeks later at Anfa, an elegant residential suburb of Casablanca, where Churchill and Roosevelt met to discuss wartime strategy. The role</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Legislating for La France Nouvelle:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Provisional Consultative Assembly</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The demand for the creation of an assembly which would reflect the democratic aspirations of Fighting France had been growing since the early days of La France libre in London. Dedicated republicans including Henry Hauck, Pierre-Olivier Lapie and, most persistently, René Cassin, had been pressing de Gaulle to create such a body as had Félix Gouin, Blum’s emissary in London, who chaired a group of French parliamentary exiles in the British capital. Anxious to see some restraints placed on the authoritarian side of the general whose cause he had endorsed from the beginning, Churchill gave the idea his full support.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>Liberation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Triumph of Political Ecumenism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having established the CFLN and the Provisional Consultative Assembly to help him debate both wartime strategy and post-war planning, Charles de Gaulle waited through the winter of 1943–44 in Algiers to be invited to London to join in devising Allied strategy for the liberation of France. Much time was spent during these months in vain efforts to secure formal recognition of the CFLN by the Allies. Thanks to the unbudging antipathy of Roosevelt to de Gaulle and to the growing bitterness of Churchill toward what he saw to be the general’s increasingly perfidious behaviour, this diplomatic acceptance would not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE</title>
                     <subtitle>Political Ecumenism, 1945–2005</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the Free French camp, there had been a lively debate about whether the close communion among the men and women who had joined de Gaulle in London or Algiers should be transformed after victory into a permanent political<italic>rassemblement.</italic>Such a regrouping, it was argued, would perhaps even replace the pre-war parties whose sectarianism was seen as partly responsible for the catastrophe of 1940. The case for such a radical shift was put most passionately by Pierre Brossolette, who foresaw the emergence under de Gaulle’s leadership of a vast political communion beyond old divisions of class and confession, citing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80x6j.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
