<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Identity and Networks</book-title>
         <subtitle>Gender and Ethnicity in a Cross-Cultural Context</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bryceson</surname>
               <given-names>Deborah Fahy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Okely</surname>
               <given-names>Judith</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Webber</surname>
               <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782381983</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782381988</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Deborah Fahy Bryceson</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Judith Okely</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Jonathan Webber</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btc01f"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Contrary to the negative assessments of the social order that have become prevalent in the media since 9/11, this wide-ranging collection of essays, mostly by social anthropologists, focuses instead on the enormous social creativity being invested as collective identities are reconfigured. Using fieldwork findings drawn from Africa, Asia, and Europe, special emphasis is placed on the reformulation of ethnic and gender relationships and identities in the cultural, social, political, and religious realms of public life. Under what circumstances does trust arise, paving the way for friendship, collegiality, knowledge creation, national unity, or emergence of leadership? How is social life constructed as a collective endeavour? Does the means towards sociability become its end? And what can be said about the agency and collegiality of women? The inspiration for examining these conundrums is the work and persona of Shirley Ardener, to whom the volume is dedicated.</p>
         <p>Contributors:Jonathan Benthall, Deborah Fahy Bryceson, Gina Buijs, Sandra Burman, Hilary Callan, Gaynor Cohen, Janette Davies, Tamara Dragadze, Ronnie Frankenberg, Peter Geschiere, Kirsten Hastrup, Paula Heinonen, Maria Jaschok, Grazyna Kubica, Rhian Loudon, Sharon Macdonald, Zdzislaw Mach, Fiona Moore, Judith Okely, Lidia D. Sciama, Shui Jingjun, Cecillie Swaisland, Jacqueline Waldren, Jonathan Webber.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="316"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <collab>The Editors</collab>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Artistry of Social Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bryceson</surname>
                           <given-names>Deborah Fahy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Currently, much of anthropological literature on identity finds itself in unanticipated dialogue with other social science disciplines in a period of deepening global insecurity. The optimism of the last half-century, an era viewed as one of unparalleled economic progress for much of the world, is now being replaced by a profound pessimism in the West about the spread of social intolerance and terrorism in the twenty-first century. Even before the events of 11 September and the London bombings of July 2005, unease was surfacing. American political scientists took the lead in the cultural commentary, drawing attention to the decline in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Changing Cultures, Changing Rooms:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fashioning Identities and Anthropological Research</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Moving across and between cultures is at the heart of anthropology. Ethnography is an inherently mobile enterprise, involving the ethnographer literally moving across space, over time, and between the relatively familiar and unfamiliar. Although the idea of ‘multi-sited fieldwork’ has become fashionable recently, good anthropology has always entailed a degree of multi-sitedness, even if some of those sites might be called ‘home’ and some might be encountered vicariously. Good anthropological training entails learning about many peoples and parts of the world and going to seminars beyond geographical specialisms. The themed seminar and the edited collection, in which scholars are brought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Identity at Play:</title>
                     <subtitle>Individuals, Characters, and Theatres of Action</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hastrup</surname>
                           <given-names>Kirsten</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Identity categories are at the core of anthropological practice, in terms of both individual identities (or notions of the self ) and collective identities (or notions of ethnicity). In this chapter I shall deal primarily with the interface between the self and the collectivity in order to discuss identity as a response to multiple actualities rather than a fixed frame of subjectivity. This tallies with other attempts at understanding the self as composite and malleable (Cohen 1994; Rapport 1997). It also in its own way reflects the insight of relational identities provided by scholars of gender such as Shirley Ardener</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Constructing Identities in a Post-Communist Society:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethnic, National, and European</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mach</surname>
                           <given-names>Zdzisław</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The long and complicated process of social, economic, and political transformation of central and eastern Europe, which began in 1989, is still far from complete and needs much more research to be fully understood in its many aspects. The decomposition, construction, and reconstruction of collective identities constitute one of the dimensions of this transformation that has been widely debated, but which still causes controversy and must be better understood. Contemporary central and eastern Europe is thus a very productive place to study – a social laboratory ideal for researchers interested in social change.</p>
                     <p>In this essay I intend to discuss</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Making Sense of the Past:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Jewish Historical Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Webber</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Making sense of the past ranks among the key intellectual activities of any society and indeed of any individual. Not only must we learn to select those social and personal events with which we have had direct or indirect experience, make connections between these events, smooth out inconsistencies, establish meanings, construct narratives, mask out uncertainties, and develop an aesthetic appreciation of our historical understanding of things; we also seem to be able to do it all the time. We know how to adapt previous interpretations to suit new circumstances, and we are capable of remodelling our memories of the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>A Sense of People and Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Chapel and Language in Sustaining Welsh Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Gaynor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within Britain, the Welsh language is often presented by the English media as controversial. In some cases it is seen as the instrument through which the minority, namely Welsh language speakers, impose their will on the majority. Promoters have been accused of encouraging linguistic racialism in Wales in the context of bilingual education policy. Yet few would deny the importance of language in a person’s identity: ‘For a man to speak one language rather than another is a ritual act, it is a statement about one’s personal status; to speak the same language as one’s neighbours expresses solidarity with those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Towards an Ethnography of Colleagueship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callan</surname>
                           <given-names>Hilary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this short essay I focus on two issues relating to colleagueship and anthropology. First, I look at a case drawn from my own occupational experience and recent analytical work, where it seems to me that colleagueship is germane to an understanding of institution building and the negotiation of identities in a particular environment. Secondly, using the same material, I consider the ‘colleague relationship’ as a context and a tool for ethnography. The designation of this relationship is, inevitably, imprecise, but perhaps no more so than others that have been much discussed as a basis for the production of anthropological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Thinking the Unheard, Writing the Unwritten:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflecting on Marginality, Ethnography, and Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jaschok</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jingjun</surname>
                           <given-names>Shui</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the core of my last years of research – indeed, all-pervasive in its implications – is the ongoing dialogue with my Chinese–Hui research collaborator, co-author and friend, Shui Jingjun. One of the prompters of this enduring conversation, begun over nine years ago, was my correspondence with Shirley Ardener, then not known to me in person. It was about 1994, when conducting fieldwork in Henan Province, in the interior of China, that I wrote to Shirley about the relevance of issues addressed in<italic>Perceiving Women</italic>¹ to problems arising from my own crosscultural and collaborative research. And I wrote of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Women’s Movement:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Formative Years, 1850–1930</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swaisland</surname>
                           <given-names>Cecillie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In early 1902, following the Report of the Fawcett Commission, also known as the Ladies’ Commission, sent to South Africa by the British Government to investigate conditions in the Boer War concentration camps, an appeal was made for teachers and nurses from Britain and Canada to serve in the camps. Two hundred women were needed but two thousand applied. Were the women motivated by patriotism, or did the response reflect a shortage of vocational outlets for women in these professions?</p>
                     <p>The year 1900 may be described as a watershed in the struggle of British women to achieve, as of right,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>A Good Lady, Androgynous Angel, and Intrepid Woman:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maria Czaplicka in Feminist Profile</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kubica</surname>
                           <given-names>Grażyna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay discusses the Polish-British anthropologist, Maria Czaplicka (born 1884), a contemporary of Bronisław Malinowski, who like him came to England in 1910 and studied under C.G. Seligman at the London School of Economics and Political Science. Later she worked with R.R. Marett and obtained a Diploma in Anthropology from Oxford University. In 1914–15, she led the Jenisei Expedition to Siberia, where she became an experienced fieldworker and made important finds for the Pitt Rivers Museum. While she was the first female lecturer in anthropology at Oxford University, she was also a tragic figure without a secure academic appointment.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>‘Ritual Sisters’ or Female Rulers?</title>
                     <subtitle>Gender and Chiefship Revisited in Southern Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buijs</surname>
                           <given-names>Gina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a truism that social anthropologists often arrive in the field with the mores and expectations of the societies they come from. Such embedded baggage may have unforeseen but real consequences which appear in the ethnographic accounts subsequently presented. I have written previously (Buijs 2002a, b) of the ways in which historians, social anthropologists and colonial officials have marginalised some of the customary social and political roles of women in African and especially southern African societies. Mesmerised by the apparent power exercised by men over women in patrilineal African societies as well as their own patriarchal surroundings, Evans-Pritchard, for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Revolting, Revolutionary, and Rebellious Women:</title>
                     <subtitle>Symbolic Disruption of Traditional Femininity and the Liberation of Femineity and Other Muted Identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loudon</surname>
                           <given-names>Rhian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frankenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Ronnie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay uses some of the Ardeners’ seminal/uterine, even vaginal insights to analyse the way that anthropological research can be seen as a cooperative exercise between subjects rather than merely informant and fieldworker – to illuminate such diverse investigations as resistance and struggle in West Africa and images in art and drama. Finally, on the basis of Rhian Loudon’s own field research, they inform analysis of the both vulnerable and powerful, dominant and muted, speech and actions of British Asian women, observed in shared multiple simultaneous realities of home and health-service/social-service workplace. It accepts one challenge posed by Ardener’s discussions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>What Women Really Want:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gender, Ethnicity, and Job Expectations on an Automobile Factory Assembly Line</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Fiona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Traditionally, social studies of factories have focused on issues of discrimination, oppression, and resistance. The earliest studies in industrial anthropology, the Hawthorne research projects, examined the ways in which workers controlled the production process against the interests of management (Baba 1986). More recently, the work of Roberts et al.,<italic>Language and Discrimination</italic>(1992) focused on ways in which English managers unconsciously exclude their non-English workers through the use of language and communication, and Westwood’s (1984)<italic>All Day, Every Day</italic>analyses how women from a variety of ethnic origins gain empowerment against their male relatives and bosses through subversive practices. Much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Can You Call This Fieldwork?</title>
                     <subtitle>September in Venice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sciama</surname>
                           <given-names>Lidia D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reflexive anthropology, anthropology ‘at home’ or ‘half-way home’, and the recognition of the researcher’s as well as her informants’ subjectivity have dominated much of anthropology since the 1970s. All are intimately bound with feminist critiques of ethnographic approaches and have been guiding principles in research conducted within the framework of Oxford’s Centre for Cross-Cultural Research on Women (E. Ardener 1975; S. Ardener 1975; Ardener and Burman 1995). To reach a closer understanding of women’s lives, it proved essential to focus on the contacts and active interactions of women in the societies we studied. Indeed, one of the questions we posed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Gendered Lessons in Ivory Towers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Okely</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Feminist knowledge entails a theory of power because, as Ramazanoglu and Holland assert in relation to feminist methodology, ‘the power to produce authoritative knowledge is not equally open to all’ (2002: 13). Certainly this has been my experience as a woman academic. I am confronted with disparities in power. I am obliged to confront my gender because it is made clear to me on a daily basis. In what is ideally presented as a centre for open and rational knowledge, the university is not free of specificity in history and is marked by gender, class, and ethnic differences. Nevertheless, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gendering Oxford:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shirley Ardener and Cross-Cultural Research</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davies</surname>
                           <given-names>Janette</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Waldren</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacqueline</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the early 1970s, Shirley Ardener has applied her intellect, creativity and enthusiasm to the development of women’s studies at the University of Oxford and further afield. Her contribution to social anthropology and women’s studies is revealed in the chapters of this book and in her innumerable publications. She recognised the similarity between the ‘consciousness-raising’ proposed by Western feminist movements and the social anthropological techniques of ‘isolating from their context statements which though trivial in themselves carry assumptions with wider significance’ (Ardener 1978: 45, n. 9). The category ‘women’ was problematised in different contexts; individual cultural models of women –</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shirley Ardener’s Habitus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benthall</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I used to think of women anthropologists prominent during the last quarter of the twentieth century, either the profile would come to mind of a figure with arms akimbo ready to pounce on some ill-judged generalisation that I might have let slip, or alternatively a texture of silky meekness charged with static electricity and sheathing a healthy set of claws. The fault for these warped representations was, of course, entirely mine, and was no doubt due to schooling in competitive male boarding institutions where the opposite sex had been a reality only at the margins. Shirley Ardener, however, seemed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Circumstance, Personality, and Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dragadze</surname>
                           <given-names>Tamara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the beginning there was turmoil in our Oxford Institute of Social Anthropology the year the Women’s Seminar was born, partly because of a controversial appointment and partly because of the cold weather. In this ‘winter of discontent’ with power shortages, some of us had to bring blankets to our seminars. And there was also the curious Friday Seminar, bringing staff and postgraduate students together. At a time when Wendy James was the only female don as far as the eye could see in our Institute, and when a professor at St Antony’s could say to me in the Common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shirley in My Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kubica</surname>
                           <given-names>Grażyna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I met Shirley Ardener for the first time in spring 1986, during a ceremonial dinner at St John’s College, Oxford. I had come from the Jagiellonian University, Cracow, and had received a grant from the Oxford Colleges Hospitality Scheme for Polish Scholars and was therefore able to spend some time in this magnificent place. St John’s contributed to the Scheme by having one person each month. I was thus a piece of the ‘Polish sausage’, to quote Edwin Ardener’s fine turn of phrase. Shirley struck me aesthetically as delightfully eccentric: no make-up, just a dash of red lipstick to mark</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Titi ikoli in the Academy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among so many engaging memories of Shirley, one that especially stands out for me is her performance at the Decennial Conference of the Association of Social Anthropologists (ASA), which was held in Cambridge in 1983. I was myself a novice anthropologist at this time, having just completed a year of postgraduate anthropology at Oxford, though I had already had the opportunity to get to know Shirley and maybe shouldn’t have been as surprised by her as I was. As an undergraduate, I was partly taught by Shirley and remember being disconcerted at our first meeting at how swiftly she honed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Going the Extra Mile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burman</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Invited to reminisce about Shirley in a page, I find it difficult to select from some forty years of memories since we first met. It is also difficult to convey briefly her many notable qualities, such as her originality of thought and quiet zest for life that make her such excellent company. But in the end I realise that an underlying feature of all my many recollections of Shirley is her empathy with those she encounters. Although she is a very private person, her concern for people who work with her has led to a greater intermingling of her personal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Her Powers of Persuasion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Fiona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I first knew Shirley Ardener as a name in textbooks, in the sections on Africa and on gender studies, and so meeting her for the first time in 1997 was an overwhelming experience. Given that she was such a well-known figure, how could I not agree to her polite request to attend the seminars on Gender and Tourism at Queen Elizabeth House, even though my research interests lay very much in the opposite direction? In doing so, I learned quickly that any seminar series organised by Shirley is sure to have something of interest for any researcher regardless of their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shirley Ardener:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mentor and Friend</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Heinonen</surname>
                           <given-names>Paula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My relationship with Shirley and Edwin Ardener began in 1977 when I came to Oxford as a Human Sciences undergraduate. My first glimpse of Shirley was in the quad at St John’s College when one of my friends pointed her out as one of our anthropology tutors. I blinked and she was gone. For the next few months, the same thing happened. She either flew or zoomed past me on her bike or on foot. Nothing has changed, since I found it hard to keep up with her when we eventually carried out fieldwork together on body piercing in 2003.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The African Connection in Oxford</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buijs</surname>
                           <given-names>Gina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I first met Shirley in 1990 when I arrived at the CCCRW as a Visiting Fellow from Venda (Limpopo Province), South Africa. When I had applied to the Centre for a fellowship I had thought I would be returning to Venda, but it was not to be, and when I arrived in Oxford I found myself in a hiatus, not at all sure what the future would bring and whether I should return permanently to England, a country I had left for South Africa some twenty years before and where I felt myself to be a stranger. Shirley quickly summed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shirley’s African Roots</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swaisland</surname>
                           <given-names>Cecillie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shirley Ardener has a long association with West Africa, beginning when she accompanied her husband Edwin Ardener to Nigeria for his fieldwork. They had met when they were students at the LSE together. Subsequently, in the 1950s, Shirley and Edwin Ardener moved to the Cameroons, where Edwin became the Honorary Adviser on Archives and Antiquities (see S. Ardener’s introduction to her edited volume,<italic>Kingdom on Mount Cameroon</italic>, Berghahn Books, 1996). So began Shirley’s interest and concern with the Cameroons. She acted as Edwin’s associate and developed a love of the land, the people and especially the Bakweri in the south.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Returning to ‘The Mountain’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geschiere</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1995, my colleague Piet Konings and I arranged for Shirley’s return to Cameroon after more than twenty years. It did not take much persuasion to get her back. Clearly she felt it was time to revisit Buea, where she and Edwin had done so much ethnographic work beginning in the 1950s. The occasion was a conference Piet and I organised with Paul Nkwi, then at the Ministry of Scientific Research in Yaoundé. We were delighted that Shirley had agreed to attend, thus returning to Cameroon after so long.</p>
                     <p>Of course, there was a deeper reason as well. The archives</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shirley’s Magic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Webber</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shirley Ardener has taught me some important things in the thirty years I have known her. If I were to pick out just one of them, one that has run like a thread throughout these long years, it would be the theory and practice of magic.</p>
                     <p>Let me explain.<italic>JASO: Journal of the Anthropological Society of Oxford</italic>was founded by Edwin Ardener in 1970 to disseminate new approaches in social anthropology. Little did I realise, when I became its editor in 1979, just what it meant in practice to be associated so closely with the Ardeners, even though I had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Published Works by Shirley Ardener</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btc01f.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
