<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z6vm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT660.T48D83 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mary, Blessed Virgin, Saint</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Cult</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Tinos Island</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian pilgrims and pilgrimages</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Tinos Island</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hieros Naos Euangelistrias (Tinos Island, Greece)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Tinos Island (Greece)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In a Different Place</book-title>
         <subtitle>Pilgrimage, Gender, and Politics at a Greek Island Shrine</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dubisch</surname>
               <given-names>Jill</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400884414</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400884411</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dxg8nz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>In a Different Place</italic>offers a richly textured account of a modern pilgrimage, combining ethnographic detail, theory, and personal reflection. Visited by thousands of pilgrims yearly, the Church of the Madonna of the Annunciation on the Aegean island of Tinos is a site where different interests--sacred and secular, local and national, personal and official--all come together. Exploring the shrine and its surrounding town, Jill Dubisch shares her insights into the intersection of social, religious, and political life in Greece. Along the way she develops the idea of pilgrimage-journeying away from home in search of the miraculous--as a metaphor for anthropological fieldwork. This highly readable work offers us the opportunity to share one anthropologist's personal and professional journey and to see in a "different place" the inadequacy of such conventional anthropological categories as theory versus data, rationality versus emotion, and the observer versus the observed.</p>
         <p>Dubisch examines in detail the process of pilgrimage itself, its relationship to Orthodox belief and practice, the motivations and behavior of pilgrims, the relationship between religion and Greek national identity, and the gendered nature of religious roles. Seeking to evoke rather than simply describe, her book presents readers with a sense of the emotion, color, and power of pilgrimage at this Greek island shrine.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Plates</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Transliteration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is, first of all, a book about a pilgrimage site, the Church of the Madonna of the Annunciation (<italic>Evangelístria</italic>) on the Aegean island of Tinos, Greece, where I have been conducting research since 1986.¹ My account, however, is more than a simple ethnographic description. Indeed, in the context of contemporary anthropology, one would be hard put to maintain that any ethnographic description is ever really simple—or that any ethnography can be simply description. Acknowledging this, I seek here to experiment with several types of what might be termed “ethnographic exploration” in order to pursue the aims I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Pilgrim and the Anthropologist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The summer traveler to Tinos will be struck first by two things about the island—the arid barrenness of the landscape, and the wind.</p>
                     <p>Tinos is a rugged island, one of a group of the Aegean Islands of Greece known as the Cyclades, a name derived from the fact that they form a circle (<italic>kíklos</italic>) around the ancient sacred island of Delos. For contemporary pilgrims, however, it is not Delos but Tinos that forms the sacred center of the Cyclades. These pilgrims come in droves during the summer months, in ships buffeted by the<italic>meltémi</italic>, the relentless north wind of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Anthropological Study of Pilgrimage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I first began my research on pilgrimage at the Church of the Annunciation on Tinos in 1986, the phenomenon was not one that had been well studied by anthropologists. Aside from Victor Turner’s works on pilgrimage as ritual and on the place of pilgrimage in the Christian tradition (1974, 1979; Turner and Turner 1978), works that provided much of the initial inspiration for my own research, there existed only a handful of anthropological studies of pilgrimage. Recently, however, anthropological interest in the topic has burgeoned. While there are still no general theoretical works of a scope to rival Turner’s,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Observing Pilgrimage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Churches, Icons, and the Devil</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the evening of August 12, 1986, at around eight o’clock, I left my apartment on Tinos accompanied by a visitor, my partner and companion Ray, who had come to visit me for six weeks.¹ It was Ray’s last evening on the island and we had planned a nice dinner at our favorite restaurant. Since it was still a little early to eat (by Greek standards), we thought we would first take a stroll along the waterfront and perhaps sit at a sidewalk cafe and watch the passing crowds.</p>
                     <p>It was only a few days before Tinos’s main religious holiday,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Pilgrimage Observed:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Journey and the Vow</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pilgrimage involves by definition a journey of some sort, usually one of enough distance to constitute a hardship, or at least an inconvenience, to the pilgrim.¹ With today’s rapid and comfortable transportation, however, pilgrimage to Tinos cannot be considered too great an ordeal (though on major holidays the crowded passenger ships can make the journey an uncomfortable one, and winter storms or the<italic>meltémi</italic>, the summer wind, can create rough seas). Pilgrims arrive on large passenger boats, a journey of three to four hours from Piraeus. On Tinos they can stay in private rooms and hotels and eat in restaurants.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>The Observer Observed</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My own “vow” reflects a particularly complex, long-term, and even intimate relationship with a certain set of religious practices. As I look back on my earlier fieldwork, I realize that religion was part of my experience of Greek life almost from my first days in the village. This is illustrated by an entry in my journal on August 4, 1969, about two weeks after my husband and I had settled in Falatados. I spent part of this day with some village women, accompanying them to their garden in the countryside. It was a frustrating experience for me as I struggled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>An Island in Space, an Island In Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far I have brought both the pilgrim and the anthropologist to Tinos and have described something of the activities of each at the pilgrimage site. These activities are located within two larger fields: the practices and beliefs of the Greek Orthodox religion on the one hand, and the practices and beliefs of anthropology on the other. Up to this point Tinos, the island, has remained in the background, noted merely as the location of the Church of the Annunciation, as the site of my earlier village fieldwork, and as a place to which both pilgrim and anthropologist must travel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Writing the Story/History of the Church:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Panayía and the Nun</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On July 9, 1822, an elderly nun named Pelayia, who lived at the monastery of Kekhrovouno on the island of Tinos, had a vision. This vision appeared to her in the form of a woman surrounded by light who came to the nun as she slept. This lady approached Pelayia’s humble bed, and speaking to her, told the nun to go to the<italic>epítropos</italic>of the monastery and tell him to excavate a field outside the town, a field belonging to one Andonis Dhoksaras, in order, in her words, to find “my house” and there to begin “the building of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Of Nations and Foreigners, Miracles and Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1880s an Englishman named James Theodore Bent made a tour of the islands of the Cyclades. He visited Tinos twice on his travels, once to attend the festival of the Annunciation on March 25, and the second time, not quite a year later, to tour the island. Unlike many such travelers to Greece, Bent did not confine his attentions to antiquities but was also interested in contemporary customs and was willing to learn modern Greek. Nonetheless, he saw many continuities between the modern Greeks and the ancients, and drew upon both past and present in describing what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Women, Performance, and Pilgrimage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Beyond Honor and Shame</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a warm morning in July 1986, I left my apartment on Tinos and headed into town to pick up fresh bread for breakfast at a nearby bakery. My walk took me down the road along a low cliff above the sea and then along the waterfront, past a large concrete wharf, restaurants, shops, bars, and stores to the bakery, tucked into a narrow whitewashed alley. As always in the summer, the town was bustling at that hour. Local housewives haggled at the produce and fish market in the square near the waterfront, shopkeepers and restaurant owners swept out their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Virgin Mary and the Body Politic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In may 1990 a woman made a pilgrimage to Tinos in order to fulfill a vow.¹ In and of itself, this was an event so common as hardly to be worthy of notice. This particular woman, however, was more famous than most of the pilgrims who come to Tinos. She was a former Olympic airline stewardess and former mistress (and now wife) of the recently defeated Socialist prime minister Andreas Papandreou. Their affair prior to Papandreou’s divorce from his American-born wife had received considerable attention in the press, and may have helped contribute to the downfall of the Socialist government.²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>In a Different Place</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>250</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In june 1993, I returned to Tinos for a short visit. Although I was in Greece for research purposes, 1 my trip to the island was not connected to this research. I had simply come to visit friends and to enjoy the island for a few days. I had, however, timed this visit for a particular event: the arrival of an Elderhostel boat at Tinos. One of the lecturers on the boat was a historian, George Moutafis, the husband of Vasiliki Galani-Moutafi, a Greek anthropologist who teaches at the University of the Aegean on Mitilini. When I had visited the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8nz.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
