<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2585.53 .R434 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Mark</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Redescribing the Gospel of Mark</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Crawford</surname>
               <given-names>Barry S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Miller</surname>
               <given-names>Merrill P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884142041</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884142034</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1qd8zmm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>A collaborative project with a variety of critical essays</italic>
         </p>
         <p>This final volume of studies by members of the Society of Biblical Literature's consultation, and later seminar, on Ancient Myths and Modern Theories of Christian Origins focuses on Mark. As with previous volumes, the provocative proposals on Christian origins offered by Burton L. Mack are tested by applying Jonathan Z. Smith's distinctive social theorizing and comparative method. Essays examine Mark as an author's writing in a book culture, a writing that responded to situations arising out of the first Roman-Judean war after the destruction of the Jerusalem temple in 70 CE. Contributors William E. Arnal, Barry S. Crawford, Burton L. Mack, Christopher R. Matthews, Merrill P. Miller, Jonathan Z. Smith, and Robyn Faith Walsh explore the southern Levant as a plausible provenance of the Gospel of Mark and provide a detailed analysis of the construction of Mark as a narrative composed without access to prior narrative sources about Jesus. A concluding retrospective follows the work of the seminar, its developing discourse and debates, and the continuing work of successor groups in the field.</p>
         <p>Features</p>
         <p>A thorough examination of the relation between structure and event in social and anthropological theory that provides conceptual tools for representing the project of the author of MarkAn exploration of the southern Levant as a plausible provenance of the Gospel, a permanent site of successive imperial regimes and culturally related peoplesA detailed analysis of the construction of Mark as a narrative composed without access to prior narrative sources about Jesus</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="708"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crawford</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is the third of a three-volume series of studies by members of the society of biblical literature’s consultation (1995–1997), then seminar (1998–2003), on ancient Myths and Modern Theories of christian origins, both concerned with redescribing the beginnings of christianity as religion, that is, with theories and methods developed in the social sciences and related areas for studying religious phenomena of various sorts and geographical locations, not just the specific literature, beliefs, and practices of early christians. The work of the consultation and seminar did not end, however, with the completion of the seminar’s term in 2003. Its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conjectures on Conjunctures and Other Matters:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Essays</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fieldwork, the distinctive procedural hallmark of the anthropological enterprise, became an unquestioned professional requirement during the decades of sociocultural anthropology’s “classical period,” roughly 1925 to 1960. for our purposes, the major consequence of this is a presentism characteristic of much ethnographic reporting: the society as observed at the time of the fieldworker’s interaction with it. While this presentism raises large conceptual questions,¹ its practical result with respect to theory was a strong bias against the historical in dominant approaches, whether the latter was functionalism or structuralism (to name but two, all but opposite options). in addition to reflecting contemporary practice,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Markan Site</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the various Oceanic specialists who have remarked on Marshall Sahlins’s work, Nicholas Thomas, at the Australian National University, is perhaps the most interesting, both in his particular studies, as represented by<italic>Entangled Objects: Exchange, Material Culture, and Colonialism in the Pacific</italic>, and in his more theoretical work,<italic>Out of Time: History and Evolution in Anthropological Discourse</italic>.¹ In the latter, Thomas develops the argument that Sahlins’s mechanisms of reproduction/transformation, which stress “the creative dynamics of the indigenous cultural scheme,” entail “a particular power relation which could exist only at a certain phase of colonial history, namely the period between initial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cartwheels:</title>
                     <subtitle>Or On Not Staying Upside Down Too Long</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mack</surname>
                           <given-names>Burton L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While i know that there are no originary events, no replications, that all moments of construal are reinterpretation or redescription of reinter-pretations and redescriptions, there are times when knowing the pre-remoments help in explaining the re-re-moments. This seems to be one of those pre-pre-re-re cases. What the seminar does not know, but I know full well, is that, trading letters, papers, phone calls, and memos with Jonathan Z. Smith in the course of what he has called receiving his “assignment” from the executive committee, has had me doing cartwheels all summer long. Willi braun has written to say that receiving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Smith, On Myth, On Mark</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arnal</surname>
                           <given-names>William E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is extraordinarily difficult to find a place from which to respond adequately to Jonathan Z. Smith’s tour de force on the ways in which Marshall Sahlins’s conceptual apparatus may assist the work of this seminar. I will, therefore, simply use Smith’s massive papers as a launching pad for some of my own concerns, without making the futile attempt to do these papers justice thereby.</p>
                     <p>Musings on the Role of Theory</p>
                     <p>As a preliminary matter, I note that i find myself increasingly ambivalent about the role of theory in the study of religion. On the one hand, I have long</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Markan Grapplings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matthews</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My agreement with the steering committee for this paper was to offer reflections on aspects of the other papers prepared for our sessions in Toronto. Both Burton L. Mack and William E. Arnal have responded in some detail to Jonathan Z. Smith’s extensive work that allows the seminar to conceptualize a theoretical grappling hook for the recovery of the “submerged” Markan situation. Mack’s and Arnal’s coverage of Smith’s contributions has allowed me the luxury of focusing on some of the issues that they have raised from my own perspective. I am in complete accord with Arnal’s sentiments, expressed at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Spyglass and the Kaleidoscope:</title>
                     <subtitle>From a Levantine Coign of Vantage</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mack</surname>
                           <given-names>Burton L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The meetings of the seminar on Ancient Myths and Modern Theories of Christian Origins, held in toronto, produced several challenges to our categories of social formation and mythmaking. We had asked Jonathan Z. Smith to consider the Levant as a social setting for the Gospel of Mark. Merrill P. Miller had<italic>Jesus and the Village Scribes</italic>¹ in mind, where William E. Arnal set the text of the Sayings Gospel Q aside while he worked out a social description of the Galilee as the setting into which Q could then be placed. So we asked Smith if something like that might</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Social Logic of the Gospel of Mark:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cultural Persistence and Social Escape in a Postwar Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Merrill P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This introduction is not intended as a summary of the ten sections of the main body of the paper to follow, though for convenience, given the length of the paper, I list the sections of the paper and their inclusive pages at the end of the introduction. Having completed the paper, it appeared to me that some of the theoretical and analytical influences on positions taken in the paper had not been sufficiently spelled out, in particular the problems of “ethnicity,” “identity,” and “community” as analytical terms. There were studies that had influenced my thinking in preparing the paper which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mark, War, and Creative Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arnal</surname>
                           <given-names>William E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel according to Mark, arguably, laid the framework for most subsequent understandings of Jesus and of the “movement” he allegedly instigated.¹ The predominant “ancient myth” with which our “modern theories” are struggling is thus precisely the one laid down by Mark. It receives fuller elaboration and extension forward in time in Luke-Acts, which in its turn offers a basis for Eusebius’s even more ambitious conceptualization.² But the narrative<italic>mode</italic>and the substantive implications of that mode—the view, in short, that Jesus is understood best in terms of his activity and particularly in terms of a series of sequential</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Q and the “Big Bang” Theory of Christian Origins</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walsh</surname>
                           <given-names>Robyn Faith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>483</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our earliest writings about Jesus are artifacts not only of the ancient Mediterranean but also of eighteenth-, nineteenth-, and twentieth-century thought.¹ Others, such as Wilfred Cantwell Smith, have made similar claims, noting that scholars of (so-called) Christian origins should approach their source material “not merely as a set of ancient documents or even as a first-and second-century product but as a third-century and twelfth-century and nineteenth-century and contemporary agent.”² This call for attention to hermeneutics and the inheritances of reception history presents a conceptual paradox. We are trained in the field to position these writings in their “original” context, that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Myths and Modern Theories of Christian Origins:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Consultation (1995–1997) and Seminar (1998–2003) in Retrospect with Attention to Successor Groups and a Recommendation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crawford</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Merrill P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>535</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction to<italic>Redescribing Christian Origins</italic>, the editors of the volume stated that the purpose of the project was both historical and theoretical: to redescribe the beginnings of christianity and contribute to the construction of a social theory of religion.¹ At the outset of these be inseparable from challenging the theory of religion, which continues to be presupposed and to support the dominant historical paradigm, characterized in short as the lukan-eusebian model of christian origins.²</p>
                     <p>The agreement of burton Mack and Jonathan Z. smith not merely to support a proposal to the society of biblical literature for a consultation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>575</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>647</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>649</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Modern Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>664</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zmm.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>672</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
