<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Restorative Christ</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Broughton</surname>
               <given-names>Geoff</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893798</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843441</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Geoff Broughton</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdvsk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The conviction that Jesus is the restorative Christ demands a commitment to the justice he articulated. The justice of the restorative Christ is justice with reconciliation, justice with repentance, justice with repair, and justice without retaliation. The Gospel of Luke and the book of Acts portray the life, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ through the radical concept of "enemy-love." In conversation with Dietrich Bonhoeffer (Jesus-for-others), John Howard Yoder (a nonviolent Jesus), Miroslav Volf (an embracing Jesus), and Chris Marshall (a compassionate Jesus), Broughton demonstrates what the restorative Christ means for us today. Following the restorative Christ faithfully involves imaginative disciplines (seeing, remembering, and desiring), conversational disciplines (naming, questioning, and forgiving), and embodied disciplines (absorbing, repairing, and embracing).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="202"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jusus and Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The city streets exhibit a peculiar justice. Poets, filmmakers and songwriters romanticize it, but many of those found at the margins of city life must live by it. It is an adversarial justice, often enacted violently. It is a world where “just desserts” are meted out with Old Testament severity. Occasionally this includes demanding a “ life for a life.” Security guards regulate access to many nightclubs and entertainment venues on the main strips. Cloistered inside the boardrooms and backrooms, albeit with slightly more sophistication, the same, adversarial justice reigns. Found amidst the rough justice of the alleyways, the clubs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Reconciliation or Justice?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rage. Insults. Honor. Revenge. Resistance. Restoration. Homer introduces these common—if complex—moments in relationships (both human and divine) in the opening of his classic myth,<italic>The Iliad</italic>. The thirst for justice and quest for reconciliation are as old as human storytelling itself. We have never grown tired of hearing stories of reconciliation and justice. Vince Gilligan, the creator of the award winning television series<italic>Breaking Bad</italic>wonders, “if there is no such thing as cosmic justice, what is the point of being good? That’s the one thing that no-one has ever explained to me. Why shouldn’t I go rob</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Justice without Retaliation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Victim</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The restorative Christ restores victims. The compassionate Jesus, according to Chris Marshall, offers restoration to both victim and wrongdoer because they are on a parallel journey. Does the “rule of compassion” deliver justice for both victim and wrongdoers? How can victims forgo retaliation—and the concomitant renunciation of violence—without denying their right to justice? Jesus’ command to “turn the other cheek” appears to invite the wrongdoer to further acts of aggression and violence. How might ordinary victims of everyday wrongs capture the imaginative vision of Gandhi or Martin Luther King? Or does their extraordinary example make justice without retaliation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interlude:</title>
                     <subtitle>JESUS’ DEATH AND JUSTICE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The restorative Christ absorbs the cost of repentance and repair, forgiveness and reconciliation in his death on the cross. The restorative Christ is the saving victim and<italic>merciful</italic>judge. Compassion and nonviolence are signatures of Jesus’ justice. The section provides the bridge from teaching of the compassionate Jesus, the life of the nonviolent Jesus, the death of Jesus-for-others and the risen life of the embracing Jesus.</p>
                     <p>The nonviolence of Jesus is a shared feature of all four theologians in this book. Each identifies and endorses Jesus’ commitment to nonviolence. It is more explicit in Marshall’s compassionate Jesus and Yoder’s nonviolent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Justice with Repentance:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Wrongdoer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was Saint Augustine who first used the Latin phrase incurvatus in se which means to be turned (or, literally “curved”) inward on oneself. It is a theological phrase used by other Christian thinkers like Martin Luther and Karl Barth to describe a life lived<italic>inward</italic>for self rather than<italic>outward</italic>for God and others. Wrongdoers, preoccupied with themselves, suffer from<italic>incurvatus in se</italic>. Examples abound in the accusations made against wrongdoers. They are selfish, self-centered or perhaps just self-absorbed. Such accusations elicit responses varying from self-defense, self-justification or sometimes self-condemnation. Some strategies that encourage wrongdoers in the art of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Justice with Repair:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To repair is to make amends. These simple words separate the justice that merely reconciles from the deeper justice of the restorative Christ. Repair describes the work of justice<italic>after</italic>reconciliation. The idea emerges from the restorative justice movement and the repair required in the aftermath of genocide in Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Bosnia, Cambodia, Liberia, and Uganda. Repair is partly symbolic because nothing—this side of heaven—can mend the atrocities witnessed in such countries during our own lifetime. Mass murder has become the weapon of choice for some regimes. Repair, however, must be pursued. It will be unusually costly.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Justice of the Restorative Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can the Anglican Church of Australia play its part in repairing the past injustices to Indigenous Australians? How might the restorative Christ make an appreciable difference? There are compelling reasons for wanting to avoid the complexities associated with achieving reconciliation and repair between Indigenous and non-Indigenous Australians. I am not Indigenous. I am an Anglican priest representing an institution with a history of misplaced presumptions and misguided policies in its dealings with Indigenous people. The practice of restorative justice among Indigenous Australians has not been uniformly welcomed or effective. The potential to repeat these mistakes of the past is ever-present.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvsk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
