<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN98.E36M38 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ecocriticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Materialism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ecology in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Environmental Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Material Ecocriticism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Iovino</surname>
               <given-names>Serenella</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Oppermann</surname>
               <given-names>Serpil</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253013958</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253014009</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025301400X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzq85"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Material Ecocriticism offers new ways to analyze language and reality, human and nonhuman life, mind and matter, without falling into well-worn paths of thinking. Bringing ecocriticism closer to the material turn, the contributions to this landmark volume focus on material forces and substances, the agency of things, processes, narratives and stories, and making meaning out of the world. This broad-ranging reflection on contemporary human experience and expression provokes new understandings of the planet to which we are intimately connected.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="376"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword:</title>
                     <subtitle>Storied Matter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey Jerome</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>A rock jumps</italic>. Every hiker has had the experience. The quiet woods or sweep of desert is empty and still when a snake that seemed a twig writhes, a skink that was bark scurries, leaves wriggle with insectile activity. This world coming to animal life reveals the elemental vibrancy already within green pine, arid sand, vagrant mist, and plodding hiker alike. When a toad that seemed a stone leaps into unexpected vivacity, its lively arc hints that rocks and toads share animacy, even if their movements unfold across vastly different temporalities. Just as the flitting hummingbird judges hiker and toad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stories Come to Matter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iovino</surname>
                           <given-names>Serenella</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Oppermann</surname>
                           <given-names>Serpil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An ancient Mediterranean landscape; an endangered species in the Amazon; the Library of Congress; the Gulf Stream; carcinogenic cells, DNA, dioxin; a volcano, a school, a city, a factory farm; the outbreak of a virus, a toxic plume; bio-luminescent water; your eyes, our hands, this book: what do all these things have in common? The answer to this question is simple. Whether visible or invisible, socialized or wild, they are all material forms emerging in combination with forces, agencies, and other matter. Entangled in endless ways, their “more-than-human” materiality is a constant process of shared becoming that tells us something</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>From Ecological Postmodernism to Material Ecocriticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Creative Materiality and Narrative Agency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Oppermann</surname>
                           <given-names>Serpil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The conception of physical reality within the framework of ecological postmodern thought and the nature of the material world described by quantum theory have recently been given new life by the emergence of the new materialist paradigm. The radical revisions of our ideas about the description of physical entities, chemical and biological processes, and their ethical, political, and cultural implications represented in recent discourses of feminist science studies, posthumanism, and the environmental humanities have also occasioned considerable interest among ecocritics, leading to the emergence of material ecocriticism. Proposing that we can read the world as matter endowed with stories, material</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Limits of Agency:</title>
                     <subtitle>Notes on the Material Turn from a Systems-Theoretical Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bergthaller</surname>
                           <given-names>Hannes</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If one had to choose an epigraph for the new materialisms, one could do worse than settle for the closing lines of<italic>The Order of Things.</italic>The new materialist thought takes as a given the “crumbling” of the conceptual foundations of modern humanism that Foucault anticipated; its intellectual project is a redescription of the world that dissolves the singular figure of the human subject, distinguished by unique properties (soul, reason, mind, free will, or intentionality), into the dense web of material relations in which all beings are enmeshed. This move cuts two ways. On the one hand, the new materialists</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Creative Matter and Creative Mind:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cultural Ecology and Literary Creativity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zapf</surname>
                           <given-names>Hubert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would like to focus in my chapter on the question of creativity, which after long neglect in literary and cultural studies is reemerging on the agenda of scholarship, especially within recent directions of ecocriticism. For a long time, the concept of creativity appeared to be inextricably bound up with a notion of radical individualism and of the quasi-godlike creative genius of the human mind, which seemed to represent a classic case of an anthropocentric metaphysics. In ecocritical perspective, however, creativity is beginning to newly move into the focus of attention not alone as an exclusionary feature of human culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Natural Play, Natural Metaphor, and Natural Stories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Biosemiotic Realism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wheeler</surname>
                           <given-names>Wendy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As philosopher Thomas Nagel writes in his 2012 book,<italic>Mind and Cosmos: Why the Materialist NeoDarwinian Conception of Nature Is Almost Certainly False,</italic>the three-hundred-year grip of materialism and reductionism in evolutionary biology seems to be weakening. Not only is this—Nagel calls it “physico-chemical reductionism in biology” (5)—because the ability of such a widely held position convincingly to explain the evolution of mind from physico-chemical nature has failed, but it is also because the difference between “ontological dependence upon” and “reduction to” has in recent years been addressed by the concept of emergence, or emergent features in complex</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Ecology of Colors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Goethe’s Materialist Optics and Ecological Posthumanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                           <given-names>Heather I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The primary goal of this chapter is to unsettle our basic assumptions regarding nature as a “place” separate from the human realm and to posit it instead as natural-cultural processes continually occurring<italic>all around, through,</italic>and<italic>in us.</italic>With the ecology of colors, I therefore explore nature in terms of dynamic material and informational exchanges. There is no doubt that the scenic places traditionally viewed as “nature” are rapidly being transformed—destroyed, developed, logged, mined, polluted. Yet bounded<italic>places</italic>are not the trope here. Instead, nature is unbounded by material ecocriticism and reconfigured in an inclusive, naturalcultural sense of energy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Bodies of Naples:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stories, Matter, and the Landscapes of Porosity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iovino</surname>
                           <given-names>Serenella</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the heart of the city of Naples there is a place with a curious name: Largo Corpo di Napoli. This little square opens up like an oyster at a point where the<italic>decumani,</italic>the Greek main streets, become a tangle of narrow medieval lanes and heavy gray-and-white buildings. Like an oyster, this square has a pearl: an ancient statue of the Nile, popularly known as<italic>Corpo di Napoli,</italic>the body of Naples. The story of this statue is peculiar. Dating back to the sec ond or third century, when it was erected to mark the presence of an Egyptian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>When It Rains:</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duckert</surname>
                           <given-names>Lowell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Responding to his country’s record rainfalls in the beginning of the twenty-first century, British journalist Brian Cathcart seems to bring more of it.<italic>Rain</italic>makes a dreary forecast: “It is only when things go wrong that our dim consciousness of scientific meteorology rises to the surface” (66). French sociologist of science Bruno Latour would diagnose this tendency as “blackboxing.” Focusing only on the success of a scientific or technological apparatus paradoxically renders “the joint production of actors and artifacts entirely opaque” (<italic>Hope 183</italic>).¹ When a meteorology machine runs smoothly, it produces factual climates that we can reasonably predict and accurately</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Painful Material Realities, Tragedy, Ecophobia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Estok</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The biological, chemical, and material bases of human ontology constitute central sites of investigation and theoretical comment for material ecocriticisms. If we understand pain as a fundamental part of human ontology, then we must also understand that<italic>theorizing matter</italic>profits from understanding the importance of relationships among cultural representations of pain, matter, and environment. Building on “a field that defines itself by a neologism (<italic>ecocriticism</italic>), based on another neologism (<italic>ecology</italic>)” (7), as Middlebury Shakespearean ecocritic Dan Brayton has recently described ecocriticism, material ecocriticisms seek both to further complicate and to further define what it is that ecocriticism pursues and how.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Semiotization of Matter:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Hybrid Zone between Biosemiotics and Material Ecocriticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maran</surname>
                           <given-names>Timo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A basic claim of the newly developing field of material ecocriticism appears to be that matter has agency and embodied meanings and that it is possible to decipher this matter in the framework of textual criticism. As Serenella Iovino has put it in her<italic>ISLE</italic>introductory essay on material ecocriticism, “The ‘material turn’ is the search for new conceptual models apt to theorize the connections between matter and agency on the one side, and the intertwining of bodies, natures, and meanings on the other side” (“Stories” 450). Material ecocriticism, she continues, “comes from the idea that it is possible to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Pro/Polis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Forays into the Political Lives of Bees</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sandilands</surname>
                           <given-names>Catriona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his essay “Ten Theses on Politics,” Jacques Rancière writes that politics is a specific mode of action with its own rationality: politics is neither the general exercise of power nor the specific capacity of a select group of individuals to rule, but is instead fundamentally concerned with the constitution of a particular kind of subject of ruling, one “that is at once the agent of an action and the matter upon which that action is exercised” (<italic>Dissensus 29</italic>). The political ubject, here, is only possible on the assumption of equality. To partake in the paradox of<italic>simultaneously</italic>ruling and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Excremental Ecocriticism and the Global Sanitation Crisis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Phillips</surname>
                           <given-names>Dana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>New materialists are fond of lists. Consider, as a first example, the beginning of Myra Hird’s 2009 review essay on “material feminism”: “Trans-corporeality. Entanglement. Meeting-with. Matter. Nonhuman. Causality. Intra-action. Disclosure. Agential realism.” Each of the terms on this list names a concept central to the “emerging field” Hird is preparing to survey (329). Most of them have come to occupy an equally important position in the discourse of new materialist theory broadly speaking, which draws on material feminism but also taps additional sources, such as phenomenology and the philosophy of science, for ideas.</p>
                     <p>Some new materialist list makers are evidently</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Oceanic Origins, Plastic Activism, and New Materialism at Sea</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alaimo</surname>
                           <given-names>Stacy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Climate change. Ocean acidification. Dead zones. Oil “spills.” Industrial fishing, overfishing, trawling, long lines, shark finning. Bycatch, bykill. Ghost nets. Deep-sea mining. Habitat destruction. Dumping. Radioactive, plastic, and microplastic pollution. Ecosys tem collapse. Extinction. The state of the oceans is dire. The destruction of marine environments is painful to contemplate and tempting to ignore. Having returned from a week on the Gulf of Mexico, where sea life was sparse, I could hardly bear to read Callum Roberts’s<italic>The Unnatural History of the Sea,</italic>which describes the staggering abundance of fish and mammals that once inhabited the oceans. Roberts argues that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Meditations on Natural Worlds, Disabled Bodies, and a Politics of Cure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clare</surname>
                           <given-names>Eli</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>You and I walk in the summer rain through a thirty-acre pocket of tallgrass prairie that was, not so long ago, one big cornfield. We follow the path mowed as a firebreak. You carry a big pink umbrella. Water droplets hang on the grasses. Spiderwebs glint. The bee balm hasn’t blossomed yet. You point to numerous patches of birch and goldenrod; they belong here but not in this plenty. The thistle, on the other hand, simply shouldn’t be here. The Canada wild rye waves, the big bluestem almost open. Sunflowers cluster, spots of yellow orange amid the gray green of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Corporeal Fieldwork and Risky Art:</title>
                     <subtitle>Peter Goin and the Making of Nuclear Landscapes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glotfelty</surname>
                           <given-names>Cheryll</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may go without saying that a landscape photographer must do fieldwork. How can you take a picture of a place without being there? But this very presumption of physical presence tends to obscure the role of fieldwork in landscape photo graphy, a process that resonates strongly with the material turn in ecocritical theory. Photographer Peter Goin (b. 1951) has devoted more than thirty years to photographing altered landscapes in America, documenting the legacy of human actions on the land. Author of more than a dozen books and recipient of numerous awards, including two National Endowment for the Arts fellowships,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Of Material Sympathies, Paracelsus, and Whitman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bennett</surname>
                           <given-names>Jane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paracelsus (1493–1541) experienced the natural world as a complex order of sympathies, resonances, magnetic attractions, and analogies (Pagel 52).¹ Though Paracelsus is variously categorized as physician, philosopher, alchemist, herbalist, I like to think of him as a plant physiognomist, as, that is, a practitioner of the art of discovering temperament and character from outward appearance. Each natural object bore for him a divine “signature” encoded in the thing’s shape, smell, texture, color, posture. This equivocal sign served as a spur to the human perceiver to engage in the artistry—the speculative thinking and practical experimentation—that would give determinacy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Source of Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Avatar, Amazonia, and an Ecology of Selves</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adamson</surname>
                           <given-names>Joni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of the eighteenth century, German intellectual and scientist Alexander von Humboldt traveled to the Amazon. Later, back in Europe, the publication of his five-volume<italic>Cosmos</italic>would influence a generation of thinkers on several continents. Today, his work still resonates strongly among scholars who are studying “the material interactions of bodies and natures” (Iovino and Oppermann, “Material” 77). According to Laura Dassow Walls, who describes the impact of his journey on both the sciences and the aesthetics of the Americas in her book A Passage to Cosmos, Humboldt considered “nature” as “a planetary interactive causal network operating across</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Liminal Space between Things:</title>
                     <subtitle>Epiphany and the Physical</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morton</surname>
                           <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this essay comes from Marcia Carter, my administrator in my new position at Rice University. She was recommending that I go to see the opening of the James Turrell piece, called<italic>Twilight Epiphany,</italic>installed at Rice and opened on June 14, 2012. Marcia said that what was valuable about Turrell was his understanding of how “art happens in the liminal space between things.” As we proceed, we shall see that it is a deeply appropriate way to think about poems as relationships between beings—and indeed<italic>relationship as such,</italic>which here is understood to encompass causality, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Spirits That Matter:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pathways toward a Rematerialization of Religion and Spirituality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rigby</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In entitling my contribution to this postscript “Spirits That Matter” (with thanks to the editors for their inspired suggestion), my intention is not to oppose something immaterial called “spirit” to the materiality of “the body,” as might be implied for those readers who hear in this phrase an allusion to Judith Butler’s influential<italic>Bodies That Matter.</italic>On the contrary: my implied divergence from Butler moves, rather (in company with other new materialists), in the direction of a more thoroughgoing materialism than that which is entailed in Butler’s discursive constructivism. As Karen Barad has observed, Butler’s model of discursive performativity accords</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Mindful New Materialisms:</title>
                     <subtitle>Buddhist Roots for Material Ecocriticism’s Flourishing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaard</surname>
                           <given-names>Greta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is Saturday-morning yoga class at the Minneapolis Midtown YWCA. A diverse group of practitioners assembles, varying in ages, genders, classes, races, sexualities, and nationalities, all gathered to practice an hour of mindful yoga. In Pali (the language of the Buddha), “yoga” means “to join” or “to unite,” and its practice involves joining attention to movements involving the body, the breath, the mind, and the larger interconnectedness of all beings. We begin with sun salutation and end in a position familiar to those who have seen the most common depictions of the Buddha, seated in yogic meditation. Joining body ecology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Commonwealth of Breath</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abram</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gusting the tops of small waves, a wind carrying salt spray collides with another thick with tree pollen; edges of both merge with a breeze plucking lichen spores from the surface of rocks as it rides up the hill where I sit, high above the coast, gazing at a far-off tanker filled with tar sands crude. Behind me another breeze lingers at the forest edge, spiced by truck exhaust and the reek from two oyster shells broken open by a raven. I breathe in, and all those unseen currents converge, pollen and petrol fumes flooding up through my nostrils (tweaking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzq85.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
