<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442674455</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HD59.3.R87 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Advocacy advertising</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Advocacy advertising</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Television advertising</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Television advertising</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Advertising, Public service</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Advertising, Public service</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Marketing &amp; Advertising</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Endless Propaganda</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Advertising of Public Goods</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RUTHERFORD</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780802083012</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442674455</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press Incorporated</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442674455"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Rutherford shows how politics, social behaviour, and public morals have become subject to the philosophy and discipline of marketing.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="400"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF FIGURES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUTHERFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustration Credits</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Advertising as Propaganda</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The little messages are scattered all over our memories.</p>
                     <p>Consider these incidents from life in and around big cities during the nineteen-nineties. The walls of London subway stations one summer day in 1994 sport a poignant plea to help find a cure for multiple sclerosis. An electronic sign on a highway to Florence (August 1998) urges Italians not to abandon their pets; street posters in Paris (also August 1998) tell walkers, in English, ‘Better off alive with it than dead without it,’ referring to a condom. The advertisements in a Toronto subway car call upon riders to get involved with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART I: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Habermas defined the problem. Or, rather, his book on the public sphere did. Jürgen Habermas matured in the Marxist tradition of western Europe, specifically that associated with the Frankfurt School of Critical Theory (he once referred to himself, a bit ruefully, as feeling like ‘the last Marxist’).² By then (1989), Habermas as philosopher had moved far away from any recognizable Marxism to articulate a vision of an egalitarian order that rested upon the act of speech. His heresy was apparent early on. He wrote a postdoctoral thesis, rejected by his Marxist supervisors, that became<italic>The Structural Transformation of the Public</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Imperialism of the Market:</title>
                     <subtitle>The United States, 1940–1970</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1943, so the story goes, an English visitor was struck by the signs of ‘normality’ everywhere as he flew over the state of Nebraska – ‘hundreds of miles of it and not a sight or sound to remind one that this was a country at war.’ But when his lunch arrived, he received a small jolt: there, stamped on his pat of butter, was the command, ‘REMEMBER PEARL HARBOR.’ ‘Of course they knew there was a war on,’ commented George Will. ‘However, Americans believe that a bit of advertising never hurts.’¹</p>
                     <p>The term ‘market revival’ featured</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At bottom, ‘hegemony’ means rule via persuasion. But its articulation is much more complex than such a modest formulation suggests. For hegemony is grounded upon an apparent contradiction between inequality and consent. And the very process of securing consent conjures up the spectre of conspiracy.</p>
                     <p>We owe the concept of hegemony to the<italic>Prison Notebooks</italic>of Antonio Gramsci (1891–1937), an Italian Communist leader who produced a formidable body of writings during the many years he was incarcerated by the Fascist regime.² The<italic>Prison Notebooks</italic>were no ordinary collection. They included thoughts, notations, drafts of essays, reconsiderations, musings, much of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Restoring Order:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nixon’s America, Etcetera</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The authoritarian menace of the ad is obvious. ‘THIS TIME VOTE LIKE YOUR WHOLE WORLD DEPENDED ON IT’ – that apocalyptic slogan appeared on many a Nixon spot. The Republicans were trying to promote and exploit fear among ordinary Americans. Angry youth, the New Left, violence in the streets, riots and lootings, all were presented as signs of the breakdown of law and order.</p>
                     <p>In fact these were symptoms of a hegemony in trouble, a crisis but not a collapse of legitimacy (there never was a revolutionary moment), because the prevailing élites were no longer able to negotiate differences effectively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Governing Affluence:</title>
                     <subtitle>The First World in the Seventies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Searching</italic>(1975) was an instance of shock advertising, sponsored by the British government, probably appearing courtesy of its Central Office of Information (COI). What the Americans had started spread to other parts of the advanced world (and sometime s beyond) in the course of the 1970s. There were differences. Corporate advocacy never reached the same proportions outside of the United States, though by the early 1980s it was sufficiently prominent in Canada to justify a special public affairs conference of luminaries from business, government, and academe.² Britain prohibited the brand of broadcast political advertising that the United States had come to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART III: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the moment of his death, the philosopher-historian Michel Foucault (1926–84) was the premier theorist, at least in the western world, of those human sciences he had so often criticized.¹ His books, essays, lectures, interviews, and musings, many published or republished in a variety of editions and collections after he died, had challenged orthodoxies, fostered controversy, and inspired innovation in a range of disciplines.² There was a quality of the perverse about his views: he seemed to delight in arguing the contrary. The past became a topsy-turvy realm where that bright march of progress might now be revealed as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Healthy Bodies, or the New Paranoia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consider this litany of alarm. Smoking now kills more than ‘3 million people per year.’ Since 1950 cigarettes and the like have brought death to ‘more than 60 million people in developed countries alone.’ Tobacco use produces ‘a global net loss of U.S.$ 200 billion per year.’ In three or four decades the death rate should hit ‘10 million per year.’ These estimates came from a Web site of the World Health Organization (WHO) devoted to promoting World No-Tobacco Day, 31 May 1997. They justified the director’s declaring ‘a global public health emergency,’ and calling on governments and activists worldwide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Charitable Souls:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Practice of Altruism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These are no ordinary children. You can find them looking out from posters and billboards, in the pages of newspapers and magazines, sometimes on movie screens and on television. They may be infants or teens, a boy or a girl, with different skin colours, and of any age up to about twenty. They can be forlorn, injured, starving, abused, neglected, frightened, disturbed, expectant, hopeful, happy, or sometimes thankful. They do share one characteristic: they are disadvantaged – by race, class, gender, health, situation, or other circumstances. They are meant as objects of pity. They plead with us – as caring</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Administered Minds, or Shaming the Citizenry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only in Singapore? Not so.<italic>Smile</italic>typified a common brand of propaganda – call it ‘administrative advertising’ – used throughout the affluent world of the 1980s and 1990s. It was part of a much wider effort at social engineering in which marketing was only one tool (legislation was equally, if not more, important) used in efforts to program affluent populations. Authorities, and not just the state, set out to construct or reconstruct the citizen – his behaviour, her attitudes, their conducts – in way that suited some purpose or agenda. That priority inspired an assault upon the personal – or,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Appropriations:</title>
                     <subtitle>Benetton and Others</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A defining attribute of culture at the end of the twentieth century is the appeal of the eclectic, a penchant for hybrids, fusions,<italic>bricolage</italic>. And this attribute of the culture is reflected in its advertising. Consider events in the United States, always the home of experiment, in 1997 and 1998: the federal government adopted paid PSAs (for the census and for anti-drug campaigns), the Ad Council agreed to tailor PSAs to the network’s promotional efforts, the Arthritis Foundation turned to an ad-supported infomercial to raise funds, and the Children’s Television Network (purveyors of<italic>Sesame Street</italic>) proudly announced a new initiative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART IV: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Arthur Herman has coined the term ‘declinism’ to refer to a species of deep pessimism that represents the West as horribly flawed, in a state of severe decay, usually on the edge of catastrophe. That radical doubt he finds pervasive nowadays and in the recent past. ‘We live in an era in which pessimism has become the norm, rather than the exception.’¹ Perhaps so, especially in circles frequented by the best educated. Herman cites a considerable range of thinkers, profound or otherwise, who believe things are getting worse, and getting worse rapidly.² But what Herman does not consider is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Technopia and Other Corporate Dreams</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Let’s Make Things Better.’ So announced Philips, the transnational electronics giant, in a new global ad campaign launched in September 1995. The company explained how the theme and slogan were a far better representation of its purposes than the more obvious brag, ‘We make better things.’¹ In fact, the statement was pathetic: bland, vague, and hackneyed. No wonder it fostered an initial flurry of boring ads which featured a smiling employee saying trite things to magazine readers. More interesting than Philips’s lack of inspiration was its commitment of time and funds to this kind of image campaign. Here it followed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Green Nightmares:</title>
                     <subtitle>Humanity versus Nature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Exit technopia. Exit the Land of Cockaigne, as well. This is an example, albeit one of the more extreme versions, of a genre of civic advocacy I call ‘green nightmares.’ Here is a very different realm, where technology threatens the survival of humanity. Risks abound. ‘Progress’ is a sinister word that signifies not improvement but its reverse. The obsession with private goods fosters social risks: masses of garbage, devastating explosions, air and water pollution, ozone depletion, toxicity, cruelty to animals, and species extinctions. Standing against the tide are the greens, the champions of the environment and the animals. Especially in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART V: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Foucault was wrong. Not completely wrong, because ‘the panoptic machine’ certainly did work to discipline the individual, but wrong about spectacle, a power which has waxed greatly in the twentieth century. Understanding why and how requires a quick tour through both theory and history.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Discipline and Punish</italic>opened with a gripping discussion of premodern publicity, including ‘the spectacle of the scaffold’ (32)² where punishment was enacted on the body of the criminal to reaffirm the authority of the sovereign. This account was a gruesome exploration of the ways in which, as Jürgen Habermas argued, lordship represented its publicness in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>When Politics Becomes Advertising:</title>
                     <subtitle>The American Scene</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In November 1996, by one measure, the United States dropped out of the list of mass democracies. The incumbent president, Bill Clinton, had won easily over the Republican challenger, Bob Dole. But the real land slide was the non-vote against the two contestants: less than half of the voting-age population cast a ballot for president.¹ In off years voter turnout was even worse: less than 40 per cent of the same population brought about the ‘Republican revolution’ of 1994 that transformed the partisan complexion of the Congress. Such dismal totals take us back to Jürgen Habermas, who counted the level</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Postmodern Democracy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The poster was by Barbara Kruger, a radical, a feminist, a film critic, and an artist already well known for her unusual presentations of social and political dissent. The next year that image would appear in an art book entitled<italic>Love for Sale</italic>, published by Abrams, further evidence of Kruger’s stature. During the 1980s and 1990s she has had exhibitions throughout the United States, in western Europe, and in Australia and New Zealand. Kruger was trained in the graphic arts and worked, in the 1970s, at Condé Nast Publications. One source of her inspiration was feminism. Another was French theory,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442674455.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
