<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Scripture to Hear God</book-title>
         <subtitle>Kevin Vanhoozer and Henri de Lubac on God's Use of Scripture in the Economy of Redemption</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Storer</surname>
               <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175316</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227904695</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Kevin Storer</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgfbb2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Recent theological discussions between Catholics and Evangelicals have generated a renewed appreciation for God's ongoing use of Scripture for self-mediation to the Church. Noting the significant influence of Henri de Lubac (one of the drafters of 'Dei Verbum' and proponent of a renewal of the Patristic and Medieval emphasis on a spiritual sense of Scripture), and Kevin Vanhoozer (the leading Evangelical proponent of a theological interpretation of Scripture), Kevin Storer seeks to draw Evangelical and Catholic theologians into dialogue about God's ongoing use of Scripture in the economy of redemption. Storer suggests that a number of traditional tensions between Catholics and Evangelicals, such as the literal or spiritual sense of Scripture, a sacramental or a covenantal model of God's self-mediation, and an emphasis on the authority of Scripture or the authority of the Church, can be eased by shifting greater focus upon God's ongoing use of creaturely realities for the building of the Church in union with Christ. This project seeks to enable Evangelicals to appropriate the insights of de Lubac's Catholic Ressourcement project, while also encouraging Catholic theologians to appreciate Vanhoozer's Evangelical emphasis on God's use of the literal sense of Scripture to build the Church.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="186"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Theological Interpretation of Scripture and the Opportunity for Evangelical and Catholic Dialogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the past several decades, the theological interpretation of Scripture has emerged as an identifiable discipline within systematic theology.¹ The theological interpretation of Scripture emerged as an attempt to bridge the ugly ditch between biblical studies and systematic theology which has been dug since the Enlightenment. In response to this modernist divorce between theological disciplines, the theological interpretation of Scripture attempts to explain how Scripture functions as the “soul of sacred theology,” by articulating how Scripture operates as a locus of God’s ongoing self-communicative action, and why scriptural reading must be primarily an activity performed by the church and for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>God’s Use of Scripture for Self-Communication:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Speaking in the Literal and Spiritual Sense</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On first read, Vanhoozer and de Lubac would seem a most unfit choice of dialogue partners of the topic of God’s use of Scripture. Vanhoozer insists on the sufficiency of the literal sense, while de Lubac insists on the indispensability of the spiritual sense. Vanhoozer develops an elaborate proposal for God’s authorship based on speech-act theory, while de Lubac largely ignores divine authorship and instead focuses attention on God’s sacramental presence in Scripture. Vanhoozer focuses on Scripture’s determinate meaning, while de Lubac focuses on Scripture’s infinite meaning. Yet what the two have in common is their persistent emphasis on God’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Vanhoozer’s Covenantal Ontology and de Lubac’s Sacramental Ontology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Different Models of Christ’s Self-Mediation in the Economy of Redemption</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter we examined the way in which Vanhoozer and de Lubac both seek to show that God’s use of Scripture is the foundational norm for all subsequent hermeneutical reflection. God’s use of precisely this collection of texts for self-mediation to readers is what makes Scripture unique, and all rules for reading should be developed from this assumption.Vanhoozer’s understanding of God’s speaking action through a clear, determinate canonical sense of Scripture, and de Lubac’s understanding of God’s speaking action through a three-fold spiritual sense of Scripture both arise from the same desire to articulate God’s present speaking action</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>God’s Use of Scripture and Church in the Economy of Redemption</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter we saw that Vanhoozer envisions God’s communicative action taking covenantal form in the Scriptures which mediate Christ to the church. We also saw that de Lubac envisions Christ’s self-communication taking sacramental form in Scripture, church, and Eucharist, so that each builds the other sacramental realities. Without leaving the discussion of ontology aside, this chapter will focus specifi-cally on the relationship between Scripture and church in the economy of redemption. The relationship between Scripture and church has been a significant issue in Catholic and Protestant interpretations of Scripture, and it remains the area of greatest disagreement between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The cumulative argument of this book has been that a much greater similarity between Vanhoozer and de Lubac (and hence between much Evangelical and Catholic theological interpretation of Scripture) can be seen when explicit focus is placed upon God’s use of Scripture and church in the economy of redemption. I have argued that Vanhoozer’s development of an economy of communication is very similar to de Lubac’s development of a sacramental ontology, as both insist on God’s ongoing self-mediation through Scripture, both develop an understanding of scriptural meaning which requires participation and which emerges in the whole economy of redemption, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbb2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Backmatter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
