<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Archaeology</subject>
         <subject>Psychology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In the Fellowship of His Suffering</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Theological Interpretation of Mental Illness — A Focus on "Schizophrenia"</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hessamfar</surname>
               <given-names>Elahe</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Swinton</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843472</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Elahe Hessamfar</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cg4kgg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Schizophrenia is often considered one of the most destructive forms of mental illness. Elahe Hessamfar’s personal experience with her daughter’s illness has led her to ask some pressing and significant questions about the cause and nature of schizophrenia and the Church’s role in its treatment. With a candid and revealing look at the history of mental illness, In the Fellowship of His Suffering describes schizophrenia as a variation of human expression. Hessamfar uses a deeply theological rather than pathological approach to interpret the schizophrenic experience and the effect it has on both the patients and their families. Effectively drawing on the Bible as a source of knowledge for understanding mental illness, she offers a reflective yet innovative view of whether the Church could or should intervene in such encounters and what such an intervention might look like. Hessamfar’s comprehensive work will provoke powerful responses from anyone interested in the prominent social issue of mental illness. Her portrayal of the raging debate between treating “insanity" either pastorally or medically will enthral readers, be they Christians, medical students or those in the field of psychiatry and social sciences.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="388"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swinton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world of mental health and illness is a strange place. It is strange, not because people are strange, but because it is essentially mysterious. What exactly do we mean by mental illness? How can a mind be ill? Indeed, how can something immaterial be either broken or mended? It is clear that whatever mental illness is, it is not the same as measles or influenza. It may be that some claim to have tracked down biological, neurological, or genetic causes for our psychological disturbances. But such explanations, whilst arguably telling us from where such experiences come from, do little</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hessamfar</surname>
                           <given-names>Elahe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ubiquity of mental illness and its exponential growth in the US has made it the primary “medical disability” of our time. This pervasiveness and the destructive force behind it to destroy human spirit demands an urgent attention not only from medical community and social policy makers, but also from the church. In the history of Christian communities, mental illness has tended to be viewed as some form of malignant manifestation that stands against the will and rule of God. It has thus tended to evoke a response from within the church. Today, for the most part, that response has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Theological Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we will lay down our anthropological foundation, which will shape our analysis of mental illness as a human phenomenon. Throughout history man has been an enigma, and a paradox, not only in the pages of Scripture, but also to himself and his fellow human beings. Although there have been many studies on every detail of a human’s life concerning his social, psychological, economical, political, physiological, and cultural status in life, one seemingly trivial question that has puzzled philosophers, scientists, and laymen alike, driving the fundamental answer to all aforementioned categories, is<italic>What is a human being?</italic>The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Historical Contexts of Psychiatry and Mental Illness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we will begin to develop a rich<italic>situational</italic>perspective to further our investigation. In order to grasp the reality behind the phenomenon of mental illness, we need to contextualize it within its historical framework and understand why and how it is culturally perceived, and how that perception has influenced the treatment options. What are the historical and political dimensions of this phenomenon? Who is benefiting from it, and who are the victims? What are the real barriers to recovery? Situations, including illness, never happen in abstraction; they always happen in a context and have different forces affecting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Theology of Illness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we evaluated the burgeoning psychiatric research to get a handle on the medical framing of madness. Our evaluation left us wanting. We realized that science with all its claims has yet to conquer the stunning complexities of this phenomenon. I argued, based on a variety of research findings, that “schizophrenia” should be regarded as a variation of human expression, rather than as pathology.² To unravel the mystery of madness as a human phenomenon, I suggest that we need to shift our paradigm of understanding and appeal to biblical revelation for illumination. The broken voices of sufferers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Path Forward:</title>
                     <subtitle>Healing Together</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, I argued that illnesses are not purely meaningless biological phenomena. Particularly, with regards to mental illness (an area where medical science has been severely challenged to offer satisfactory explanations of the experience), the voice of illness ought to be heard in the context of the sufferer’s community. In reference to a psychotic experience Aderhold et al., remind us that, “It is not the psychosis—whatever this might be—that is being treated, but a human being in the midst of an altered experience” who should be “supported and accompanied, realizing that each individual is very different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this study we observed that the experiences of those suffering from mental illness call into question our collective Western understanding of these phenomena. Historically, how the experiences are named determined the types of treatment that were deemed to be appropriate. The church has participated in this process, but laterally, the naming, framing and responding to those experiences have become the terrain of psychiatry. Psychiatry has a questionable history and has been the location for various political, economic, and professional power struggles as the discipline has developed and has sought to offer a rationale for its existence.</p>
                     <p>The twentieth century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4kgg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>334</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
