<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8m3</collection-id>
      <volume>228</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PL247I.Z6M27 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Confucius. Lun yu</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Transmitters and Creators</book-title>
         <subtitle>Chinese Commentators and Commentaries on the Analects</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Makeham</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674012165</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684173907</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684173906</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tg5j9s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Analects (Lunyu) is one of the most influential texts in human history. As a putative record of Confucius’s (551–479 B.C.E.) teachings and a foundational text in scriptural Confucianism, this classic was instrumental in shaping intellectual traditions in China and East Asia until the early twentieth century. But no premodern reader read only the text of the Analects itself. Rather, the Analects was embedded in a web of interpretation that mediated its meaning. Modern interpreters of the Analects only rarely acknowledge this legacy of two thousand years of commentaries. How well do we understand prominent or key commentaries from this tradition? How often do we read such commentaries as we might read the text on which they comment? Many commentaries do more than simply comment on a text. Not only do they shape the reading of the text, but passages of text serve as pretexts for the commentator to develop and expound his own body of thought. This book attempts to redress our neglect of commentaries by analyzing four key works dating from the late second century to the mid-nineteenth century (a period substantially contemporaneous with the rise and decline of scriptural Confucianism): the commentaries of He Yan (ca. 190–249); Huang Kan (488–545); Zhu Xi (1130–1200); and Liu Baonan (1791–1855) and Liu Gongmian (1821–1880).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="484"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conventions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Analects</italic>(<italic>Lunryu</italic>論語) is one of the most influential texts in human history. As a putative record of Confucius’ (551–479 B.C.) teachings, for the past two thousand years authoritative interpretations of this classic were instrumental in shaping the orientation of an array of intellectual traditions in China and, more generally, East Asia. Together with the other core texts of the classical corpus, the<italic>Analects</italic>has functioned as a key point of reference for inquiry, debate, and conilict within the traditions of classical scholarship and for the political and social institutions that sought ideological grounding in this scholarship. Whether</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>He Yan, Authorship, and Xuanxtie Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Collected Explanations of the Analects (hereafter Collected Explanations)</italic>¹ is a corporate work of unusual importance and complexity. It is important because it is the representative writing of the “old commentary” tradition of the Analects, as opposed to the “new commentary” tradition represented by Zhu Xi’s Collected Annotations on the Analects. Collected Explanations preserves a selection of some of the earliest commentaries ever written for the Analects, including substantial selections attributed to two of the earliest commentators, Kong Anguo and Bao Xian 包咸 (6 B.C.–A.D. 65).² Although Zheng Xuan was arguably the single most influential commentator between the Han and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Innovation As / Through Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I argue that the editors of the<italic>Collected Explanations</italic>sought to present that commentary as a performative expression of Confucius’ claim to have been a transmitter rather than a creator; by ostensibly venturing no interpretation of their own, they exercised a degree of hermeneuticallatitude unknown to previous commentators. I examine their strategies of commentarial control, their unique apologist portrayal of Confucius in response to Zheng Xuan’s depiction of him as human and fallible, their use of the Kong Anguo commentary to challenge Sima Qian’s authority, and their attempts to secure a cosmological grounding for Confucius as sage.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Huang Kan and the Shu Genre</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the late Han to late<italic>Tang, Mr. Zheng’s Annotations on the Analects</italic>and<italic>Collected Explanations if the Analects</italic>remained the two most influential<italic>Analects</italic>commentaries. Although a number of other commentaries were written during this seven-century period, virtually none remains extant. The subject of Part II is a commentary written during this period that is extant, thanks to its continued transmission in Japan (and eventual reintroduction into China during the Qing period): Huang Kan’s<italic>Elucidation if the Meaning if the Analects. Elucidation if the Meaning</italic>is one of the earliest known examples of the<italic>shu</italic>疏, or subcommentary, genre</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Philosophical Character of Elucidation of the Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Freed from the constraints imposed by the “closed system” that had been both the sustainer and the stifler of much Han classical scholarship, thinkers increasingly used the commentary as a vehicle for expressing individual thought from the early third century on. Although all interpretation can be considered a creative act,¹ when a commentary introduces a philosophical platform or series of platforms that are foreign to or undeveloped in the original text, it becomes more than an appendage to another body of writing and a work in its own right. Some of the more prominent examples of this written in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Buddhist and Institutional Influences on Huang’s Thought Buddhism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My interpretation in the two previous chapters of Huang’s<italic>shu</italic>commentary is drawn substantially from evidence internal to that commentary. I have attempted to show that it can be read as an integrated philosophical statement grounded in a theory of hierarchically differentiated grades of human nature. Where possible, I have also attempted to indicate the influence of earlier thinkers on Huang’s thought. Particularly important in this regard are Wang Chong, Wang Bi, and Xiang Xiu and Guo Xiang. What remains to be addressed is the matter of influences or shared discourses that are less readily identifiable because they are not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Zhu Xi, Commentary and the Analects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This part introduces and analyzes the philosophical import of Zhu Xi’s<italic>Collected Annotations on the Analects</italic>(hereafter,<italic>Collected Annotations</italic>). This opening chapter provides some social, institutional, and historical contexts for Zhu Xi and his commentary. The main topics are the<italic>daoxue</italic>(learning of the way) fraternity; the new textual hermeneutics developed in the Song dynasty; Zhu’s concept of<italic>daotong</italic>(interconnecting thread of the way); the Four Books as an alternative canon and the place of the Analects within that canon; Zhu’s attitude toward earlier commentaries; and his tactics for overcoming historical distance. Chapter 7 examines Zhu Xi’s hermeneutics of reading,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Zhu Xi on Learning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I examine three topics relating to Zhu Xi’s views on learning: his hermeneutics of reading; learning and human nature; and the learning of the sage. For Zhu Xi, reading is an exemplary form of learning. Most immediately, the aim of learning is to discover the authorial intention/meaning imparted by the words of former sages. To this end, Zhu outlined a core group of reading skills: “playing with the savor of the text” (<italic>wanwei</italic>玩味); “emptying the mind [of preconceptions]” (<italic>xuxin</italic>虛心); “making the meaning personally relevant” (<italic>qieshen</italic>切身); and following a sequence of what one reads and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>The Rhetoric and Reality of Learning to Be a Sage Zigong</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Part II, we saw that Huang Kan’s exclusivist theory of human nature left little possibility that even the most gifted of Confucius’ disciples might become sages. Given Zhu Xi’s repeated exhortations to his own students to follow the proper sequences in learning to become a sage, was Zhu promoting a method to achieve sagehood rather than simply applying the accommodationist strategy of “expedient means” to encourage his students to develop as far as they could? Zhu Xi’s assessments of three of Confucius’ disciples—Yan Hui, Zengzi, and Zigong—provide the answer to this question. Central to understanding these assessments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Liu Baonan and Liu Gongmian</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In contrast to Zhu Xi’s attempt to bypass Han commentaries and scholarship entirely, some 600 years later, scholars associated with the Han Learning movement made Han writings central to their project of historical reconstruction. “New Text” scholars of the<italic>Gongyang Tradition</italic>similarly reinvigorated nineteenth-century classical scholarship, hermeneutics, and philosophy by promoting and developing ideas first adumbrated in the writings a attributed to Han thinkers such as Dong Zhongshu and He Xiu 1ar 何休 (129-82). Liu Baonan, the author of<italic>Correct Meaning of the Analects</italic>(hereafter,<italic>Correct Meanini</italic>), was influenced by each of these developments, but the complexity of his thought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Liu Baonan and Han Learning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines some of the defining features of Liu Baonan’s scholarship and philosophy to show how they inform the interpretations in<italic>Correct Meaning.</italic>The central question is whether Liu’s commitment to the methodology of evidential scholarship warrants identifying him as a Han Learning (<italic>Hanxue</italic>漢學) partisan. Three broad issues are examined: Liu’s assumptions about, and attitudes toward, influential Han scholars of the<italic>Analects</italic>(Sima Qian, Wang Su, Kong Anguo, and Zheng Xuan); the question of how narrowly committed Liu was to the authority of Han sources and Han philology; and the role of ethical values (traditionally emphasized by Song</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Confucius as Cultural Custodian</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this chapter is Liu’s Confucius, particularly Liu’s portrayal of Confucius as a preserver and transmitter of the cultural legacy of the early Zhou and as a sage who had encoded the<italic>Analects</italic>and the<italic>Annals</italic>with subtle words and profound meanings. I begin by outlining what Liu’s commentaries reveal about his understanding of Confucius’ failure to have secured office commensurate with his sagely virtue, a recurring problematic in the<italic>Analects</italic>commentary tradition. Did this failure mean that Confucius could not realize humaneness; that he could complete only himself but not others; that he could be<italic>zhong</italic>but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has often been observed that tradition exists only in the repeated play of its own interpretation.¹ There is, however, more to tradition than its mere reception and appropriation; something must be transmitted. According to Edward Shils, “In its barest most elementary sense, it simply means<italic>traditum;</italic>it is anything which is transmitted or handed down from the past to the present.”² Yet, tradition is also more than mere custom. To quote David Gross: “It is not the assumption that an act was previously formed that makes it tradition; rather it becomes traditional when it is replicated precisely because it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX A</title>
                     <subtitle>Developments in the Earfy Commentarial Tradition of the Analects</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX B</title>
                     <subtitle>The Eight Commentators Selected by the Collected Explanations Editors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>378</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX C</title>
                     <subtitle>Earfy History of Collected Explanations and Main Editions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>386</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX D</title>
                     <subtitle>Format and Earfy History of Elucidation of the Meaning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX E</title>
                     <subtitle>Zhu Xi’s Analects Commentaries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX F</title>
                     <subtitle>Liu Baonan’s Writings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index to Analects Passages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>445</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5j9s.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
