<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94q4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BV2040.E48 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Missions</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Encyclopedias</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Missionaries</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Encyclopedias</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Encyclopedia of Missions and Missionaries</book-title>
         <subtitle>Volume 9 of Religion &amp; Society</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bonk</surname>
               <given-names>Jonathan J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>Editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780415880893</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781614728610</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berkshire Publishing Group LLC</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Berkshire Publishing Group</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1jd94tp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Encyclopedia of Missions and Missionaries is the ninth and final volume of the acclaimed Religion and Society series, focusing on the historical impact of missions over the centuries.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="450"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editorial Advisory Board</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Entries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bonk</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any single volume purporting to be encyclopedic requires an explanation, or at least an excuse. The idea for the<italic>Encyclopedia of Mission and Missionaries</italic>—to take its place among already published volumes in Routledge’s Religion and Society series of encyclopedias—was spelled out to me by David Levinson in a letter dated 30 August 2004, excerpted below:</p>
                     <p>Our vision for the missions and missionaries volume is to focus on central themes in the missionary enterprise and not cover specific missionaries or missionary organizations, as these are well documented in existing reference works…. We would also like the volume to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emphasis on the great missionary movement of the nineteenth century sometimes gives the impression that Africa was one of the last continents to be evangelized and that missionary work was largely undertaken by Europeans and North Americans. This seriously misrepresents the state of affairs. Orthodox Christianity flourished in northeast Africa for more than a millennium before the onset of the Western missionary endeavor. The Acts of the Apostles records a story of the conversion of an Ethiopian (or Nubian) official by the evangelist Philip. This comes in the chapter before Paul, the apostle to Europe, is introduced. A flourishing A</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>B</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When William Carey published his<italic>Enquiry into the Obligations of Christians, to Use Means for the Conversion of the Heathens</italic>, in 1792, he was doing what Christians traditionally do (but in Carey’s day had been badly neglected), namely demonstrating from the Bible that cross-cultural missionary work was an essential part of the calling of the church.</p>
                     <p>The text Carey chose to expound as his primary justification was Matthew 28:18–20, in which the risen Jesus, on the basis of his claim to authority as Lord of heaven and earth, mandated his own disciples to go and make disciples of all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>C</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Caribbean is a microcosm in which cultural diversity, religious crossroads, language formation, music creativity, poetic imagination, and new social fabric have expressed the richness of a people who have tried to fulfill their future and destiny.</p>
                     <p>Christopher Columbus landed in Guanahaní (part of the Bahamas) in 1492 and changed its name to San Salvador (Holy Savior), a clear reference both of his conquering project and the conviction that naming was a fundamental principle in expanding Christendom in the Caribbean. The region was a laboratory at the beginning of the sixteenth century for all kinds of colonial experiments, including the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>D</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term<italic>development</italic>in missionary activity has normally referred to the process by which the physical and social needs of persons and groups are given attention along with their spiritual needs. The goals have been to raise people from poverty, alleviate suffering, and improve the social situation of the oppressed. The motive has been twofold. First was the desire to follow the mandate of the Old Testament prophets, who called on Israel to care for the poor, the widow, and the orphan, and to follow Jesus Christ, who healed the sick and reached out to the marginalized. Second came the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>E</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Missionaries have always had to deal with economic issues whether they wanted to or not—partly because they needed to finance their religious and humanitarian projects, partly out of concern for the economic condition of the people they served, and partly to induce local rulers to allow missionary access and local people to voluntarily expose themselves to missionary teaching.</p>
                     <p>Out of necessity, missionaries and their organizations found ways to finance their overseas operations. Some of these methods were successful, a few were not, and most had some negative aspects that made them problematic.</p>
                     <p>One approach missionaries used to finance themselves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>F</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many Evangelical Protestant missions, including many of the largest and most influential, have their roots in the faith-mission tradition. Examples of such missions include the China Inland Mission (now the Overseas Missionary Fellowship), Africa Inland Mission, Christian and Missionary Alliance, Wycliffe Bible Translators, and New Tribes. The founding principle, which remained the most distinctive characteristic of faith missions, was that they permitted no overt fundraising but relied on quiet faith in God to meet financial needs.</p>
                     <p>Designed initially as complements to the denominational mission boards that dominated the missionary enterprise in the nineteenth century, faith missions were offering a competing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>G</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The largest organized women’s movement in North America in the early twentieth century was the women’s missionary movement, whose expansive involvement reached across the globe into Asia, Africa, Latin America, and the Middle East. Women missionaries constituted an indispensable workforce in the foreign missionary enterprise, representing almost 60 percent of the entire mission personnel by 1890. Despite the significant role of women in the foreign missionary enterprise, it is only since the 1980s have women missionaries and their subjects of conversion begun to draw scholarly attention. Since then, much research has shown that, although women were precluded from clerical rights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>H</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the course of the twentieth century, mission history became an object of concern to a growing legion of scholars. Besides missiologists and religious historians, the history of mission now draws the interest of specialists in politics and economics, Marxists, feminists, historical anthropologists, and many other kinds of social historians. In this article, the study of mission history from within the discipline of missiology will be highlighted.</p>
                     <p>Missiologists who study the history of mission share many overlapping concerns with their colleagues in other disciplines, not the least of which is the requirement to practice good historical technique. Some common aims</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “inculturation” or “enculturation” was originally coined by sociocultural anthropologists to refer to the process by which individuals acquire their culture as members of a human society. Subsequently, “inculturation” was appropriated by mission theologians to refer to the evangelization of culture, the process by which the Gospel illuminates and transforms culture, while culture reexpresses and even—to a certain extent—reinterprets the Gospel. Joseph Masson, SJ, first used the term in this way in 1962, but it came into current usage in the 1970s, after the earlier terms “adaptation” and “incarnation” were deemed missiologically unsatisfactory. The most important influence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>J</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Considered an insignificant American sect with around 500,000 followers in 1955, the Jehovah’s Witnesses, or The Watchtower Bible and Tract Society of New York Inc. to give them their official name, have experienced exponential growth for the past fifty years, making them a minor world religion with around 6,613,829 core members, 98,269 congregations, and 16,383,333 followers in 2005. Of these only 1,035,802 are in the United States and 127,206 in the United Kingdom; the rest are scattered across the globe.</p>
                     <p>As late as the 1970s sociologists like James Beckford were able to characterize the Jehovah’s Witnesses as a working-class phenomenon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>L</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the late fifteenth century to the present, Latin America has been the recipient of continuous missionary activity. Sometimes myopic and sometimes farsighted, this activity has played a major role in shaping the culture of the southern half of the Western Hemisphere.</p>
                     <p>In 1493 Christopher Columbus made his second voyage to America. Included with his colonists were members of religious orders, but only three of these attempted to evangelize the native population. They were lay brothers Ramón Pané, a Jeronymite who in 1498 wrote a short account of his mission work, and Juan Deledeule and Juan Tisin, both Franciscans about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>M</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A martyr is defined as “one who voluntarily suffers death as the penalty of witness to and refusing to renounce his religion” (<italic>Webster’s Third New International Dictionary of the English Language</italic>). For purposes of quantification, Christian martyrs are “believers in Christ who have lost their lives prematurely, in situations of witness, as a result of human hostility.” This definition can be expounded as follows: “Believers in Christ” are individuals from the entire Christian community of Roman Catholics, Orthodox, Protestants, Anglicans, Marginal Christians, and Independents. “‘Lost their lives” restricts it to Christians actually put to death, for whatever reason. “Prematurely” means</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>N</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mission work among Native Americans, whether Catholic or Protestant, is marked by incongruities and inconsistencies. Missionaries, though fired by zeal for the Christian faith, love of God, and concern for humankind, often confused Christianity with their own Western cultures. Wittingly or unwittingly, they frequently worked hand in hand with national governments as the humanitarian arm in colonial conquests. They could show deep compassion for those they sought to “save,” while exhibiting the attitudes of paternalistic superiority that were current in their day. It should be little wonder that after five hundred years of missionization the number of Native American adherents</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>O</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christian missionary work in the Pacific Islands and Australasia has been dominated by two main expressions of Christianity: Protestantism rooted in Britain and North America and Roman Catholicism from continental Europe. Christianity first entered the Pacific Islands through the Spanish colonial presence on the Pacific Rim. In the sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries Spanish navigators in the Pacific searched for peoples to bring under the rule of imperial Spain and to convert to Catholic Christianity. They took away a small number of islanders for instruction and baptism. In the 1660s the Spanish royal house sent Jesuits from the Philippines to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>P</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pacifism is a philosophy whose adherents reject violence, particularly war. The root meaning of the word comes from the Latin<italic>pax</italic>(peace) and<italic>facere</italic>(to make); i.e., to make peace. Pacifism is found from ancient times to the present, among both secular and religious persons, in simple societies as well as in advanced technological states. Pacifism is not to be confused with passivity. Making peace is active—adherents are committed to building a peaceful world.</p>
                     <p>When pacifists refuse to serve in the military, they are known as conscientious objectors. Today a growing number of countries legally recognize conscientious objection, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>R</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is difficult to make blanket statements about missionaries and their ideas concerning race because such ideas have differed dramatically over time. Moreover, racial attitudes have differed according to denomination, among sponsoring groups, from mission field to mission field (e. g., the attitudes of missionaries to Africa differed from those of missionaries to Asia), from mission station to mission station, and even among individual missionaries working in the same area and for the same organization.</p>
                     <p>During the age of exploration, Europeans struggled to “make sense” of previously unknown parts of the world. European ideas about Africans and Asians differed markedly.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>S</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Secularism” is a philosophy that holds that the affairs and organization of society should be arranged according to principles and rules derived from experience and human insight without reference to customs, revelations, or sacred books whose authority is derived from God or the gods or ancestors. It is distinct from the process of “secularization” whereby the state, professions such as medicine and law, and academic fields such as archeology gradually take over areas of human life once governed by religion and the church. Both words derive from the Latin word<italic>saeculum</italic>([this] world).</p>
                     <p>“Atheism” is a philosophical position that holds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>T</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Technology refers to the material elements of human culture—including artifacts, tools, machines, and computers—that help facilitate the pursuit of goals. Although technology predates science, today it commonly relates to applied science, including engineering, modes of transport, communication, medicine, warfare, print and visual media, electronics, and the digitization of information. Christian mission has learned to use technology to pursue its own goals.</p>
                     <p>Technology increases the capacity of people to achieve desired outcomes. It also creates its own cultural space with outcomes that may not have been anticipated. As a form of power, technology may contribute to oppression or to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>U</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>World urbanization is one of the most significant developments facing the planet and the mission of the church. While at the beginning of the twentieth century less than ten percent of the world’s population was urban, with the dawn of the twenty-first century more than half of Earth’s population is/will be living in cities. Ahead is an urban millennium. As a result, urban mission is one of the primary expressions of the mission of the church in the world today.</p>
                     <p>Size and scale do not tell us everything about cities, and statistics are not always agreed upon or clear, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>W</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether viewed as the breakdown of civilization, as its ultimate and most ennobling expression, or as something in between, war has always been fraught with possibility and peril for religious leaders, activists, and people of faith. War amplifies passions and exposes societal rifts even as it generates calls for unity and narratives of common experience. War offers the hope of transforming hostile nations and peoples politically, culturally, and religiously, but also threatens to poison relations between victor and vanquished, liberator and liberated. War creates mission fields and troubles those very same fields.</p>
                     <p>After a brief historical review of Christian reflection</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jd94tp.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
