<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Transcendence and the Concrete</book-title>
         <subtitle>Selected Writings</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WAHL</surname>
               <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schrift</surname>
               <given-names>Alan D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moore</surname>
               <given-names>Ian Alexander</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823273010</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823273041</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2kn1q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Jean Wahl (1888GÇô1974), once considered by the likes of Georges Bataille, Gilles Deleuze, Emmanuel Levinas, and Gabriel Marcel to be among the greatest French philosophers, has today nearly been forgotten outside France. Yet his influence on French philosophical thought can hardly be overestimated. Levinas wrote that GÇ£during over a half century of teaching and research, [Wahl] was the life force of the academic, extra-academic, and even, to a degree anti-academic philosophy necessary to a great culture.GÇ¥ And Deleuze, for his part, commented that GÇ£Apart from Sartre, who remained caught none the less in the trap of the verb to be, the most important philosopher in France was Jean Wahl.GÇ¥_x000D_ Besides engaging with the likes of Bataille, Bergson, Deleuze, Derrida, Levinas, Maritain, and Sartre, Wahl also played a significant role, in some cases almost singlehandedly, in introducing French philosophy to movements like existentialism, and American pragmatism and literature, and thinkers like Hegel, Kierkegaard, Nietzsche, Jaspers, and Heidegger. Yet Wahl was also an original philosopher and poet in his own right. This volume of selections from WahlGÇÖs philosophical writings makes a selection of his most important work available to the English-speaking philosophical community for the first time._x000D_ Jean Wahl was Professor of Philosophy at the Sorbonne from 1936 to 1967, save during World War II, which he spent in the United States, having escaped from the Drancy internment camp. His books to appear in English include The Pluralist Philosophies of England and America (Open Court, 1925), The Philosopher's Way (Oxford UP, 1948), A Short History of Existentialism (Philosophical Library, 1949), and Philosophies of Existence (Schocken, 1969).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Existence, Experience, and Transcendence:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction to Jean Wahl</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOORE</surname>
                           <given-names>IAN ALEXANDER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHRIFT</surname>
                           <given-names>ALAN D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean Wahl, once considered by the likes of Georges Bataille and Gilles Deleuze to be among the greatest philosophers in France, and by Emmanuel Levinas to be “the life force of the academic, extra-academic, and even, to a degree, anti-academic philosophy necessary to a great culture,”¹ has today nearly been forgotten outside France. Yet his influence on French thought can hardly be overestimated. As professor at the Sorbonne for over three de cades, president of the Société Française de Philosophie (1960–74), editor of the Revue de Métaphysique et de Morale (1950–74), and founder and director of the Collège</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Preface to Toward the Concrete</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lawlor</surname>
                           <given-names>Leonard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three years after his book on Hegel, and two years after his study of Plato’s<italic>Parmenides</italic>, Jean Wahl published a work that in many ways captured the spirit of the age. As Jean-Paul Sartre noted, many years later,</p>
                     <p>At about that time, the writers whom we loved explained to us that existence is a<italic>scandal</italic>. What interested us, however, was real men with their labors and their troubles. We cried out for a philosophy which would account for every thing, and we did not perceive that it existed already and that it was precisely this philosophy which provoked in us</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Commentary on a Passage from Hegel’s Phenomenology of Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baugh</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean Wahl’s 1929 book,<italic>Le malheur de la conscience dans la philosophie de Hegel</italic>, marked a turning point in French Hegel studies and profoundly influenced subsequent philosophers such as Jean-Paul Sartre, Jean Hyppolite, Gilles Deleuze, and Jacques Derrida. Wahl’s was the first major French study of Hegel’s<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>(1807), marking a turn away from Hegel’s Science of Logic to the affective and experiential basis of Hegel’s dialectical method. For Wahl, the key chapter in the<italic>Phenomenology</italic>is the section on “the Unhappy Consciousness,” rather than the earlier section on “master and slave,” which was the central focus of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Hegel and Kierkegaard</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ford</surname>
                           <given-names>Russell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1930, a substantial review of<italic>Le malheur de la conscience dans la philosophie de Hegel</italic>(The unhappiness of consciousness in Hegel’s philosophy) appeared in the<italic>Revue Philosophique de la France et de l’Étranger</italic>. Its author was Alexandre Koyré. Although now principally known as a philosopher and historian of science, Koyré’s initial work was in the philosophy of religion; his thesis, on René Descartes’s proofs for the existence of God, was completed in 1922—two years after Jean Wahl’s own thesis on Descartes—and in 1929 he received his<italic>doctorat d’ état for La philosophie de Jakob Boehme</italic>(The philosophy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Heidegger and Kierkegaard:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Investigation into the Original Ele ments of Heidegger’s Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is only slightly hyperbolic to say that Jean Wahl’s “Heidegger and Kierkegaard: An Investigation into the Original Elements of Heidegger’s Philosophy” legitimized Søren Kierkegaard in French academia and inaugurated French existentialism as such.¹ First published in 1932/1933 in<italic>Recherches Philosophiques</italic>, “perhaps the most significant [journal] of its time,”² it was republished in 1938 as an appendix to<italic>Études kierkegaardiennes</italic>, which would go on to become the most important book on Kierkegaard in France. Wahl’s article laid the groundwork for the anthropological, humanist reading of Martin Heidegger by showing how Heidegger’s philosophy must be seen as an attempt to ontologize</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Choice:</title>
                     <subtitle>Existence and Transcendence in Jaspers’s Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davidson</surname>
                           <given-names>Scott</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the reasons Alexandre Koyré, Henri-Charles Puech, and Albert Spaier founded the journal<italic>Recherches Philosophiques</italic>in 1931 was because, at the time, more established journals like the<italic>Revue de Métaphysique et de Morale</italic>were reluctant to publish articles characteristic of what Jean Wahl aptly named, in the lead article of the inaugural issue of<italic>Recherches Philosophiques</italic>, the turn “toward the concrete.” It accordingly gave aspiring philosophers the opportunity to discuss and advance movements such as phenomenology and the philosophy of existence.¹ While Wahl did publish extensively in<italic>Recherches Philosophiques</italic>(see Chapters 2 and 5 in this volume), he was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Subjectivity and Transcendence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Transcribed and translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emmanuel Leroux¹ had been scheduled to deliver a paper at the December 4, 1937, session of the eminent Société Française de Philosophie. When it became clear that, because of his wife’s illness, he would be unable to attend, the president of the society, Léon Brunschvicg, asked Jean Wahl to prepare a lecture and solicit responses in his stead. Wahl decided to discuss the connection between subjectivity and transcendence, and, despite the short notice, he managed to assemble contributions from some of the greatest philosophers of the day—far more than was typical²—for what would come to be called “a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Nietzsche and the Death of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Note on Jaspers’s Nietzsche</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schrift</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1936, Georges Bataille (1897–1962) and others organized a group of avant-garde intellectuals under the name Acéphale. Included among the members of this group were Pierre Klossowski (1905–2001), Georges Ambrosino (1912–84), Roger Caillois (1913–78), Jules Monnerot (1874–1942), and Jean Wahl. While the activities of this group were, to a large extent, secret, its public face was the journal of the same name:<italic>Acéphale.</italic>¹ Under Bataille’s leadership, the journal published four issues between June 1936 and June 1939. A fifth issue, titled “La folie de Nietz sche” (Nietz sche’s madness) was prepared but never published.² After</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Poetry and Metaphysics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rowen</surname>
                           <given-names>Simone</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean Wahl’s “Poetry and Metaphysics” first appeared in what, under the editorship of Jean Lescure, would soon become one of the leading literary journals of the French Resistance,<italic>Messages</italic>.¹ After a premier issue on William Blake (to which Wahl contributed advice and several poems of his own),² the journal’s second issue, in 1939, was devoted to the topic “Metaphysics and Poetry,” and included, alongside Wahl’s lead article, an important essay on the poetic instant by Gaston Bachelard, original poems by Paul Éluard, and photo graphs of Hans Bellmer’s<italic>La Poupée</italic>.³ Wahl played a major role in shaping this issue. Not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Order and Disorder in Nietzsche’s Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ford</surname>
                           <given-names>Russell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In July 1964, the eminent French historian of philosophy, Martial Gueroult, opened a five-day conference on Friedrich Nietzsche at the Royaumont Abbey just north of Paris. The conference was co-organized by Gilles Deleuze, who invited presentations from both younger philosophers like Michel Foucault and Gianni Vattimo, as well as from distinguished senior philosophers, including Jean Wahl, Jean Beaufret, Karl Löwith, and Gabriel Marcel. Deleuze was then concluding a four-year position at the CNRS (Centre National de Recherche Scientifique) and preparing to assume the position of professor of philosophy at the University of Lyon. Nietzsche’s<italic>On the Genealogy of Morality</italic>had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Experience and Transcendence; or, An Ontological Journey</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following se lection, whose title here brings together the two titles under which it was published, is more of a philosophical-poetic autobiography than an encyclopedia entry, even though it first appeared in 1957 in a volume of the<italic>Encyclopédie Française</italic>devoted to philosophy and religion. This revolutionary encyclopedia did not presume to order and record every facet of knowledge but, rather, to teach and inspire through a bold and creative synthesis of the most disparate domains.¹ Jean Wahl, surely among the greatest synthesizers of philosophy and himself a recognized poet, was no doubt fit for the task. In addition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Bibliography of Works by Jean Wahl</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn1q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
