<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt24h1dk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC580.B35 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Truth commissions</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Case studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political crimes and offenses</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Investigation</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Case studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reconciliation</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Case studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Case studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Truth Commissions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Memory, Power, and Legitimacy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bakiner</surname>
               <given-names>Onur</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780812247626</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812291926</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0812291921</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18z4gmr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since the 1980s a number of countries have established truth commissions to come to terms with the legacy of past human rights violations, yet little is known about the achievements and shortcomings of this popular transitional justice tool. Drawing on research on Chile's National Truth and Reconciliation Commission and Peru's Truth and Reconciliation Commission, and exploring the scholarship on thirteen other transitional contexts, Onur Bakiner evaluates the success of truth commissions in promoting policy reform, human rights accountability, and the public recognition of human rights violations. He argues that although political elites often see a truth commission as a convenient way to address past atrocities, the findings, historical narratives, and recommendations of such commissions often surprise, upset, and discredit influential political actors. Even when commissions produce only modest change as a result of political constraints, Bakiner contends, they open up new avenues for human rights activism by triggering the creation of new victims' organizations, facilitating public debates over social memory, and inducing civil society actors to monitor the country's human rights policy.</p>
         <p>Bakiner demonstrates how truth commissions have recovered basic facts about human rights violations, forced societies to rethink the violence and exclusion of nation building, and produced a new dynamic whereby the state seeks to legitimize its central position between history and politics by accepting a high degree of societal penetration into the production and diffusion of official national history. By doing so, truth commissions have challenged and transformed public discourses on memory, truth, justice, reconciliation, recognition, nationalism, and political legitimacy in the contemporary world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The National Theater of Guatemala City hosted an unusual crowd on February 25, 1999. The Commission for Historical Clarification, Guatemala’s truth commission, was going to hand over its final report to the nation’s president, Álvaro Arzú, before an audience of high-ranking civilian and military officials and a number of victims’ groups and human rights organizations. Members of the political elite must have been comfortable enough, thinking that the truth commission, systematically deprived of resources and juridical powers to carry out its mandate, would pre sent relatively uncontroversial results. However, the chair of the truth commission, Christian Tomuschat, took the stage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Definition and Conceptual History of Truth Commissions:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Are They? What Have They Become?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few ideas have gained as much international attention in such a short time span as the concept of the<italic>truth commission</italic>. Successful and failed initiatives to set up ad hoc panels called “truth commissions” to investigate patterns of human rights violations abound. In addition, in some countries single incidents of violence have led to calls for a commission when the facts about the event remained in the dark for decades. Two examples that come to mind are the 1985 siege and fire in Colombia’s Palace of Justice¹ and the 1994 bombing of the Israeli-Argentine Mutual Association in Buenos Aires.² Perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Speaking Truth to Power?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Politics of Truth Commissions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 1 identifies autonomy as a key ele ment of what makes a truth-finding panel a<italic>truth commission</italic>. Politicians may establish commissions with selfserving motives, but it is far from obvious that the commissioners share those motives. Commissions are neither state bureaucracies nor pure civil society initiatives. Rather, they come into existence and carry out their tasks through interactions between politicians, bureaucracies, supportive and hostile civil society actors, and the commissioners themselves. This chapter explores these complex state-society dynamics.</p>
                     <p>First, this chapter identifies the decision points before and during a commission process, and the interactions between the commissioners and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>One Truth Among Others?</title>
                     <subtitle>Truth Commissions’ Struggle for Truth and Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most truth commissions combine human rights investigation with a historical narrative explaining the causes and patterns of violence and violations. However, their historiographical function has been generally overlooked by transitional justice scholars, as well as historians.¹ It is understandable that temporary panels established primarily for human rights investigation, rather than the publication of professional historiography, fail to draw attention to their engagement with the past. In addition, not all truth commissions complement forensic investigation with a historical narrative. Nonetheless, many truth commissions do take part in academic and nonacademic controversies over the causes, patterns, and consequences of political violence: “The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Truth Commission Impact:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Assessment of How Commissions Influence Politics and Society</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In what ways do truth commissions influence policy, human rights accountability, and social norms? The transitional justice literature suggests various mechanisms through which truth commissions are expected to achieve a set of moral and political objectives in peace-building and democratization contexts. However, only a handful of studies have explored the commission<italic>and</italic>post-commission processes to assess claims of truth commission impact. In this chapter I explain whether or not, and the specific ways in which, truth commissions<italic>in fact</italic>transform the lessons from history into policy, human rights accountability, and changes in shared social norms. In short, this chapter is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Explaining Variation in Truth Commission Impact (I):</title>
                     <subtitle>Chile and Peru</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter zooms into truth commissions in two neighboring countries to examine in detail the creation, procedures, and outcomes of truth-finding panels. The first case is Chile’s 1990 National Commission on Truth and Reconciliation (popularly known as the “Rettig Commission” after its president, Raúl Rettig), and the second case is Peru’s 2001 Truth and Reconciliation Commission (popularly known by its Spanish acronym, “CVR”). The Chilean commission, established by the president and his advisers in the absence of considerable civil society participation, faced mandate constraints. The findings and recommendations satisfied the expectations of the government and were mostly incorporated into political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Explaining Variation in Truth Commission Impact (II):</title>
                     <subtitle>Evidence from Thirteen Countries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The detailed description of the pre-commission, commission, and postcommission processes in Chile and Peru in Chapter 5 reveals the complexity of interactions between politicians, state bureaucracies, civil society actors, and commission members. This chapter zooms out to explore how these dynamics influence commissions’ mandate, composition, goals, modes of operation, and outcomes in thirteen other societies that have lived through political transitions from authoritarianism to democracy and/or violent conflict to peace. There is enormous cross-national variation with respect to commissions’ impact on policy, judicial behavior, and social norms, as well as the sources of impact (i.e., political will to implement reforms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Comparing Truth Commissions’ Memory Narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Chile and Peru</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The enormous variation across truth commissions in terms of goals, findings, recommendations, and impact is explored in Chapters 5 and 6. Truth commissions’ explanations of the under lying causes of past violence and violations exhibit considerable variation as well. No doubt some of the differences owe to the context in which violations happen, as well as the nature of the violations themselves. Yet, one often observes divergent historical narratives describing comparable historical contexts. The civil wars in El Salvador and Guatemala had much in common, but the Salvadoran Truth Commission’s overall preference for avoidance and brevity shared little with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Nation and (Its New) Narration:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Critical Reading of Truth Commissions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In what ways do truth commissions transform the ways in which citizens of contemporary societies think and speak about historical truth, justice, reconciliation, and official historiography? Transitional justice mea sures, and truth commissions in particular, try to raise awareness around histories of violence and violations in the context of rebuilding state institutions and national identity.¹ Most truth commissions combine meticulous human rights investigation with a critique of the national past in order to rebuild the nation.² Aside from pursuing such goals as delivering a measure of justice and reconciliation, avoiding future violence, strengthening democratic institutions, and enhancing peace and stability,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thirty years ago nobody could have anticipated that a slightly modified inquiry commission, now called<italic>truth commission</italic>, would have become among the most widely used political-institutional mechanisms to come to terms with the legacies of violent and divisive periods. They have outlived the transitional justice paradigm, as consolidated democracies and nontransitioning regimes began to opt for truth commissions, too. Calls for subnational, national, and international truth commissions to investigate an ever-expanding list of past violations and injustices are found everywhere. In many countries, the supporters and opponents of a past truth commission still argue bitterly about its achievements and shortcomings</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4gmr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
