<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kw2849</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Spiritual Grammar</book-title>
         <subtitle>Genre and the Saintly Subject in Islam and Christianity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LONGO</surname>
               <given-names>F. DOMINIC</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ashton</surname>
               <given-names>Loye</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Thatamanil</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="series-editor">series editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823275724</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823276745</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823276740</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr64j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Spiritual Grammar identifies a genre of religious literature that until now has not been recognized as such. In this surprising and theoretically nuanced study, F. Dominic Longo reveals how grammatical structures of language addressed in two medieval texts published nearly four centuries apart, from distinct religious traditions, offer a metaphor for how the self is embedded in spiritual reality. Reading The Grammar of Hearts (Nahw al-qulūb) by the great Sufi shaykh and Islamic scholar 'Abd al-Karīm al-Qushayrī (d. 1074) and Moralized Grammar (Donatus moralizatus) by Christian theologian Jean Gerson (d. 1429), Longo reveals how both authors use the rules of language and syntax to advance their pastoral goals. Indeed, grammar provides the two masters with a fresh way of explaining spiritual reality to their pupils and to discipline the souls of their readers in the hopes that their writings would make others adept in the grammar of the heart.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction: Genre Trouble:</title>
                     <subtitle>QUEERING GRAMMAR FOR SPIRITUAL PURPOSES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Grammar is<italic>al-naḥw</italic>, “the way.” We journey along “the way” today as wayfarers before us have done. “The way” gives us direction, even if we sometimes stray from it with missteps and slipups of various magnitudes. The two texts that are the focus of the present study are works that school readers in “the way.” Their authors, both master wayfarers, hoped to make “the way” easier and clearer for those who followed. My study of their texts has led to the discovery of “spiritual grammar,” a genre of religious literature that until now has not been recognized as such.</p>
                     <p>“Spiritual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Arabic, Latin, and the Discipline of Grammar in the Worlds of Qushayrī and Gerson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>She holds a rod and a switch in her right hand and a book in her left. These pedagogical implements make Grammar recognizable, as do the two children below her, one kneeling and the other with head bowed. The southern Portail Royal of the western façade of Chartres Cathedral (ca. 1145–50) thus personifies Grammar as a disciplinarian and schoolteacher. Indeed, the discipline of grammar was largely about rectitude,¹ enforced by violence, as symbolized by the rod and the switch. None of the other Seven Liberal Arts of medieval European learning was represented in twelfth-century iconography as a teacher.² Grammar,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Genres and Genders of Gerson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Saint Jean-en-Grève Church. Paris, around the turn of the fifteenth century</italic>. It is Mass on the Feast of the Holy Trinity, a day when the church contemplates a mystery that is as central to Christian theology as it is difficult for the faithful to comprehend. Father Jean Gerson, the presider at this liturgy, is familiar to the congregants. He comes over regularly from the University of Paris, where he has been chancellor since 1395, to preach in French to the parishioners who pray at this grand church on the Right Bank of the Seine. Indeed, in 1403 Avignon’s Pope Benedict</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Gerson’s “Moralized” Primer of Spiritual Grammar</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like a catechism, the<italic>Donatus moralizatus</italic>text, which Gerson apparently wrote in the year 1411, begins with a question.¹ (See the Appendix for full translation.) That question sets up the grammatical framework that structures the rest of the text: “How many parts of speech are there?” Beginning the text already with a specialized term from the discipline of grammar, the question fronts the idea of “parts of speech,” thus emphasizing it over the number of how many parts there are. Though the word<italic>oratio</italic>, as not only “speech,” but also “prayer,” presents immediately a possible pun, Gerson passes over this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>From the Names of God to the Grammar of Hearts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We now tack east and back in history, from Latin to Arabic, French to Persian, Christian to Islamic. While juxtaposing Gerson’s<italic>Moralized Grammar</italic>and Qushayrī’s<italic>Grammar of Hearts</italic>creates a new context for the two texts, they are also linked to their respective times and places of origins. Attending to these original contexts grounds the fresh literary and theological understandings that the present study constructs. To prepare for understanding<italic>The Grammar of Hearts</italic>in both its literary form and its religious content, we will examine in this chapter two of Qushayrī’s most famous works and two of his less well-known</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Forming Spiritual Fuṣaḥāʾ:</title>
                     <subtitle>QUSHAYRĪ’S ADVANCED GRAMMAR OF HEARTS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The heart of the believer is the focus of this famous hadith, which speaks paradoxically of the presence of God in creation. The physical limits of the known world, the heaven and earth, do not delimit the divine.<italic>Allāhu akbar</italic>: God is greater and grander than the world. Yet somehow, the heart of the believer holds the presence of God. According to this saying, which was related by God to the Prophet Muhammad not as Qur’an but as another kind of divine utterance called by Islamic scholars a “holy saying,” a<italic>ḥadīth qudsī</italic>, the divine is powerfully and mysteriously enthroned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Fruits of Comparison:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONSTRUCTING A THEOLOGY OF GRAMMAR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A theology of grammar is born from our reading of<italic>The Grammar of Hearts</italic>and<italic>Moralized Grammar</italic>. These queer texts violate the law of genre. They mix. They exceed expectations and traverse disciplines. Their mingling is creative and fruitful. Through their mixing a religious genre takes form. They crossbreed and generate saintly genders, molds for holy human being.</p>
                     <p>Weaving together the linguistic and the spiritual, these pedagogical texts reveal to the seeker the structures of the realities in which we abide. Ricoeur argues that “texts speak of possible worlds and of possible ways of orientating oneself in those worlds.”¹ These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translation of Jean Gerson’s Moralized Grammar</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr64j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
