<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Taking Hold of the Real</book-title>
         <subtitle>Dietrich Bonhoeffer and the Profound Worldliness of Christianity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Harvey</surname>
               <given-names>Barry</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175972</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905555</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Barry Harvey</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1f89trh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Dietrich Bonhoeffer writes in one of his last prison letters that he had “come to know and understand more and more the profound this-worldliness of Christianity." In Taking Hold of the Real, Barry Harvey engages in constructive conversation with Bonhoeffer, contending that the “shallow and banal this-worldliness" of modern society is ordered to a significant degree around the social technologies of religion, culture, and race. These mechanisms displace human beings from their traditional connections with particular locales, and relocate them in their “proper places" as determined by the nation-state and capitalist markets. Christians are called to participate in the profound this-worldliness that breaks into the world in the apocalyptic action of Jesus Christ, a form of life that requires discipline and an understanding of death and resurrection. The church is a sacrament of this new humanity, performing for all to hear the polyphony of life that was prefigured in the Old Testament and now is realised in Christ. Unable to find a faithful form of this-worldliness in wartime Germany, Bonhoeffer joined the conspiracy against Hitler, a decision aptly contrasted with a small French church that, prepared by its life together over many generations, saved thousands of Jewish lives.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="356"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Great Wager</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“We live”, writes Dietrich Bonhoeffer, “in the time before the last things and believe in the last things, is that not so?”¹ We live, in other words,<italic>in medias res</italic>, in the middle of things. There is nothing novel in this observation, for this has been a perennial fact of human existence since our first parents were cast out of the garden. What is unprecedented, and what I attempt to account for in this book in constructive conversation with Bonhoeffer, is the distinctive character of the middle here and now. Prior to the sixteenth century there existed a recognizable consensus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Sacramental This-Worldliness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Richard Strauss’s opera<italic>Ariadne auf Naxos</italic>, the wealthiest man in Vienna hosts a grand banquet, to be followed by two performances—one a tragic grand opera based on the Ariadne legend, the other an example of Italian<italic>commedia dell’arte</italic>, featuring a cast of harlequins, nymphs, and buffoons. This is disconcerting to the young composer of the opera, given that the theme of his work is “the expression of ultimate solitude”, a subject he thinks unsuitable for pairing with a vulgar comedy. Matters are only made worse when it is announced that the lord of the manor wishes that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Ironic Myth of a World Come of Age</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One September evening in 1931, as he took a stroll around the grounds of Magdalen College with J. R. R. Tolkien and Hugo Dyson, C. S. Lewis exclaimed to his colleagues that myths “are lies and therefore worthless, even though breathed through silver.”¹ Though he eventually repented of this view, Lewis gave apt expression that evening to what many believe about the imaginative discourse of myth. Of course, not everyone speaks so contemptuously, adopting instead a more conciliatory tone (or is it condescending?). “We” now know that myths are childlike attempts on the part of primitive societies to explain the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Future of a Technological Illusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s critique of a world come of age, scattered across a handful of documents from prison, offers keen insight into the time in which we live and the place where we have been sent to testify to God’s work of judgment and reconciliation in Christ. He brings to light the irony in modernity’s claim to have reached a stage of intellectual and moral maturity, enabling us to see that for all of its knowledge, expertise, and technological success, the age is as godless and without resource as previous generations. But he also draws our attention to the distinctive and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The End(s) of “Religion”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rowan Williams ignited a heated debate in 2008 when he proposed in a lecture that Muslim construals of<italic>sharia</italic>(together with Orthodox Jewish practice) might be allowed to have a role in the conduct of public affairs, primarily in civil matters, in a religiously and culturally diverse England. He notes that social identities are not established by only one set of relations or mode of belonging, and to insist that they should be thus established is dangerous. The menace arises, Williams writes, “not only when there is an assumption on the religious side that membership of the community (belonging to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Culture, or Accounting for the Merely Different</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are we villains in the epic tale of capitalism, only accountants.¹ The division of material goods in a commonwealth, says Thomas Aquinas, “is not according to the natural law, but arose rather from human agreement which belongs to positive law…. The ownership of possessions is not contrary to the natural law, but an addition thereto devised by human reason.”² Max Weber locates the wellspring of the forces that organize capitalist markets, not in some mysterious natural or historical necessity—class conflict, for example—but in bookkeeping, a contingent operation of human intellect. Capitalism only becomes a reality when procedures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>A Social Economy of Whiteness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a radical inversion of the way Christians are taught to read scripture, Dietrich Bonhoeffer concludes his argument in the crucial letter of April 30, 1944, with a strongly worded assertion: “God is the beyond in the midst of our lives. The church stands not at the point of where human powers fail, at the boundaries, but in the center of the village. That’s the way it is in the Old Testament, and in this sense we don’t read the New Testament nearly enough in light of the Old.”¹ Bonhoeffer refers repeatedly to Old Testament texts in his prison correspondence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Reading the New in Light of the Old</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why it, asks Dietrich Bonhoeffer, that in the Old Testament we routinely read of people killing, betraying, lying, robbing, divorcing, and even fornicating, all recounted to the glory of God? We seldom encounter anything of the kind in the New Testament.¹ The easy answer, given by many in the eighteenth, nineteenth, and early twentieth centuries, but which Bonhoeffer unequivocally rejects, is that the Old Testament embodies a primitive stage of “religion.”² For him something far more significant is going on in connection with the Old Testament that bears directly and substantially on the performance of this-worldliness for a world come</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Polyphonic Worldliness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In J. R. R. Tolkien’s creation saga, “Ainulindalë,” Ilúvatar sings the world into existence, setting forth for the Ainur, the first offspring of the creator’s song, the leitmotif to which the angelic beings were to add their voices. “Of the theme that I have declared to you,” Ilúvatar said to the divine ensemble, “I will now that ye make in harmony together a Great Music. And since I have kindled you with the Flame Imperishable, ye shall show forth your powers in adorning this theme, each with his own thoughts and devices, if he will. But I will sit and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>A Tale of Two Pastors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When asked about the victory against Napoleon at Waterloo, the Duke of Wellington is said to have replied, “The battle of Waterloo was won on the playing fields of Eton.” It was the habits and dispositions that the officers and soldiers of the British army learned in boarding school that enabled Great Britain to prevail in the encounter. Samuel Wells contends that Eton and Waterloo exemplify two distinct aspects of ethical thought and behavior, the first the long period of preparation, the second “the tiny episode of implementation—the moment of decision, or ‘situation.’” Of the two, says Wells, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89trh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
