<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT122 .C65513 2018</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holy Spirit</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Doctrines</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Spirit of God</book-title>
         <subtitle>Short Writings on the Holy Spirit</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Congar</surname>
               <given-names>Yves</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">Translated by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brown</surname>
               <given-names>Susan Mader</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ginter</surname>
               <given-names>Mark E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mueller</surname>
               <given-names>Joseph G.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Clifford</surname>
               <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229935</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229942</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zqrmtj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Yves Congar was the most significant voice in Catholic pneumatology in the twentieth century. This new collection of short pieces makes his thought accessible to a broad range of readers - scholars, teachers, ecumenists and laity - and thus helps to ensure that an important theological voice, one that influenced many of the documents of the Second Vatican Council, continues to be heard.<italic>The Spirit of God</italic>brings together for the first time eight of Yves Congar's previously untranslated writings on the Holy Spirit composed after Vatican II (from 1969 to 1985). Two of these selections offer general overviews of Congar's pneumatology, a pneumatology based upon Scripture and the Tradition of the Church, but articulated in conversation with philosophers, ecumenical partners and non-believers. Other articles make clear the historical context of Vatican II's pneumatology and the Holy Spirit's crucial influence upon the unfolding of history and upon the moral life, the efficacy of the sacraments and, especially, upon ecclesial life.The writings in<italic>The Spirit of God</italic>have been translated and edited by a team of scholars familiar with the work of the French Dominican theologian. An introduction situates each of the writings historically and highlights its theological significance. A bibliography lists Congar's publications on the Holy Spirit, the major articles and books written about his pneumatology, and the major scholarly resources to which Congar made reference in the notes that accompanied these writings. An index of biblical references and of personal names is also included.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ginter</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <role content-type="author">with</role>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan Mader</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mueller</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Spirit of God</italic>brings together eight significant apologetic and scholarly writings on the Holy Spirit by Yves Cardinal Congar, OP (1904–95), previously un translated into English. These publications also touch upon the fields of patristic and medieval theology, fundamental and sacramental theology, Christology and ecclesiology, spirituality and ecumenism. They show Congar’s familiarity not only with the Catholic tradition but also with Orthodox and Protestant perspectives. One of the most influential theologians at Vatican II, Congar is widely regarded as the most significant voice in Catholic pneumatology in the twentieth century. The nearly 1800 articles and books in Congar’s bibliography</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Word about the Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan Mader</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ginter</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mueller</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifford</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In translating Congar’s words, we have tried to remain faithful both to the substance and to the style of the French text from which we worked. Our aim has been to make Congar’s ideas and his enthusiasm accessible to contemporary readers. To the extent that it has been possible to do so, we have supplemented Congar’s notes by giving complete publication data and by noting, in square brackets, where passages to which he refers would be found in English translations. For those writings of St. Thomas Aquinas that are cited frequently enough to appear in our list of abbreviations, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART ONE Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This piece, a requested summary of<italic>I Believe in the Holy Spirit</italic>, offers a compact, contemporary defense of the claim that “God is present and active in our lives by a non-coercive Power” and of the Church’s teaching about the Holy Spirit. Its value is indicated by the frequency with which it is cited by scholars,¹ as well as by the fact that it was re-issued in French in 1998 and remains in print in several languages.</p>
                     <p>Sections 1, 3, and 4 take much of their material from<italic>HS</italic>. How- ever, section 2, which summarizes the main sorts of objections</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Evidence of the “Holy Spirit” in the Past and Today</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Christian branch of religion, itself an off shoot of Judaism, a claim pervades all times and places. Its unanimity is impressive, considering the diversity of sources from which it comes. The claim is this: God is present and active in our lives by a non-coercive Power that we call the Holy Spirit. The following examples, chosen from among the hundreds available, attest to this.</p>
                     <p>There are the seventy elders who assist Moses (about 1230 BCE). “When the Spirit rested upon them, they prophesied” (Nm 11:25). There is Samuel (about 1040 BCE) who says to Saul, “You will run</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Difficulties:</title>
                     <subtitle>Critical Objections</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world born of the eighteenth-century Enlightenment is suspicious of our statements about the Holy Spirit. It calls them into question. Indeed, it has learned to mistrust every explanation involving a transcendent, unverifiable “cause.” The spirit it favors is<italic>ours</italic>, not that unknown One beyond the clouds. Its suspicion takes many forms and I do not claim to deal with all of them. Nevertheless, here are five or six of its principal manifestations, from the most superficial to the most philosophically sophisticated.</p>
                     <p>Christians affirm a newness of life. To be more precise, they say that, with the resurrection of Jesus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Spirit Is the Source of Life in Us Personally and in the Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having recalled the fact of an uncritical but constant claim that the Spirit<italic>of God</italic>is at work in us and in the world, I have highlighted the main difficulties to which this claim gives rise. This sequence is well known to believers: after a time of peaceful possession of the faith, they become aware of challenges to it. If not doubt, at least an ongoing questioning—what St. Thomas called the<italic>cogitatio</italic>—is a part of the faith. It is the passport into what Paul Ricoeur calls the second naiveté,¹ which is more or less the state of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Theology of the Third Person</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A theology of the Holy Spirit and, in more general terms, a theology of Christ and of the tri-unity of God, took a long time to develop. There was no model to follow. The chapter was blank and yet, in a sense, its contents were already determined. Antiquity knew a broad diff usion of Stoicism, so widespread that it touched the class of ordinary people and even the world of slaves. And Stoicism envisaged a divine Breath animating the world but saw it as an element of this world itself. It tended to see the Word or Wisdom of God,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have spoken of the Holy Spirit, albeit in a very rudimentary way. However, to speak of the Spirit is less important than to live in the Spirit. The initiative belongs to the Spirit. In so far as anything depends on us under the Spirit’s sovereign impulse, this will be grounded in prayer. It is worth noting that prayers to the Holy Spirit begin by this appeal: “Come!” The Spirit is already there. Indeed, the Spirit is the very one who moves us to pray. Yet we beg the Spirit to come as a visitor, as a power, and as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART TWO Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Pneumatologie dogmatique” was one of Congar’s contributions to a five-volume set,<italic>Initiation à la pratique de la théologie</italic>, edited by Bernard Lauret and François Refoulé in 1982. The book’s title might be rendered in English as “Beginning to Do Theology.” Still in print, the volumes—entitled Introduction, Dogmatics 1, Dogmatics 2, Ethics, and Practice—are meant for an academic setting, especially for the Catholic seminary context in which most of Congar’s teaching career was spent. Although an apologetic character is not absent from this presentation, Congar is here working more as a dogmatician than as an apologist, giving primacy to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Testimony about the Holy Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Third Person is not revealed to us in the way that the Son is revealed in Jesus Christ. However, the Spirit¹ has been and is made manifest by what the Spirit brings about. That is why we must examine the evidence—whether of Scripture, liturgical celebrations, or personal Christian experience. I have organized the testimonies in this section with an emphasis above all on the<italic>practical</italic>. One cannot say everything all at once, even about matters that are simultaneous and connected.<italic>The Spirit inspires people to pursue God’s work</italic>.</p>
                     <p>The most constant of the testimonies we have about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Spirit in the Personal Prayer and in the Personal Lives of Christians</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a fact that prayers to the Holy Spirit begin with the cry, “Come!” Thus begin the hymn<italic>Veni Creator</italic>(ninth century), the antiphon and sequence<italic>Veni, Sancte Spiritus</italic>(twelfth century, with a sequence attributed to Stephen Langton), the great lyric prayer of Symeon the New Theologian that is placed at the beginning of his hymns, or a prayer of Jean de Fécamp, from 1060 (<italic>ES</italic>2:147 and 148, n. 2 [<italic>HS</italic>2:112]).¹ It is not that the Spirit is not already there, but the Spirit is implored to bring, by a new coming, what we lack. These prayers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>An Ecclesiological Pneumatology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On two occasions the Second Vatican Council speaks of the Church in Trinitarian terms as the “people of God, body of Christ, temple of the Holy Spirit.”¹ In St. Paul, the repeated affirmation of the Spirit’s indwelling in us as in the Spirit’s sanctuary (<italic>naos Theou</italic>) is applied simultaneously to persons and to the community as such (1 Cor 3:16–17; 6:19; 2 Cor 6:16; Rom 8:9; Eph 2:19–22). The Tradition—patristic, spiritual and medieval—has never stopped saying that every soul is the Church; the spiritual dimensions of the latter, as Temple and Spouse, are also made real</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Spirit Is the Breath of the Word and the Spirit of the Son</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite how this title might be understood, my focus remains on the economy. At issue here is not the eternal processions but the work accomplished for our salvation.</p>
                     <p>The gift of the Spirit is the endpoint, the<italic>telos</italic>, the perfection of God’s self-communication to those who believe. It is linked to the mission and the gift of the Word-Son to the world (Gal 4:4–7). The two “missions,” the two gifts are connected. The mission and gift of the Spirit presuppose those of the Son-Word. The mission and the gift of the Spirit aim to make us children of God;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Spirit, the Eschatological Gift, Brings the “Redemption” to Fulfillment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Propter nostram salutem [for our salvation]”: our “salvation” is the reason for the self-revelation and self-communication of God which constitutes the “economy.” It is through this economy that we have some access to “theology,” that is, to the knowledge of the intimate and eternal mystery of God. What “salvation” of human beings means can clarify for us what the Holy Spirit is.</p>
                     <p>Revelation and Tradition say that man (man/woman) is in the image of God. That means human beings are destined to reflect God’s image, to reproduce that image as a child does that of its father. To this revealed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART THREE Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the three articles that form Part Three were written and published before the works in Parts One and Two, they represent well the biblical, historical, sacramental, and pneumatological character of Congar’s mature thought. All three come from the last period of Congar’s scholarly life, 1969 to 1991, according to the periodday ization of Cornelis Van Vliet.¹ The climax of this part is arguably Congar’s most important article on the Holy Spirit, “Pneumatology or ‘Christomonism’ in the Latin Tradition?” We have included two additional writings, “Theology of the Holy Spirit and Theology of History” and “The Holy Spirit in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 1</label>
                     <title>Theology of the Holy Spirit and Theology of History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First of all, I must clarify the meaning of some terms. “Pneumatology” designates the ensemble of actions proper to the Holy Spirit (or appropriated to the Holy Spirit) in the life of the Church and of the world. It is obvious that what I will say on this subject makes sense only if one presupposes the traditional Christian faith. But that is true, too, for “theology of history.” This expression designates, in the most general way, a consideration of history from God’s point of view in so far as we know it, that is, in the light not only of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 2</label>
                     <title>The Holy Spirit in the Thomistic Theology of Moral Action</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will first present the Holy Spirit’s role in moral action according to St. Thomas, relying primarily on the thorough treatment in the<italic>Summa</italic>. I will then ask what these views can contribute to [the resolution of] certain problems of our own time in this field.</p>
                     <p>This is a very important topic. Part Two of the<italic>Summa</italic>, especially 2a2ae, presents us with a moral ideal so balanced, so reasonable, so nourished by categories stemming from Aristotelianism and Stoicism, that one might well wonder if this humanism fulfills what the gospel requires. Of course, Thomas has introduced into his vision of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 3</label>
                     <title>Pneumatology or “Christomonism” in the Latin Tradition?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The observers at the Second Vatican Council often made the reproach that the schemas, in particular those of the dogmatic constitutions<italic>Lumen Gentium</italic>and<italic>Dei Verbum</italic>, lacked a pneumatology.² One of them, Nikos A. Nissiotis, currently [in 1970] director of the Ecumenical Institute in Bossey, voices the same reproach.³ He has returned insistently to what he calls the “Christomonism” of the Latins and an “ecclesiological pneumatology” which the Latins lack and which is said to be the soul of Orthodox ecclesiology. The Latins tend to make the Holy Spirit merely one of Christ’s functions—the function of bringing salvation to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART FOUR Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Here we present three significant articles on ecclesiology primarily from the point of view of Congar’s post–Vatican II pneumatology. They can all be read in light of his contributions to the Council.¹</p>
                     <p>“Pneumatology Today” was delivered at a special 1982 Vatican celebration of the 1550th anniversary of the Third Ecumenical Council (in Ephesus in 431) and the 1600th anniversary of the Second Ecumenical Council (in Constantinople in 381). Congar was invited to speak to the contemporary status of pneumatology because the Second Ecumenical Council had expanded the third article about the Holy Spirit in the Nicene Creed. On this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 4</label>
                     <title>Pneumatology Today</title>
                     <subtitle>(Relazione, March 22, 1982)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Each Tuesday during the Second Vatican Council, the Secretariat for Christian Unity held a meeting with the observers in the Unitas Residence on the via dell’Anima. There they explained and discussed the questions with which the conciliar assembly was currently dealing or that it expected to take up. Now the observers—Protestant, Orthodox, Anglican—frequently found fault with the conciliar texts for their lack of pneumatology. Account was taken of these critical comments, and Paul VI noted that there are 258 references to the Holy Spirit in the documents of Vatican II.² But is that all that is required to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 5</label>
                     <title>Christological and Pneumatological Implications of Vatican II’s Ecclesiology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I agreed to treat this subject without giving it very much thought. When I began to write, I wondered exactly what it might include, what was expected of me in the overall context of this colloquium. So I sketched out for myself an outline that unfolded, it seemed to me, from the very statement of the theme, and then I re-read all the conciliar documents, pencil in hand.² Here is what, as a result, I propose to consider: (1) what Christ did, as far as the Church is concerned, while he was on the earth; (2) what the glorified Christ</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ARTICLE 6</label>
                     <title>The Third Article of the Creed:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Impact of Pneumatology on the Life of the Church</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of the Council of 381, its historical context and the part played by each of its “personae dramatis [role players],” is easily read, and I am not going to recall it. I am going to take the Creed as we have received it. I am even going to accept, along with the majority of today’s historians, that it really does come from the Council.</p>
                     <p>A creed is, in the domain of expression of the faith, a specific genre different from the “confessions of faith” of Protestant communions. The latter are specific responses made in a context determined by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Biblical References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zqrmtj.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>298</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
