<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7mr99</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D16.9.I74 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Experience</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Subaltern Appeal to Experience</book-title>
         <subtitle>Self-Identity, Late Modernity, and the Politics of Immediacy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ireland</surname>
               <given-names>Craig</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773527553</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773572140</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zxm6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Combining historical findings with discourse analyses and diagnostic readings of recent subaltern and aesthetic inquiry, Ireland reveals that the term experience has been incorrectly understood. Since the 1970s, persistent appeals to experience in identity politics and cultural inquiry testify not only to the influence of a particular modern concept but, more importantly, to the historical status of modern self-identity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the last few decades, the term “experience” has persistently preoccupied certain strands in cultural, subaltern, and aesthetic inquiry concerned with issues of agency, identity formation or counterhegemonic resistance. This preoccupation with experience has also sparked a series of skirmishes since the 1970s between those who debunk experience as the stuff of an antiquated philosophy of consciousness and those who, on the contrary, seek its rehabilitation by resurrecting Dilthey or Dewey. Heated and protracted exchanges on experience take place to this day in such journals as the<italic>New Left Review, Critical Inquiry, New Literary History</italic>, and the<italic>Yale Journal of</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Appeal of Immediate Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of experience has elicited the interest of various academic disciplines for at least the last two centuries. But only the last three decades can rightly be called, to borrow Michael Rutschky’s expression, decades of<italic>Erfahrungshunger</italic>.¹ Unlike in earlier decades, where it had remained largely within the confines of academia, by the 1970s the concept of experience had frequently become the stuff of programmatic manifestos, and it was enlisted as the ground from which it was (and still is) believed could be erected microstrategies of resistance, subaltern counterhistories, and a politics of identity. Experience spilled over into the streets,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Mediacy of Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their bid to preserve agency or at least a means of resistance against strong structural determination, strands in cultural and subaltern theory, then, have wagered on the perceived counterhegemonic immediacy of experience. As to why such a venture should find immediate experience so seductive, poststructuralist critiques of presence in general and of immediate experience in particular tell us little that has not already been told by Adorno, if not by Hegel: “In schools of philosophy that make emphatic use of the concept of experience, in the tradition of Hume, the character of immediacy – immediacy in relation to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Experience and the Prospective Gaze to the Future</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a popular term that gained currency in tandem with philosophical formulations of<italic>Erfahrung</italic>and as a term that points no less than does its philosophical counterpart to a dialectic of continuity and discontinuity, the neologism<italic>Erlebnis</italic>of course testifies to a certain convergence between both academic and para-academic dealings with experience. But what is striking here is not that the dialectical aspect of experience should receive its first systematic philosophical formulation through Hegel while almost simultaneously finding its way into popular fiction and biographical literature – after all, we have already seen how such a dialectic informs an etymological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Experience and the Retrospective Glance to the Past</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The experiential process may well appear future-oriented insofar as it remains recalcitrant to seamless integration within prior expectations and insofar as it perturbs routinized perceptions, actions, and attitudes. Yet it also involves the<italic>retrospective revision</italic>, and not the outright dismissal, of the earlier orientations it disrupts. Experience harbours two temporal maneuvers: an initial disruption of the given is followed by a retrospective revision of the past so as to accommodate the new and reestablish continuity. At hand in dialectical experience is what can be called – what has in fact already been called by Kristeva, Heidegger, Luhmann, and others –</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Experience and the Temporal Logic of Late Modernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A confluence of sociohistorical vectors so impinged on processes of self-formation, then, that by the mid- to late eighteenth century the self increasingly becomes a narrative of events, or, to use Taylor’s expression, a “chain of happenings.” And these events, or happenings, insofar as they are reflexively reworked into a self’s horizon, are what experience is all about. But it is legitimate at this point to ask whether the continuity between the late eighteenth and the late twentieth century noted by Taylor still holds – whether, in other words, those late-eighteenth-century socio-historical preconditions for an accentuated role of experience in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Reassessing Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At hand in the temporality of the last two to three decades is not, as Ricoeur would have it, the exacerbation of temporal divergence beyond the mediating capacities of narratives;¹ at hand instead is the contraction of temporality within the narrow horizons of an extended present where a culture of immediacy, not temporal extension, becomes the order of the day. It is just this apparent culture of immediacy that brings us back to our initial problem – the Thompson-inspired subaltern appeal to<italic>immediate</italic>experience.</p>
                     <p>We have seen in the first chapter that because Thompson-inspired cultural, feminist, and subaltern theory regards</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zxm6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
