<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15m7nnr</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">N8023 .A78 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Illustrations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. New Testament</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretations, etc.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian art and symbolism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Art of Visual Exegesis</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rhetoric, Texts, Images</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Robbins</surname>
               <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Melion</surname>
               <given-names>Walter S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jeal</surname>
               <given-names>Roy R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884142140</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884142133</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pk86wt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A critical study for those interested in the intersection of art and biblical interpretation</p>
         <p>With a special focus on biblical texts and images, this book nurtures new developments in biblical studies and art history during the last two or three decades. Analysis and interpretation of specific works of art introduce guidelines for students and teachers who are interested in the relation of verbal presentation to visual production. The essays provide models for research in the humanities that move beyond traditional disciplinary boundaries erected in previous centuries. In particular, the volume merges recent developments in rhetorical interpretation and cognitive studies with art historical visual exegesis. Readers will master the tools necessary for integrating multiple approaches both to biblical and artistic interpretation.</p>
         <p>Features</p>
         <p>Resources for understanding the relation of texts to artistic paintings and imagesTools for integrating multiple approaches both to biblical and artistic interpretationSixty images and fifteen illustrations</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="540"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Melion</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jeal</surname>
                           <given-names>Roy R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume emerged in the context of the academic year 2013–2014, during which monthly sawyer seminars held at emory university in Atlanta, georgia, focused on visual hermeneutics and exegesis in multiple religious traditions. The year-long series was titled “Visual exegesis: Images as instruments of scriptural interpretation and hermeneutics.” The seminar was proposed by Walter S. Melion and funded by the Andrew W. Mellon foundation through emory university. As the seminars unfolded, Vernon Robbins, assisted by Walter Melion and Roy Jeal, selected certain participants to revise their presentations for publication and in some instances invited authors to write essays based</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>New Testament Texts, Visual Material Culture, and Earliest Christian Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay addresses the interpretation of New Testament texts in the context of visual material culture. Especially during the last two decades, interpreters have begun to produce explicit exegesis of New Testament texts in the context of statues, frescoes, archaeological structures, inscriptions, pottery, coins, paintings, and other artifacts that existed in the Mediterranean world during first-century emerging Christianity. A major question is how the presence of a display of visual material culture in the context of interpretation of a text may be legitimately persuasive. is the presence of the visual display simply a tour de force that has no scholarly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Visual Interpretation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Blending Rhetorical Arts in Colossians 2:6–3:4</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jeal</surname>
                           <given-names>Roy R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin with a photograph, a “writing of light” (φωτός + γραφή),¹ which is, of course, like a painting or movie screen, of only two dimensions, having length and width, not depth. But allow your eyes and your imagination (i.e., your brain) to visualize the illusion of depth, the third dimension, as we humans easily and normally do when we look at paintings, photographs, or films. Allow your mind to enter the symbolic world, to grasp and understand the geometry of space, of three dimensions.</p>
                     <p>This is Moses: “So come, i will send you to Pharaoh to bring my people,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Methodology Underlying the Presentation of Visual Texture in the Gospel of John</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bloomquist</surname>
                           <given-names>L. Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>specialists in rhetoric—especially those who deliver addresses, even more than those who analyze them—have long recognized the power of the image to get a point across. One of the first extant examples of sophistic practice, gorgias’s<italic>Encomium of Helen</italic>, uses words to set beautiful Helen before the audience’s eyes, but also her case.¹ Aristotle’s second book of his<italic>Rhetoric</italic>is devoted to the means of picturing and presenting character, primarily that of the speaker.² Examples of the power of imagery in contemporary rhetorical practice also abound, especially in the realm of advertising and preaching.³ Preaching is especially interesting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Eyes Wide Open, Seeing Nothing:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Challenge of the Gospel of John’s Nonvisualizable Texture for Readings Using Visual Texture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bloomquist</surname>
                           <given-names>L. Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would like you to visualize God. If you are able to do so, your visualization of God is probably drawn from images that you have seen of God. These images themselves are drawn from various sources: stained glass windows, statuary, children’s Bibles, shrines, stories that you have heard. you may imagine a patriarchal-style God with long beard, a multiarmed God fighting with a sword in each of many hands, a triangle with an eye, and so on. The task I assigned you is probably especially hard if you are Jewish or Muslim, but it is not impossible. You might</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Paul, Imperial Situation, and Visualization in the Epistle to the Colossians</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maier</surname>
                           <given-names>Harry O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout the past decade, scholars of Christian origins have turned their attention increasingly to the relationship of emergent Christianity to the roman empire.¹ The themes taken up in fact echo ideas presented by new Testament exegetes over a hundred years ago, when German archaeologists made new discoveries about the imperial cult in Asia Minor. Adolf Deissmann, Adolf von Harnack, Ernst Lohmeyer, Paul Wendland, and Karl Bornhäuser, for example, recognizing New Testament echoes of imperial language, argued that biblical authors used political terms and images drawn from the imperial cult to oppose persecuting emperors and a hostile empire.² Contemporary exegetes largely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Galatian Suicide and the Transbinary Semiotics of Christ Crucified (Galatians 3:1):</title>
                     <subtitle>Exercises in Visual Exegesis and Critical Reimagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kahl</surname>
                           <given-names>Brigitte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The room was dimly lit and evoked a sanctuary-like feeling. Artifacts of the Pergamene kings and their deities in dignified poses stood watching from the side wings behind pillars draped in crimson. On a long table running down the central aisle, four human bodies were on display, the whiteness of their marble flesh in stark contrast to the bright red of the countertop that carried their collapsed shapes as if they were floating on a stream of blood. Bleeding they were, profusely, in petrified gushes from gaping wounds in their chests, bellies, backs— a<italic>Dead Giant</italic>, a<italic>Dying Gaul</italic>, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Armor, Peace, and Gladiators:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Visual Exegesis of Ephesians 6:10–17</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Canavan</surname>
                           <given-names>Rosemary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ephesians 6:10–17 employs clothing and armor imagery to describe the spiritual struggle of the Pauline communities addressed in the letter. A growing field of interpretation looks to the systematic interpretation of such imagery in relation to and in dialogue with the sociopolitical visual landscape. for my part, I wish to engage with the iconographic panorama of the cities in which the biblical texts were written, heard, and read to illuminate the meaning of the text. In this essay, using an adapted sociorhetorical analytic, I engage in a visual exegesis of the clothing and armor images in eph 6:10–17</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Graphic Exegesis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on the Difficulty of Talking about Biblical Images, Pictures, and Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nygren</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Art history is a discipline of images, but more than that it is a discipline that relies on the flexibility of the term<italic>image</italic>. Images are the vital essence at the center of art history, the essential constituent that distinguishes the field from aesthetics. Most art historians study pictures or sculptures, concrete instances of cultural production, items that index the agency of some person, group, or force that created—or even simply chose to frame or set apart—some object. yet over the last hundred years or so, art history has developed into an increasingly promiscuous field of inquiry that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Gifts of Epiphany:</title>
                     <subtitle>Geertgen tot Sint Jans and the Adoration of the Magi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Luttikhuizen</surname>
                           <given-names>Henry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To be human is to be<italic>humus</italic>, to be of the soil or the dirt. Yet for millennia people from around the world have searched the heavens for answers to earthly questions. The stars, planets, and comets, it is believed, might offer gifts of illumination, providing potential signs of the future, premonitions of what is yet to come. Unfortunately, celestial bodies do not readily reveal their secrets. Their truth is latent, waiting to be unconcealed. Interpreting their meaning demands effort, and this can be a risky enterprise. Signals can get crossed, and beholders can lose sight of their position. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Exactitude and Fidelity”?</title>
                     <subtitle>Paintings of Christ Healing the Blind by Nicolas Poussin and Philippe de Champaigne</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifton</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a lecture of January 7, 1668, to the Académie Royale de Peinture et de Sculpture, Philippe de Champaigne famously criticized Nicolas Poussin for his failure to adhere faithfully to sacred history in his painting of<italic>Rebecca and Eliezer</italic>of ca. 1648 (in the Louvre), specifically for not including the camels mentioned in the biblical text, which deserved to be shown, he said, in order to prove the exactitude and the fidelity of the painter in a true subject.¹ Champaigne might well have attended Sebastien Bourdon’s lecture on Poussin’s<italic>Christ Healing the Blind</italic>of 1650 (also in the Louvre; see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Topos versus Topia:</title>
                     <subtitle>Herri met de Bles’s Visual Exegesis of the Parable of the Good Samaritan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weemans</surname>
                           <given-names>Michel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The emergence and development of landscape painting in Flanders during the sixteenth century, far from coinciding with a secularization of art and the rise of a purely aesthetic appreciation of nature—according to a late modern conception of landscape that has long been applied to these early works—actively participated in the “visual piety” that characterizes the early modern period.¹ “The pleasure of contemplating landscape paintings is as great as that experienced in the contemplation of nature itself,” stated Cardinal Borromeo, patron and friend of Jan Brueghel and Paul Bril and himself a famous collector of Flemish landscapes. He added:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Signa Resurrectionis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Vision, Image, and Pictorial Proof in Pieter Bruegel’s Resurrection of Circa 1562–1563</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Melion</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Engraved by Philips galle after Pieter Bruegel, the<italic>Resurrection</italic>of ca. 1562–1563 explores a problem central to the exegetical tradition—namely, that this great mystery of faith as set forth in the gospels and epistles was witnessed by no one and must thus be known solely by means of the prophecies it fulfilled and the evidentiary signs left in its wake (fig. 1).¹ Published by hieronymus Cock, who perhaps also commissioned the drawing in pen, brown ink, and wash and almost surely retained possession of the large copperplate, the<italic>Resurrection,</italic>as manfred sellink has recently observed, emulates the huge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>485</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient and Medieval Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>487</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>497</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pk86wt.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
