<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8btr</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Levinas and the Trauma of Responsibility</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Ethical Significance of Time</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Coe</surname>
               <given-names>Cynthia D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253031969</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253031983</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253031982</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cynthia D. Coe</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt20d87sf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Levinas's account of responsibility challenges dominant notions of time, autonomy, and subjectivity according to Cynthia D. Coe. Employing the concept of trauma in Levinas's late writings, Coe draws together his understanding of time and his claim that responsibility is an obligation to the other that cannot be anticipated or warded off. Tracing the broad significance of these ideas, Coe shows how Levinas revises our notions of moral agency, knowledge, and embodiment. Her focus on time brings a new interpretive lens to Levinas's work and reflects on a wider discussion of the fragmentation of human experience as an ethical subject. Coe's understanding of trauma and time offers a new appreciation of how Levinas can inform debates about gender, race, mortality, and animality.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Intrigues of Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The image on the cover of this book is a photograph of plaster casts and masks made in the studio of sculptor Anna Coleman Ladd for French World War I veterans who had suffered facial wounds. Fred Albee, an American surgeon who treated soldiers in that war, noted that the way that the war was fought, including the relatively new military technology of machine guns, made soldiers more vulnerable to such wounds: “soldiers failed to understand the menace of the machine gun. They seemed to think they could pop their heads up over a trench and move quickly enough to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Deformalizing Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 1988 interview, Levinas claims that the “essential theme of my research is the deformalization of the notion of time” (OUJ 232). At first glance, this identification of time as his “essential theme” seems counterintuitive, given his steadfast focus on the nature of responsibility and the subject’s relation to alterity. However, how we understand time shapes how we understand the self, and Levinas argues that a formal conception of time supports the modern ideal of autonomous subjectivity. Time can be seen as either enabling or disrupting the position of the subject as a detached knower and willful agent in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Traumatic Impact of Deformalized Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On levinas’s reading, formal conceptions of time depict a neutral order within which we experience events and beings. These accounts correlatively naturalize a subject who comprehends and controls her surroundings. When Levinas identifies the deformalization of time as central to his philosophical work, he is thus engaged in the critique of the image of subjectivity presupposed by formal conceptions of time. Starting in the late 1960s, Levinas describes time’s “meaningful content somehow prior to form” as traumatic: a responsibility for the other imposed on the subject, which consciousness is always too late to assimilate as a phenomenon (OUJ 232).</p>
                     <p>In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Method of An-Archeology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’s prominent use of the concept of trauma provokes the question of how responsibility can be thematized at all, given its status as a trace rather than a phenomenon—an experience that can be unproblematically represented by consciousness. Through its rhetorical peculiarities, his philosophical style reflects his claims about the subject’s encounter with what exceeds, frustrates, or otherwise interrupts conceptualization. This chapter will analyze Levinas’s method of “saying and unsaying,” with particular attention to his repudiation of narration in<italic>Otherwise than Being</italic>. Given that narration is one way to reduce the lapse of time to a unified representation, this methodological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Between Theodicy and Despair</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’s critique of narrative and the conception of the narrating subject that underlies it leads him to the issue of how time is synchronized in the philosophy of history, where the process of abstraction from the singular other is most prominent. By interpreting the significance of disparate events and integrating them into a coherent account, the disciplinary approaches of history typically assume a formal conception of time, in which a linear chronology can be represented by consciousness. In other words, past events are treated as intentional objects. This synchronization of time entails generalizing from people’s experiences, selectively emphasizing certain elements</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Sobering Up of Oedipus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>enemies of the People</italic>, a documentary film about the Cambodian genocide under the Khmer Rouge, the former leader known as Brother Number Two tells his subordinates, who tortured and executed political prisoners: “You did not have any intention, therefore you did not commit any sin.”¹ Although we may well reject the claim that these agents of violence remained morally innocent, the idea that responsibility depends upon intentions dominates the moral and legal imaginary of modern Western thought. It is a claim that Levinas associates with the Greek tradition, and one that he insistently challenges. However, the undermining of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Anxieties of Incarnation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A year after Hitler came to power in Germany, Levinas published a short essay titled “Some Thoughts on the Philosophy of Hitlerism,” which delineates the struggle between two movements within European thought: liberalism and Hitlerism. Somewhat surprisingly, Levinas treats Hitlerism as a philosophy, if a “simplistic” one. He interprets it as “the primary attitude of a soul faced with the whole of the real and its own destiny” (PH 13). Certainly Hitlerism was or is a form of ideology, but why should Levinas grace it with the name of what has systematically opposed dogmatism? Yet Levinas insists that the “awakening</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Rethinking Death on the Basis of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I draw out the implications of Levinas’s argument that the body is ethically significant and the relationship between his understanding of the body and his emphasis on diachrony. In its very susceptibility to illness, injury, and aging, the body reveals our radical exposure to others. His refusal to consider the particularity of the body—its race or gender, for instance—as part of this ethical significance certainly limits the usefulness of his understanding of embodiment to political questions, as he employs that term. In addition, feminist philosophers have been wary of the implications of Levinas’s direct references</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Animals and Creatures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous two chapters have raised a cluster of issues about the implications of Levinas’s understanding of embodiment for the relationship between human and nonhuman animals, particularly given his emphasis on the subject’s status as a creature. Levinas defends a very traditional form of anthropocentrism, which leads him to the conclusion that animals fall outside of the ethical encounter between the self and the other. He thus has very little to say about animals. But in the wake of his radical reconception of subjectivity—as heteronomous, embodied, and ineradicably affected by time—the question of how human creatures relate to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Inheriting the Thought of Diachrony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has focused on the array of issues around subjectivity and time that emerges out of Levinas’s thought and particularly how he challenges the mastery over time that helps to define the ideal of the sovereign subject—an ideal that has prevailed in various iterations in modern Western culture. That sense of mastery and its accompanying anxieties have shaped dominant conceptions of not only responsibility, justice, and freedom, but also of gender, race, embodiment, mortality, and animality. For Levinas, this understanding of subjectivity affirms and perpetuates the basic attitude of the<italic>conatus essendi</italic>, the striving to persevere in one’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20d87sf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
