<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>God's Wounds</book-title>
         <subtitle>Hermeneutic of the Christian Symbol of the Divine Suffering, Volume 2. Evil and Divine Suffering</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pool</surname>
               <given-names>Jeff B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173602</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903155</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jeff B. Pool</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf8fn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book constitutes the second volume of a three-volume study of Christian testimonies to divine suffering: God's Wounds: Hermeneutic of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering, vol. 2, Evil and Divine Suffering. The larger study focuses its inquiry into the testimonies to divine suffering themselves, seeking to allow the voices that attest to divine suffering to speak freely, then to discover and elucidate the internal logic or rationality of this family of testimonies, rather than defending these attestations against the dominant claims of classical Christian theism that have historically sought to eliminate such language altogether from Christian discourse about the nature and life of God. This second volume of studies proceeds on the basis of the presuppositions of this symbol, those implicit attestations that provide the conditions of possibility for divine suffering-that which constitutes divine vulnerability with respect to creation-as identified and examined in the first volume of this project: an understanding of God through the primary metaphor of love (God is love); and an understanding of the human as created in the image of God, with a life (though finite) analogous to the divine life-the imago Dei as love. The second volume then investigates the first two divine wounds or modes of divine suffering to which the larger family of testimonies to divine suffering normally attest: (1) divine grief, suffering because of betrayal by the beloved human or human sin; and (2) divine self-sacrifice, suffering for the beloved human in its bondage to sin or misery, to establish the possibility of redemption and reconciliation. Each divine wound, thus, constitutes a response to a creaturely occasion. The suffering in each divine wound also occurs in two stages: a passive stage and an active stage. In divine grief, God suffers because of human sin, betrayal of the divine lover by the beloved human: divine sorrow as the passive stage of divine grief; and divine anguish as the active stage of divine grief. In divine self-sacrifice, God suffers in response to the misery or bondage of the beloved human's infidelity: divine travail (focused on the divine incarnation in Jesus of Nazareth) as the active stage of divine self-sacrifice; and divine agony (focused on divine suffering in the crucifixion of Jesus of Nazareth) as the passive stage of divine self-sacrifice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="529"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Central Mystery of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book continues my interpretation of the Christian symbol of divine suffering. The first volume of this hermeneutical endeavor disclosed both the hypothetical structure of this symbol and the two primary presuppositions or claims on the basis of which attestations to the symbol emerge.¹</p>
                     <p>In my study, the emerging basic structure of the symbol included a distinct creaturely occasion that correlated with each mode of divine suffering. Consequently, the first volume of my study identified a basic three-fold structure in the Christian symbol of divine suffering, three wounds of God that constitute divine responses to creaturely occasions:<italic>the grief of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part One:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure of Divine Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part one of this second volume in my study examines the first explicit moment (rather than the implicit condition of its possibility in divine vulnerability) in the Christian symbol of divine suffering, the first wound of God. I have described this moment of the symbol, following a majority of Christian attestations to divine suffering, as divine grief.¹</p>
                     <p>This moment in the symbol, like all three of this symbol’s principal moments, develops through the interaction of the two presuppositions that I have already analyzed in volume one of this project.² I repeat the most general features of those two presuppositions.<italic>First,</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division One:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sin as Occasion of Divine Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>God’s creation of humans in the divine image established the conditions of possibility for the occasion of the first divine wound. I have shown previously that the Christian symbol of divine suffering construes human being or life in the image of God as love. Furthermore, as being-inact (<italic>ens actu</italic>), the<italic>imago Dei</italic>actualizes itself as<italic>imitatio Dei</italic>. The human never loses or annihilates the<italic>imago Dei</italic>, but certainly can distort and pervert itself as such.¹ Thus, humans always actualize their being or life as love in an imitation of God either authentically or inauthentically. As Augustine said to God in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Human Cupiditas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human life as<italic>cupiditas</italic>, human sin as the occasion for the first divine wound or divine grief, exhibits several formal characteristics. By no means do I pretend, with my identification of these formal characteristics, exhaustively to analyze this occasion for divine suffering. I only examine here the broad contours of the factors that structure the beloved human’s infidelity, those structural characteristics of human sin that figure most prominently as features of the occasion for the first divine wound. Most generally, according to the Christian symbol of divine suffering, the creaturely occasion for the first divine wound exhibits six formal characteristics:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Human Cupiditas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human life as<italic>cupiditas</italic>, or human sin as the creaturely occasion for divine grief, also exhibits several material characteristics. The disruption among, and the re-ordering of, both the dimensions of human love and the sequentiality of the subjects in the love-relationships determine the material characteristics of sin. When the human lives as<italic>cupiditas</italic>, or when the human falsely actualizes the<italic>imitatio Dei</italic>, then the human disorders both the dimensions and the subjects of its love. As I stated in the first volume of this study, the sequentiality of human love refers to the order among the subjects of love, while</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Two:</title>
                     <subtitle>First Stage of Divine Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human sin, the false or inauthentic actualization of human life as love, human life as<italic>cupiditas</italic>, or the beloved human’s betrayal or rejection of the divine lover, occasions the first divine wound, according to the Christian symbol of divine suffering. Of course, although prominent theologies from the European reformations of the sixteenth century tended to found themselves on theologies of the cross, even those theologies refused to attribute any actual form of suffering to the divine nature: this refusal, of course, extended to divine grief as well.¹ Nonetheless, by radical and intentional contrast, Christian testimonies to divine suffering consistently, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Divine Sorrow:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter identifies and examines the formal characteristics that structure divine sorrow.¹ Several questions immediately arise concerning the interaction among the characteristics of this symbol’s two presuppositions² with reference to the characteristics of human sin in division one of the present volume of studies. (1) What is the relationship between divine vulnerability and this passive stage of divine grief? (2) To which operation or role of the Christian God does the symbol of divine sorrow refer? (3) Toward which subjects does divine sorrow direct itself or with which subjects does God concern the divine self in God’s sorrow? (4) What</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Divine Sorrow:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout my previous analysis of the formal characteristics of divine sorrow, various aspects of divine<italic>caritas</italic>have repeatedly surfaced. In this chapter, then, I will draw together the major strands of those dimensions in divine<italic>caritas</italic>that have emerged in divine sorrow. The three dimensions (philial, agapic, and erotic) of divine love, as expressed in the passive stage of divine grief, constitute the material characteristics of divine sorrow. While all three dimensions of divine<italic>caritas</italic>operate in divine sorrow, the erotic dimension predominates in this mode of divine suffering. Moreover, for this symbol, God actualizes each material characteristic of divine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Three:</title>
                     <subtitle>Second Stage of Divine Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the Christian symbol of divine suffering, God grieves<italic>not only passively</italic>, not only with sorrow over radical human distortion of the relationship between divine creator and creatures, not only about both creaturely self-willed refusal of authentic alterity and God’s un-desired loss of genuine divine enrichment. Due to this selfwilled human abandonment of both God and the human’s own genuine actualization, God also grieves<italic>actively</italic>, a stage of divine grief to which numerous Christian attestations to divine suffering witness.¹ Following numerous testimonies to divine suffering, I have designated the active of divine grief as divine anguish, the anguish of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Divine Anguish:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will inquire into the formal characteristics of the second stage in divine grief through questions that resemble those questions with which I have already examined the first, more passive, stage of this symbol. Again, these questions will also reappear in the following studies of this symbol. (1) What is the relationship between divine vulnerability and the active stage of divine grief? (2) To which divine role or operation does the symbol of divine anguish primarily refer? (3) Toward which subjects does divine anguish direct itself or which subjects concern God in divine anguish? (4) What spatial and temporal features</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Divine Anguish:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The philial, agapic, and erotic dimensions of divine love, as expressed in this active stage of divine grief, constitute the<italic>material</italic>characteristics of divine anguish. Like my study of divine sorrow, in my previous analysis of the<italic>formal</italic>characteristics of divine anguish, various aspects of divine<italic>caritas</italic>have appeared several times. In this chapter, then, I will draw together the major strands of those dimensions in divine<italic>caritas</italic>as they display themselves in divine anguish.</p>
                     <p>All three dimensions in divine love operate within divine anguish as they do in each moment of divine suffering. In divine anguish, however, the order</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part Two:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure of Divine Self-Sacrifice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In part two of this volume of studies, I analyze the second major moment in the Christian symbol of divine suffering, the second wound of God. Following the overwhelming majority of Christian attestations to this symbol, I have described this second divine wound as<italic>divine self-sacrifice</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Like the first divine wound, this second wound of God originates from the interaction of the two presuppositions that I examined in the first volume of this work.¹ The second divine wound, however, differs from God’s first wound in the following way. Human betrayal of the divine lover inflicted the first divine wound, thereby</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Four:</title>
                     <subtitle>Misery of Sin as Occasion for Divine Self-Sacrifice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Christian attestations to<italic>divine self-sacrifice</italic>, the predicament of the beloved human occasions this second mode of divine suffering as well. Strictly considered, however, both the beloved human’s infidelity (human sin) and the misery of the beloved human’s infidelity (the consequences of human sin) comprise the occasion for divine selfsacrifice. Neither sin nor its consequences ever appear isolated from one another, cannot even occur apart from one another. For this reason, previously, I examined as one formal characteristic of human sin the indissoluble bond between sin and its consequences. Nevertheless, the Christian symbol of divine suffering distinguishes these two aspects</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Misery of Human Cupiditas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The formal characteristics of human misery certainly include those initial consequences of human infidelity to God that I briefly described in chapter 1: guilt (<italic>culpa</italic>), self-enslavement to selfdeification or life against God (<italic>servum arbitrium</italic>), and sinful social fatedness or subjugation to a world of sin (<italic>peccatum originale</italic>). For the purposes of this chapter, however, first, I will more fully develop from chapter 1 only my interpretation of the second consequence, since it forms the taproot from which the other formal characteristics of human misery grow. Nonetheless, the second formal characteristic of human misery, human self-destruction, also stems from the central</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Misery of Human Cupiditas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Just as the formal characteristics of human misery depended upon and extended the formal characteristics of human sin from chapter 1, so too the material characteristics of human misery depend upon and extend the basic quality of the material characteristics of the beloved human’s infidelity that I analyzed in chapter 2. The inescapability and conflicts that constitute the misery of human infidelity, however, intensify the disruption and re-ordering of human life as<italic>cupiditas</italic>, both in the dimensions of human love and in the sequentiality of subjects within the relationships of love. In the exposition that follows, I will not repeat</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Five:</title>
                     <subtitle>First Stage of Divine Self-Sacrifice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The misery of the beloved human’s infidelity occasions the second divine wound, according to the Christian symbol of divine suffering. Christian testimonies to this moment in divine suffering overwhelmingly describe this wound of God as divine self-sacrifice for the sake of human reconciliation with God or for the healing of relationships between the divine creator and self-estranged creatures.</p>
                     <p>The verb, “to sacrifice,” originates from the Latin term “<italic>sacrifico</italic>,” a word constructed by combining the word “<italic>sacra</italic>,” from the Latin word “<italic>sacer</italic>,” meaning “holy” or “sacred,” and “<italic>facio</italic>,” meaning “to make” or “to do.” Thus,<italic>etymologically</italic>, “to sacrifice” means to make</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Divine Travail:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my study of the first stage of divine self-sacrifice, or divine travail, I commence with an analysis of the formal characteristics in this moment of divine suffering as I have done previously. Those questions with which I formerly isolated and examined the principal formal characteristics of the first divine wound function similarly here with respect to divine travail. (1) What is the relationship between divine vulnerability and activity in the first stage of divine self-sacrifice? (2) To which divine role or operation does the symbol of divine travail refer? (3) Toward which subjects does divine travail direct itself, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Divine Travail:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In divine travail, the operations and interactions of the three dimensions of divine<italic>caritas</italic>produce divine travail’s material character, but involve even greater complexity than in the two stages of the previous divine wound, principally due to the self-externalization or self-concentration of the divine presence within the creation, through God’s becoming-human as Jesus of Nazareth. Strictly speaking, then, I should examine divine travail by combining analyses that follow<italic>both</italic>the pattern of my analyses of human life as love in terms of<italic>caritas</italic>and<italic>cupiditas and</italic>the pattern of my previous analyses of divine life as love.¹ While aspects of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Six:</title>
                     <subtitle>Second Stage of Divine Self-Sacrifice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the Christian symbol of divine suffering, the misery of human infidelity occasions a second or passive stage in divine self-sacrifice as well, a mode of divine suffering that I have called the agony of God.¹ Although God’s self-relinquishment in order to make possible reconciliation with the unfaithful human also established the conditions of possibility for this second stage in divine self-sacrifice, God neither intended nor planned the divine agony. Divine travail, of course, increased divine risk or vulnerability with respect to unfaithful humans in all of their misery. Thus, while God voluntarily endured the agony of divine sacrifice,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Divine Agony:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formal Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I initiate this analysis of divine agony, as I have in each interpretation of the previous stages in divine suffering, with an exposition of the formal character of divine agony. Furthermore, once again, I submit the same four principal questions to this stage in the Christian symbol of divine suffering, the answers to which yield the formal character or structure of divine agony. (1) What is the relationship between divine vulnerability and this more passive stage of divine self-sacrifice? (2) To which operation or role in the divine life does the symbol of divine agony refer? (3) Toward which subjects</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Divine Agony:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Characteristics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the second stage of divine self-sacrifice, the material character of divine agony closely resembles the material character of divine travail. God has lost the equilibrium between the agapic and erotic dimensions of divine love in divine travail, however, as divine travail progressed into divine agony. Although God’s erotic<italic>caritas</italic>continues to motivate divine agapic<italic>caritas</italic>toward the divine philial goal, during the human’s victimization of the divine lover, the human disequilibrates the operations between these two dimensions of love in divine life. Consequently, the agapic dimension of divine love, with its predominantly self-sacrifi-cial character, assumes the leading role in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Divine Agony to Divine Affliction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While I have concluded my exposition of Christian attestations to divine agony, perhaps the most negative though perhaps not the most perplexing moment in the Christian symbol of divine suffering, I acknowledge that I have left many areas unexplored and other areas more under-developed than I would prefer. Specifically, I would have preferred to develop more extensively my exposition of the features of God’s active resistance in the second divine wound, features that already provide the basis for diverse communities of genuine solidarity with those who suffer oppression, suppression, repression, abuse, marginalization, and victimization. Nevertheless, the Christian symbol of divine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Insights from the Reformed Doctrine of Total Depravity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Concepts of ύβρις and έπιθυμία</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ancient Hellenistic Philosophy and the Christian Concept of Divine Impassibility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 4:</title>
                     <subtitle>Analytical Distinctions between Fear, Anxiety, and Anguish</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>385</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 5:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Impassibility and Passibility in the Theology of Origen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 6:</title>
                     <subtitle>Arian Christologies of the Suffering Logos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 7:</title>
                     <subtitle>Historic Variations on the Classic Christian Theory of Atonement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 8:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fragments from the History of Patripassianist Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 9:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fragments from the History of Theopaschite Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Scriptures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Persons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Topics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>498</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf8fn.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>530</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
