<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Cinema of the Soviet Thaw</book-title>
         <subtitle>Space, Materiality, Movement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Oukaderova</surname>
               <given-names>Lida</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253026354</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253027085</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025302708X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Lida Oukaderova</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz0fb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Following Joseph Stalin's death in 1953, the Soviet Union experienced a dramatic resurgence in cinematic production. The period of the Soviet Thaw became known for its relative political and cultural liberalization; its films, formally innovative and socially engaged, were swept to the center of international cinematic discourse. In The Cinema of the Soviet Thaw, Lida Oukaderova provides an in-depth analysis of several Soviet films made between 1958 and 1967 to argue for the centrality of space-as both filmic trope and social concern-to Thaw-era cinema. Opening with a discussion of the USSR's little-examined late-fifties embrace of panoramic cinema, the book pursues close readings of films by Mikhail Kalatozov, Georgii Danelia, Larisa Shepitko and Kira Muratova, among others. It demonstrates that these directors' works were motivated by an urge to interrogate and reanimate spatial experience, and through this project to probe critical issues of ideology, social progress, and subjectivity within post-Stalinist culture.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="228"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In May 1961 the Soviet film journal<italic>Iskusstvo kino</italic>(<italic>The Art of Cinema</italic>) published a short review of the just-released documentary The City of Great Fate (<italic>Gorod bol’shoi sud’by</italic>), directed by Il’ia Kopalin. The film—selected as an offi-cial Soviet entry for the shorts competition at the Cannes Film Festival taking place the very same month—is a visual lexicon of Moscow and joins numerous other Soviet productions of the 1960s that sought to define the image of the capital city within the more tolerant framework of post-Stalinist Soviet culture. The reviewer A. Zlobin unequivocally praised the film for its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE PERSISTENCE OF PRESENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>SOVIET PANORAMIC CINEMA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Perhaps as no other place, first in the USSR and now Russia, Moscow’s Exhibition of Achievements of the People’s Economy, known widely as the VDNKh, has always operated as a sensitive seismograph of the country’s ambitions and failures. An expansive complex to the north of Moscow’s center, it has lived through several stages of construction throughout its history, each reflecting a particular moment in the developments of Soviet and post-Soviet economy, science, culture, and, most remarkably, ideology. The park opened in its initial form in 1939, with major additions during the first half of the 1950s.¹ In subsequent years the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>MIMETIC PASSAGES:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CINEMA OF MIKHAIL KALATOZOV AND SERGEI URUSEVSKII</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 1962 roundtable discussion on the use of wide and panoramic screens in Soviet cinema conducted by<italic>Iskusstvo kino</italic>, the prominent Soviet director Mikhail Kalatozov advised against an overreliance on new film technologies but declared simultaneously his interest in “achieving the effect of widescreen cinema shooting with 16mm film.”¹ Kalatozov’s opinion carried significant weight. Since the mid-1950s, he had emerged as one of the most respected Soviet filmmakers, especially after his war melodrama<italic>The Cranes Are Flying</italic>(<italic>Letiat zhuravli</italic>, 1957) won the Palme d’Or at the 1958 Cannes Film Festival, an event that returned Soviet cinema to the attention</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE ARCHITECTURE OF MOVEMENT:</title>
                     <subtitle>GEORGII DANELIA’S I WALK THE STREETS OF MOSCOW</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a surprising correspondence in the opening seconds of two very different films: Georgii Danelia’s<italic>I Walk the Streets of Moscow</italic>, a Soviet production from 1964 that is relatively unknown to international audiences, and Jacques Tati’s<italic>Playtime</italic>, a widely discussed French masterpiece from 1967. The Soviet film begins at a Moscow airport, with a young woman dancing and humming as she moves along a glass-curtain exterior wall (figure 3.1). The French film, set in Paris, begins with two nuns walking first on the outside of and then on the interior side of a glass terminal façade, eventually disappearing around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A WALK THROUGH THE RUINS:</title>
                     <subtitle>LARISA SHEPITKO’S WINGS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A dialogical interaction between body and space; an unfolding of the built environment through bodily motion; the body’s becoming like space: These are the visual tropes that have dominated our discussion of the films in the previous two chapters. In their radical portrayals of the body– space relations, Mikhail Kalatozov’s<italic>The Unsent Letter</italic>and<italic>I Am Cuba</italic>and Georgii Danelia’s<italic>I Walk the Streets of Moscow</italic>displayed a certain level of utopian imagining, in which participants functioned less as specific, psychologically nuanced characters than as poetic, and in that way abstract, figures. We can remember once more the critique of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE OBDURATE MATTER OF SPACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>KIRA MURATOVA’S BRIEF ENCOUNTERS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The interior environment that Kira Muratova creates in<italic>Brief Encounters</italic>, her first independently made film, is strange, to say the least. Overflowing with objects and textures of all kinds—heavily ornamented furniture, kitchenware, bookshelves, wallpaper, curtains, sculptural reliefs, pictures, and much more—her environments monopolize our attention, drawing us away from the people who inhabit and have shaped them. Sometimes these objects appear next to a human figure, doubling the focal point of the image; at other times they alone are presented in prolonged, nearly immobile shots reminiscent of still-life compositions. We can observe this, for instance, in the opening</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE OTHERNESS OF SPACE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The cinematic scrutiny of space in Soviet culture of the 1950s and 1960s was rooted in an urgency to find new forms of social engagement. It was also propelled by a need to redefine the role of cinema in the wake of Stalin’s death. Rethinking the language of cinema, Soviet filmmakers began to emphasize the production of the environment as a social and filmic problem, creating spatial experiences within theatrical walls that differed significantly from those of established socialist practices. These filmmakers reorganized the spaces of familiar cities, landscapes, and public and private interiors, opening them up to dialogical interactions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FILMOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0fb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
