<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p09z</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ4479.P48 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Petrarca, Francesco, 1304–1374. Rime</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Petrarch's 'Fragmenta'</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Narrative and Theological Unity of 'Rerum vulgarium fragmenta'</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PETERSON</surname>
               <given-names>THOMAS E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781487500023</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781487510015</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1ch7768"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Building on recent Petrarch scholarship and broader studies of medieval poetics, poetic narrativity, and biblical intertextuality, Peterson conducts a rigorous examination of the<italic>Fragmenta's</italic>poetic language.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Petrarch’s composition of<italic>Rerum vulgarium fragmenta (Fragments of Vernacular Matters</italic>) over more than four decades, the conscious manipulation of narrative time is critical.¹ The story that is told and the account of the telling are constantly interwoven and complicated by their relationship to the author’s life. In recognition of the intrinsic complexity of the work’s narrative and compositional scheme, recent commentators have voiced scepticism about long-accepted interpretations of the work.² As Marco Santagata writes, “Delle strutture simboliche, dei sovrasensi, della complessa trama di richiami di cui il libro è gravato, né i contemporanei, né i posteri si sono accorti.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Historical Context and Poetic Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Starting with the court of Frederick II and the poetics of the Sicilian school, a doctrine of love with its origins in philosophy and medical science was disseminated. The elevation of the imagination by the Sicilian school had its highest manifestation in Giacomo da Lentini, for whom the image of the beloved, painted in the lover’s heart, corresponded to the Aristotelian notion of the phantasm, the<italic>quo</italic>of sense cognition. This<italic>fantasma</italic>could preserve the beloved’s presence in the heart when she was absent. The imagination could exist independently of any physical object or perception, being, as Aquinas would argue,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Temporality and Desire (Rvf 22–100)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To tell a fable requires great cultivation of language but also great simplicity. The fabulist confronts an enigma, as in the “daily bread” of the Gospel, which is ordinary bread to eat but also the “supersubstantial” bread of the sacrament.² Within the space of the early poems of the<italic>Fragmenta</italic>, the Petrarchan subject has experiences that are difficult, dominated by beauty and fear, a wondrous imprisonment. This is the space of fable.</p>
                     <p>Fables rely on magical objects, more powerful than the characters; around these objects a force field exists that determines the narrative links of cause and effect. These events</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>The Language of Tears (Rvf 92–122)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The language of tears seen in poem 92, “Piangete, donne, et con voi pianga Amore” (“O ladies weep, and may Love weep with you”), mourning the death of Cino da Pistoia, establishes the act of weeping not simply as a natural part of grief but as a means of prostrating oneself before God together with the community.¹ To weep openly is to break stoic apathy. In fact, the prominence of tears in Petrarch’s poetry is not unrelated to his practice of the Holy Offices and recitation of scripture (especially the Psalms): weeping is an ingredient of his prayers that finds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>In fresca riva:</title>
                     <subtitle>Landscape and History (Rvf 125–183)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The great canzoni series,<italic>Rvf</italic>125 to 129, stands at the centre of all the canzoni in the<italic>Fragmenta</italic>and establishes the mediating role of landscape in the development of the book’s major themes.¹ As canzoni of “lontananza” (distance from the beloved), the poems establish the means by which the subject will integrate personal history within the larger collective history of the day and the providential history of Christian piety. Within the macrotext, this series marks the eclipse of a dichotomous view in which the subject and Laura are opposed to one another for the sake of a view of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>The Penitent Lover (Rvf 184–263)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 4 we saw emerge a history of the subject who foregrounded the act of writing by documenting his past and affirming the ethically constructive nature of poetry. In the desire to narrate was discovered a source of the sacred, a spiritual quality intrinsic to the act of selfdisclosure. In my analysis of the poet’s use of antithesis, I showed how this trope belied the stereotype of psychological inertia and became a source of eurhythmic harmony. So, too, the use of parallelism was seen to bring into focus the problematic of desire and the will, mitigating the presence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Songs of Grief and Lamentation (Rvf 264–318)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Five blank pages in Vat. Lat. 3195 separate Part 1 and Part 2; the break comes between poems 263 and 264 and does not coincide with the death of Laura. If the poems of Part 1 immerse us in the story of the Petrarchan subject, whether in the fabulous mode of homodiegetic fiction or that of historical narrative, in Part 2 the voices of character, narrator, and author converge, consolidating the mode of spiritual autobiography.</p>
                     <p>With the advent of a unitary subject in Part 2, we see the intervention of a contemplative time frame that vitiates the dichotomy between the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>Songs of Consecration (Rvf 319–366)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the final forty-eight poems, many of which are rearranged during the late 1360s, one is abreast of the ultimate dilemma, that of time.¹ The emotional oscillations of the earlier poems of Part 2 recede as the narrative incorporates the events of the personal story into the metaphysical prospects of eternity and timelessness. We saw in chapter 6 the confrontation between the progressive time of history and the circular, repetitive time of nature. Now the neutral (kairotic, rhythmic) time of contemplation has assumed prominence. The appropriate narrative form for this “in-between” time is the parable, a mode that is accompanied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As new critical perspectives unfold, today’s reader can better grasp how the publication and reception of<italic>Rerum vulgarium fragmenta</italic>has varied over the centuries, revealing the literary biases of different eras. Starting with Velutello’s<italic>Il Petrarca</italic>(1525), the original structure and sequence of the<italic>Fragmenta</italic>was lost sight of as the work was cut apart and rearranged. Though later editions included all 366 poems in the proper order, the convention of beginning Part 2 at poem 267 and titling the parts “in vita” and “in morte” persisted. Writing in the second half of the sixteenth century, Antonio Minturno perceived the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7768.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
