<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h09qg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">H61.B855 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social sciences</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Methodology</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanities</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Methodology</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Building New Bridges - Bâtir de nouveaux ponts</book-title>
         <subtitle>Sources, Methods and Interdisciplinarity - Sources, méthodes et interdisciplinarité</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Keshen</surname>
               <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Perrier</surname>
               <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615523</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615521</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Ontario</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ch77q1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Questions of methodology and the use of sources are fundamental to all academic disciplines. In recent years, this topic has become far more challenging as scholars are increasingly adopting an interdisciplinary approach to achieve richer and deeper analyses, particularly in the humanities and social sciences. Building New Bridges / Bâtir de nouveaux ponts is a collection of scholarly papers that deals with the first principles of source identification and their effective utilization.</p>
         <p>The contributors to the volume come from a wide range of disciplines and represent both French and English Canada. Together, they explore and encourage the interdisciplinarity trend - around which considerable academic trepidation remains - and seek to explain, for example, how historians and those in English or Lettres françaises analyze texts, how scholars approach paintings, photography, and film, and how the study of music relates tempo and lyrics to wider societal trends. They utilize their respective research to elucidate means of effectively employing evidences and methods to achieve richer, deeper, and more nuanced results. As a whole, the collection provides an excellent primer for scholars of methodology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="300"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keshen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perrier</surname>
                           <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Interdisciplinarity</italic>, a term scarcely known as recently as a decade ago, today seems all the rage within academe. Cutting edge research is now often perceived as synonymous with interdisciplinarity. Bringing together scholars from different disciplines, often for team-based research, projects are now being tackled by experts from a variety of perspectives and, as often claimed, at a depth beyond the capacity of a single researcher. Melding older, often traditional, disciplinary-based approaches and utilizing sources in novel ways, interdisciplinarity has supposedly taken scholarship to a higher level, yielding fresher, more nuanced, and ultimately more sophisticated analyses.</p>
                     <p>The practitioners of interdisciplinarity are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Vellum and Vaccinium:</title>
                     <subtitle>Documentary and Archaeological Evidence in the Study of Medieval Produce</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Masemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The systematic study of gardens as loci of food production during the Middle Ages has largely been overlooked by agrarian historians. Economic agrarian history is based epistemologically on the idea that human actions can best be understood through their economic foundations and consequences, and methodologically on the idea that the best and most accurate conclusions can be reached from a base of quantifiable and documented evidence. This strong epistemological and methodological base has resulted in a large body of excellent and rigorous work. Its focus on numbers and documents has, however, largely obscured the economic importance of cultivation carried out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Talking Numbers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Deconstructing Engineering Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hull</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consider the following:</p>
                     <p>(i) For columns reinforced with both longitudinal steel and spirally wound hooping when the volume of hooping is equal to at least one per cent of the volume of the enclosed concrete and the longitudinal reinforcement is not less than one per cent, and not more than four per cent of the cross sectional area, the safe load shall be computed as follows:</p>
                     <p>Safe load (in pounds) = 650 (Ac + 15 As).</p>
                     <p>Ac = Net cross sectional area of concrete enclosed in hooping in square inches</p>
                     <p>As = Cross sectional area of longitudinal reinforcement in square</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Model Behaviour:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Material Culture Approach to the History of Anatomy Models</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lamb</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The anatomical model - a re-creation of normal or pathological anatomy created in various material - is usually regarded as simply a teaching aid for those studying to be physicians, and although the historical discourse surrounding anatomy often testifies to that purpose alone, a diversity in its function emerges if the researcher looks beyond the written text. The artistic choices made by creators of anatomical models reinforce messages about how a society views its own corporality, and by examining the way in which anatomy models are fabricated and decorated, cultural attitudes about the body in a given time period can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Re-disciplining the Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Helps</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the “veritable flood of books, conferences, and panels on body history, or bodies in history,” why, historian Kathleen Canning asks, has the body remained a largely “unexplicated and undertheorised historical concept.”¹ I would add that this lack of<italic>historical</italic>theorization is particularly surprising in light of the veritable torrent of literature on the body over the last fifteen years in areas as diverse as geography, philosophy, anthropology, cultural studies, and biology, to name only a few. In addressing this disparate body of work, medieval historian Caroline Bynum has argued that “despite the enthusiasm for the topic, discussions of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Uncooperative Primary Source:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literary Recovery versus Historical Fact in the Strange Production of Cogewea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strong</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the first novel written by a Native American woman,<italic>Cogewea</italic>:<italic>The Half-Blood</italic>holds a position of historical and symbolic importance for American literature. Prepared in manuscript form as early as 1914, but not published until 1927,<italic>Cogewea</italic>is a fascinating read that blends tropes from romance, Western, autoethnography, captivity narrative, and realism. In its confusions, earnestness, and collaborative minglings, Mourning Dove’s novel is uniquely North American; it could not have been written by anyone but a North American. The excitement and tension of its contents, its multi-voicings, and the necessary frustrations of its narrative sutures comprise a consummate artistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Reading Books/Reading Lives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Culture, Language and Power in Nineteenth-Century School Readers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lorenzkowski</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Barbara Lorenzkowski Written in pencil, the letters on the page are fading, yet still convey a boyish exuberance. “Today,” Louis Breithaupt scribbled into his diary on March 21, 1867, “I received a beautiful picture from Mr. Wittig (the German teacher at school) because I read from page 120 to 215 in the German reader. I’m good.” In deciphering the Gothic print of his German reader, the twelveyear heir of one of Berlin's premier families enjoyed a distinct advantage. Louis was growing up in Waterloo County, the heartland of German settlement in nineteenth century Ontario, whose residents lived their lives in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Rigueur et sensibilite dans un parcours historien</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Watelet</surname>
                           <given-names>Hubert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’expose comprend deux parties. La premiere traite d’exigences de rigueur dans une these sur la revolution industrielle dans un bassin houiller beige. Concue dans les annees 1950-1970, elle s’inscrit dans le contexte des belles theses franfaises d’histoire economique regionale de l’epoque. Cependant c’est aussi une etude de<italic>business history</italic>, qui relevait plutol d’historiens britanniques ou de Harvard. A cet egard, elle se differencie de l’historiographie francaise. Le titre du livre signale cette originalite en annon? ant la specificite de la region etudiee et l’approfondissement d'une entreprise¹. La recherche ful pensee Ires tot selon les theses d'Elal encore en cours en</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Inside Out:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Use and Inadvertent Misuse of Oral Histories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ettinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Laura E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the space of a few years, I did two very different kinds of research projects. One involved interviewing Jews, who, as children, had attended a social settlement house in early twentieth century Rochester, New York, while the other entailed interviewing nuns, who had gone to nurse-midwifery school at Catholic Maternity Institute in Santa Fe, New Mexico, in the 1950s and 1960s.¹ This article focuses on oral histories and interviewers’ complex relationships with their subjects by comparing the interviews I conducted for these two projects. In one case, I shared the cultural background of the people I interviewed - that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Les sources juridiques au service de l’histoire socio-culturelle de la France médiévale et moderne</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fianu</surname>
                           <given-names>Kouky</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perrier</surname>
                           <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Depuis quelques décennies, l’histoire sociale, médiévale aussi bien que modeme, exploite ce matériau de choix que sont les archives judiciaires pour étudier le fait social dans toute sa complexité: travail, migrations, pratiques matrimoniales, marginalité, criminalité, etc. Depuis peu cependant, le questionnement s’est porté sur la nature et la signification des actes juridiques et sur les pratiques qu’ils révèlent. Le renouveau de l’histoire du notariat, en particulier, a amene les historiens à s’intéresser à la pratique notariale autant qu’au contenu des actes, redonnant ainsi sa juste place au contexte juridicoprofessionnel qui a produit a ces sources incontournables de l’histoire sociale¹.</p>
                     <p>De</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Revisiting Quantitative Methods in Immigration History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Immigration History Immigrant Files in the Archives of the Russian Consulates in Canada</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kukushkin</surname>
                           <given-names>Vadim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two decades, quantitative methods of analyzing historical sources seem to have lost much of their appeal in Canadian and American immigration historiography, reflecting a trend common to social historians in general. Historians on both sides of the border have largely abandoned analyzing international population movements from a macrohistorical perspective in favour of studying local immigrant neighbourhoods through the prism of ethnicity/race, class, and gender.¹ Influenced by the postmodernist critique of historical objectivity and the knowability of the past, academic scholars are becoming increasingly sceptical of seeing population statistics and other serial datasets as windows on past reality.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Réflexions sur la question identitaire d’après les recensements informatisés:</title>
                     <subtitle>L’exemple des « Suisses » en Ontario (1871-1881)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Khalid</surname>
                           <given-names>Samy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>En 1871, François Challet est fermier près du lac Huron, en Ontario. A l’occasion du recensement cette année-là, il explique qu’il est Suisse de naissance, mais Français de nationalité. Au même moment, à Toronto, l’apprenti Charles Sutter déclare au recenseur qu’il est né en Suisse et de nationalité suisse.</p>
                     <p>Dix ans plus tard, en 1881, François Challet confirme qu’il est né en Suisse, mais, cette fois, se décrit comme étant Suisse de nationalité. Quant à Charles Sutter, le recenseur le retrouve à Edmonton, où il se définit comme Allemand et affirme qu’il est né en Ontario.</p>
                     <p>Ces personnages n’ont rien</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The Politics of Sources and Definitions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bradatan</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Demographic transition is a well-known theory in demography, and it is still considered one that is “alive” (Hirschman, 1994). The ideas of a changing demographic pattern as societies modernize appeared sometime at the beginning of the nineteenth century. Among the first who gave a shape to this theory were Notenstein (1953) and Davis (1963). They observed that fertility and mortality decreased in most of the industrialized world and noted the relationships between these demographic phenomena and some other components of social life, such as modernization and economic development. The classical form of demographic transition states that industrialization and urbanization created</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Reporting the People’s War Ottawa (1914-1918)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keshen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was Canada’s first total war. It defined politics, economics, and the ideological milieu. But until recently, nearly all works on Canada’s home front in the Great War have kept analysis to the macro level, removing the conflict from day-to-day life to focus on matters such as the war’s role in building Canadian nationalism, as well as, conversely, national cleavages. This is now changing as demonstrated by recently published works on World War I Toronto and a comparative study of the Great War experience in Guelph, Medicine Hat and Trois-Rivieres.¹ Still, as historians Jay Winter and Jean-Louis Major wrote in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Documents in Bronze and Stone:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memorials and Monuments as Historical Sources</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vance</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1925, in passing its verdict in the competition to design Winnipeg’s civic war memorial, the judging panel declared for the winner with the following words: “The sentiment is simply and directly expressed in a manner about which no doubt can be felt and no questions need to be asked.”¹ For these judges, the winning design was not open to interpretation; it had one meaning and one meaning only, and that meaning would endure for all time.</p>
                     <p>Nearly a century’s worth of experience with commemoration later, it seems ludicrous to suggest that the meaning of a monument could be so</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>The Evidence of Omission in Art History’s Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Romba</surname>
                           <given-names>Katharine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Katharine Romba Historians have long sought the assistance of written texts when examining the visual and material evidence of a culture, considering what is said in the writings of the time to be an important indicator of pertinent issues, themes, and perspectives regarding the object.</p>
                     <p>Art historians are no exception. They have looked to artists and architects - like Wassily Kandinsky and Le Corbusier - as well as to theorists and critics - like Charles Baudelaire and Clement Greenberg - for elucidation of the content and meaning of art and architecture. In addition, the rise in archival research has taken</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Images:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mode(s) d’emploi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>De Groote</surname>
                           <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’image est un mode d’expression fixé dans le temps et dans l’espace. Bien lue, elle fournit des éléments de compréhension sur une époque et un endroit donnés. Les qualités des images n’ont pas échappé aux historiens. Encore faut-il pouvoir les lire et les regarder, bien voir pour bien comprendre. Dans notre contribution, nous nous proposons de mettre en évidence les atouts et difficultés du discours iconographique comme source historique. Les historiens exploitent de plus en plus les témoignages figurés, essentiellement dans le secteur de l’histoire des mentalités. Les images portent en elles des signes de leur époque et de leur</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>What do the Radio Program Schedules Reveal?</title>
                     <subtitle>Content Analysis versus Accidental Sampling in Early Canadian Radio History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacLennan</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although content analysis is used extensively in the field of communications, it has been applied only sporadically to broadcasting history. Most of the standard works on Canadian radio history are nationalistic in tone and make reference to the threat of American programming without quantifying its impact for assessment. Extensive content analysis of Canadian radio program schedules during the 1930s in Vancouver, Montreal, and Halifax questions some of the long-held historical misconceptions about Canadian radio. While judgmental samples and the representations of lobbyists to government commissions would be considered suspect and completely unsuitable for a contemporary study, these remain the standard</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Television as Historical Source:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Images in Cultural History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caron</surname>
                           <given-names>Caroline-Isabelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us reflect on the state of historiography in Canada and the usual reluctance of Canadian historians, whether English- or French-speaking, to use audio-visual sources in their research. Whereas they readily use all forms of textual sources, oral sources, and even some iconographic sources, historians shy away from film and television. They rarely refer to these productions for purposes other than as illustrative and teaching tools. Historians do not readily analyze audio-visual sources in Canada. They leave them to specialists of film and communication studies.</p>
                     <p>In my research on Quebec cultural history I have purposefully looked at representations of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>“Wie es eigentlich gewesen?”</title>
                     <subtitle>Early Film as Historical Source?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beaulieu</surname>
                           <given-names>Michel S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a phrase, a “dirty” one to use my grandmother’s vocabulary, which is a mere whisper in the hollowed halls of academia in North America. But, on exceptionally cold winter nights, it can still be faintly heard -haunting and taunting - the hordes of structuralists, post-structuralists, modernists, and post-modernists that can be found huddled in every nook and corner of university campuses:</p>
                     <p>It is a belief, an incantation as E. H. Carr suggests, that while “not a very profound aphorism [it] had an astonishing success.”² This sentence embodied for nearly a century the activity performed by academic historians. Leopold</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Evidence of What?</title>
                     <subtitle>Changing Answers to the Question of Historical Source as Illustrated by Research Using the Census</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaffield</surname>
                           <given-names>Chad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Surprisingly and in repeatedly unexpected ways, historians have continued to debate in recent decades the central question of their craft: how can the past be described and explained? At each stage of the debate, the answers to this question have reflected and contributed to larger epistemological discussions across the disciplines. The following discussion examines selected aspects of the twists and turns of recent historical debate by using the example of research on census enumerations. From the time of the “new social history” of the 1960s and 1970s to the cultural history of the 1980s and 1990s, scholars have focused on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch77q1.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors/Collaborateurs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
