<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1551mts</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sanctity as literature in late medieval Britain</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VON CONTZEN</surname>
               <given-names>EVA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BERNAU</surname>
               <given-names>ANKE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780719098178</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0719098173</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Manchester University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1mf7103"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Explores how sanctity and questions of literariness are intertwined across a range of medieval genres.This collection explores some of the many ways in which sanctity was closely intertwined with the development of literary strategies across a range of writings in late medieval Britain. Rather than looking for clues in religious practices in order to explain such changes, or reading literature for information about sanctity, these essays consider the ways in which sanctity - as concept and as theme - allowed writers to articulate and to develop further their 'craft' in specific ways. While scholars in recent years have turned once more to questions of literary form and technique, the kinds of writings considered in this collection - writings that were immensely popular in their own time - have not attracted the same amount of attention as more secular forms. The collection as a whole offers new insights for scholars interested in form, style, poetics, literary history and aesthetics, by considering sanctity first and foremost as literature</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Contzen</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bernau</surname>
                           <given-names>Anke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>sanctity as literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Contzen</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does it mean to approach sanctity as<italic>literature</italic>? ‘Literature’ is often used as the umbrella term for any kind of writing produced in the medieval period, but this is not the kind of literature the title of this collection refers to. Instead, ‘literature’ is used synonymously with ‘the literary’ or ‘literariness’ – that is, a special quality of some texts. The explicit aim of this volume is<italic>not</italic>to provide an exhaustive definition of the literary in the late medieval period. Such an attempt can only fail given the complexity of the concept and its manifold implications. The examples considered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>St Margaret and the literary politics of Scottish sainthood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ash</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canonised in 1250, Queen Margaret of Scotland is perhaps one of the most familiar Scottish saints to modern readers, yet surprisingly little material relating to her life (beyond brief mentions in chronicles) survives from the Middle Ages. Furthermore, there has been little scholarly consideration of the literariness of representations of Margaret. What work has been done focuses on Margaret as a historical figure, or uses material relating to her sanctity as evidence for the existence of particular sites of veneration within Scotland. These studies are useful for understanding Margaret’s role in Scotland in historical and religious terms, and suggest avenues</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Good knights and holy men:</title>
                     <subtitle>reading the virtue of soldier-saints in medieval literary genres</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lynch</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hagiography and romance have long been understood to have some important elements in common, such as narrative patterns of edification and exemplarity, an overlapping repertoire of incidents and motifs, and a penchant for valuing strenuous affectivity, especially bodily suffering. It is not surprising that these literary genres quite frequently occur in the same manuscript miscellanies, or that their heroes can sometimes switch genres.¹ Nor is it surprising that actual knights claimed for themselves a form of religious virtue on the grounds of their bodily trials.² Yet secular knighthood and Christian sanctity are by no means a perfect match. Although soldier</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Englishing the saints in Robert Mannyng’s Handlyng Synne</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Greenspan</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In medieval England, as elsewhere, episodes from the lives of the saints constituted one of the most common sources of story, both for layfolk and professional religious. Saints were popular heroes in every genre, held up for admiration, imitation, a good laugh, or the relief of a despairing heart. In their piety and love of God, saints provided models for all of Christendom. Their deeds could be recast for specialised purposes: to demonstrate, for example, how to wield earthly power, conduct oneself appropriately towards superiors or inferiors, resist oppression, or recognise the sins arising from inborn qualities. In Robert Mannyng</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modelling holiness:</title>
                     <subtitle>self-fashioning and sanctity in late medieval English mystical literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barr</surname>
                           <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Dere lord Ihesu mercy, þat welle art of mercy, why wyl not myn herte breste and cleue in-two?’¹ So begins the shorter of Richard Rolle’s<italic>Meditations on the Passion</italic>, a fourteenth-century affective devotional text that describes the speaker’s imagined witnessing of Christ’s passion. Noteworthy here is the use of pronouns: while the<italic>Meditations</italic>is in a large sense for its audience’s spiritual benefit, the speaker’s focus is on his own emotional state; it is<italic>his</italic>heart that he wishes would split, so overwhelmed is he by the evidence of Jesus’ sacrifice and his own unworthiness. In a work that serves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Body and soul:</title>
                     <subtitle>from doctrine to debate in medieval Welsh and Irish literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fulton</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Middle English poem attributed to John Lydgate,<italic>The Pilgrimage of the Life of Man</italic>, translated from the French poem by Guillaume de Deguileville, the allegorical figure of Grace Dieu, hoping to guide the Pilgrim safely on his journey to salvation, describes the relationship between the body and the soul. Addressing the Pilgrim’s soul, the seat of his intellect and cognition, Grace Dieu tells him that he must fight ‘lyk a myghty champyoun’ against the ‘deceyt &amp; flaterye’ of the body who will otherwise lead him to damnation.¹</p>
                     <p>To illustrate her point that the body and soul are separate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Chaucer and hagiographic authority</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sisk</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While much has been written about Chaucer’s debt to French, Italian and Classical literature,¹ comparatively little attention has been devoted to Chaucer’s engagement with hagiography, even though writing about the saints was the most popular and widespread medieval narrative tradition.² Chaucer’s own legend of St Cecilia is generally regarded as the first (or most)<italic>literary</italic>example of vernacular hagiography produced in late medieval England, but his engagement with the tradition goes far beyond the application of verbal artistry to the celebration of sanctity. After writing this legend (later repurposed as the tale told on the road to Canterbury by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Reading classical authors in Capgrave’s Life of St Katherine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>James</surname>
                           <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To characterise John Capgrave as a writer of ‘literature’ has been, until recently, to court controversy, if not outright dissent. In his foreword to the Early English Text Society’s edition of Capgrave’s<italic>Life of St Katherine</italic>, Frederick Furnivall spares no time to consider what, if any, literary merit might attach to the work, being instead concerned to provide a rather patronising author portrait before launching into an embittered attack upon Carl Horstmann’s editorial decision-making; the text, it seems, is of no more than antiquarian concern.¹ More recently M. C. Seymour dismisses Capgrave’s literary credentials; his<italic>Life of St Norbert</italic>is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Lydgate’s saintly poetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bernau</surname>
                           <given-names>Anke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While most scholarship on the works of John Lydgate has tended to concentrate on ‘secular’ works such as<italic>Troy Book</italic>(<italic>c</italic>. 1412–20) or Fall of Princes (<italic>c</italic>. 1431–38), more recently some voices have started to speak out about the innovative aspects of his religious writings, especially his saints’ lives. Thus, in 2006, Fiona Somerset urged scholars to look across Lydgate’s immense and diverse oeuvre, arguing that ‘Lydgate’s hagiographical writings are a particularly fertile ground for such cross-comparison’.¹ Jennifer Sisk, taking up that invitation in 2010, writes about<italic>St Edmund and St Fremund</italic>(<italic>c</italic>. 1433) that it ‘modulates in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Narrating vernacular sanctity:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Scottish Legendary as a challenge to the ‘literary turn’ in fifteenth-century hagiography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Contzen</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fifteenth century, it has been argued, hagiography underwent a ‘turn to more “literary” saints’ lives’.¹ This turn, which is characterised by a new depiction of saintly exemplarity and a new self-understanding among the authors of hagiographic writings, is said to have inaugurated the saint’s life as a literary genre.² Chaucer’s<italic>Second Nun’s Tale</italic>marks the turning point, although the change is fully realised half a century later only, in the saints’ legends composed by John Lydgate, Osbern Bokenham, John Capgrave, and others. That there are discernible differences between a compilation such as the South English Legendary or the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Reforming sanctity:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Digby Mary Magdalen and Lewis Wager’s Life and Repentaunce of Marie Magdalene</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Atkin</surname>
                           <given-names>Tamara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sanctity, the quality of being holy, is by definition an inviolable state.¹ This chapter takes as its subject two plays that give dramatic shape to the life of Mary Magdalene, the sinner turned saint whose conversion might best be read as a crash course in becoming holy. They are: the Digby<italic>Mary Magdalen</italic>(<italic>c</italic>. 1490s), which survives in a single manuscript, Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Digby 133; and Lewis Wager’s<italic>Life and Repentaunce of Marie Magdalene</italic>(<italic>c</italic>. 1553), which was printed twice in the 1560s. Although both plays work to reveal the holiness of the Magdalene’s life, the decisions made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The humanist grammar of sanctity in the early Lives of Thomas More</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Larsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna Siebach</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the dedicatory epistle of his<italic>Life of Sir Thomas More</italic>, Nicholas Harpsfield refers to his text as ‘a garlande decked and adorned with pretious pearles and stones’, fashioned from the ‘pleasaunt, sweete nosegaye of most sweete and odoriferous flowers’ of William Roper’s own, earlier<italic>Lyfe of Sir Thomas Moore</italic>.¹ Collapsing temporal and technological boundaries, Harpsfield’s description encompasses his subject, his style, and – in its evocation of the verdant borders of the manuscript or the woodcut title page – the potential materiality of his text. It indicates a moment of transition, in which familiar motifs, genres, and symbols can be reappropriated,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>calendar time in balade form</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sanok</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a stanza at the close of his mid-fifteenth-century<italic>Life of St Ursula and the 11,000 Virgins</italic>, Osbern Bokenham outlines how readers might say 11,000 Pater nosters during the course of a year in order to secure the intercession of this heavenly company.¹ The stanza is readily categorised as instrumental verse: its single function is announced in the preceding stanza: ‘And who-so lyste knowe how he may do / This nowmbyr to perform euen in a yere / the next kalende shewyth doctryn clere’ (‘And whoever would like to know how he may perform this number accurately in a year,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf7103.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
