<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8wwmkk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Emyr Humphreys</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Postcolonial Novelist?</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GREEN</surname>
               <given-names>DIANE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780708322178</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780708322598</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Wales Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CARDIFF</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Diane Green</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qhf1h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book explores in detail the novels written by Emyr Humphreys during a timespan of over fifty years, from his first, A Little Kingdom, published in 1946, to The Gift of a Daughter, published in 1998.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Editor’s Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thomas</surname>
                           <given-names>M. Wynn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Postcolonialism and Wales:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Effects of Cultural Imperialism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A discussion of Emyr Humphreys as a postcolonial author involves a number of issues alongside an examination of his work, including whether postcolonial theories are in fact relevant in the study of Welsh literature. However, it is clear from international events in the early years of the twenty-first century that concepts of nation and national identity merit careful examination and are still a motivating force engendering significant repercussions. Throughout the twentieth century a variety of commentators from myriad backgrounds took part in the public discussion of what exactly Welsh identity comprises, alongside literary discussions concerning Welsh literature and its relationship</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>‘A serious Welsh novelist’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Redressing the Balance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emyr Humphreys’s views on his fiction writing and postcoloniality will be the subject of this chapter. As we have seen, there are a variety of attitudes towards the consideration of Wales as a postcolonial nation. What is of paramount concern here is the attitude of the novelist himself, and the possible reasons for that vision: the personal connections with Wales, the education and career, the important influences, the conjunction of artistic and political aims. An understanding of these issues throws light upon the fiction itself and the reasons for considering it to be postcolonial work. Indeed, one way of regarding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Emergence of Humphreys as a Postcolonial Writer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is concerned with Humphreys’s early fiction: the first six novels published between 1946 and 1957 and particularly the seventh,<italic>A Toy Epic</italic>, which was finally published in 1958. The main postcolonial strategies that Humphreys has used throughout his career emerged and were refined during this period: the use of Wales as the location of the plot, the use of Welsh history and myth, the discussion of the variety of Welsh life. The focus of the discussion will be on the ways in which these techniques evolved and the reasons behind their use – the extent to which those reasons</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Consolidation of Strategies in Outside the House of Baal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Outside the House of Baal</italic>builds on Humphreys’s achievement in<italic>A Toy Epic</italic>and is certainly the single text in which he best achieves his aims as a novelist-cum-Welsh nationalist. Whereas ‘The Land of the Living’ sequence will in its seven volumes cover a greater stretch of Welsh history and chart its effect on a wider range of characters, this single novel’s scope is both more specifically focused and in literary terms more adventurous. The novel has aWelsh setting and is a realistic portrayal of life in various areas of Wales, particularly the north, from the end of the nineteenth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Strategies of Resistance:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Use of Indigenous Myth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Using indigenous myth within a work of fiction is an established postcolonial strategy of resistance. The fact that Humphreys made a practice of using classical myth in a variety of narrative techniques in his fiction before he began to use Celtic myths predominantly does not prevent his use of indigenous myth being considered as a deliberately anti-imperial strategy. ‘The Land of the Living’ sequence is perhaps the best, certainly the most complex, example of his use of a variety of tales from<italic>The Mabinogion</italic>, although the Blodeuwedd archetype has occurred in his fiction throughout his career.² Humphreys has written extensively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Strategies of Resistance:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Use of Indigenous History in ‘The Land of the Living’ Sequence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emyr Humphreys’s later novels fall naturally into two groups: ‘The Land of the Living’ sequence (197–91) and the independent novels:<italic>The Anchor Tree</italic>(1980),<italic>Jones</italic>(1984),<italic>Unconditional Surrender</italic>(1996) and<italic>The Gift of a Daughter</italic>(1998). In both groups there is deliberate intention on the part of the author to utilize Welsh history, whether by using ‘textbook’ or anecdotal sources, his own memory of events and their repercussions in Wales during the twentieth century or, indeed, by using the history of other nations as a commentary on the Welsh situation. Each way in which Humphreys uses history may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Strategies of Resistance:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Use of History in the Independent Novels of the 1980s and 1990s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is the issue with which Emyr Humphreys wrestles both in his sequence of novels and in the independent novels written concurrently. Using very different techniques, Humphreys is concerned, no less in the independent novels than in his ‘The Land of the Living’ sequence, both to express the importance of its history to Welsh society and to instruct his reader about that history. After writing<italic>National Winner</italic>in 1971, and<italic>Flesh and Blood</italic>and<italic>The Best of Friends</italic>in 1974 and 1978 respectively, Humphreys produced two novels, independent of the sequence,<italic>The Anchor Tree</italic>(1980) and<italic>Jones</italic>(1984). Four more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Monstering and Disabling:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paradigms and Tropes of Dispossession</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout his long career as a novelist Emyr Humphreys has been inclined to reuse certain tropes, archetypes and paradigms, albeit in novels of a variety of types. We have seen in the earlier chapters that his protagonist is often a weak, over-sensitive male who is failing in some way in his familial or social life. From<italic>A Man’s Estate</italic>onwards this character has increasingly dominated and particularly in those novels concerned with the matter of Wales. John Cilydd More, in ‘The Land of the Living’ sequence, is a prime example. This character may in certain ways epitomize for the author</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Postscript:</title>
                     <subtitle>Speaking Welsh in English – a Postcolonial Purpose</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jonathan White quotes Ngugi Wa Thiong’o’s description of imperialism’s ‘cultural bomb’ which has the effect of annihilating ‘a people’s belief in their names, in their languages, in their environment, in their heritage of struggle, in their unity, in their capacities and ultimately in themselves’.² This is the effect which Humphreys’s writing constantly attempts to counter but problems occur, as we have seen, because of his writing in English, in his eyes, the language of imperialism. White criticizes Ngugi’s main solution, which is the rejection of the language of the colonizer, arguing that strategies are needed to overcome the worst legacies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Selected Bibliography of Emyr Humphreys’s Fiction and Essays</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Selected Bibliography of Writing on Emyr Humphreys’s Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>262</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhf1h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
