<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18dxwm7</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>South African performance and archives of memory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HUTCHISON</surname>
               <given-names>YVETTE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780719083730</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781526103239</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yvette Hutchison</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18mbfgr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book explores how South Africa is negotiating its past in and through various modes of performance in contemporary theatre, public events and memorial spaces. It analyses the Truth and Reconciliation Commission as a live event, as an archive, and in various theatrical engagements with it, asking throughout how the TRC has affected the definition of identity and memory in contemporary South Africa, including disavowed memories. Hutchison then considers how the SA-Mali Timbuktu Manuscript Project and the 2010 South African World Cup opening ceremony attempted to restage the nation in their own ways. She investigates how the Voortrekker Monument and Freedom Park embody issues related to memory in contemporary South Africa. She also analyses current renegotiations of popular repertoires, particularly songs and dances related to the Struggle, revivals of classic European and South African protest plays, new history plays and specific racial and ethnic histories and identities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTE ON TERMINOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For decades theatre in South Africa had a specific role: to ‘protest’ injustices, to break silences, to provoke debate on issues in spaces that could facilitate discussion, often actually during performances. This theatre was about lived experiences that were often officially denied. As Fugard suggests, play-makers like himself sought ‘to witness as truthfully as [they] could, the nameless and destitute (desperate) of this one little corner of the world’ (1983: 172). This witnessing extended beyond telling one’s own stories, to the dramatisation of those of wider communities. These plays were not about the past; they explored present realities, while rehearsing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Truth and Reconciliation Commission’s reconfiguring of the past:</title>
                     <subtitle>remembering and forgetting</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter begins with the moment of rupture: with the release of Mandela in 1990 and the negotiations for full democracy in South Africa to be achieved by 1994, followed by a period of transition, characterised publicly to a large extent by the Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), which sat from 1994–98. It will look at the role the TRC has played, both as live event and as an archive produced from oral testimonies, in the construction of a ‘new’ South Africa. In analysing the archive, I explore its function, how it has been performed and constructed, the various</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Dramatising the Truth and Reconciliation Commission:</title>
                     <subtitle>the role of theatre practitioners in exploring the past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The end of apartheid brought with it many changes, including changes to the memories with which we engage. The TRC and arts practitioners have played different roles in piecing together fragments of memories: in reconstructing a sense of a shared past and thereby formulating a narrative for the new ‘rainbow nation’, or by challenging the silences in official histories. This chapter focuses on the contributions of the performing arts in these processes.</p>
                     <p>During apartheid many artists, such as Athol Fugard, saw their role as ‘just to witness as truthfully as [they] could’ the experiences of South Africa (Fugard, 1983: 172).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Staging a nation:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Voortrekker Monument and Freedom Park</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The inherited apartheid archives embody particular narratives of South Africa, especially those that defined separate cultural identities, with their relative worth and histories. The way these archives of memory were constructed and controlled is important (Rokem, 2000), especially insofar as they affected the social structure of the nation, beyond apartheid legislation. This chapter looks at how at moments of political crisis or transition, specific narratives of history, from particular cultural perspectives, have been performed in public spaces to define national identities. It begins by looking at how South Africa narrated and performed itself in the 1910 South African Pageant of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Performing the African Renaissance and the ‘rainbow nation’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far I have explored how South Africa has renegotiated its geopolitical spaces, defined in its social relations, political imperatives, value systems and the way it has constituted its authority via the TRC. I have also examined how it has negotiated its psychosocial construction of nation by foregrounding particular memories through the TRC and physicalised these narratives in commemorative spaces, specifically in Freedom Park. I now turn to explore Thabo Mbeki’s South African Renaissance project, which is significant insofar as it shifted South African engagement with local memories and histories to situating the country within the context and discourses of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Post-apartheid repertoires of memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I turn now from these performances of memory by state or cultural institutions to look at embodied repertoires in the public sphere and in theatres. While the TRC clearly attempted to hear hidden stories and renegotiate the perceptions and values of South Africans, its effect was limited because a state of mind, values, and peoples’ views cannot be easily changed. Thus the extent to which the creative arts can facilitate further dialogue on the past and what the ‘rainbow nation’ means for individual people are important insofar as the arts can reach local communities in spaces outside of everyday reality.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECT BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbfgr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
