<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">LCC B3279.H49 I358 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Husserl, Edmund, 1859–1938</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Technology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Technology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Husserl's Missing Technologies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>IHDE</surname>
               <given-names>DON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823269600</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823269631</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19x3jd4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Husserl's Missing Technologies looks at the early-twentieth-century "classical" phenomenology of Edmund Husserl, both in the light of the philosophy of science of his time, and retrospectively at his philosophy from a contemporary "postphenomenology." Of central interest are his infrequent comments upon technologies and especially scientific instruments such as the telescope and microscope. Together with his analysis of Husserl, Don Ihde ventures through the recent history of technologies of science, reading and writing, and science praxis, calling for modifications to phenomenology by converging it with pragmatism. This fruitful hybridization emphasizes human-technology interrelationships, the role of embodiment and bodily skills, and the inherent multistability of technologies. In a radical argument, Ihde contends that philosophies, in the same way that various technologies contain an ever-shortening obsolescence, ought to have contingent use-lives.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="184"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface:</title>
                     <subtitle>First Encounters with Husserl’s Phenomenology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophy of Technology, Technoscience, and Husserl</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about and in response to Edmund Husserl’s phenomenology and his notion of science. No one would claim that Husserl was a founder of philosophy of technology, although his writings about science are substantial and persistent. Readers may note that my<italic>Heidegger’s Technologies: Postphenomenological Perspectives</italic>(Fordham, 2010) was a response to Heidegger’s foundational work in precisely philosophy of technology. This book parallels that work by turning to Husserl on technologies despite his ambivalence and lack of focal attention to technologies or even to instruments in science. Husserl remained throughout his life a believer in the primacy of science</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Where Are Husserl’s Technologies?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I begin the analysis of Husserl’s technologies, I now raise the stakes. It was noted previously that his references to technologies, by wide consensus of Husserl scholars, are sparse, and one can add, for the most part, these are mentioned in passing without serious or in-depth philosophical analysis. Thus I am calling these his “missing technologies.”</p>
                     <p>In what sense are technologies missing from Husserl? In a first, very ordinary sense, they are mostly missing from his writings. He infrequently refers to what today we would call technologies, and in this sense one has to conclude that they do not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Husserl’s Galileo Needed a Telescope!</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is a look at Husserl’s explicit philosophy of science in the light of contemporary analyses of science in practice. The<italic>Crisis,</italic>published in 1936, was his last major publication on this topic. Yet it takes very little imagination to realize that since 1936, epochal changes have occurred in both the sciences and the interpretations of science, including philosophy of science.</p>
                     <p>Twentieth-century history of science, I argue, has been marked by changes that are at least as profound as those that marked the turn from Aristotelian science to early modern science in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. Since World</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Embodiment in Reading-Writing Technologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter describes a transition from Husserl’s classical phenomenology to postphenomenology. Here I examine, primarily, Husserl’s own technologies—reading and writing technologies, including his eyeglasses for his aging sight problems, his own writing style, which uses pens and standup and then sit-down desks, the role of the typewriter and its associated copy processes with references to early twentieth-century scholarly distribution—and then I contrast these with his informal comments concerning scientific technologies, those of optics, and other tools.</p>
                     <p>I return first to a theme introduced in Chapter 1, the finite life-spans of technologies. Because I am going to discuss the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Whole Earth Measurements Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Society for Philosophy and Technology met in Puebla, Mexico, 1996, and I presented a paper titled “Whole Earth Measurements,” a bit tongue-in-cheek, which looked at the problem of global warming. My subtitle was “How Many Phenomenologists Does It Take to Detect a Green house Effect?” and I turned to both Heidegger and Husserl as my exemplary phenomenologists. This was before today’s grand political debate about climate change with so many rightwing people not only denying global warming but arguing particularly that the homogenic factors claimed are a great hoax. Here I return to that issue as a crucial testcae</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Dewey and Husserl:</title>
                     <subtitle>Consciousness Revisited</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Phenomenology as a twentieth-century philosophy has since its classical beginnings been portrayed as a subjective philosophy and frequently claimed to be antiscience. I argue that both characterizations are false or distortions of phenomenology, and so a modification of classical phenomenology is needed, and that is postphenomenology. This chapter follows that trajectory in a somewhat different way. The late twentieth century began to see two science paradigm shifts in the Kuhnian sense. The first was a revival and renewal of interest in consciousness and the other, often closely related, in animal studies. Here I interweave these two contemporary movements to a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Adding Pragmatism to Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pragmatism and phenomenology are twentieth-century American-European philosophical twins. Both began early in the twentieth century and have undergone modifications that still hold in the twenty-first century. Here I examine both Deweyan and Husserlian beginnings with a look at their later developments and with an eye to postphenomenology.</p>
                     <p>Previous scholarship has pointed up many of the inter-connections between pragmatism and phenomenology: Husserl was strongly influenced by William James, whose principles of psychology he had already digested in the 1890s, and he credited James with showing him the way out of “psychologism.” Bruce<italic>Wilshire’s William James and Phenomenology</italic>(Indiana, 1968) thoroughly traces</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>From Phenomenology to Postphenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The act of naming frequently follows somewhat behind the thing or process to be named. That was clearly the case with both science and technology. If early modern science began, as the standard view has it, in the seventeenth century, it was not until 1833 that it was named<italic>science</italic>by William Whewell. Earlier the most frequent name was<italic>natural philosophy</italic>. Similarly, technology for a long time, even after the Industrial Revolution, was called a product of the industrial arts, or simply<italic>machines</italic>, or products of engineering. Historians of technology, including Thomas Hughes and David Nye, point out that technology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Epistemology Engines</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19x3jd4.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
