<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>London Irish Fictions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Narrative, Diaspora and Identity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MURRAY</surname>
               <given-names>TONY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846318313</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846317897</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Tony Murray</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vjm19"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is the first book about the literature of the Irish in London. By examining over 30 novels, short stories and autobiographies set in London since the Second World War, London Irish Fictions investigates the complex psychological landscapes of belonging and cultural allegiance found in these unique and intensely personal perspectives on the Irish experience of migration. As well as bringing new research to bear on the work of established Irish writers such as Edna O’Brien, John McGahern, Emma Donoghue and Joseph O’Connor, this study reveals a fascinating and hitherto unexplored literature, diverse in form and content. By synthesising theories of narrative and diaspora into a new methodological approach to the study of migration, London Irish Fictions sheds new light on the ways in which migrant identities are negotiated, mediated and represented through literature. It also examines the specific role that the metropolis plays in literary portrayals of migrant experience as an arena for the performance of Irishness, as a catalyst in transformations of Irishness and as an intrinsic component of second-generation Irish identities. Furthermore, by analysing the central role of narrative in configuring migrant cultures and identities, it reassesses notions of exile, escape and return in Irish culture more generally. In this regard, it has particular relevance to current debates on migration and multiculturalism in both Britain and Ireland, especially in the wake of an emerging new phase of Irish migration in the post-‘Celtic Tiger’ era.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="222"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For centuries, London has occupied a powerful place in the imagination of artists of all kinds. Writers, in particular, have profoundly influenced popular perceptions of the city. This has especially been the case for people who have visited or migrated to London from elsewhere. New arrivals, whether from the provinces, continental Europe or further afield, have all formed relationships with the city in the light of work by writers such as Samuel Pepys, Charles Dickens, Virginia Woolf and Zadie Smith. For arrivals from other parts of the former British Empire or the Commonwealth, coming to London has often been a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Irish in London</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Irish people have been deeply woven into the fabric of London life for centuries. The first records of Irish migrant workers originate from the twelfth century, when the majority were employed as labourers and street-vendors, although some had to resort to other means of survival, as evidenced by a statute in 1243 to expel Irish beggars.¹ By Tudor times, the Irish were no strangers to a city which had, in John Denvir’s lurid description, ‘seen many an Irish chief and noble brought in chains to perish miserably in the gloomy dungeons of the Tower’.² Lesser mortals were excluded from work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the mid-1930s Britain had overtaken the United States as the primary destination for Irish migrants.¹ By the end of the Second World War, when Ireland experienced the largest wave of emigration since the Great Famine of the 1840s, this had become overwhelmingly the case.² Whereas in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries Scotland and the north of England had been the favoured destinations for Irish migrants, London and the south-east of England now emerged in this position.³ According to Jackson, the Irish-born population of London rose by more than half between 1951 and 1961 to reach 172,493.⁴ After the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Navvy Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the closing days of 2003, heated debates took place in the Irish parliament over the plight of elderly Irish men in Britain in the wake of a documentary shown on national television.¹ Many of the interviewees in the programme had spent the best part of their working lives on the building sites of England, but due to major changes in the construction industry over the previous twenty years and the financially insecure nature of their employment, such men were now living out their final days in extremely impoverished conditions in the very towns and cities they helped rebuild after</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Escape and its Discontents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Edna O’Brien is regarded today as one of Ireland’s most eminent writers. Declan Kiberd, for instance, has referred to her prose style as one of ‘surpassing beauty and exactitude’.¹ Such accolades, however, are a relatively recent phenomenon. It is only in the last ten to fifteen years that substantial critical attention has been paid to her work, largely due to the endeavours of feminist scholars.² Most criticism of O’Brien’s work has been from the perspective of gender and sexuality, something which is not surprising given the subject-matter of her early work.³ For critics who read her through psychoanalytical theory, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Ersatz Exiles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prospects for pursuing a literary career in the censorious moral climate of mid-twentieth-century Ireland were seriously circumscribed. Literature was a key target of the draconian censorship laws passed by the government of the Irish Free State and there were few opportunities and outlets for young aspiring writers, many of whom were forced (in time-honoured fashion) to seek fulfilment of their ambitions abroad.¹ For centuries, London had provided Irish writers with a potentially international market for their work. As a global hub of theatre and publishing, and by 1945 more physically accessible than hitherto, it became the favoured choice of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Departures and Returns</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emigration has been at the heart of Irish life for centuries, not least in the post-war years. Even if many men and women chose not to leave Ireland, nobody was entirely immune to the effects of migration. Most people knew at least one person, whether it was a relative or an acquaintance, who had decided to ‘take the boat’. Conversation and, to some degree, preoccupations and way of life in Ireland during the post-war years were deeply underscored by emigration. Even if its economic and social ravages were sometimes consigned to the periphery of public debate by politicians and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Ireland slipped into severe recession in the late 1970s and early 1980s, unemployment rose dramatically. By 1984, it accounted for 16.4 per cent of the workforce and one in three out of work were under the age of twenty-five.¹ In parts of Dublin the figures were much higher, and it was here that the social consequences of unemployment were most marked, with a major drug and crime epidemic hitting the city. Meanwhile, in Northern Ireland, the intransigent position of the Thatcher government in relation to republican prisoners’ demands for political status led to the hunger strikes of 1981. As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Gendered Entanglements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Margaret Mulvihill is one of the few Irish women writers to have written consistently about the experiences of the post-war Irish in Britain. Her three novels are all period pieces set in London in the 1980s and early 1990s and her characterizations of young Irish migrants from this time mirror some of the satirical observations in earlier work by Anthony Cronin and Donall Mac Amhlaigh. However, for Mulvihill, who was born in Dublin in 1954 and came to London in her twenties, her perspective on the subject of migration was also imbued with a pronounced feminist sensibility. Apart from being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Ex-Pat Pastiche</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the economic and political circumstances of 1980s’ Ireland, emigration presented an attractive option – and in some cases the only option – for young people north and south of the border. The two key protagonists of the works I examine in this chapter, the first from Dublin and the second from Belfast, are representative of these changes. Their authors, Joseph O’Connor and Robert McLiam Wilson respectively, were typical of a new generation of Irish authors at the time who brought a renewed youthful iconoclasm to the pages of Irish fiction. Here, familiar locations of Irish London (the building site;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Transit and Transgression</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her inaugural address as President of Ireland in 1990, Mary Robinson stated that she saw her election as an opportunity for Irish people worldwide to ‘tell diverse stories […] stories of celebration through the arts and stories of conscience and social justice’.¹ Seven years later Gerry Smyth argued that</p>
                     <p>something fundamentally different has overtaken novelistic discourse in Ireland since the mid-1980s […] a willingness to confront the formal and conceptual legacies of a received literary (and wider social) tradition alongside a self-awareness of the role played by cultural narratives in mediating modern (or perhaps it would be better now</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the British census of 2001, which for the first time allowed respondents to indicate their ‘cultural background’, only seven to eight per cent of an estimated two to two and a half million second-generation Irish people in Britain ticked the box marked ‘Irish’. Researchers have offered a number of reasons why such a small percentage of second-generation migrants were disinclined to identify themselves in this way, among them being a tendency to read the concept of ‘cultural background’ (or ethnicity) as equivalent to formal nationality.² The outcome of the census illustrates just how difficult it is to quantify or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Irish Cockney Rebels</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The authors of the three memoirs I analyse in this chapter are all second-generation Irish men who grew up in working-class neighbourhoods of post-war London and explore this experience from the perspective of middle age. In the course of writing about their backgrounds, they regenerate themes and tropes familiar from texts in the previous two parts of this study. These occur in relation to narratives of nationality and gender, and also with regard to religion, class and sexuality. The conflicts and disjunctions of belonging that ensue are in part common experiences of childhood and adolescence, but in other ways they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Elastic Paddies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In September 2009, Fintan O’Toole wrote an article in the<italic>Irish Times</italic>in tribute to the late second-generation Irish poet, Michael Donaghy. Born in the Bronx, Donaghy lived most of his life in London and, through his work, epitomized the ambivalent yet undeniable attachment to Ireland experienced by many of the second generation. In the article, for which O’Toole coined the term I have used to title this chapter, he makes the following statement about Irishness:</p>
                     <p>Irish culture is nothing if not persistent. It can sometimes seem so elastic, so open to infinite variation and appropriation, as to be virtually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The novels, short stories and auto/biographical texts I have examined in this book are written and peopled by men and women who, as well as making journeys from one country to another, have embarked upon narrative journeys of the mind. Unlike the geographical journey of migration, however, narrative is not a linear process. Instead, it possesses an inherent temporal elasticity that often enables writers to deploy inventive methods and modes of storytelling and characterization. Rather than simply providing a series of period snapshots, these texts reveal how identities are configured over time as well as space. In other words, they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author Biographies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm19.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
