<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Hidden Intercourse: Eros and Sexuality in the History of Western Esotericism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hanegraaff</surname>
               <given-names>Wouter J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kripal</surname>
               <given-names>Jeffrey J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823233410</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246441</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Koninklijke Brill NV</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5cjzn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>From rumors about gnostic orgies in antiquity to the explicit erotic symbolism of alchemical texts, from the subtly coded eroticism of medieval kabbalah to the sexual magic practiced by contemporary occultists and countercultural translations of Asian Tantra, the history of Western esotericism is rich in references to the domains of eros and sexuality. This volume, which brings together an impressive array of top-level specialists, is the first to analyze the eroticism of the esoteric without sensationalism or cheap generalizations, but on the basis of expert scholarship and attention to textual and historical detail. While there are few domains where the imagination may so easily run wild, the various contributions seek to distinguish fact from fiction-only to find that historical realities are sometimes even stranger than the fantasies. In doing so, they reveal the outlines of a largely unknown history spanning more than twenty centuries.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="568"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THINGS WE DO NOT TALK ABOUT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kripal</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanegraaff</surname>
                           <given-names>Wouter J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, the academic study of Western esotericism has been developing rapidly from a somewhat obscure specialty pursued by a few dedicated researchers into a burgeoning professional fi eld of scholarly activity and international organization. Once a domain restricted to the relatively secluded circles of specialists and hence hidden from the sight of most academic and non-academic readers, it is now becoming an increasingly popular topic of public and critical discussion in the context of journals, monographs, conferences, and scholarly organizations.¹ The book you now hold in your hands is the fruit, one of many, of this growing branch</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SEXUALITY AND SEXUAL SYMBOLISM IN HERMETIC AND GNOSTIC THOUGHT AND PRACTICE (SECOND–FOURTH CENTURIES)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van den Broek</surname>
                           <given-names>Roelof</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this fi rst chapter we will be dealing with two broad, variegated, and partly interconnected religious currents that both fl ourished in Late Antiquity and emphasized the importance of spiritual knowledge (<italic>gnōsis</italic>). One of them is known as Hermetism, and the other is usually called Gnosticism.</p>
                     <p>The hermetic current claimed to transmit the teachings of the ancient Egyptian sage Hermes Trismegistus.¹ The magical, astrological, and alchemical hermetic writings attributed to Hermes, and usually referred to as the “technical hermetica,” fall beyond the scope of the present chapter, which concentrates on what is known as “philosophical Hermetism.” Its most characteristic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCEIVING SPIRITS:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MYSTERY OF VALENTINIAN SEX</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DeConick</surname>
                           <given-names>April D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Valentinian thought and practices have been the subject of countless academic studies even prior to the discovery of the Nag Hammadi collection in 1945. In this literature, the Valentinians were characterized as elitist Gnostics who believed in the certainty of their salvation due to the existence of a particle of spirit within them, a “seed” which guaranteed the acquisition of<italic>gnosis</italic>. Due in part to their characterization as spiritual snobs and intellectual egotists, they have been portrayed either as libertines who believed that they could claim a certain sexual freedom denied to other Christians, or as conservatives who embraced celibacy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SEXUAL INTERCOURSE BETWEEN HUMANS AND DEMONS IN THE ISLAMIC TRADITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lory</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “esoteric” has a very specific meaning in the Islamic tradition. The Koran as well as other fundamental religious texts emphasize the difference between what is “ apparent” and “ outward” (<italic>zâhir</italic>) and what is “hidden” and “inward” (<italic>bâtin</italic>).<italic>Zâhir</italic>is everything that is obvious in our perceptions and thoughts (an empirical phenomenon, the meaning of a text), about the presence of which no doubt can be raised.<italic>Bâtin</italic>is what is not expressed outwardly (feelings for instance), what is hidden in natural phenomena, or concealed in speech. The “hidden” is, however, no less real than the “apparent.” On</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MURMURING SECRETS:</title>
                     <subtitle>EROTICISM AND ESOTERICISM IN MEDIEVAL KABBALAH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wolfson</surname>
                           <given-names>Elliot R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I commence with a generalization the validity of which must be illustrated from particular instantiations: eroticism and esotericism converge at the point of their divergence. Or, so it might seem, as eroticism ostensibly exposes the concealed and esotericism conceals the exposed. On closer examination, however, this contrast does not engender divergence as much as difference that suggests its own sameness in being different. Alternatively expressed, exposure of the concealed and concealment of the exposed ought not be seen as binary opposites; hermeneutically, exposure is the most exposed concealment, and concealment the most concealed exposure. To attend this paradox is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TA‘ANUG:</title>
                     <subtitle>EROTIC DELIGHTS FROM KABBALAH TO HASIDISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Idel</surname>
                           <given-names>Moshe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Describing feelings is a notoriously difficult thing to do. The problem is enhanced when those who do so use a language that is not their vernacular, and even more so when that language is part of sacred scriptures, which are understood as paradigmatic and as informing or teaching some sublime forms of experience that took place in the glorious past. Caught between the artificiality of the language and the authority of the sacred texts, the dimension of personal experience is often attenuated and sometimes even obliterated. Clichés, models, paragons, rituals, and ideals canonized in the ancient past are powerful obstacles</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COMPLICATIONS OF EROS:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SONG OF SONGS IN JOHN OF MORIGNY’S LIBER FLORUM CELESTIS DOCTRINE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fanger</surname>
                           <given-names>Claire</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the long and varied tradition of medieval Christian commentaries on the Song of Songs, the yearning for the beloved, articulated from both masculine and feminine perspectives, becomes key to a hermeneutic construction illuminating the relation of the divine to the cosmos, the community of believers, and the individual soul. There are specific adumbrations of this tradition in which the virgin Mary is read into the story as the desiring bride. The liturgies for the Marian feast days drew upon the Song (as well as on other passages from the biblical Wisdom literature), and these Marian liturgies in turn necessitated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>UNDER THE MANTLE OF LOVE:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MYSTICAL EROTICISMS OF MARSILIO FICINO AND GIORDANO BRUNO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanegraaff</surname>
                           <given-names>Wouter J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary and philosophical phenomenon of the Renaissance<italic>trattati d’amore</italic>began with the publication in 1484 of Marsilio Ficino’s highly influential<italic>De Amore</italic>(first manuscript version 1469) and found an impressive culmination in Giordano Bruno’s<italic>De gli eroici furori</italic>published in 1585. Many greater or lesser authors contributed to the development of the genre during the intervening century,¹ resulting in an extensive corpus of treatises devoted to “Renaissance love theory.”² John Charles Nelson, in one of many scholarly studies that have been devoted to the subject, emphasizes that these writers</p>
                     <p>chose to treat love “Platonically” as an intellectual, nonsexual, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REVEALING ANALOGIES:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE DESCRIPTIVE AND DECEPTIVE ROLES OF SEXUALITY AND GENDER IN LATIN ALCHEMY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Principe</surname>
                           <given-names>Lawrence M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sexual and erotic language and imagery is extremely common in alchemy. Its most visible form occurs in oft-reproduced alchemical emblemata that routinely contain graphic depictions of gendered entities and copulating couples. Alchemical texts regularly employ erotic language as well, often describing extended allegorical sequences that occasionally involve sexual intercourse of various kinds or at least employ highly gendered imagery. Even at the most basic level, alchemists frequently speak of their substances as gendered—some as female, some as male, and some, rather famously, as hermaphroditic. Among modern commentators, the presence of such imagery has engendered a variety of explanations—of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PROBING WOMEN AND PENETRATING WITCHCRAFT IN EARLY MODERN EUROPE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coudert</surname>
                           <given-names>Allison P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout western history knowledge has been conceived of as a commodity controlled and rationed by those in authority. Kant’s<italic>sapere aude</italic>(dare to know) would have made no sense if it had not been preceded by centuries of admonitions about the dangers of knowledge and especially of curiosity. A condemnation of curiosity runs like a leitmotif through the medieval and early modern periods, persisting among social, intellectual, and religious conservatives to this very day.¹ For example, Roger Shattuck’s relatively recent book Forbidden Knowledge offers a modern version of the very old critique of the impious nature of seeking out the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SENSUOUS RELATION WITH SOPHIA IN CHRISTIAN THEOSOPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Faivre</surname>
                           <given-names>Antoine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The biblical texts which mention Sophia, “the Divine Wisdom” (hokmâ in Hebrew, sapientia in Latin),¹ have been the object of many commentaries throughout the history of Christianity.² Her ontological status is one of the most debated issues in the history of sophiology. Two interpretations have been, and still are, particularly prominent. The first one considers her as a “personification,” that is, just an aspect or even a mere metaphor of Christ or of the Holy Spirit (an interpretation fostered by the use of the very term “Divine Wisdom”); whereas, according to the other, she is a “real Person,” alongside the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>DEADLY DATES:</title>
                     <subtitle>BODIES AND SEX IN SPIRITUALIST HEAVENS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
                           <given-names>Cathy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his writings on love and marriage, eighteenth-century visionary Emanuel Swedenborg asserts that conjugal love can take one of two trajectories and unite either the good with the true or else the false with the evil; participants in such unions are bound for heaven or hell respectively. Marriage is divinely ordained, and the union of God and the church stands as the ideal union to which humans should aspire. Reporting from his mystical visits to a heaven resonating with Neoplatonic overtones in which the lower and higher worlds mirror each other, Swedenborg’s writings intimate that the image of God is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SEXUAL MYSTICISMS IN NINETEENTH CENTURY AMERICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>JOHN HUMPHREY NOYES, THOMAS LAKE HARRIS, AND ALICE BUNKER STOCKHAM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Versluis</surname>
                           <given-names>Arthur</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we look at the more noteworthy developments in nineteenth-century American attitudes regarding sexuality, we can consider them in terms of broad social changes—like the emergence of the “free love” movement in the nineteenth century—or focus on particularly significant individuals. Here we choose the latter approach, for while a general understanding of broad social movements is of course important as background, the study of American esotericism inexorably requires one to consider specific individuals, their context, writings, and thought. This is particularly true when it comes to nineteenth-century American exemplars of sexual mysticism—that is to say, authors whose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PASCHAL BEVERLY RANDOLPH AND SEXUAL MAGIC</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deveney</surname>
                           <given-names>John Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the mid-nineteenth century, magic (and the occult generally) in the West were in parlous straits, paralleling those described in the surprising recent bestseller by Susanna Clarke,<italic>Jonathan Strange &amp; Mr. Norrell</italic>.¹ The novel is set in a fair approximation of early nineteenth-century England and depicts a world in which magic was venerated, indeed diligently studied, but in an antiquarian fashion only, with no thought of—and indeed a horror of—practical application of the trove of abstruse knowledge. Magic before the arrival of the mysterious Mr. Norrell is a bit of flotsam only, the debris of a once-great synthesis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE KNIGHT OF SPERMATOPHAGY:</title>
                     <subtitle>PENETRATING THE MYSTERIES OF GEORGES LE CLÉMENT DE SAINT-MARCQ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pasi</surname>
                           <given-names>Marco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do you want to know a secret? It is a secret that has been kept intact for centuries, but it is of supreme importance, actually indispensable for understanding the real essence of Christianity and the hidden development of Western culture. It can give you the key to penetrating the core of all religious traditions in the world. Here it is: during the Last Supper, it is not bread and wine that Jesus Christ gave to the apostles as symbols of his body and of his blood. What Jesus really offered on that occasion, which was to become the model for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE YOGA OF SEX:</title>
                     <subtitle>TANTRA, ORIENTALISM, AND SEX MAGIC IN THE ORDO TEMPLI ORIENTIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Urban</surname>
                           <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since their first discovery of the complex body of texts and traditions known as “Tantra,” Western authors have been at once horrified and tantalized, scandalized and titillated, by this seemingly exotic form of Eastern spirituality. Above all, Western authors have been particularly obsessed with the use of sexual rituals in Tantric practice—a phenomenon that was a source of disgusted revulsion for most Christian missionaries and Orientalist scholars, even as it was a source of erotic allure for many European esoteric groups. By the end of the nineteenth century, in fact, Tantra had begun to be appropriated by various European</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE THEORY AND PRACTICE OF SEXUAL MAGIC, EXEMPLIFIED BY FOUR MAGICAL GROUPS IN THE EARLY TWENTIETH CENTURY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hakl</surname>
                           <given-names>Hans Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>445</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For obvious reasons, sexual magic is a subject that evokes controversy and curiosity. Surprisingly, however, there exists—with the laudable exception of two works on the Hermetic Brotherhood of Luxor and on Paschal Beverly Randolph¹—practically no critical scholarly literature that studies it as a historical phenomenon and, as a result, the information available to a wider public tends to be sensationalist, secondhand, and mostly unreliable. In this chapter we will present a factual presentation of the theories and practices of four of the most important groups and orders devoted to sexual magic in the twentieth century, based upon direct</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE ROAR OF AWAKENING:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE EROS OF ESALEN AND THE WESTERN TRANSMISSION OF TANTRA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kripal</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The multiple weavings of eroticism and esotericism within the history of the Esalen Institute in Big Sur, California—the mother of the American human potential movement founded in 1962 by Michael Murphy (1930) and Richard Price (1930–1985)—is a vast half-century tapestry whose multiple patterns, colors, and textures I have woven elsewhere in some detail.¹ The present essay is not a summary or replication of that historiographic project. Rather it is a further theorization of and reflection on the results of it. It is a “standing back” to see one, and only one, of the final weaves or gestalts,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>521</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF PERSONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjzn.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF SUBJECTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>540</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
