<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r6b0f9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Fundamental Theology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mansini</surname>
               <given-names>Guy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229850</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229867</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1z27h24"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Fundamental Theology</italic>examines the light by which the mysteries of Christ and the Church, the Trinity and the Sacraments, are revealed to us. That light we call "revelation," and fundamental theology examines in the first place what this light shows about itself, and how it is sustained in the world. Or again, fundamental theology considers what the word of God has to say both about itself and what it has to say about where in the world it is to be heard. So, first it is a theology of Revelation (chapter 1), and second, a theology of the transmission of Revelation in Tradition, Scripture, and the Church (chapters 2, 3, and 4). Why must Revelation have the shape it does, and why must it be constituted by both word and event? Why is Tradition prior to Scripture, why must the word of God be written down, and why must Scripture come to us in two testaments? And why must the message conveyed in Tradition and Scripture have a living interpreter in the Church?Since no word is spoken unless it is heard, fundamental theology also investigates the conditions of hearing the word of God, the very hearing itself in the assent of faith, and a necessary consequence of this hearing. The remote conditions of hearing are also what theology calls our ability to come to the knowledge of the<italic>preambula fidei</italic>- the things about God than can be known by the natural light (chapter 5). The immediate condition of hearing is the credibility of the word (chapter 6). Hearing is faith (chapter 7). And true hearing gives the hearer to recapitulate what is heard in his own wondering and thankful voice in theology (chapter 8). The introduction to theology in the last chapter is by way of considering the history of Catholic theology in the 20th century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theology is a word about God—talk about God. When it is simply our talk, purely human talk about God, it can be philosophical, something we find in Aristotle’s<italic>Metaphysics</italic>. More originally, there is God’s talk about God. Before the foundations of the world were laid, there is the eternal Word of God, the Word that St. John says was “in the beginning” (Jn 1:1). Since God’s Word expresses not only the infinite intelligibility of God, but contains the original pattern of every created thing, it already encompasses within itself all true human speech about God, including true philosophical speech</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>REVELATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The second paragraph of<italic>Dei Verbum</italic>, the<italic>Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation</italic>(1965) of the Second Vatican Council, provides a helpful outline of things to be treated in considering Revelation.¹ The paragraph begins with a declaration of the end of revelation, to wit, that the Father so reveal himself through Christ and in the Holy Spirit that we can draw near to him (Eph 2: 18) and share in the divine nature (2 Pt 1: 4). Thus we become friends with God (Jn 15: 14–15), and God enters into our life. Second, it turns to the nature of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>TRADITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are four things that follow upon revelation, that keep revelation present and complete it—completion in a sense other than its completion at the death of the last apostle. Revelation is first communicated by the words and deeds that make salvation history and which culminate in the Paschal Mystery. “The things we have heard from our fathers,” however, “we will not hide from their children, but tell them to the next generation, the children yet to be born” (Ps 78: 3–4). This handing on of the deeds of the Lord and the words that illuminate them is Tradition.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>SCRIPTURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is hard to imagine a long transmission and therefore a long ecclesial tradition of the word of God without writing, and so without the Writings, the Scriptures.¹ Revelation consists in words and deeds. Deeds, or facts, are difficult to fix in permanent form without writing, and difficult to arrange in some ordered sequence without writing.² As for the New Testament, the necessity of recording in some stable form both eyewitness testimony to the events of Jesus’ life, as well as an accurate remembrance of his words, plays an important role here, as we shall see in more detail in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>CHURCH AND DOGMA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Revelation occurs only if the one addressed, the Church, hears it. But hearing is an active reception of what is heard. When the Church hears the word of God, revelation overflows Scripture itself and passes into the Church’s liturgy, practice, and dogma.¹ When the word is heard the first response is praise (liturgy). The second response is enacting the mission of charity that those who hear the word obediently embrace: first, there is sharing the truth, evangelizing those who have not heard; second, there is enacting the truth in the bodily works of love for the hungry and the naked.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>PRAEAMBULA FIDEI</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We come now to the second part of this book. The first part considered God speaking a word to us. Now we turn to our hearing of that word in faith. Before faith, however, there are the<italic>praeambula</italic>—the things that walk before it.</p>
                     <p>For instance, the last topic discussed in chapter 4 was dogma. Dogmas speak of a reality, divine reality, transcendent to the world. This supposes that human language can meaningfully speak of things we do not sense and that cannot be sensed. Furthermore, dogmas purport to speak of this reality in a trans-cultural, trans-temporal way. As we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>CREDIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The credibility or believability of divine revelation is a property that follows from its nature. God does not speak unless he can be heard, and he does not command unless he can be obeyed. The actuality of hearing what God says is the topic of the chapter on faith. Between the speaking and the hearing, however, there is this third thing, the credibility of what is said: the ability of revelation to be heard as what it really is, its capacity to be taken as true by the hearer.</p>
                     <p>There can be distinguished a created and an uncreated credibility. Uncreated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>FAITH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction to the previous chapter, it was observed that the word of God received in faith has a certain preeminence over all other words: it judges and orders them. That is, the knowledge of God in faith is a higher knowledge than any other, both as to its content and as to its way of knowing. As to its content: it tells us of the intimate things of God, his triune life which otherwise we could not know, and of his will to invite us to share this life, and of the way to this goal. As to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>THEOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>God speaks to us, and his speaking demands an answer; he accomplishes our salvation in history, and that accomplishment commands a response. The first answer is the prayer of the Church in praise and thanksgiving, in words first taught to us by God in the Psalms; the first response is a re-actualization of the work of salvation in the liturgy, especially in Baptism and the Eucharist. A second response is the repetition of the word of God in evangelizing and catechesis and preaching, and the extension of God’s salvation of us in the works of love we do for others.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h24.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
