<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9dgg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P301 .R356 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rethinking Rhetorical Theory, Criticism, and Pedagogy</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Living Art of Michael C. Leff</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>de Velasco</surname>
               <given-names>Antonio</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Campbell</surname>
               <given-names>John Angus</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Henry</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781611862133</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609175009</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michigan State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt1d10hh7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What distinguishes the study of rhetoric from other pursuits in the liberal arts? From what realms of human existence and expression, of human history, does such study draw its defining character? What, in the end, should be the purposes of rhetorical inquiry? And amid so many competing accounts of discourse, power, and judgment in the contemporary world, how might scholars achieve these purposes through the attitudes and strategies that animate their work?<italic>Rethinking Rhetorical Theory, Criticism, and Pedagogy: The Living Art of Michael C. Leff</italic>offers answers to these questions by introducing the central insights of one of the most innovative and prolific rhetoricians of the twentieth century, Michael C. Leff. This volume charts Leff 's decades-long development as a scholar, revealing both the variety of topics and the approach that marked his oeuvre, as well as his long-standing critique of the disciplinary assumptions of classical, Hellenistic, renaissance, modern, and postmodern rhetoric.Rethinking Rhetorical Theory, Criticism, and Pedagogy includes a synoptic introduction to the evolution of Leff 's thought from his time as a graduate student in the late 1960s to his death in 2010, as well as specific commentary on twenty-four of his most illuminating essays and lectures.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="506"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What distinguishes the study of rhetoric from other pursuits in the liberal arts? From what realms of human existence and expression, of human history, does such study draw its defining character? What, in the end, should be the purposes of rhetorical inquiry? And amid so many competing accounts of discourse, power, and judgment in the contemporary world, how might scholars achieve these purposes through the attitudes and strategies that animate their work?<italic>Rethinking Rhetorical Theory, Criticism, and Pedagogy: The Living Art of Michael C. Leff</italic>offers answers to these questions by collecting the key works and introducing the key insights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 1. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Readers in search of an entry point into Michael C. Leff’s signature talent for weaving histories of rhetoric together with theoretical innovations attuned to the present will want to start with “Tradition and Agency in Humanistic Rhetoric.” For Leff, the standard opposition of individual agency to collective tradition had to be reconfigured and rethought for rhetoric’s intelligibility to break through the grid of modernist and postmodernist attitudes towards language, culture, and power. Leff notes how in both ancient and modern times rhetoricians have been taxed with not being independent agents but merely mouthpieces for popular and received opinion. And yet,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tradition and Agency in Humanistic Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I intend to approach the issue of tradition indirectly by first considering some problems connected with rhetorical agency. This strategy might seem awkward, if not actually dangerous, since it entangles two equally complex and disputed concepts. Nevertheless, I hope to show that, within the humanistic strand of rhetoric, these concepts are linked in a way that is not now recognized but has an important bearing on our understanding of both. Specifically, I argue that the humanistic approach entails a productively ambiguous notion of agency that positions the orator both as an individual who leads an audience and as a member</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Uses of Aristotle’s Rhetoric in Contemporary American Scholarship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The reception of Aristotle’s<italic>Rhetoric</italic>in the twentieth century presents us with a complicated and somewhat ironic tale. Through much of the century, while rhetoric remained an unfashionable subject, the treatise was largely ignored or dismissed by philologists and philosophers, but it was studied avidly by scholars in the language arts, especially by those in the emerging discipline of speech communication and by literary critics concerned about close, formalistic readings of poetic texts. More recently, as interest in rhetoric has revived, the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>has attracted broader attention: Classicists, after a long hiatus, have produced new commentaries and translations; philosophers have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Genre and Paradigm in the Second Book of De Oratore</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Cicero’s rhetorical works, the concept of genre appears in two rather different and largely independent contexts. One of these involves the division of style into three general types (<italic>tria genera dicendi</italic>), while the other has to do with the conventional tripartite division of types of speeches (<italic>tria genera causarum</italic>). Among recent scholars, attention has centered on the first of these divisions, and for good reason. Although Cicero did not originate these stylistic categories, his formulation of them proved to have an abiding influence,¹ and he applied them in ways that suggest a striking and probably original contribution to rhetorical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Topics of Argumentative Invention in Latin Rhetorical Theory from Cicero to Boethius</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rhetorical arguments generally deal with confused notions, with ideas and concepts that do not admit of a single, unequivocal meaning.¹ Consequently, rhetorical argumentation normally does not begin with fixed axioms in the manner of demonstrative reasoning. Instead rhetoricians must draw their starting points from accepted beliefs and values relative to the audience and the subject of discourse. When these beliefs and values are considered at a high level of generality, they become “commonplaces” or “common topics” for argumentation: the attempt to render a systematic account of such topics therefore has been a major concern of rhetorical theory from antiquity to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 2. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An evolving interpretation of the Greco-Roman rhetorical traditions of antiquity grounded Leff’s guiding vision of the purpose and distinctiveness of rhetoric study. And yet this vision advanced, became more complex, and found new audiences thorough its intimate connection to the social and political tensions of nineteenth and twentieth Century American public address and through its dialogue with philosophies of language and hermeneutics that he encountered in his early years as a scholar.</p>
                     <p>In “Piety, Propriety, and Perspective: An Interpretation and Application of Key Terms in Kenneth Burke’s<italic>Permanence and Change</italic>” Leff and Thomas Rosteck bring each of these streams together</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Piety, Propriety, and Perspective:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Interpretation and Application of Key Terms in Kenneth Burke’s Permanence and Change</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rosteck</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the second main section of<italic>Permanence and Change</italic>, near the end of the chapter entitled “The Range of Piety,” Kenneth Burke presents us with an unlikely vision. Imagine, says Burke, a scene where Matthew Arnold is found “loafing on the corner with the gashouse gang.” Picture Arnold studiously trying to ape the style of his buddies—the casual lean on the lamppost, the cut of a cap across the eyes, the demeanor of calculated indifference. It is a wildly implausible scene, and Arnold emerges as a hapless figure. Witness, says Burke, “the crudeness of his perception as regards the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Topical Invention and Metaphoric Interaction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the course of his analysis of traditional principles of rhetoric, Kenneth Burke makes the curious remark that “the Aristotelian topics shift so imperceptibly between ideas and images that you wonder how the two realms could ever come to be at odds.”¹ The remark is curious, perhaps even subversive, since it associates two domains that both ancient and modern theorists generally have kept apart. In classical rhetoric, of course, images belong to the office of style and function to ornament the language of oratory. Topics, on the other hand, refer to matters of thought and to the office of invention.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Up from Theory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Or I Fought the Topoi and the Topoi Won</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I first began to study rhetoric, some forty or so years ago, the terms “substance” and “theory” occupied privileged positions in disciplinary consciousness. “Substance” referred to content or subject matter, and in this pre-postdisciplinary scheme of things, scholars were supposed to work within bounded and clearly differentiated domains of inquiry. A discipline, that is, needed to have a proper subject, and since scholarship demanded rationally refined, systematically organized abstract principles that stood above and apart from particulars, the study of an academic subject required the use of “theory.” In the quasi discipline then known as speech (<italic>requiescat in pace</italic>),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Habitation of Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem I want to engage is both fundamental and ancient. When Cicero wrote his<italic>De inventione</italic>, it already had had a long history. Yet his comments on that history still retain a lively theoretical interest for students of rhetoric and argumentation. Consequently, they can serve as an appropriate text for introducing and locating the issues addressed in this paper.</p>
                     <p>As part of the standard<italic>accessus</italic>to the technical precepts of the art, Cicero considers the definition of rhetoric and its placement relative to other disciplines. One aspect of this task is to understand the material of rhetoric, by which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Decorum and Rhetorical Interpretation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Latin Humanistic Tradition and Contemporary Critical Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to begin with an unlikely text, Jonathan Valin’s novel<italic>Day of Wrath</italic>, a crime novel, in fact a work belonging to that unrefined subgenre known as the “hard-boiled” detective story. The novel’s protagonist and narrator is named Harry Stoner, and the name aptly suggests the qualities of a detective-hero. Stoner, of course, has a hard and tough exterior, but more than that, his name defines a set of psychological traits which set him apart from his environment. He is self-contained, independent, resistant to the corruption that surrounds him, and impervious to social pressure. A rugged individualist and an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>In Search of Ariadne’s Thread:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Review of the Recent Literature on Rhetorical Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My assignment was to review the articles on rhetorical theory that appeared in the speech communication journals during the years 1976 and 1977. Although the editor provided a list of the relevant journals, I was left to my own devices in selecting the articles that fell under the heading of rhetorical theory. I approached this task with profound reservations, since, as we all know through bitter experience, rhetorical theory is virtually impossible to define. Thus, I was afraid that I would either have to report on everything in the journals or appear to be arbitrary.</p>
                     <p>After reading a few essays,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 3. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In Search of Ariadne’s Thread” shows how Leff’s understanding of the classical tradition made him sympathetic to, yet critical of, the changes occurring in the field in the 1970s. Leff’s mixed response to these changes as a historian of rhetoric is interesting in its own right. More impressive, however, is how persistently he sought to work through the complexities of his response through elaborating (and continually modifying) his own “theory” of rhetorical criticism—close reading.</p>
                     <p>What Leff at times also deemed “textual analysis” and “textual criticism,” close reading was cultivated across the expanse of his theoretical, historiographical, and critical work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interpretation and the Art of the Rhetorical Critic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purposes of this essay are both diagnostic and prescriptive. The diagnosis involves an attempt to locate a few common themes that recur throughout this issue. In some measure, this task is no more than a summary of ideas developed in the preceding pages, but as these ideas are isolated and connected with one another, an argumentative configuration begins to emerge. The authors represented here find evidence of health and vigor in the field, but a comparative reading of their essays indicates that the art suffers from a set of related problems. These problems are expressed in terms of confusion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Textual Criticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Legacy of G. P. Mohrmann</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the moment of his fatal heart attack last November, Jerry Mohrmann was engaged in his normal academic business. He was writing rhetorical criticism. More specifically, he was completing a close analysis of a short but important speech text—John Calhoun’s oration “On the Reception of the Abolition Petitions.” This study had a specific and seemingly narrow focus, but it arose from a number of complex, general issues and incorporated many of Jerry’s characteristic interests. Thus, to recall the history of this project allows us to learn much not only about the man but also about the vocation he pursued.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Words Most like Things:</title>
                     <subtitle>Iconicity and the Rhetorical Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sachs</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thirty-five years ago, in his classic essay “The Study of Speeches,” Wayland Maxfield Parrish argued that critics ought to isolate and carefully evaluate the “content” of a speech. This “often difficult task” required separating “<italic>what</italic>was said from<italic>how</italic>it was said,” a matter best done “by making a summary or précis of the speaker’s thought which avoids the wording of the original.”¹ Holding consistently to this dualism between wording and content, Parrish regarded style as “another” aspect of persuasion, something to be set off from the rest of the critical apparatus. The major elements of style—vivacity or “setting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Things Made by Words:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Textual Criticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is in part an effort to influence the continuing debate about textual criticism and critical rhetoric and in part an exercise in self-criticism. Since I am a principal in the debate, I cannot pretend to assume a neutral or disinterested position, but my present concern is not polemic, or at least not explicitly polemic. Instead, following and extending a point made by Dilip Gaonkar,¹ I want to frame the debate in terms that differ from the prevailing conception and in fact differ from the way I have thought about it in the past. Gaonkar argues—quite rightly, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hermeneutical Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Hermeneutical rhetoric” is the counterpart of Steven Mailloux’s “rhetorical hermeneutics.” In an article bearing that title and more extensively in his book<italic>Rhetorical Power</italic>, Mailloux offers an “antitheory theory” of interpretation that situates literary hermeneutics within the context of rhetorical exchange.¹ Traditional literary theory, Mailloux argues, relies upon a general conception of interpretation as the basis for justifying particular interpretative acts. Such “theory” takes two forms—“textual realism,” where meaning is found in the text, and “readerly idealism,” where meaning is made through intersubjective agreements among a community of interpreters. As theories, these positions are diametrically opposed, but, Mailloux maintains,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 4. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first two essays in this section—“Lincoln at Cooper Union: A Rhetorical Analysis of the Text” and “Lincoln at Cooper Union: A Rationale for Neo-Classical Criticism”—have earned a place in the literature of rhetorical criticism as milestones of inventional practice. In the generation immediately following their publication in the early 1970s, the Cooper Union essays, each written with G. P. Mohrmann, challenged rhetorical critics of diverse theoretic tendencies to reconsider the potential resources of a rich heritage that the neo-Aristotelian program had at best only hinted at and, at worst, had discredited and distorted rather than deployed. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lincoln at Cooper Union:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Rhetorical Analysis of the Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mohrmann</surname>
                           <given-names>G. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Abraham Lincoln spoke at the Cooper Union on the evening of February 27, 1860, his audience responded enthusiastically, and the speech has continued to elicit praise throughout the intervening years. Biographers, historians, and literary scholars agree that it was “one of his most significant speeches,”¹ one that illustrated “his abilities as a reasoner,”² and one to which posterity has ascribed his “subsequent nomination and election to the presidency.”³ Ironically, however, this model of “logical analysis and construction”⁴ has failed to generate a critical response in kind. Most of what has been written treats of the background, and, too often,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lincoln at Cooper Union:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Rationale for Neo-Classical Criticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mohrmann</surname>
                           <given-names>G. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last issue of this journal included our critique of Lincoln’s Cooper Union Address, and we assume that the neo-classical origins of the analysis were apparent, even though methodological concerns were slighted. A more elaborate statement on methodology appeared in an earlier version, but the editors cautioned that the single article did not offer sufficient scope for both an explication of the rationale and its application. Accepting their advice, we deleted most of the theoretical material, but having offered the critique, we want to explore further its theoretical bases.</p>
                     <p>Our approach is neo-classical. That is, it is rooted in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Instrumental and Constitutive Rhetoric in Martin Luther King Jr.’s “Letter from Birmingham Jail”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Utley</surname>
                           <given-names>Ebony A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Almost thirty years ago, in an essay devoted to the<italic>Autobiography of Malcolm X</italic>, Thomas Benson commented that rhetoric is, among other things, a way of constituting the self within a scene composed of “exigencies, constraints, others and the self,” and it is also a resource for “exercising control over self, others, and by extension the scene.”¹ Thus, Benson assigns rhetoric a dual function. It is simultaneously generative and instrumental, since it helps to constitute the identity of self, other, and scene, while it also pulls these identities within the orbit of situated interests. Moreover, once this duality is acknowledged,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lincoln among the Nineteenth-Century Orators</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have two purposes in writing this paper. The first and primary objective follows a conventional agenda in historical and critical studies: it is to contribute something to our understanding of Lincoln’s influence on late nineteenth-century American oratory. That influence is so broad and so obvious that it would seem to command attention, but, so far as I know, no one has yet studied the matter in any detail.¹ This paper, then, attempts to help fill a gap in the historical scholarship.</p>
                     <p>Given the existing climate of academic opinion, however, this conventional objective is neither self-explanatory nor self-justifying. Traditional studies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART 5. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Teaching rhetoric, like rhetorical criticism, was one of Leff’s living arts. In the course of his varied career, he taught at Indiana University, the University of California at Davis, and the University of Wisconsin, and he chaired the Departments of Communication at both Northwestern University and the University of Memphis. He mentored countless undergraduate and graduate students at those institutions; he was also an active presence in the lives of students beyond his own university. Leff worked to build an infrastructure for rhetoric’s future that could unite students and teachers of rhetoric across the country, even the world. Scarcely a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Teaching Public Speaking as Composition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This article is intended as a call for reform, but I must begin by confessing some uncertainty about what it is that I am attempting to reform. The fact is that I do not have a secure understanding about the state of the art as it is now practiced in teaching public speech. I have not made a survey of the methods now used in classroom instruction, nor undertaken a systematic study of the textbooks, and I have not reviewed the current scholarly literature. What I have to say is based upon personal experience and depends on anecdotes, hunches, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kenneth Burke in the Classroom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all the lessons I have learned from Kenneth Burke, none is more valuable than what he shows and tells about irony. For Burke, irony is not simply a strategy that allows us to say one thing when we mean something else. Instead, irony becomes a point of coalescence between strategy and substance—a way of talking and thinking that simultaneously constructs, engages, and alters our encounters in the social world. Among other things, Burkean irony suggests a way for us to teach rhetoric rhetorically, and that is the issue I want to explore in this paper.</p>
                     <p>To begin, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Theory and Practice in Undergraduate Education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question posed for this panel is both new and old. In the context of our own lives and careers, it is something new to question the nature and role of theory in our work. As Jo Sprague said, in her letter attempting to orient today’s speakers, not so long ago we were quite confident that we knew what theory was and how to use it as teachers. Theory, on this view, was something that stood apart from and above practice. It consisted in a set of hierarchically ordered abstract propositions (i.e., laws or rules) that were capable of explaining</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cultivating the Useless:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rhetoric and Liberal Arts Education in an Age of Consumerism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>457</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Liberal arts education is education to virtue. It aims to be more than an instrument for enhancing the material prospects of students. It has less tangible ends, such as making students better citizens or better, more critical thinkers. And liberal education claims intrinsic merit; what it provides students is not meant to be simply useful but good in itself.</p>
                     <p>This broad definition leaves ample room for variation and diversity, but the two main possibilities are indicated by the word “liberal,” and as that term shifts in meaning so also does the conception of the purpose and nature of the liberal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d10hh7.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What Is Rhetoric?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I need to begin on two rather different notes—conventionally but sincerely with some words of gratitude and then somewhat unconventionally (and perhaps a bit less sincerely) with an apology. First, I want to express thanks to Tony Blair and his colleagues for their invitation to visit here and their kind hospitality over the past several days. It is real pleasure to meet and talk with members of the Centre for Research in Reasoning, Argumentation and Rhetoric and to make another pilgrimage to this mecca for the study of informal logic. The apology concerns the subject of the lecture and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
