<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Criticism in the Wilderness</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Study of Literature Today</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HARTMAN</surname>
               <given-names>GEOFFREY H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>0082</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300028393</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300157857</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cc2mjv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Originally published in 1980, this now classic work of literary theory explores the wilderness of positions that grew out of the collision between Anglo-American practical criticism and Continental philosophic criticism. This second edition includes a new preface by the author as well as a foreword by Hayden White."A key text for understanding 'the fate of reading' in the Anglophone world over the last fifty years."-Hayden White, from the Foreword"<italic>Criticism in the Wilderness</italic>may be the best, most brilliant, most broadly useful book yet written by an American about the sudden swerve from the safety of established decorum toward bravely theoretical, mainly European forms of literary criticism."-Terrence Des Pres,<italic>Nation</italic>"A polemical survey that reaffirms the value of the Continental tradition of philosophical literary criticism."-Notable Books of the Year,<italic>New York Times Book Review</italic>
         </p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Hayden</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is an honor to introduce this new edition of Geoffrey Hartman’s<italic>Criticism in the Wilderness</italic>. The book is a key text for understanding the “fate of reading” in the Anglophone world over the past fifty years. Coincidentally, it is also a key text for understanding the trajectory of Geoffrey Hartman’s career as a critic and reader, from his first book,<italic>The Unmediated Vision</italic>(1954), to his most recent one,<italic>The Geoffrey Hartman Reader</italic>(2004), which won last year’s Truman Capote Award for Literary Criticism.<italic>Criticism in the Wilderness</italic>appeared in 1980, the midpoint—give or take a few months</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hartman</surname>
                           <given-names>Geoffrey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book of experiences rather than a systematic defense of literary studies. The best apology for criticism (as for literature) is doing it; and, at present, reading it closely. Though we have perfected—some will say overperfected—the technique of close reading, it has been applied almost exclusively to creative ,writing rather than to criticism or nonfictional prose. What follows is an attempt to bring together my reading of criticism with my reading of literature: to view criticism, in fact, as within literature, not outside of it looking in.</p>
                     <p>The truth of art and the useful mediation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Understanding Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What difference does reading make? Is it perhaps, like traveling, a fool’s paradise? “We owe to our first journeys,” writes Emerson, “the discovery that place is nothing. At home I dream that at Naples, at Rome, I can be intoxicated with beauty, and lose my sadness. I pack my trunk, embrace my friends, embark on the sea, and at last wake up in Naples, and there beside me is the stern Fact, the sad Self, unrelenting, identical, that I fled from. I seek the Vatican, and the palaces. I affect to be intoxicated with sights and suggestions, but I am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Sacred Jungle 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Carlyle, Eliot, Bloom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the conclusion to his comprehensive work<italic>The Symbolism of Evil</italic>, Paul Ricoeur calls us “the children of criticism,” who “seek to go beyond criticism by means of a criticism that is no longer reductive but restorative.” The intellectual scheme revealed by those words goes back to the German Romantics. It presupposes that as moderns we aim at a second naiveté in and through critical reflection. It also presupposes that the concepts of immediacy and of the sacred (“the immediacy of the symbol”) are identical and that it is the aim of restorative criticism to disclose that identity. Criticism, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Sacred Jungle 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Walter Benjamin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is but twenty-five years since Walter Benjamin’s writings began to be published in full. Whatever the merit of this extraordinary man of letters, whom it has now become fashionable to invoke, his interest in both Marxist thought and Jewish mysticism has made him a war zone subject to incursions by competing factions. Is he a religious thinker, or is he a social thinker inspired primarily by Marxism? Though the terms of the debate seem naive, they suggest that religious and political modes of thought are enemy brothers disputing the same territory. After Marx and Freud, there is a tendency</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Sacred Jungle 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frye, Burke, and Some Conclusions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Arnoldian tradition received the English Romantics in a defensive and limited way. What was considered valuable was their “creative power”; what was lacking was “knowledge,” or the integration of intellectual with creative power. Such integration made Dante exemplary, while Shakespeare and Donne showed it could be achieved, with strain, in the modern period. Perhaps there would be a second Renaissance, a literature of imaginative reason as Arnold called it, growing out of a more intensely self-conscious and critical age, one which could not rely on the unified world-view theology had once provided.</p>
                     <p>That poetry thinks does not seem to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Purification and Danger 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>American Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Art is a radical critique of representation, and as such is bound to compete with theology and other, ritual or clinical, modes of purification. “The pure products of America / go crazy,” William Carlos Williams wrote; and it is necessary to admit from the outset that the word “pure” has many meanings, some ambiguous, some downright deceptive. Though my theme is purity, and more specifically language purification in American poetry, one could easily write on “Seven Types of Purity.” Empson’s<italic>Seven Types of A mbiguity</italic>was, in fact, a response to doctrines of “pure poetry” around him.¹ Our new, hypothetical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Purification and Danger 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Critical Style</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A strange thought comes to Errlerson on reading Carlyle’s<italic>Sartor Resartus</italic>. It is an uncleanly book, a rag-bag philosophy, conceived (Carlyle jokes) among the Old Clothes shops of London, though rising to transcendental flights of fancy. “There is a part of ethics,” writes Emerson, “... which possesses all attraction to me; to wit, the compensations of the Universe, the equality and the coexistence of action and reaction, that all prayers are granted, that every debt is paid. And the skill witll which the great All maketh clean work as it goes along, leaves no rag, consumes its smoke.”¹</p>
                     <p>Undoubtedly there</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Work of Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the matter of art we cannot draw up a Guide for the Perplexed. We can only urge that readers, inspired by herrneneutic traditions, take back some of their authority and become both creative and thoughtful, as in days of old. It is true, of course, that today they are less<italic>liable</italic>for their mistakes, and that being creative is for many a defense for whatever they do. The rabbinical or patristic exegete was creative within a scrupulosity as exacting as any invented by extreme apostles of the Catholic or Puritan conscience; he pretended not to violate the letter of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Literary Commentary as Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The school of Derrida confronts us with a substantial problem. What are the proper relations between the “critical” and “creative” activities, or between “primary” and “secondary” texts? In 1923, writing his own essay on “The Function of Criticism,” T. S. Eliot accused Matthew Arnold of distinguishing too bluntly between critical and creative. “He overlooks the capital importance of criticism in the work of creation itself.” Eliot’s perception was, of course, partially based on the literary work of French writers since Flaubert and Baudelaire, including Mallarmé, Laforgue, and Valéry. But Eliot is wary lest his charge against Arnold, and in favor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Centaur:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Psychology of the Critic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literature of criticism exists, yet we show it ambivalence and condescension. Literary devices when found in the language of critics are viewed as a breach of decorum: we like our criticism neat, a secondary and clearly separated activity in style and function. We could echo the reply of Thamus to Egyptian Theuth, in Plato’s<italic>Phaedrus</italic>, after Theuth has extolled Writing, which he has invented. “O most ingenious man,” says Thamus, “to one is given to create the things of art, and to another to judge what measure of harm and profit they have for those that employ them.”</p>
                     <p>We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Past and Present</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rumors abound that the New Criticism, no longer fighting for its place in the university but accepted as the standard of an urbane and teachable discipline, is being challenged by a still newer criticism. “After us the Savage God,” said Yeats; and that is how the new “revisionist” or “hermeneutic” critics are being perceived.¹ They seem to profess an esoteric and personalist approach; all amalgam, encouraged in part by contemporary French speculation, of linguistics, psychoanalysis, Kabbalistic paradigms, and other dark sublimities. This higher criticism bursts upon a scene of mass education where English teachers are trying to instill a minimum</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Recognition Scene of Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Wallace Martin’s response to “Literary Criticism and Its Discontents” is anything but naive. Its most sophisticated device is to posit my invention of a “naive reader” and to suggest that I would place the New Critics and their heirs in that category. But when I see the movement of criticism after Arnold as exhibiting an anti-self-consciousness principle or being so worried about a hypertrophy of the critical spirit that that spirit is acknowledged only by refusing it seminal or creative force, I am not alleging naivete but “organized innocence,” or the privileged assignment of some given, intuitive (in that sense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Criticism, Indeterminacy, Irony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Indeterminacy” is a word with bad vibes. It evokes a picture of the critic as Hamlet, “sicklied o’er with the pale cast of thought.” It is often said to involve an attack on the communicative or edifying function of literature. A pseudoscientific or anti-humanist bias is ascribed to critics when they do not replace words by meanings quickly enough. We like to consume our literature. We like to think of critics as service stations that keep readers fueled for their more important business, refreshing them and speeding them on.</p>
                     <p>Yet indeterminacy, though not an end to be pursued but something</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Short History of Practical Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What at present preoccupies scholars and students in the literary humanities is clear: the lack of interaction between their profession and the mainstream of society. Though this is a recurrent problem, I. A. Richards had thought to find a secure place for literary studies by denying the existence of a “phantom aesthetic state” and basing the critic’s work on two pillars. “The two pillars upon which a theory of criticism must rest are an account of value and an account of communication” (<italic>Principles of Literary Criticism</italic>, 1924). Having established these principles, an eminently “practical criticism” became possible; the book<italic>Practical</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>302</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2mjv.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
