<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>God's Wounds</book-title>
         <subtitle>Hermeneutic of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering, Volume 1. Divine Vulnerability and Creation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pool</surname>
               <given-names>Jeff B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173596</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903148</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jeff B. Pool</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgfbxv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book constitutes the first volume of a three-volume study of Christian testimonies to divine suffering: God's Wounds: Hermeneutic of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering, Divine Vulnerability and Creation. This study first develops an approach to interpreting the contested claims about the suffering of God. Thus, the larger study focuses its inquiry into the testimonies to divine suffering themselves, seeking to allow the voices that attest to divine suffering to speak freely, to discover and elucidate the internal logic or rationality of this family of testimonies, rather than defending these attestations against the dominant claims of classical Christian theism that have historically sought to eliminate such language altogether from Christian discourse about the nature and life of God. Through this approach, this volume of studies into the Christian symbol of divine suffering then investigates the two major presuppositions that the larger family of testimonies to divine suffering normally hold: an understanding of God through the primary metaphor of love (God is love); and an understanding of the human as created in the image of God, with a life (though finite) analogous to the divine life - the imago Dei as love. When fully elaborated, these presuppositions reveal the conditions of possibility for divine suffering and divine vulnerability with respect to creation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Terrible Sublimity of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ultimate gloom, vulgarity, grim severity, horror, even apparent conceptual paradoxes, in Christian testimonies to divine suffering repel many people in their initial encounters with various forms of this Christian symbol.¹ Such revulsion for language that attributes suffering to God, however, may surprise contemporary Christians who easily attribute all sorts of emotions and experiences to God and may lead such Christians to criticize classical Christian theism itself, when they discover how the vast majority of official teachings and dogmas of orthodox Christianity (Eastern Orthodoxy, Roman Catholicism, and many of the major Protestant denominations that emerged from the reformations of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part One:</title>
                     <subtitle>Approaching the Symbol</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an encounter with the Christian symbol of divine suffering, a maze of problems opens before the inquirer, beckoning, with promises of both disclosure and transformation, the seeker to enter into its mysteries. The interpreter of this symbol must enter its maze carefully, always keenly aware of every clue, in order wisely to discern the next most favorable move to make through the ever more complex difficulties in an encounter with this religious symbol.</p>
                     <p>I intend carefully to follow this caution in my own journey through this maze of problems. To fulfill this aim, I have assigned two tasks to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Delimitation of the Problem</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By delimiting the problem for investigation, this chapter provides the first orientation that an encounter with the Christian symbol of divine suffering requires. I will delimit the problem for inquiry in a series of steps. (1) In the first step, I will circumscribe<italic>the question</italic>with which to approach this symbol. (2) Second, I will specify the meaning of this symbol as a<italic>Christian</italic>symbol. (3) My third step will describe the<italic>concept of symbol</italic>that I have employed to formulate the problem that this larger study addresses. (4) In a fourth step, I will clarify the nature and extent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Procedural Principles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I initiated the orientation of this study by clarifying its object through a series of steps to delimit the problem. Building upon that first orientation, this present chapter more fully orients my work by outlining the major principles on the basis of which I have interpreted the Christian symbol of divine suffering.</p>
                     <p>The procedural principles that roughly define my method in this work constitute the outline of a strategy for a<italic>Chaoskampf</italic>, a struggle for the discovery of a pattern within the competing and often conflicting varieties of Christian attestations to the suffering God. ¹ I have not formulated this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Hypothetical Structure of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the basis of my previous preparatory steps, this chapter supplies a third, briefer, and final orientation for interaction with the Christian symbol of divine suffering. In one sense, this chapter initiates that interaction, since it provides a hypothetical overview of the symbol’s structure. In another sense, however, this chapter retains its orienting character, in that it does not yet<italic>fully</italic>begin to interpret actual Christian attestations to divine suffering. Rather, in this chapter, I offer an overview of the symbol’s structure as a hypothesis that I will demonstrate throughout all three volumes of this work. The present chapter serves,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part Two:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conditions of Possibility for Divine Suffering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In part two, the most complex transitional steps emerge in the movement of this study into the more concrete analyses of this Christian symbol. In the chapters that follow, I will examine this symbol’s two principal presuppositions, both of which taken together supply part two of this book with its title: Presuppositions of the Christian Symbol of Divine Suffering. Nevertheless, a moment of abstraction remains. I have drawn these two presuppositions from testimonies to divine suffering in which they remain embedded as the conditions of possibility for divine suffering.</p>
                     <p>Although I have spoken previously of two symbolic presuppositions in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division One:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Life and Creative Activitiy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The confluence of two powerful confessional streams form the first presupposition within the Christian symbol of divine suffering: (1) an attestation to God as creator—principally, although not exclusively, upon the basis of testimonies from the first Christian canon; and (2) an attestation to God as love—again, principally, although not exclusively, upon the basis of attestations within the second Christian canon to God’s self-disclosure in the event of Jesus the Christ.¹ As these two streams of piety have flowed together, and have confessed a confidence in the first conditions of possibility for divine suffering, the first presupposition has taken</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Divine Lover:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Life As Love</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter constitutes the first stage in my analyses of the first presupposition of the Christian symbol of divine suffering. I repeat my formulation of this presupposition:<italic>The God whose life is love limits the divine self in God’s creative activity; or, as the creator who is love, God limits the divine self as God creates</italic>. This first stage of my analysis works on the basis of an abstraction of divine life or being from divine activity, in order to clarify the characteristic ways in which this symbol envisions the actualization of divine love in divine creative activity. In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Divine Lover:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Life As Love in Creation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I now shift from considering God’s being and activity, as methodologically abstracted from one another, to discussing divine love’s actualization in God’s creative activity.1 Previously, I have surveyed characteristics and dimensions of God’s being as love through attestations to divine activity in the history of Jesus the Nazarene. The present chapter examines the character of God’s creative activity, as determined by the divine being, in order to disclose the meaning of the first presupposition for the Christian symbol of divine suffering as well as to illumine the basis upon which to analyze this symbol’s second presupposition. Thus, I proceed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Division Two:</title>
                     <subtitle>Human Life As Image and Imitation of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My analysis of this symbol’s first presupposition disclosed the implicit character of the second presupposition in the first presupposition. As a consequence, that disclosure requires an analysis of the second and implied presupposition, in order to comprehend as satisfactorily as possible even the first presupposition. Having begun with an analysis of this second presupposition would have required the same procedure in reverse. The elegant and fertile dialectical network between this symbol’s first and second presuppositions, as a result, begins to appear in all of its complexity through the present exposition. Although herein I continue to<italic>treat</italic>these two presuppositions<italic>distinctly</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Beloved Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>Imago Dei As Love</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter develops the first half of an exposition of the second major presupposition of the Christian symbol of divine suffering. As I have mentioned already, most specifically, this presupposition takes the following form:<italic>God has created human life or being, through the actualization of the divine being as love in God’s self-limiting creative activity, in the image of God with the being or life of love</italic>. Working on the basis of the abstraction of being or life from its actualization, this chapter will identify and analyze the formal and material structures of the human as the image of God,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Beloved Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>Imitatio Dei As Love</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In moving from the distinction between human being and human action to their union, through the present consideration of human being’s actualization, I note again the abstract character of this distinction: human being always remains, and one can examine it empirically only as,<italic>ens actu</italic>, being-in-act. Also, the insights that this abstraction discloses about this symbol’s anthropological presupposition refer to aspects of essential human being.</p>
                     <p>So far, my analyses have identified both formally and materially the structural characteristics of human being in this anthropological presupposition of the Christian symbol of divine suffering, characteristics of authentic human being or human being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Human Life As Caritas and the Cosmos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As stated in chapter 2, every religious symbol expresses, either explicitly or implicitly, a threefold referentiality: (1) reference to some notion of ultimate reality, the sacred, or God; (2) reference to a concept of the human; and (3) reference to a specific vision of the world. The Christian symbol of divine suffering naturally exhibits that threefold referentiality in both the explicit symbol and its twofold presupposition. Thus, in these two primary presuppositions, the human and God do not relate to one another in some sort of vacuum. The human (Ο άνθρωπος) and God (Ο θεός) relate to one another in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Divine Vulnerability to Divine Suffering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this study, I have aimed both to establish an approach to the Christian symbol of divine suffering and to inaugurate the first stages of an interpretation of this symbol through an analysis of its two principal presuppositions. The dialectical network between these two presuppositions constitutes the symbol of divine vulnerability: the symbolic condition of possibility for all forms or modes of actual divine suffering, according to the Christian symbol of divine suffering.</p>
                     <p>My interpretation of this symbol’s construal of divine vulnerability, consequently, requires me to step across, to trans-gress, the gaps between this first volume in my study of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Scriptures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Persons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Topics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbxv.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>360</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
