<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>After Imperialism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christian Identity in China and the Global Evangelical Movement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cook</surname>
               <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pao</surname>
               <given-names>David W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718892579</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718840730</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Richard R. Cook</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>David W. Pao</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cg4mgz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This collection of essays is committed to the belief that evangelicalism continues to have the historical assets and intellectual (hermeneutical and theological) tools able to contribute to the global church.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cook</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pao</surname>
                           <given-names>David W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection of essays arises from a commitment to the belief that evangelicalism continues to provide the historical assets and intellectual (hermeneutical and theological) tools for the global church. Evangelicalism possesses assets with explanatory power able to address significant theological and cultural issues arising out of the churches in the global south. We believe evangelical approaches to contextualization and biblical studies can produce valuable fruit. One such issue is that of identity. In May 2008 over a dozen evangelical scholars, Chinese and Western, from the United States, Hong Kong, and Taiwan, came together to address issues of Christian and evangelical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Modern Evangelicalism and Global Christian Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Promise and Peril as Seen through the Eyes of a North American Church Historian</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sweeney</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the demographers who study global religion, more than one out of every eight people in the world is an evangelical. By the dawn of 2008, the world population had exceeded 6.6 billion people. Nearly a third of these identified with Christianity. Roughly 900 million were evangelicals. A century ago, Christians of any kind were much fewer in number, and the vast majority lived in Europe and North America. But the twentieth century witnessed a major explosion of evangelicalism, a blast that rocked the two-thirds world more powerfully than the West. By the early 1970s, most Christians lived outside</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Missions, Cultural Imperialism, and the Development of the Chinese Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>
                           <surname>Leung</surname>
                           <given-names>Ka Lun</given-names>
                        </string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Developments in the twenty-first century are altering perceptions of Christianity and the relationship of Christianity to culture around the world. Churches in Asia, Africa, and Latin America now have an opportunity to challenge the Western-American monopolization of Christianity. While local expressions of Christianity might in some ways hinder global fellowship, I believe now is an ideal time for churches around the world to share resources and experiences and to develop strong local cultural identities as well as strong global bonds. The churches in China have begun this process of local indigenization and have also initiated global networking. This chapter will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Overcoming Missions Guilt:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robert Morrison, Liang Fa, and the Opium Wars</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cook</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Protestant missionary movement had a profound impact on China, but also left an unintended legacy in the West. Western missions guilt is an unanticipated backlash from the missionary movement, which still reverberates today. Did the missionary movement draw the missionaries inexorably into the imperial project and, thus, the sins of the West? Popular culture in America has castigated the missions movement for decades, and missions in America has seemed to be in a defensive mode. Although missions, particularly North American evangelical missions, continued to expand—with an estimated more than 110,000 American and Canadian long-term Protestant missionaries serving today—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Chinese Evangelicals and Social Concerns:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Historical and Comparative Review</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>
                           <surname>Yao</surname>
                           <given-names>Kevin Xiyi</given-names>
                        </string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social concern and involvement is undoubtedly one of the major indicators of the changing ethos of the evangelical movement in the twentieth century. Take the example of North America, where the evangelical movement has been influential not only in the Protestant church but society as a whole. From evangelicals’ balanced approach to soul-saving and social services, to the “Great Reversal” completed during the fundamentalist-modernist controversy of the 1920s and 1930s, to the re-emergence of the sense of social responsibility among evangelicals since the 1970s, the rise of American evangelicals’ social consciousness and commitment is quite dramatic. Nevertheless, American evangelicals’ experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Old Testament in Its Cultural Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>Implications of “Contextual Criticism” for Chinese and North American Christian Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Younger</surname>
                           <given-names>K. Lawson</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christians all over the world struggle with issues of identity within the various different cultures in which they find themselves. Some Christians identify themselves through “Christian” tradition, which may or may not actually be Christian. No matter what culture Christians are in, they ultimately should derive their identity from the Bible. But this presents an ongoing problem. The Bible (whether Old or New Testament) was written in different cultural settings than the one Christians are in today. There are, of course, varying degrees of difference, but all cultures are different from those of biblical times. In the case of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“Holy War” and the Universal God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Old Testament Holy War Texts in a Biblical-Theological and Postcolonial Setting</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Longman</surname>
                           <given-names>Tremper</given-names>
                           <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “divine warrior” with its background in “holy war” is one of the most stirring themes in the Old Testament, but also one of the most difficult for a modern Christian to understand and appreciate. The battle of Jericho, for instance, is a magnificent display of divine power as the walls of this powerful Canaanite city-state come tumbling down so that the Israelites can defeat it without even raising a single siege ramp. On the other hand, if, as I believe we can safely presume, Joshua followed the requirements of<italic>ḥierem</italic>(Deut 20:16–18) on this occasion, this victory would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“Holy War” and the Universal God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the New Testament Conquest Accounts in a Post-Colonial Setting</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pao</surname>
                           <given-names>David W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The celebration of the 200th anniversary of the first Protestant missionary’s arrival in China provides us with an opportunity to consider various topics related to the impact of the missionary movements, the development of Western evangelicalism and global Christianity, the relationship between biblical confession of faith and indigenous religions, and the reading of the Bible in various cultural contexts. At the intersection of these various considerations, one often finds the symbol of the Holy War. This symbol points to various periods of our history that many people find disturbing. For those who consider themselves to have been manipulated by such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Group and the Individual in Salvation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Witness of Paul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thielman</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the New Testament speaks of salvation, does it refer primarily to the salvation of the individual or to the salvation of a people? This is an important question for at least two reasons.</p>
                     <p>First, evangelical Christianity, with its emphasis on the worldwide proclamation of the Gospel, has traditionally been strongest in North America.¹ The roots of evangelical Christianity in North America, however, lie firmly planted in the middle-class values of nineteenth-century American culture.² Did the missionaries who were a product of North American evangelicalism export the individualism of their culture to other places along with the Gospel, as if</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Boundaries in “In-Christ Identity”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paul’s View on Table Fellowship and Its Implications for Ethnic Identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>
                           <surname>Yeung</surname>
                           <given-names>Maureen W.</given-names>
                        </string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Frank Thielman’s chapter, “The Group and the Individual in Salvation: The Witness of Paul,” cautions us not to belittle the individual dimension in salvation at the expense of the collective one, a tendency which is in vogue in Pauline scholarship today. Indeed, the individual and the collective aspects in salvation are closely related. This is clearly seen in the issue of identity. The identity of a person is always defined in relation to others.¹ When a person accepts Jesus Christ as Lord, he or she immediately gains a new identity: he or she is now a Christian, or a person</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“Who Am I?”</title>
                     <subtitle>Theology and Identity for Children of the Dragon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Priest</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My family and I enjoy movies made by the Hong Kong actor and movie producer Jackie Chan. In one movie, Jackie loses his memory and cries out, “Who am I?” For the rest of the movie, he goes by the name “Who am I?”</p>
                     <p>“Who am I?” is an important question, historically answered by different people in different ways. Who am I?<italic>I am the son of my father, and I bear his surname, Priest. I am the grandson of my mother’s father Robert, and my father’s father, Joseph. My name is Robert Joseph Priest. I am American, not British;</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Chinese Contextual Theology:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Possible Reconstruction?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lee</surname>
                           <given-names>David Y. T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evangelicals uphold the supremacy and authority of the Holy Scripture. As noted by Anthony Lane, the<italic>sola Scriptura</italic>principle essentially holds that Scripture is the final authority or norm for Christian belief. As Lane acknowledges, the finality of Scripture should always be fiercely defended, but it is not the sole source or resource for theology. Lane further explains that there is no need to regard the<italic>sola Scriptura</italic>principle as antithetical to the validity of church tradition, Christian experience, human reason, or cultural understanding.¹ Without undermining the<italic>sola Scriptura</italic>principle, this paper asserts that it is possible to construct a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Forging Evangelical Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Integration of Models of Theological Education in the Global Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>
                           <surname>Yu</surname>
                           <given-names>Carver T.</given-names>
                        </string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last fifty years, the world has witnessed some rather drastic changes. From the Christian perspective, the most significant changes may crudely be epitomized by two juxtaposed pictures. One picture is the unrelenting acceleration of secularization disseminating from the West, or, more accurately, from the North. The other is that of Christian expansion in Africa, Latin America, and Asia. Combined, these two pictures pose a serious challenge for theological educators.</p>
                     <p>Secularization has been with us for the last three hundred years, but the speed with which it is now transforming fundamental values, as well as the basic structure of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4mgz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
