<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p1h2</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442676947</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN475.6.M53 1997</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Evil eye</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Evil eye</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Sicily</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Italian Canadians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Folklore</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Italian Canadians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mal'uocchiu</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ambiguity, Evil Eye, and the Language of Distress</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MIGLIORE</surname>
               <given-names>SAM</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780802079220</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442676947</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press Incorporated</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442676947"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Migliore examines the vague, ambiguous, and variable nature of mal'uocchiu (evil eye) among Sicilian-Canadians, shifting the focus of attention from explaining the concept to examining how "folk constructs" are used in everyday life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="144"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book represents my attempt to understand and discuss a complicated phenomenon:<italic>lu mal’uocchiu,</italic>the Sicilian-Canadian ‘evil eye’ complex. Sicilians often present complicated ideas through an indirect process that makes extensive use of proverbs, analogy, and metaphor (Giovannini 1978; Migliore 1993; Sciascia 1984). With this in mind, I would like to begin with a short story I call ‘Alone Together.’ It is a story I heard on several occasions while growing up as a member of a Sicilian-Canadian household in Southern Ontario. The story does not deal with the evil eye, but it does reveal how I intend to approach</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Ethnographic Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since 1977, I have conducted periodic field research among Sicilian Canadians residing in a large urban centre of Southern Ontario, Canada. I also have travelled to Sicily, where I collected background information. Although my work has focused on various topics, I have concentrated primarily on<italic>idioms of distress</italic>– the culturally recognized means by which members of a particular group interpret and communicate their experience of some kinds of suffering (Nichter 1981 and Parsons 1984). The specific idioms I have examined include the evil eye (Migliore 1981; 1983; 1990), pain (Migliore 1989) and, more recently, the concept of ‘nerves’ (Migliore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Power of Strong Emotions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Constructing the Sicilian-Canadian Evil-Eye Complex</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ‘evil eye,’ the notion that a<italic>look</italic>or<italic>stare</italic>can operate as a potential source of human suffering, is prevalent in a number of societies. How people conceptualize the phenomenon, however, varies considerably not only from society to society, but also from individual to individual. Following Pirandello’s (1990) logic, I believe that there are as many models of evil eye as there are people who have formulated some idea about the phenomenon.² The model I am about to present is not necessarily shared by all Sicilian Canadians. Instead, it represents my understanding of the phenomenon based on a synthesis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Mal’uocchiu and the Language of Distress</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pirandello regards human emotions, feelings, and other sensations as an integral part of an individual’s experience of the<italic>flux of life</italic>. In order to understand and communicate these sensations, however, the individual must find a way to give them ‘form’ or ‘meaning.’ Speaking through the philosopher in his play<italic>At the Exit</italic>, for example, Pirandello (1964a: 179) states: ‘it is not enough for the living to<italic>feel</italic>; they want to see their feelings expressed concretely, be able to touch them, and so they build a house for them.’ In the play, the philosopher is referring specifically to the notion that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Mal’uocchiu in Everyday Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During a telephone conversation, several weeks before I began to write this book, I revealed to my mother that I was concerned about how some community members might react to my publishing a book on<italic>mal’uocchiu</italic>. My concern was, and still is, that certain individuals, people who have not participated in the study, will feel that I am presenting a negative image of Sicilian Canadians – that I am depicting community members as ‘superstitious’ people. This is not my intent, but I obviously have no control over how others will interpret my work. My mother’s response surprised me. She stated:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Extending the Web of Significance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sicilian Canadians can make use of<italic>mal’uocchiu</italic>to explain a variety of experiences, and to communicate a number of messages. The vague, ambiguous, and variable nature of the concept provides the type of flexibility that enables people to use<italic>mal’uocchiu</italic>as a component in an intricate web of significance that sometimes links together the<italic>language of distress, moral commentary,</italic>and the<italic>language of argument</italic>. This would make a good ending for my story. Unfortunately, it would also misrepresent the phenomenon. Not everyone within the community makes use of<italic>mal’uocchiu</italic>in these ways. For some, the concept has little or no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would like to begin the conclusion the same way I began the introduction – with an analogy. The analogy involves what is probably Pirandello’s (1952b) best-known play,<italic>Six Characters in Search of an Author</italic>.¹ The work focuses on six partially developed characters who have been discarded by their creator. As the drama unfolds, the characters enter the stage and interrupt a theatre company about to rehearse a play. The characters are in search of an author who can give them a more definitive ‘form,’ and an opportunity to communicate their story. Although the drama presents the characters’ story (or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Don Gesualdo’s statement, which appears both here and at the beginning of the Preface, is a short protective charm to ward off the possible effects of<italic>mal’uocchiu</italic>and related phenomena. He provided the charm many years ago for inclusion in my MA thesis; it was his way of protecting readers from potential harm. Since this book is dedicated to his memory, and I owe a great deal to him, it is only fitting that the charm should appear here. Besides, why take chances.</p>
                     <p>At the risk of repeating myself, I would like to conclude by stating that anthropologists (including myself)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary of Sicilian Terms and Phrases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442676947.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
