<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Preaching and the Personal</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Howell</surname>
               <given-names>J. Dwayne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893323</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718842178</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf and Stock Publishers</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdvp1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Preaching and the Personal' is a collection of papers that have been presented at the Society of Biblical Literature in sessions sponsored by the Homiletics and Biblical Studies section. The Homiletics and Biblical Studies section encourages dialogue among scholars in both fields who share an interest in critical exegesis, its various methods, and the unique hermeneutical and theological problems inherent to the relationship between biblical interpretation and proclamation. The concept for this book began with the panel discussion "Preaching and the Personal: Prophecy, Witness and Testimony" at the 2010 meeting in Atlanta. Each paper explores various ways the personal can be found in the biblical text, in the preacher, and in the congregation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="172"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Howell</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Dwayne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Personal Nature of Preaching</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOWELL</surname>
                           <given-names>J. DWAYNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Preaching is a personal event. Obviously, it involves the individual preparation and presentation by a minister or speaker. However, preaching also includes the Bible as a central source. This source comes from and provides a basis for the believing community. The preaching event is also personal for the members of the congregation. They are not simply receptors of the preacher’s words based on a biblical text. The congregation is also involved personally in how each individual interprets the words and the text. What is said in the text, what is said in the sermon, and the listener’s response comprise parts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Preaching and the Personal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLORENCE</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNA CARTER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First off, let me say how delighted I was to learn that there is a homiletics workgroup at the society for Biblical literature. It isn’t a self-evident reality. You probably know that. Studying the text is often preferable to talking about it in public.</p>
                     <p>I teach preaching, which is not something that is easy to tell people who are sitting next to you on airplanes. It is also not an easy thing to explain to one’s colleagues, even in a theological education setting. I will never forget a conversation I once had with a man I like and respect, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Personal and Its Others in the Performance of Preaching</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOOKE</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTHANNA B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A former student once told me a story about how she deals with her fears when she is about to preach. She said that when she was a child and was nervous about serving for the first time as an acolyte in a worship service, the priest with whom she was serving comforted her by saying, “Remember, they didn’t come here to see you.” She told me that she remembers these words and is still calmed by them when she is about to step into the pulpit.</p>
                     <p>This comment—“they didn’t come here to see you”—brings to the fore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Risk of Testimony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRUEGGEMANN</surname>
                           <given-names>WALTER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1977, Elie Wiesel notably wrote,</p>
                     <p>If the Greeks invented tragedy, the Romans the epistle, and the Renaissance the sonnet, our generation invented a new literature, that of testimony.¹</p>
                     <p>In a contribution to a volume titled<italic>Dimensions of Holocaust</italic>, Wiesel refers specifically to the death-camp survivors who are the surviving witnesses and testifiers to a truth that might otherwise be ignored and forgotten and, in some quarters, vigorously denied. Of course, Wiesel, for obvious reasons, overstates the case of new twentieth-century inventiveness. He wants to insist that the entire reality of the death camps is without precedent or parallel. Given</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Collaborative Preaching and the Bible:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Practical Theology of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCCLURE</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Several long-standing shifts in biblical studies suggest that biblical interpretation is done best in a collaborative way. Fernando Segovia, in<italic>Reading from This Place: Social Location and Biblical Interpretation in the United states</italic>, asserted that reading the Bible should involve “positioned readers, flesh-and-blood persons” who are in “critical dialogue” within a “truly global interaction” regarding the meaning of biblical texts.¹ Daniel Patte, in his book<italic>Ethics of Biblical Interpretation: A Re-evaluation</italic>, argued for a conversation between levels of exegetical practice and for the inclusion of the “ordinary reader” in that conversation.² in his book,<italic>Texts under Negotiation: The Bible and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“It Ain’t Necessarily So”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Resistance Preaching and Womanist Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRIDGEMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>VALERIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1935, the musical “Porgy and Bess” made headlines because it was the first all African American cast to take to Broadway stages. Written by George and Ira Gershwin, it pushed American publics to see African American life. It was, to be sure, stereotypical in a lot of ways. When “Sportin’ Life,” a drug dealer, questions devotion of churchgoing listeners, he sings, “De things dat yo’ liable to read in de Bible, it ain’t necessarily so.” His words are heretical and scandalous. What he does in the song, and what people in marginalized communities continue to do, is to suggest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Liberating Preaching:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hispanic Hermeneutics and Homiletics: Collaborative and Contextual Approaches to Preaching</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CORTÉS-FUENTES</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hispanic homiletics has evolved from a traditional art imitating Anglo-Saxon styles and themes to a more autochthonous, critical, and liberating movement in recent years. As a field of study and research, it is fairly recent, especially within the Hispanic protestant tradition. It begins with the arrival of the earliest protestant missionaries to Latin America who brought with them their homiletic manuals and preaching traditions from North America. Pablo a. Jiménez¹ identifies three stages in the development of a Hispanic homiletics theory: transculturation, inculturation, and contextualization.</p>
                     <p>Transculturation is characterized by the missionary movement of North America into Latin America. Most of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Preaching John:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Word Made Flesh as Theological and Interpretive Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEWIS</surname>
                           <given-names>KAROLINE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Preaching the Fourth Gospel has consistently been a challenge for preachers, especially within the parameters of the Revised common Lectionary in which the Gospel of John appears as supplemental and even subsidiary to the theological and structural concentration on the synoptic Gospels. Preachers do not know quite what to do with this gospel that is at the same time theologically rich and narratively complex. Perhaps one of the most misunderstood aspects of the Fourth Gospel that continues to have a profound effect on its preaching is the portrait of Jesus himself. There is a perceived distance about this Jesus, certainly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Scholars and Soccer Moms:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Objectivity and Subjectivity in Moving from Text to Sermon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AARON</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A marine biologist and an artist look at the ocean differently. A marine biologist asks questions about the ecosystem and the inter-relation of species within that system. This approach to the ocean proceeds by collecting and interpreting data, with a goal of accuracy. An artist sees the beauty and power in the ocean, ruminating on the ways it evokes metaphors about the unknown or the expanses we cannot traverse, with a goal of insight. I do not know enough about marine biology or art to know if a painter and scientist can learn anything from each other. I do know,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Hearing the Voices of Others:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Collaborative Reading of Leviticus 19</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOWELL</surname>
                           <given-names>J. DWAYNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2003, I participated in a group presentation at the annual meeting of the Southeastern Commission of the Study of Religion in Chattanooga, Tennessee. The topic of discussion was, “Responses to 9/11.” My paper, titled “An Understanding of the<italic>gēr</italic>in Leviticus 19:33–34 and the treatment of the immigrant,” dealt with the rise of xenophobia in the United States after the attack of 9/11 and the appropriate response to the immigrant (<italic>gēr</italic>). The tragedy of 9/11 has been compounded by the rise in hate crimes against those citizens of foreign birth or ancestry. Especially affected by this rage are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOWELL</surname>
                           <given-names>J. DWAYNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Bible, the sermon, and the congregation are all intricately related to the personal. Each is influenced by what is seen and heard and by how events and words are interpreted. The biblical text has a rich historical context in the ancient Near East that aids the reader in understanding what the text meant. However, this history is not a static history, locked in the past. Instead, it is a dynamic history of the divine acts of God that can be seen throughout the canonizing process as successive generations interpreted the tradition and text for their situations. The interpreted history</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix</title>
                     <subtitle>Hispanic Biblical Hermeneutics and Homiletics: A Brief Bibliography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CORTÉS-FUENTES</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdvp1.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
