<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8btr</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD450.L555 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Derrida, Jacques</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lévinas, Emmanuel</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Rigor of a Certain Inhumanity</book-title>
         <subtitle>Toward a Wider Suffrage</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LLEWELYN</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253003263</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253005861</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253005868</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Llewelyn</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz7jj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Focusing on the idea of universal suffrage, John Llewelyn accepts the challenge of Derrida's later thought to renew his focus on the ethical, political, and religious dimensions of what makes us uniquely human. Llewelyn builds this concern on issues of representation, language, meaning, and logic with reflections on the phenomenological figures who informed Derrida's concept of deconstruction. By entering into dialogue with these philosophical traditions, Llewelyn demonstrates the range and depth of his own original thinking. The Rigor of a Certain Inhumanity is a rich and passionate, playful and perceptive work of philosophical analysis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How wide is our usual conception of what we call universal suffrage? The aim of this book is to show that that usual conception is not wide enough and that it is not wide enough because it does not do justice to what the book’s title and one of its epigraphs calls “inhumanity.” The envisaged widening of that common conception referred to in the book’s subtitle is simultaneously a widening of our conceptions of the ethical and the political toward the ecological. The eco-logical. The envisaged progression starts in logic and the philosophy of logic—unless it is prevented from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Ideologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Order may be conferred upon the following unchronologically arranged reminders of the history of thinking about linguistic representation if they are prefaced by the reminder that the word<italic>Gegenstand</italic>, so frequently used by Wittgenstein in the<italic>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</italic>, and that word’s Latinate predecessor “object” bring with them the notion of something that is over against or cast in front and so stands in the way. A further complexity arises for us today from the fact that when the Scholastics, followed by Descartes and others, speak of the objective reality of an idea as distinct from its formal reality, objective means</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Worldviews</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Presented by Wittgenstein in the<italic>Philosophical Investigations</italic>is the idea that nominal, referential, and predicative representation presupposes a non-representational purpose or point (<italic>Witz</italic>).¹ Can the same be said of the closely related if not identical idea defended by Heidegger in<italic>Being and Time</italic>according to which the apophantic “as” of assertion or “judgment,” for example the assertion “This hammer is too heavy,” is a graft upon a hermeneutic “as,” for example the experience of this hammer as too heavy expressed not by putting this finding into words but just by putting the hammer down and picking up one that is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Experience of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How close does the experience of language let reading get? How close is close reading? Taking close reading as its point of departure, this chapter will then widen its focus in order to consider the experience of language with some reference to art, interpretation, and what we are now accustomed to calling archi-writing. This last will also be called telescripture, written in the lower case, so that through its first and second syllables, derived not from “<italic>telos</italic>,” end, but from “<italic>tēle</italic>,” distant, far, and through the allusion to uppercase (Holy) Scripture which its third and fourth syllables make, we do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology as Rigorous Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a student of mathematics at Berlin, Husserl became acquainted with Karl Weierstrass and his project for founding mathematical analysis on the concept of number. Not without finding Weierstrass guilty of a certain naïve empiricism, Husserl himself aimed to further this program in the dissertation<italic>On the Concept of Number</italic>(1887) which he went on to compose at Halle under the direction of Carl Stumpf, a former student of Brentano, and which became integrated into his<italic>Philosophy of Arithmetic</italic>(1891).¹ In these works Husserl demonstrates that numbers belong to a continuum that presupposes a mental act of collecting. It is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Pure Grammar</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the idea of pure grammar to which the title of Husserl’s fourth Investigation refers? What is the idea of a grammar of pure logic to which §14 of that Investigation refers? What is the logic of this grammar? What is the grammar of this logic? And what is the philosophical significance of his idea of pure logical grammar? I shall begin to try to answer these questions by way of the answer Husserl himself gives from a historical point of view to the last of them, explaining what part he sees this answer contributing to philosophy. I shall</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Meanings and Translations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Speech and Phenomena</italic>one reads that “<italic>Bedeutung is reserved</italic>[by Husserl] for the content in the ideal sense of<italic>verbal</italic>expression, spoken language….”¹ This may not mean, as it is taken to mean by J. Claude Evans in<italic>Strategies</italic>, that “<italic>Bedeutung</italic>is used to characterize speech” by Husserl as opposed to characterizing something else.² What it says is that “<italic>Bedeutung</italic>” is used to characterize<italic>the content in the ideal sense</italic>of verbal expression, whereas “<italic>Sinn</italic>” is not limited to that.</p>
                     <p>Further, the statement in<italic>Speech and Phenomena</italic>that “for Husserl, the expressiveness of expression—which always supposes the ideality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Re-introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far we have been considering chiefly the case where representation is semantic. But consider now more closely the case where representation is, for instance, ethical. Consider first such a case on analogy with legal representation. Advocates represent their clients at the bar by making representations on their behalf. To make a representation in this context is to make or defend a claim. Further, it can be to make (or defend) a claim that a client has a claim. And the latter claim can be one that is founded in the claimant on behalf of whom the advocate pleads. Or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Approaches to Quasi-theology via Appresentation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The strictness of a conception may be measured in two ways. A conception will be more strict than another if it requires the fulfilment of a larger number of possible criteria than the other. Alternatively, it may be more strict than another if it insists on the fulfilment of a particular criterion that for the other conception is one of an optional set. That is to say, one may measure strictness either according to the standard of the number of conditions deemed necessary or according to the degree of necessity that is deemed to attach to a particular condition. So</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Who Is My Neighbor?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who is my neighbor? The discussion of this question throughout the ages has ranged from asking whether my neighbor is the Jew and the friend, through asking whether my neighbor is any and every other human being including the stranger and my enemy, to asking whether he or she is God. Is it conceivable that my neighbor might be a nonhuman animal? Would this be conceivable to Levinas? If it is claimed that Levinasian “metaphysical” ethics as ethics of human beings beyond their being (<italic>phusis</italic>) can meet a shortcoming in the ethics of utilitarianism at least as this is understood</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Who or What or Whot</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kierkegaard’s statement “The metaphysical, the ontological, is [<italic>er</italic>], but it does not exist [<italic>er ikke til</italic>]” draws the line that separates him from Hegel and both of them from Levinas.¹ His Danish does this distinctly. On the one hand, the preposition “<italic>til</italic>,” “to,” indicates a relation between subjectivity and otherness that, Kierkegaard maintains, cannot be subsumed within the sphere of being or essence. On the other hand, while agreeing with Kierkegaard’s denial, Levinas argues against Kierkegaard (and Heidegger) that the ec-static, ex-sistent to-ness and toward-ness of the relation indicated by Kierkegaard’s preposition presupposes an inward-ness without which there can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Ecosophy, Sophophily, and Philotheria</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once upon a time I took part in a trek along a network of valleys to the base camp of the 1970 British expedition to the south summit of Annapurna in the Himalayas. Although our final destination was merely the edge of the Hiunchuli glacier, our sirdar Yong Tenzing acceded to my request that I might proceed on my own to a cairn a little higher up. On top of the cairn was a Norwegian 10-<italic>øre</italic>coin. Had this been placed there, I mused, by the philosopher and mountaineer Arne Naess with some of whose writings I was familiar? If</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Barbarism, Humanism, and Democratic Ecology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the final sentence of his book<italic>The New Ecological Order</italic>Luc Ferry writes: “Between barbarism and humanism, it is now up to democratic ecology to decide.”¹ He means by this that democratic ecology, as that has been described in his book, must decide between barbarism and humanism, and from what has been said in his book it follows, he maintains, that it is for humanism that democratic ecology must opt. Ecology would not be democratic unless it were an ecology centered on the<italic>dēmos</italic>. By<italic>dēmos</italic>he means humankind, the third of the three things mentioned in the subtitle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Where to Cut:</title>
                     <subtitle>Boucherie and Delikatessen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Referring in<italic>The Animal That Therefore I Am to The Middle Voice of Ecological Conscience</italic>, Derrida says that he wishes to recommend the latter book especially because, sharing the author’s concern, he will perhaps proceed a little differently.¹ My concern in that book and particularly in chapter 8 of this one is to raise consciousness. It is to raise consciousness, where it seems to me to need raising, to conscience, and to raise conscience, where it seems to me to need raising, to responsibility. By responsibility I mean ethical responsibility in a sense I take to be the sense proposed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Passover</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ce sacré pas du repas</italic>, this blessèd and blasted<italic>pastoverness</italic>of the<italic>repast</italic>, was something that made Derrida and me smile. The occasion was the colloquium “Victor Cousin, the Ideologists, and their Relations with Scottish Philosophy” that took place at the International Study Center of Sèvres in 1982 under the direction of Derrida on the French side, of myself on the Scottish side, and of Pierre Alexandre, who, as then co-director of the Center and formerly director of the French Institute in Scotland, was well placed to coordinate our energies. Professor Henri Gouhier honored us with his presence and his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Rigor of a Certain Inhumanity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A passing bell sounds in the word “rigor” used in the phrase borrowed from Derrida in the title of this book to perform a double service. On the one hand the title refers to the<italic>rigor mortis</italic>threatened by the rigidly rigorous pure science of representation that Husserl and the young Wittgenstein both sought as an ideal and feared as an instigator of crisis. On the other hand the title refers to a deepening of crisis, to what may be described as a hyperCritical crisis because it is a crisis provoked by a responsibility, spelled out in the second part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7jj.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
