<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Engaging the Powers</book-title>
         <subtitle>25th Anniversary Edition</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WINK</surname>
               <given-names>WALTER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506438160</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506438542</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7j16"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this brilliant culmination of his seminal Powers Trilogy, now reissued in a twenty-fifth anniversary edition, Walter Wink explores the problem of evil today and how it relates to the New Testament concept of principalities and powers. He asks the question, "How can we oppose evil without creating new evils and being made evil ourselves?"</p>
         <p>Winner of the Pax Christi Award, the Academy of Parish Clergy Book of the Year, and the Midwest Book Achievement Award for Best Religious Book.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="520"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations and Symbols</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most pressing questions facing the world today is, How can we oppose evil without creating new evils and being made evil ourselves?</p>
                     <p>It is my conviction that any attempt to face the problem of evil in society from a New Testament perspective must be bound up with an understanding of what the Bible calls the “Principalities and Powers.” I am also convinced that no social ethic can be constructed on New Testament grounds without recognition of the role of these Powers in sustaining and subverting human life.²</p>
                     <p>The Powers, unfortunately, have long since been identified as an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Myth of the Domination System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Violence is the ethos of our times. It is the spirituality of the modern world. It has been accorded the status of a religion, demanding from its devotees an absolute obedience to death. Its followers are not aware, however, that the devotion they pay to violence is a form of religious piety. Violence is so successful as a myth precisely because it does not seem to be mythic in the least. Violence simply appears to be the nature of things. It is what works. It is inevitable, the last and, often, the first resort in conflicts. It is embraced with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The Origin of the Domination System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How did the Domination System get started? The myth of redemptive violence gives this answer: war, conquest, plunder, rape, and enslavement are all ordained in the very constitution of the universe, which itself is formed from the corpse of a murdered goddess. “Civilization” is a condition of periodic or perpetual warfare, “peace” the achievement of warfare, “prosperity” the fruit of warfare successfully accomplished. If human beings are created from the blood of a slaughtered god, how can one expect from them anything but violence?</p>
                     <p>Is violence then our fate? Is there no alternative to the Domination System? Students of animal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Naming the Domination System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The New Testament is thoroughly familiar with the Domination System, and has specific terms for describing it. In this chapter we examine three terms whose real meaning has sadly been obscured for many readers of the Bible. They are the Greek words<italic>kosmos</italic>(world),<italic>aiōn</italic>(age), and<italic>sarx</italic>(flesh). With these terms the biblical writers named the Domination System and thus stripped it, for those who understood, of its invisibility and legitimacy.</p>
                     <p>The Greek word kosmos means, variously, world, universe, the creation, humanity, the planet earth, the theater of history.² These conventional usages of<italic>kosmos</italic>/“world” are roughly similar in Greek</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>The Nature of the Domination System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The good news is that God not only liberates us from the Powers, but liberates the Powers as well. The gospel is not a dualistic myth of good and evil forces vying for ascendancy, as in the myth of redemptive violence. It is a sublimely subtle drama about the intertwining of good and evil in all of historical reality. The Powers are not simply evil. They are a bulwark against anarchy, and a patron, repository, and inspirer of art. They inculcate values that encourage interdependency, mutual care, and social cohesiveness. They encourage submission of personal desires to the general good</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Unmasking the Domination System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the Domination System is so insufferable, why do people tolerate it? Why do they not rise up against a way of life that provides advantages to so few and misery to so many? How is it possible that literally billions of people permit themselves to be hoodwinked and fleeced by tiny circles of elites propped up by armies far from adequate to subdue the population of the world? Surely this is the greatest political mystery ever: the regular failure of the masses to use their overwhelming numerical superiority to throw off their oppressors.</p>
                     <p>One of the first to identify</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>God’s Domination-Free Order:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jesus and God’s Reign</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The irreducible fact about Jesus is that he was executed. Yet he did not represent an armed threat to the existing order. He broke no civil or criminal laws. He violated religious laws and customs regarding the Sabbath, hand-washing, and holiness, but in every case the issue hung on interpretation, and no doubt some rabbis would have supported him; at least they would not have condemned him to death. He mainly taught, healed, and exorcised. Why then was he such a threat that he had to be killed?</p>
                     <p>Scholars have suggested a variety of reasons, none of them alone adequate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Breaking the Spiral of Violence:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Power of the Cross</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the Domination System catches the merest whiff of God’s new order, by an automatic reflex it mobilizes all its might to suppress that order. Even before Jesus experienced its full fury against himself, he apparently predicted the outcome.² The Powers are so immense, the opposition so weak, that every attempt at fundamental change seems doomed to failure. The Powers are seldom content merely to win; they must win overwhelmingly, in order to demoralize opposition before it can gain momentum. Always there is the gratuitous violence, the mocking derision, the intimidating brutality of the means of execution.³ All of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>To Wash Off the Not Human:</title>
                     <subtitle>Becoming Expendable</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One does not become free from the Powers by defeating them in a frontal attack. Rather, one dies to their control. Here also the cross is the model: we are liberated, not by striking back at what enslaves us—for even striking back reveals that we are still determined by its violent ethos—but by dying out from under its jurisdiction and command. As one founder of New Forum, which orchestrated the collapse of the communist regime in East Germany in 1989, put it, “You don’t need courage to speak out against a regime. You just need not to care</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part III. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Powers are not incorrigible. What fell in time can be redeemed in time. Even in their fallenness, institutions are able to some degree to preserve freedoms and secure justice. The flight of the communist bloc from totalitarianism shows how deep is the longing of the human spirit for the liberty to speak, travel, work, and pursue creative initiatives.</p>
                     <p>Ideally, democracy is nonviolence institutionalized. It is the only political order that rejects domination in principle and grounds itself in equality before the law. Despite its susceptibility to manipulation by the rich and powerful, democracy is the best system yet devised</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Jesus’ Third Way:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nonviolent Engagement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human evolution has provided the species with two deeply instinctual responses to violence: flight or fight. Jesus offers a third way: nonviolent direct action.² The classic text is Matt. 5:38-42:</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>38</sup>You have heard that it was said, “An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.”<sup>39</sup>But I say to you, Do not resist an evildoer. But if anyone strikes you on the right cheek, turn the other also;<sup>40</sup>and if anyone wants to sue you and take your coat, give your cloak as well;<sup>41</sup>and if anyone forces you to go one mile, go also the second</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>On Not Becoming What We Hate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I suggested that “Resist not evil” is better rendered “Do not return evil for evil,” “Do not mirror evil,” “Do not respond to evil in kind.” This refusal of reactive opposition is one of the most profound and difficult truths in Scripture. We become what we hate. The very act of hating something draws it to us. Since our hate is usually a direct response to an evil done to us, our hate almost invariably causes us to respond in the terms already laid down by the enemy. Unaware of what is happening, we turn into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Beyond Just War and Pacifism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The new reality Jesus proclaimed was nonviolent. That much is clear, not just from the Sermon on the Mount, but from his entire life and teaching and, above all, the way he faced his death. His was not merely a tactical or pragmatic nonviolence seized upon because nothing else would have “worked” against the Roman Empire’s near monopoly on violence. Rather, he saw nonviolence as a direct corollary of the nature of God and of the new reality emerging in the world from God. In a verse quoted more than any other from the New Testament during the church’s first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>But What If …?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is surprising how few people have seriously considered nonviolence as a way of life and a strategy for social change. We are so inured to violence that we find it hard to<italic>believe in</italic>anything else. And that phrase “believe in” provides the clue. We trust violence. Violence “saves.” It is “redemptive.” All we have to do is make survival the highest goal, and death the greatest evil, and we have handed ourselves over to the gods of the Domination System. We trust violence because we are afraid. And we will not relinquish our fears until we are able</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Re-Visioning History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nonviolence Past, Present, Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History has been written by the victors. What young people learn in schools is largely a chronicle of kings and dynasties, wars and empires. Androcratic systems teach androcratic history. Even where nonviolent resistance was successfully used, it tends to be neglected. A people kept ignorant of the existence of the history of nonviolence will naturally believe that it is impractical and unrealistic. In those cases where it is known, as in Gandhi’s struggle for independence in India or the civil rights movement in the United States, it is regarded as an unrepeatable oddity. The Powers know all too well that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>The Acid Test:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loving Enemies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the spiritual renaissance that I believe is coming to birth, it will not be the message of Paul that this time galvanizes hearts, as in the Reformation and the Wesleyan revival, but the human figure of Jesus. And in the teaching of Jesus, the sayings on nonviolence and love of enemies will hold a central place. Not because they are more true than any others, but because they are the only means known for overcoming domination without creating new dominations.</p>
                     <p>I submit that the ultimate religious question today should no longer be the Reformation’s question, “How can I find</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Monitoring Our Inner Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am not a very nonviolent person. I have a sharp temper that I have learned to control fairly well, and find myself indulging at times in violent fantasies. I am trying to discover how a person as deeply schooled in violence as I was can begin to practice nonviolence. As I indicated earlier, one could characterize the approach I have been developing in this book as nonviolence for the violent.</p>
                     <p>There was a period in high school when I flirted with pacifism, but it quietly evaporated in seminary before the onslaught of Reinhold Niebuhr’s “Christian realism,” with its invective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Prayer and the Powers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are not easily reduced to prayer. We who grope toward praying today are like a city gutted by fire. The struggle against injustice has exacted from us an awful cost. In a similar period with similar smuggles, Camus wrote, “There is merely bad luck in not being loved; there is tragedy in not loving. All of us, today, are dying of this tragedy. For violence and hatred dry up the heart itself; the long fight for justice exhausts the love that nevertheless gave birth to it. In the clamor in which we live, love is impossible and justice does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>Celebrating the Victory of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How remarkable, that despite its sober exposé of the Domination System, the New Testament is so free of gloom or quailing before the Powers! From beginning to end, there is only the note of victory—a victory in the unknown and open future, for the whole human race and the universe, and victory even now, in the midst of struggle. There is an absolute and unshakable confidence that the System of Domination has an end. A new world of partnership, of compassion, of human community, of conscious awareness of the limits of power, awaits us. We are to struggle with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Passages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>447</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>493</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Author</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>495</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1tm7j16.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>496</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
