<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt195sdw9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Medium, Messenger, Transmission</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Approach to Media Philosophy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Krämer</surname>
               <given-names>Sybille</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789089647412</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789048524990</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>S. Krämer</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Amsterdam University Press B.V.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19630z0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Medium, Messenger, Transmission</italic>uses the figure of the messenger as a key metaphor for the function of all transmission media. Sybille Krämer illustrates this argument with a diverse range of situations involving some form of transmission, including the circulation of money, the translation of languages, the spread of infectious diseases, processes of transference and countertransference as seen in psychoanalysis, and even the development of cartography. This rich study provides a comprehensive introduction to the field of media philosophy while illuminating transmission media as active mediators in all systems of exchange.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Recursions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Editors’ Introduction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parikka</surname>
                           <given-names>Jussi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tuschling</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Winthrop-Young</surname>
                           <given-names>Geoffrey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Media Philosophy of Sybille Krämer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Enns</surname>
                           <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canadian media theorist Marshall McLuhan famously argued that the purpose of media studies was to make visible that which normally remains invisible – namely, the effects of media technologies rather than the messages they convey. When he originally proposed this idea in the 1960s McLuhan was widely celebrated as the great prophet of the media age, but in the decades that followed his work gradually fell into disregard. In the 1970s, for example, Raymond Williams claimed that McLuhan’s ideas were ‘ludicrous’¹ and Hans Magnus Enzensberger dismissed him as a ‘charlatan’ who was ‘incapable of any theoretical construction’ and who wrote</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue</title>
                     <subtitle>Transmission and/or Understanding? On the ‘Postal’ and ‘Erotic’ Principles of Communication</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can the meaning of media be thought about in such a way that we acquire an understanding of our relationship to both the world and to ourselves? How can a concept of the medium be developed that encompasses our experiences using media? How can we determine what media ‘are’ in a way that embraces both generally accepted (voice, writing) and newer forms of media (computer, Internet)? How can media be conceptualized in a way that enables not only a reformulation of traditional philosophical questions but also a new conception of philosophy? Assuming first of all that one media concept</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Methodological Considerations</title>
                     <subtitle>Is a Metaphysics of Mediality Possible?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following section continues with a look at contemporary reflections on media, albeit limited to the discourses of cultural studies and philosophy.¹</p>
                     <p>The debate over media that was first articulated in the 1960s and continues to flourish today is confusing, multivocal and heterogeneous: there is no consensus in the phenomenal domain, the methodological approach or even the very concept of media. Nevertheless, through the multitude of heterogeneous voices – at least in the cultural studies camp – it is possible to perceive a certain vocal range that could be called the ‘bon ton of the media debate’. This ‘bon ton’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introductions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The foregoing preliminary considerations show what the following study intends to accomplish and what it intends to avoid:</p>
                     <p>(1) The medium will not be theorized as a means or an instrument but rather as a<italic>middle</italic>and a<italic>mediator</italic>. In light of this mediating function, the ‘transmission perspective’ and the ‘postal principle’ will be explored by investigating whether ‘transmission’ is definable in a way that at the same time reveals how media affect and shape what they transmit. The original scope of medial effectiveness will also be reconstructed as a<italic>perceptual relation</italic>and a<italic>letting-appear</italic>(<italic>Erscheinenlassen</italic>), in which the communicative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Messenger Model</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The texts by Benjamin, Nancy, Serres, Debray, and Peters are all extremely different. It may seem peculiar to invoke these authors as ‘introductions’ to the theme of mediality when only the last one actually discusses concrete media, yet this is quite deliberate. I want to debate the question of ‘What is a medium?’ from the very beginning in the context of mediality. ‘Mediality’ does not refer to media that are distinct from each other, like sound, text, and image, but rather its aim is to describe an elementary dimension of human life and culture.¹</p>
                     <p>Consider, therefore, the following question: Is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Transmissions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In religion, myth, legend, and above all in the arts there is an imaginary space populated with messengers: It is the world of angels, of placeless mediators between heaven and earth. The study of angels (‘angelology’¹) is an epiphenomenon of monotheism: Judaism, Christianity, and Islam have added a more or less extensive army of angels to the statuary isolation of their God; the constitutional invisibility, unrepresentability, and remoteness of God is therefore supplemented with the offer of something holy that is visible, representable, and close, which takes on an allegorical form in angels. Angels are not simply there, but rather</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>So What Does ‘Transmission’ Mean?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Up until now I have been dealing with forms of transmission in widely diverse fields. I have also been dealing with forms of transmission that are not obviously subject to the regime of a medium, like radio or television, as this – albeit entirely random – selection of transmission modalities was designed to trace by analogy the functional logic of the messenger precisely where the mediality of this process was not at all obvious. And the discovery of these forms of transmission was bound up with the hope that their subtlety and diversity could assess and also expand the categorical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Test Case</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have not yet provided an example of a phenomenon that can unproblematically be identified as a medium or demonstrated how the messenger and transmission perspective I have developed actually brings to light<italic>new</italic>aspects of this phenomenon. There are two additional requirements that would – ideally – be satisfied by such a test case: It should be a medium that cuts across different times, that is not rooted in only one respectable tradition, but rather that provides a context in which the changes associated with the development of information technologies and digitalization can also be reflected and studied. Furthermore,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>Worldview Dimensions, Ambivalences, Possible Directions for Further Research</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This discussion is (almost) at an end; all that remains is a conclusion, and I want to open this conclusion by raising a concluding and very fundamental question: What is the use of a study that proposes to rehabilitate the model of the messenger and transmission? Surely it is intended to develop a more interesting – if also slightly outmoded – approach to media theory, but isn’t the risk of misunderstandings too high a price to pay for this mediatheoretical perspective given the obvious heteronomy of the messenger figure and his apparently dependent transmission activity? This risk is further exacerbated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19630z0.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
