<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Scandal of Sacramentality</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Eucharist in Literary and Theological Perspectives</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hancock</surname>
               <given-names>Brannon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="foreword-author">Forewords by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Loades</surname>
               <given-names>Ann</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jasper</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174548</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902646</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Brannon Hancock</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf2fr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this new book, Brannon Hancock explores the theme of the "scandalous" sacrament in the context of our current Western culture which some would describe as “post-Christian", and in the light of the Christian churches who hold sacramental life as central to their faith. In the texts addressed by Hancock we return to the body in all its messy complexity, and therefore to the mystery which lies at the very heart of the sacramental incarnation, the Word made Flesh.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loades</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theologians writing on the long, prodigal, and contentious tradition of reflection on the “sacrament” of the Eucharist are in for some surprises as they read this book! Artists of many kinds resist having their insights regarded as merely “illustrative” of what theologians supposedly already “know.” Some writers have been gripped by the “scandal” (1 Cor 1: 23) of the Eucharist, of the relation of language to flesh, the profane to the sacred, the erotic and destabilising “grace” of its mystery. For Dr. Hancock to have included Graham Greene’s<italic>Monsignor Quixote</italic>was perhaps predictable, but not so the other half a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jasper</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sacramental life of the Christian Church has, from the very earliest times, been acquainted with scandal. There is reason to think that the celebration of the Eucharist, in some form, predates even the canonical Gospels, and by the end of the second century of the Christian era, Tertullian was grimly satirizing those outside the Church who clearly thought that the sacrament was shocking in the extreme and beyond what was tolerable. “We are accused,” he wrote, “of observing a sacred ritual in which we kill a little child and eat it.” He goes on to describe this action in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is an interdisciplinary inquiry into the nature of sacrament and into the relationship between the Eucharist—the ritual partaking of the body and blood of Christ in the symbols of bread and wine—as the sacrament<italic>par excellence</italic>, and sacramental themes or “traces” of sacramentality that appear in contemporary fictional narratives. In a “post-Christian” (or at the very least “post-ecclesial”) age characterized by waning participation in traditional Christian practices,² a surprising persistence and relevance of sacramental themes and eucharistic allusions may be observed within contemporary literature and the creative arts more broadly. One wonders, then—apart from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Skandalon:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stumbling over Sacrament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before we are able to discuss sacrament as a linguistic or a corporeal scandal, we must have a basic understanding of what a sacrament is . In this chapter, we will establish what we mean by<italic>sacrament</italic>and<italic>sacramentality</italic>, and examine the reasons this concept has been a stumbling-block to Christian theology and liturgy. Any understanding of sacrament must be tethered closely to the entire Christ event, to the biblical witness concerning the person of Jesus Christ and the sacred meal he instituted in the Last Supper. However, sacraments must also be understood as cultural artifacts of a sort; indeed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“The Word . . .”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Problem of Language</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we have shown that the scandal of sacramentality derives first from Christ himself, the Word of God made flesh, crucified on Calvary, which St. Paul calls a “stumbling-block” (<italic>skandalon</italic>). Sacraments are visible and tangible, yet they mediate to us the invisible and intangible saving grace of God, which is resident within the material, created order precisely because of the incarnation of God in Christ Jesus, the Word of God made flesh. Through participation in this mediation, the ecclesial community is both constituted,<italic>made into</italic>the body of Christ called Church, and unmade: fractured, broken, de-stabilized, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“. . . Made Flesh”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Problem of the Body</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have thus far established that the central corporate act of the Christian<italic>ecclesia</italic>, from which the Church derives its identity as the Body of Christ and its sacramental structure, is the Eucharist, the participation in Christ’s broken body and shed blood. The Eucharist not only points toward the cross of Christ but toward the entire narrative of the incarnation of God in human body of Jesus of Nazareth. We glimpse the central stumblingblock—what St. Paul calls a<italic>skandalon</italic>—of Christian faith and practice: “we preach Christ crucified: a stumbling block to Jews and foolishness to Gentiles” (1 Cor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fracturing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Brokenness and Sacrament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Part One, the<italic>skandalon</italic>of sacramentality was established as a two-fold scandal of language and the body. Beginning with language, this raises a hermeneutical problem: how to determine meaning, significance, from speech or text. But the<italic>skandalon</italic>of the body is also a hermeneutical problem: how to “read” the body, especially the present absence of Christ’s “displaced” body, which overextends its bounds and incorporates all bodies. In both cases, we encounter a plurisignificance that is unsettling. It seems there is no possibility of singular or univocal meaning. However, it is here that the eruptive truth of sacramentality arises, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Consuming:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cannibalism and Sacrament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we examined the traces of sacramentality in the broken, fractured body of Christ and the bodies of characters in contemporary literature. In this chapter, we will focus on the<italic>skandalon</italic>of the Eucharist as it relates to bodily consumption. We deliberately employ the ambiguous phrase<italic>bodily consumption</italic>precisely because it implies both eating—the physical, digestive processes associated with bodily consumption—as well as the more cannibalistic connotation of the phrase: the consumption of the body (as food) as well as the body’s consumption (of food). To grapple with the Eucharist as<italic>necessarily</italic>scandalous and scandalizing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Penetrating:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eroticism and Sacrament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although we have thus far avoided the language, it should be clear by now that the mediacy and materiality of sacramentality is another way of saying that sacraments are sensuous they engage us, and we participate in them, at the level of our senses. We see, taste, touch, and smell the bread and the wine; we hear the fraction of the host and the pouring of water and wine into the chalice. And relatedly, sacraments are<italic>sensual</italic>—they<italic>gratify</italic>the senses, in a way that might almost connote carnality. As we concluded the previous chapter, we began to move from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>In-Conclusion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout this book we have wrestled with the question of how to conceive of sacrament and sacramentality in a way that consists with the postmodern imagination. We have seen that the meaning of the Eucharist, and by extension sacramentality, may be derived from the endless matrix of signification within which it exists. In this sense, the Eucharist is not “rooted” in its history, but rather<italic>extends across history</italic>as an endlessly sprawling, endlessly relevant living metaphor. It recalls the Last Supper; it (re) presents Christ’s sacrificial death on Calvary; it is ratified by the<italic>living</italic>Tradition of the Body of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf2fr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
