<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>White Identities</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Critical Sociological Approach</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CLARKE</surname>
               <given-names>SIMON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GARNER</surname>
               <given-names>STEVE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745327488</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849643870</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Simon Clarke</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Steve Garner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p383"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The study of white ethnicities is becoming increasingly important in the social sciences. This book provides a critical introduction to the topic. Whiteness has traditionally been seen as "ethnically transparent" - the marker against which other ethnicities are measured. This analysis is clearly incorrect, but only recently have many race and ethnicity scholars moved away from focusing on ethnic minorities and instead oriented their studies around the construction of white identities. Simon Clarke and Steve Garner's book is designed to guide students as they explore how white identities are forged using both sociological and psycho-social ideas. Including an excellent survey of the existing literature and original research from the UK, this book will be an invaluable guide for sociology students taking modules in race and ethnicity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>RESEARCHING ‘WHITENESS’:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN INTRODUCTION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is an exploration of sociological and psycho-social theories of the construction of whiteness vis-à-vis perceptions and imaginings of otherness. It has three main aims. First, to introduce the reader to the history and theoretical unfolding of contemporary studies of whiteness in North America and Europe. Second, to explore the structural facilitating factors of these constructions, through such institutions as the state and the media. Finally, the book synthesises a psycho-social perspective to look at the underlying mechanisms which fuel social exclusion and inclusion in society. Theory is never separated from practice and the book makes full use of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>WHITENESS STUDIES IN THE CONTEXT OF THE USA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Whiteness studies’ in the USA is a broad, nebulous and multidisciplinary field whose development has provoked a good deal of debate, since the early 1990s, on issues such as epistemology, reinterpretations of American history, and the ways in which dominant identities are constructed. In this chapter we provide an outline of the key areas of debate and the principal ways in which whiteness has been conceptualised.</p>
                     <p>What is whiteness? As with most social science concepts there is a lack of consensus around it. Whiteness is difficult to define due to the diversity of ways in which the term is implicitly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>EMPIRICAL RESEARCH INTO WHITE RACIALISED IDENTITIES IN BRITAIN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The intellectual project of using whiteness as a tool of analysis is not one that has taken root in the UK. However, there are a number of empirical studies that investigate the racialisation of white identities. This bears some comparison to the themes thrown up by the plethora of American work in the loose multidisciplinary field labelled ‘whiteness studies’. Indeed, that corpus is far advanced: Winddance Twine and Gallagher (2008: 5) label the empirical studies of localised whiteness as it intersects with class, nation and gender, as the ‘third wave’ of whiteness studies. This scholarly movement has been blamed for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>BRITISHNESS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the questions we asked our interviewees in 2005–6 was what being British meant to them. Their responses reflect the precise historical moment in which this project took place: the end of the first decade of devolution, the recent 9/11 and 7/7 attacks and bombings, an intense focus on asylum and immigration, and an attempt to reinstate Britishness as an explicit point of collective identification. Starting by outlining some of the theories of national belonging, we will go on to present and analyse responses picked up in our fieldwork. We argue that the way identification is performed suggests that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>WHITENESS AND POST-IMPERIAL BRITAIN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is<italic>assumed</italic>rather than<italic>demonstrated</italic>in some key work in the field of post-colonial studies that British identity is still inflected by the experience of empire in twenty-first century Britain (Knowles, 2003). This also provides the backdrop for the work of critical race theorists such as Paul Gilroy, who grounds<italic>After Empire</italic>(2004) and its inter-related arguments about Britishness, loss, ‘conviviality’ and ‘melancholia’ in this idea. What we do in this chapter is look at data from fieldwork on identities in Britain, and advance a tentative argument about the presence of empire in people’s construction of identity in post-imperial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>PSYCHO-SOCIAL INTERPRETATIONS OF CULTURAL IDENTITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONSTRUCTING THE WHITE ‘WE’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The social construction of white identity, or indeed identities in general, can offer us a real insight into how we perceive the self and others. In this chapter we argue that a psycho-social dimension goes beyond traditional analysis and allows us to understand the emotional, affective and visceral content of identity construction. Drawing on psychoanalytic ideas and concepts, we unravel the psychological dynamics involved in the construction of the white ‘we’ in relation to the otherness of the Other. Cultural identities are marked by a number of factors – ‘race’, ethnicity, gender and class to name but a few – yet the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>MEDIA REPRESENTATIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONSTRUCTING THE ‘NOT WHITE’ OTHER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we address the issue of asylum and asylum seekers in contemporary Britain. In it we argue that there is a worrying trend towards the conflation of asylum issues with terrorism. Using examples from the media and politics we argue that there is a new politics of fear emerging, which more than ever concentrates on difference and the demonisation of the Other. This politics uses emotional and psychological methods to play on our social fears and anxieties around community. This goes hand-in-hand with a mainstreaming of anti-immigration policy as a political value: a process that has drawn Left</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>WHITENESS, HOME AND COMMUNITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea of community has always been central to the construction of group and individual identity. It has been the site of moral panics about the disintegration of traditional community and values as well as concerns around racism and segregation (see chapter 5). The notion of community is of central importance in contemporary policy and political thinking. So, for example, as Anna Marie Smith (1992) argues in the 1980s and early 1990s new right Thatcherite policy concentrated on creating a hegemonic project that aimed at defining social space through the construction of outsider figures. Smith argues that the construction of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>RESEARCHING WHITENESS:</title>
                     <subtitle>PSYCHO-SOCIAL METHODOLOGIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Psycho-social studies is an emerging tradition that very much focuses on emotion and affect to illuminate some of the core issues in the social sciences. Issues such as identity construction, dilemmas in public service sectors and the experience of rapid social change. It recognises that the split between individual and society, sociology and psychology is now unhelpful if we are to understand social and psychological phenomena. It therefore seeks to research beneath the surface using both psychoanalytic and sociological ideas using innovative new methodologies including the use of free association, biographical life history interviews and the development of psychoanalytic fieldwork.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our exploration of the themes of community and identity in provincial England is necessarily qualified. Our sample was relatively small and restricted to two cities. However, we suggest, in the light of further research, which admittedly focused on working-class respondents (Hoggett et al., 2008; Garner et al., 2009), that the discourses on community, Britishness and whiteness are generally applicable outside of some large metropolitan areas where Gilroy’s model of conviviality might be the dominant mode. The temptation for researcher and reader alike is to become absorbed into the details and start to lose track of the bigger picture. There are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p383.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
