<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8m3</collection-id>
      <volume>205</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS747.I5.S32 2001</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Zuoqiu, Ming. Guo yu</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Spring and Autumn period, 722-481 B.C.</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Zuoqiu, Ming. Zuo zhuan</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Confucius. Chun qiu</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Patterned Past</book-title>
         <subtitle>Form and Thought in Early Chinese Historiography</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schaberg</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674008618</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684173617</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684173612</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tg5npx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this comprehensive study of the rhetoric, narrative patterns, and intellectual content of the Zuozhuan and Guoyu, David Schaberg reads these two collections of historical anecdotes as traces of a historiographical practice that flourished around the fourth century BCE among the followers of Confucius. He contends that the coherent view of early China found in these texts is an effect of their origins and the habits of reading they impose. Rather than being totally accurate accounts, they represent the efforts of a group of officials and ministers to argue for a moralizing interpretation of the events of early Chinese history and for their own value as skilled interpreters of events and advisers to the rulers of the day.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="530"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conventions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dukes of Lu in the Spring and Autumn Period</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 638 B.C.E., in an episode that was to become a matter of some difficulty to Confucian commentators, an army from the southern state of Chu defeated a force of the state of Song on the banks of the river Hong. Song’s ruler, Duke Xiang (r. 650-637), had worked for some years to establish himself as hegemon (<italic>ba</italic>) of the central states, a role left vacant by the death of Duke Huan of Qi (r. 685-643).¹ His efforts had necessarily brought him into conflict with Chu, the threat against which the earlier alliance had been organized.</p>
                     <p>On the battlefield, according</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Rhetoric of Good Order</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the chapter devoted to speeches in the<italic>Shitong</italic>(Penetration of history), Liu Zhiji (661–721) emphasized both the cultured elegance and the admira, ble stylistic restraint of speeches in the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>周監二代郁郁乎文大夫行人.尤重詞命語微娩而多切.言流靡而 不淫若春秋載呂相絕秦子產獻捷.臧孫諫納鼎魏絳對戮楊干是也.</p>
                     <p>The Zhou, observing the two previous dynasties, was refined in its cultural practice. Ministers and envoys especially stressed the language of protocol; their speeches were subtle yet to the point, while their words were flowing and beautiful yet never in excess. The<italic>Chunqiu</italic>’s accounts of Lü Xiang’s break with Qin, of Zichan’s presentation of the prisoners, of Zangsun’s remonstrance with the duke over the installation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Wen and the Meaning of Verbal Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term<italic>wen</italic>, which has a pre-eminent place both in Confucian philosophy and among the virtues named in the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and<italic>Guoyu</italic>, is notorious for the complexity of its semantic range. In oracle bone and bronze inscriptions, it functions largely as an epithet for deceased ancestors and rulers and appears to mean something like “accomplished.”¹ In references to artifacts, it denotes stripes of the sort found on cowry shells or patterns woven into cloth.² It is the preferred pre-Qin word for “logograph.”³ In the writings of certain philosophers, most notably Xunzi, it becomes a more abstract sort of “pattern,” the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Intelligibility in the Extra-human World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although speakers in historiography do much of their reasoning through citation and application of the<italic>Shi</italic>and other texts, they also call on many types of knowledge beyond the reach of inherited language. The<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and<italic>Guoyu</italic>show a more sustained interest in the workings of the natural and supernatural worlds than any extant earlier works and go well beyond early Zhou texts in reasoning about the cosmos and its principles. When speeches incorporate this sort of knowledge, they put it to political and moral use, if only because the position defined for speeches within this system requires such use.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Order in the Human World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the perspective of the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and<italic>Guoyu</italic>, the known world is a space cleared in the wilderness by culture. Culture, which is both a system of prescriptions and the legitimizing account of their origins, establishes the distinctions that define the human world. This world is bounded on one frontier by the spirit world and on the other by the non-Chinese world. It is organized internally according to nested structures of kinship and obligation, which are made to account for geography and fealty. And it finds itself in the times recounted by historiography, in a consciously late Zhou moment. Although</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Anecdotal History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical knowledge can take many forms, but historical understanding always requires narration.¹ A text such as the<italic>Chunqiu</italic>, with its dates and facts, does not so much convey understanding as assume it. The<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and the<italic>Guoyu</italic>, in contrast, explain known or alleged facts of the Spring and Autumn period by recording them in the context of narratives. Although premodern critics of the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>as a commentary on the<italic>Chunqiu</italic>sometimes ranked it behind the<italic>Gongyang</italic>and<italic>Guliang</italic>commentaries, with their more direct articulations of the sage’s judgments, there have always been readers who recognized that without the narratives of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Narrative and Recompense</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The anecdote cannot easily accommodate multiple plot lines. It is well adapted for the narration of events involving a limited cast of characters and a single set of consequences, but when a narrative involves many characters or groups, with varying motivations, acting in different times and places, the anecdote falls short. For more complex chains of events, the historiographers of the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and<italic>Guoyu</italic>combined anecdotes into series, building largescale narratives that are nonetheless fundamentally anecdotal in character. The anecdote series merits study for its role as a shaper of historical memory: it is the narrative genre in which the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Aesthetics and Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One could categorize narratives by the things they represent as objects of repression, which are always the same things they represent as irrepressible. For example, Freud, the inventor of the notion of the “return of the repressed,” made unresolved childhood conflicts his focus; to defend his thesis, he wrote narratives in which these conflicts are the source of the energy that drives plots forward and disrupts patients’ sanity.¹ For the narrators of the<italic>Zuozhuan</italic>and the<italic>Guoyu</italic>, ritual propriety is the great object of repression and the continual revenant. With some consistency, they explain disasters as the consequences of deviation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Writing and the Ends of History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To narrate is to encode an ideology. Fredric Jameson, applying an insight of Levi-Strauss to the study of narrative, has written that “ideology is not something which informs or invests symbolic production; rather the aesthetic act is itself ideological, and the production of aesthetic or narrative form is to be seen as an ideological act in its own right, with the function of inventing imaginary or formal ‘solutions’ to unresolvable social contradictions.”¹ Both in selecting material and in setting the terms of its intelligibility, narrators uphold certain views on the workings of the world while rejecting others as wrong or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>Orality and the Origins of the Zuozhuan and Guoyu</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>443</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chinese Character List</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index Locorum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>487</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>491</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5npx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>505</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
