<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Nietzsche's Great Politics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DROCHON</surname>
               <given-names>HUGO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400881031</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">140088103X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wf4chc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Nietzsche's impact on the world of culture, philosophy, and the arts is uncontested, but his political thought remains mired in controversy. By placing Nietzsche back in his late-nineteenth-century German context,<italic>Nietzsche's Great Politics</italic>moves away from the disputes surrounding Nietzsche's appropriation by the Nazis and challenges the use of the philosopher in postmodern democratic thought. Rather than starting with contemporary democratic theory or continental philosophy, Hugo Drochon argues that Nietzsche's political ideas must first be understood in light of Bismarck's policies, in particular his "Great Politics," which transformed the international politics of the late nineteenth century.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Nietzsche's Great Politics</italic>shows how Nietzsche made Bismarck's notion his own, enabling him to offer a vision of a unified European political order that was to serve as a counterbalance to both Britain and Russia. This order was to be led by a "good European" cultural elite whose goal would be to encourage the rebirth of Greek high culture. In relocating Nietzsche's politics to their own time, the book offers not only a novel reading of the philosopher but also a more accurate picture of why his political thought remains so relevant today.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDITIONS AND TRANSLATIONS USED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XIII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XV</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Friedrich Nietzsche’s impact on the world of culture, philosophy, and the arts is uncontested, but his contribution to political thought remains mired in controversy. The source of that controversy resides in his political misappropriation by the Nazis during World War II, and we are still counting the cost of that appropriation for contemporary scholarship today. So the price that Walter Kaufmann—in his seminal<italic>Nietzsche: Philosopher, Psychologist, Antichrist</italic>, first published in 1950, now in its fourth edition—paid to rescue Nietzsche from the philosophical abyss he had fallen into after the war was to deny him any interest in politics.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>THE GREEKS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Looking back over his life in 1888—“What I Owe to the Ancients” serves as the starting point for Nietzsche’s “autobiography”<italic>Ecce Homo</italic>—Nietzsche declares that<italic>The Birth of Tragedy</italic>, first published in 1872, was his “first revaluation of all values’ (TI Ancients 5). It is from this “soil”—that is, his study of the Greeks—that his “will,” his “<italic>abilities</italic>grow.” During this time Nietzsche had noted a series of reflections on<italic>The Birth</italic>in preparation for his “Revaluation of All Values,” demonstrating that the book and its themes were on his mind, and a number of letters of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>THE STATE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has often been said that if Nietzsche expresses various views about the state, these do not amount to anything systematic enough to be considered a political theory. Leiter, a prominent commentator on Nietzsche, has written that the “interpretative question” concerning Nietzsche’s political philosophy is whether “scattered remarks and parenthetical outbursts add up to<italic>systematic</italic>views on questions of philosophical significance.” His own view is that Nietzsche “has no political philosophy, in the conventional sense of a theory of the state and its legitimacy.” If he “occasionally expresses views about political matters[,] … read in context, they do not add</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>DEMOCRACY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A common refrain in the contemporary scholarship is that during his so-called middle period, commonly understood as spanning both books of<italic>Human, All Too Human</italic>(1878–80),<italic>Daybreak</italic>(1881), and the first four books of<italic>The Gay Science</italic>(1882), Nietzsche demonstrates a favorable disposition toward democracy.¹ Writers such as William Connolly, Owen, Paul Patton, and Schrift offer up<italic>The Wanderer and His Shadow</italic>293 (1880), titled “Ends and Means of Democracy,” as typifying Nietzsche’s allegedly prodemocratic sentiment.² There, Nietzsche explains that “democracy wants to create and guarantee as much<italic>independence</italic>as possible: independence of opinion, of mode of life, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>PHILOSOPHY AND POLITICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much has been written about Nietzsche’s notions of the will to power, eternal return, and overman, and I do not mean to offer a comprehensive interpretation of each one of them here; that would require another three separate studies in their own right.¹ Instead, I wish to concentrate on the ethical and political dimensions of these concepts, dwelling on the philosophical aspects solely to draw out these points. So for the will to power, I want to link that idea strongly to Nietzsche’s theory of the agon, especially how it is articulated in his early, unpublished essay “Homer’s Contest,” which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>REVALUATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With<italic>Thus Spoke Zarathustra</italic>, Nietzsche has in his grasp his three fundamental philosophical notions: the eternal return, will to power, and overman. The “thought of eternal return,” which Nietzsche considers to be the “basic idea of the work,” the “highest possible formula of affirmation,” came to him on a fateful day in August 1881. In Sils-Maria, “6,000 feet beyond people and time,” on his daily walk around Silvaplana Lake, Nietzsche “stopped near Surlei by a huge, pyramidal boulder”—the rock of the eternal return—where the thought came to him (EH Z 1). Projecting himself back a couple of months</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>GREAT POLITICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nietzsche’s productive life almost exactly spans Bismarck’s era. He was a medical orderly in the Franco-Prussian War (1870–71), but fell ill and only served for two months. Serving as a medical orderly was quite a common experience for many of the more “spiritual” types of Nietzsche’s generation. Most, however, were not as fortunate as he was to have actually survived, being decimated by various diseases contracted on the battlefield—illness already being a greater harvester of souls than war itself.¹ Nietzsche had previously volunteered as a cavalry officer in his local town, Naumburg, but after a self-described promising start,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>NIETZSCHE NOW</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A little over halfway through his “Can There Be a Nietzschean Politics?” Williams offers his answer to the question that formed the title of his piece. He explains that</p>
                     <p>one effect of Nietzsche’s work, as that of others, may be to make us question how far the criteria we think we have are actually expressed in anything that actually happens. What we have to do, rather, is to take up those elements of Nietzsche’s thought that seem to make most sense to us in terms of such things as our ethical understanding, our understanding of history, and the relations of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4chc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
