<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Phenomenology in Anthropology</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Sense of Perspective</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RAM</surname>
               <given-names>KALPANA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HOUSTON</surname>
               <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib3">
            <role>AFTERWORD BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JACKSON</surname>
               <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253017543</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253017802</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253017807</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz7f0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume explores what phenomenology adds to the enterprise of anthropology, drawing on and contributing to a burgeoning field of social science research inspired by the phenomenological tradition in philosophy. Essays by leading scholars ground their discussions of theory and method in richly detailed ethnographic case studies. The contributors broaden the application of phenomenology in anthropology beyond the areas in which it has been most influential-studies of sensory perception, emotion, bodiliness, and intersubjectivity-into new areas of inquiry such as martial arts, sports, dance, music, and political discourse.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="330"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology’s Methodological Invitation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ram</surname>
                           <given-names>Kalpana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Houston</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is phenomenology? And why should anthropologists, as well as students of history, psychology, education, or political economy be interested in it? Within philosophy, phenomenology is as diverse as its practitioners. Indeed, Moran (2000: 3) in an introduction to philosophical traditions of phenomenology finds it important to warn readers not to overstate the degree to which phenomenology “coheres into an agreed method, or accepts one theoretical outlook, or one set of philosophical theses about consciousness, knowledge, and the world.” Some of this diversity continues to be a feature of anthropological uses of phenomenology, as we show here. Yet we also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Moods and Method:</title>
                     <subtitle>Heidegger and Merleau-Ponty on Emotion and Understanding</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ram</surname>
                           <given-names>Kalpana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Phenomenology can assist anthropology in two specific ways. The first is in giving us a stronger way to frame objectivity as an aspiration for anthropological knowledge and for the social sciences more generally. The sec ond is in allowing us to give emotions a methodologically central role in enhancing objectivity.</p>
                     <p>My claims for phenomenology in this essay are limited to the work of two key exponents of the philosophical method, Heidegger and Merleau-Ponty. There are specific reasons why these two philosophers recommend themselves out of the wide range of philosophers who can claim to represent phenomenological methods. Both Heidegger and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Toward a Cultural Phenomenology of Body-World Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Csordas</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For years in my seminar on embodiment I have begun by juxtaposing the work of Merleau-Ponty, Bourdieu, and Foucault, based on the intuition that the work of these three thinkers taken together established the intellectual topology of embodiment as an “indeterminate methodological field defined by perceptual experience and mode of presence and engagement in the world” (Csordas 1994: 12). Writing against the grain of the occasional antipathy toward phenomenology articu lated by both Bourdieu and Foucault, I suggest that taken together their work helps to outline the structure of this methodological field for cultural phenomenology by defining complementary aspects of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sacred Suffering:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Phenomenological Anthropological Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Throop</surname>
                           <given-names>C. Jason</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In anthropology, the sacred has long been viewed as a unique register of human existence that is at times intimately associated with human suffering in its various forms and manifestations. Often enfolded within such orientations to the potential sacredness of human suffering are associated moral experiences and ethical concerns. Whether understood in the context of painful rituals of initiation, in the light of pain-induced transformations in consciousness, in the context of particular salvational orientations to loss, illness, human finitude, and death, or in the tendency to view suffering as a means of sacrificing one’s own desires for the benefit of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Being “Sita”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Physical Affects in the North Indian Dance of Kathak</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dalidowicz</surname>
                           <given-names>Monica</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explores the centrality of both kinesthetics and emotion to dance performance, and uses phenomenology to address the challenges that arise in learning the art of storytelling in the north Indian dance form of kathak. Kathak storytelling is danced, not spoken; the story is narrated through the use of gesture, facial expression, and bodily movements. The kathaka’s performance has the intended goal of the evocation of rasa, a concept from Indian aesthetic theory most often translated as mood or aesthetic enjoyment. Limitations to learning arise for both Indian diasporic dancers and foreigners in their attempt to portray abhinaya, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Beneath the Horizon:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Organic Body’s Role in Athletic Experience</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Downey</surname>
                           <given-names>Greg</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Conducting ethnographic research on sports, one encounters individuals who almost seem to transcend the boundaries of human capacity. Arguably, one of the thrills of athletic spectatorship is to witness skills and physical abilities honed to such an exceptional degree that an athlete’s performance beggars normal imagination, at once humbling us and at the same time thrilling. For an anthropological discussion of phenomenology, these kinds of people—agents operating at a level of efficacy beyond what is normally possible—offer an opportunity to interrogate the variation of human experience.</p>
                     <p>Specifically, I conducted ethnographic research on and apprenticed in capoeira, an acrobatic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Unmeasured Music and Silence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bedford</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay originates in an effort to comprehend some aspects of music in Muslim countries. I recall my first exposure—a kind of ambush—to procedures in music new to me. Up until 1971 the nation of Pakistan precariously consisted of two wings, West Pakistan and East Pakistan, soon to become Bangladesh. In October 1970, heavy floods, a cyclone, and then a tsunami battered the East wing, with enormous loss of life. In December the country was still in mourning. There were (as ever in Pakistan) all kinds of distractions and preoccupations—with livelihood, governance, rumor. Campaigning was underway for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Experiencing Self-Abstraction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Studio Production and Vocal Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fisher</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter draws on fieldwork in an Aboriginal Australian urban radio station in order to explore some experiential aspects of vocal cultural production and the forms of mediatized self-abstraction it entails. I focus on the ways that technical features of media production and the institutional life of media in contemporary Indigenous Australia come together to make perception available for problematization in the studio. At 4AAA, a large, Indigenous-run country music station with a broad and at times national audience, young Indigenous media trainees take on the task of representing Aboriginal Australia to itself, and their experience of learning to perform</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Being-in-the-Covenant:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on the Crisis of Historicism in North Malaita, Solomon Islands</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Timmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Jaap</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Biblical prophecy makes a major contribution to discourses and practices of nation and destiny in Solomon Islands. After discussing its broader context, this article investigates the power of Old Testament prophecies through analysis of the 2010 Queen’s Birthday speech of Solomon Islands’ governor-general, Sir Frank Kabui, entitled “Our connection with the Throne of England” (Kabui 2010), given to an audience of national and international officials in Honiara, the capital of Solomon Islands. Kabui, a To’abaita speaker from North Malaita, focuses on a British-Israelite theory that claims that Jacob’s pillar stone is kept in Scotland because the kings and queens of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Seared with Reality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology through Photography, in Nepal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Desjarlais</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS IS A STORY OF PHOTOGRAPHY, of the ways in which light and color work in the world, of how certain images get about in people’s lives or linger in their memories.</p>
                     <p>While traveling in the Yolmo region of north central Nepal in the summer of 2011, visiting with families I have known for some time now, I grew fond of a small, blue stool. The family I was staying with kept this bench, a foot and a half or so tall, toward the back of their household, close to a washroom and a work table. The sides and four</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Writing Affect, Love, and Desire into Ethnography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wynn</surname>
                           <given-names>L. L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The matter-of-fact irritation that Hammond expresses toward talking about “the sexual problem” is an apt analogy for contemporary anthropology’s approach to love. Sex, of course, has figured in anthropology’s public image ever since the earliest years of the discipline, with Margaret Mead’s<italic>Coming of Age in Samoa</italic>(1928), or Malinowski’s more explicit<italic>The Sexual Life of Savages</italic>(1929), replete with descriptions of exotic sexual positions. And in recent years, “desire” has become an increasingly popular catchphrase in anthropological writing (e.g., Rofel 2007). Yet for all the attention anthropologists pay to sex and desire,<italic>love</italic>was, until quite recently, curiously rare</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Senses of Magic:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anthropology, Art, and Christianity in the Vula’a Lifeworld</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Van Heekeren</surname>
                           <given-names>Deborah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have long admired Maurice Merleau-Ponty’s writing on Paul Cézanne because it provides insight into the artist’s practice beyond the general conventions of art history. The philosopher saw the painter as a paradigm example of the essence of perception.¹ As he writes, “Cézanne did not think he had to choose between feeling and thought, between order and chaos. He did not want to separate the stable things which we see and the shifting way in which they appear; he wanted to depict matter as it takes on form, the birth of order through spontaneous organization” (Merleau-Ponty 1964 [1945]: 13).</p>
                     <p>Drawing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Neither Things in Themselves nor Things for Us Only:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anthropology, Phenomenology, and Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Houston</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fiction is a genre that tells the stories of characters whose lives are parasitic upon yet identical to none of those 15 million people. Unlike macro-social science with its illuminating focus on political economic structures that mediate personal history and condition social experience, potentially making the stories of 15 million people variations on a theme, fiction gives attentive value to the particular, the quixotic, and the perverse. Characters’ lives and experiences are different from each other yet interlocked in strange and fateful ways. Nevertheless, in fiction, too, authors work with a presumption of resemblance, even as it is shown not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jackson</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the time that I wrote my introduction to<italic>Things as They Are</italic>in 1994, very few anthropologists drew methodically on phenomenology in their work, although many explored and exemplified, in their approaches to ethnographic research and writing, key phenomenological themes, such as embodiment, lived experience, inter subjectivity, the sensorium, space and place, and critical events. Today, as the present volume attests, a significant number of anthropologists are not only engaging creatively with phenomenology, but subjecting the philo sophical insights of Husserl, Heidegger, Merleau-Ponty, Arendt, Derrida, Levinas, and Sartre to empirical tests in a variety of contemporary settings, thereby revising,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz7f0.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
