<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS366.A88E27 1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American prose literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Authors, American</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Authors, French</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">French prose literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reference (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Autobiography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Touching the World</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reference in Autobiography</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>EAKIN</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL JOHN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>1992</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691068206</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691068208</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400820641</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1992</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7t2zt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Paul John Eakin's earlier work Fictions in Autobiography is a key text in autobiography studies. In it he proposed that the self that finds expression in autobiography is in fundamental ways a kind of fictive construct, a fiction articulated in a fiction. In this new book Eakin turns his attention to what he sees as the defining assumption of autobiography: that the story of the self does refer to a world of biographical and historical fact. Here he shows that people write autobiography not in some private realm of the autonomous self but rather in strenuous engagement with the pressures that life in culture entails. In so demonstrating, he offers fresh readings of autobiographies by Roland Barthes, Nathalie Sarraute, William Maxwell, Henry James, Ronald Fraser, Richard Rodriguez, Henry Adams, Patricia Hampl, John Updike, James McConkey, and Lillian Hellman. In the introduction Eakin makes a case for reopening the file on reference in autobiography, and in the first chapter he establishes the complexity of the referential aesthetic of the genre, the intricate interplay of fact and fiction in such texts. In subsequent chapters he explores some of the major contexts of reference in autobiography: the biographical, the social and cultural, the historical, and finally, underlying all the rest, the somatic and temporal dimensions of the lived experience of identity. In his discussion of contemporary theories of the self, Eakin draws especially on cultural anthropology and developmental psychology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="268"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DO I NOT know that,<italic>in the field of the subject</italic>,<italic>there is no referent</italic>?” (Barthes,<italic>Barthes</italic>56). This question reads like one of those conundrums in philosophy, prompting the reflective to ask, “Who is this ‘I,’ then?” As an instance of discourse in an autobiography, it seems doubly problematic, for autobiography is nothing if not a referential art, and the self or subject is its principal referent. This line and the book whose essence it has seemed to epitomize,<italic>Roland Barthes by Roland Barthes</italic>(1975), have come to serve as a touchstone for assessments of the state of contemporary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>The Referential Aesthetic of Autobiography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS INQUIRY into the referential aesthetic of autobiography attempts to answer a question that has haunted me for a long time: why should it make a difference to me that autobiographies are presumably based in biographical fact? This is really another way of asking why people read autobiographies, a question intimately linked to the question of why people write them. There seems to be no doubt that readers do read autobiographies differently from other kinds of texts, especially from works they take to be “fictions.” All who have studied the reading of autobiography agree that reference lies at the heart</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Henry James’s “Obscure Hurt”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Can Autobiography Serve Biography?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE SYSTEM of classification long in place in our libraries and bibliographies posits the kinship of autobiography and biography, ranging them both under the aegis of history as categories of the literature of reference, kinds of writing determined by their presumed basis in verifiable fact. Yet it is precisely with regard to this central identifying feature of reference to a world beyond the text that theory of autobiography today differs from the practice of biography. Thus it has become commonplace for students of autobiography to assert that the past, the ostensible primary reference of such texts, is a fiction. As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Self and Culture in Autobiography:</title>
                     <subtitle>Models of Identity and the Limits of Language</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN PLACING so high an estimate in chapter 2 on autobiography as an indispensable, authoritative source of biographical insight, I may have seemed to subscribe to one of the sustaining myths of autobiography, belief in the possibility of self-determination. What—or how much—does an autobiographer really mean when he or she speaks of writing a life? The drive in writing lives toward an identity between story and the personal history that is its subject—“this is no book, / Who touches this touches a man”—is reflected in the ambiguous uses of the word<italic>life</italic>, our common term for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Living in History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WARS may not loom large in the diminishing perspective of<italic>la longue durée</italic>espoused by the French historians of the<italic>Annales</italic>school, but they are routinely invoked to demarcate historical periods. For better or worse, they function as the most familiar symbols of our collective experience. Wartime propaganda promotes this identification between the individual and society: to enlist is to enlist in history, to participate in a global movement of some kind. The pressure to make such identifications often leads noncombatants to an even livelier grasp of the dynamic at work than that of the veterans themselves. As Henry James</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Autobiography and the Structures of Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN THE PRECEDING chapters I have been investigating various dimensions of the world of fact to which autobiographies characteristically refer: biographical (chapter 2), social and cultural (chapter 3), and historical (chapter 4). At the same time, following the paradox intrinsic to the very nature of autobiographical discourse, I have had occasion to emphasize the fictive dimension of autobiography, especially in my analyses of William Maxwell in chapter 1 and Patricia Hampl in chapter 4. There I presented the making of metaphor as a response to the otherwise unacceptable testimony of the facts of experience: the death of the mother, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t2zt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
