<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Jesus and the Cross</book-title>
         <subtitle>Necessity, Meaning, and Atonement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Laughlin</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174968</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227904381</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Peter Laughlin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf285"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>According to the Nicene Creed, Christ died for us and for our salvation. But while all Christians agree that Christ’s death and resurrection has saving significance, there is little unanimity in how and why that is the case. In fact, Christian history is littered with accounts of the redemptive value of Christ’s death, and new models and motifs are constantly being proposed, many of which now stand in stark contrast to earlier thought. How then should contemporary articulations of the importance of the death of Christ be judged? At the heart of this book is the contention that Christian reflection on the atonement is faithful inasmuch as it incorporates the intention that Jesus himself had for his death. In a wide-reaching study, the author draws from both classical scholarship and recent work on the historical Jesus to argue that not only did Jesus imbue his death with redemptive meaning but that such meaning should impact expressions of the saving significance of the cross.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="286"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ormerod</surname>
                           <given-names>Neil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I can still remember as a young theology student coming across the book<italic>The Aims of Jesus</italic>by biblical scholar, Ben Meyer. It was a heady time for theology students with the appearance of works by Hans Küng (<italic>On Being a Christian</italic>) and Edward Schillebeeckx (<italic>Jesus: An Experiment in Christology</italic>) both reflecting the impact of critical biblical scholarship on our understanding of Jesus. Within the excitement of these works, Meyer’s book stood out as something different, serious, scholarly, patient and measured in its conclusions. But one thing that really struck me was the implication of the title—Jesus had intentions,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cross Intentions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her introduction to<italic>Cross Examinations</italic>, Marit trelstad remarks that the meaning of the cross is dependent upon the context in which it is found.² One can hardly dispute her point: a burning cross on the lawn of an African American home in the mid twentieth-century does not have the same meaning as a cross mounted at the focal point of a contemporary African American church. Nor does the symbol of the cross have the same meaning when worn as a fashion accessory today as it once did in its crude representations on the shields of Constantine’s army. Like any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Divine Action and the Contingent Cross</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In philosophy, some things are understood to be because they could not be otherwise; whereas other things could have been otherwise but just so happen to be. These vague intuitions are of course codified into more technical terms: it is<italic>necessary</italic>that some things are so, merely<italic>contingent</italic>that other things are so. A key metaphysical question for philosophers then, is to ask what things are necessary and what things are contingent.² From a theological perspective this question is often framed in terms of the distinction between God and the created realm. In classical theism at least, only God is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Atonement, History, and Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why should the theologian care about what Jesus of Nazareth thought of his impending death? The question becomes more potent if we phrase is slightly differently: Would it actually make any difference to the Christian faith if its doctrine of the atonement had no basis in the intention of Jesus and was merely a symbolic invention of the early church? An uncritical reaction to this type of question is to answer with an indignant affirmation, since there is more than a little audacity in the suggestion that Jesus’ intention is irrelevant to the Christian proclamation of salvation. However, does the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Meaning of Jesus’ Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I argued for the viability of a theological engagement with history for the purpose of informing our theology of the atonement with the historical intention of Jesus of Nazareth. The task now is to discuss what can be known of the world of meaning that Jesus constituted for his death and then, in the next chapter, to bring these results to bear on our understanding of Christian atonement. Easy enough perhaps to state, a rather more difficult task in practice. Indeed, the endeavor threatens to become all-consuming; John Meier’s four-volume work is ample evidence of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>From Meaning to Motif</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter one it was argued that an atonement motif that wished to remain faithful to Christianity would demonstrate a degree of continuity with the meaning that Jesus of Nazareth constituted for his death. That contention still stands, and our analysis of the previous chapter has brought us to the point in which we must now discuss what kind of continuity is, in fact, to be expected. How should we incorporate the meaning that Jesus created for his death into our contemporary presentations? What kind of continuity are we looking for? Are our articulations to be constrained to the categories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What I have attempted to demonstrate herein is the ongoing potential for theology to articulate the meaning of Jesus’ death in a way that remains both faithful to the Christian tradition and yet sensitive to the needs of any given community. Hence, the task has not been to assert any one particular motif or understanding of the cross as<italic>the</italic>expression of faithful Christianity. Such an assertion (be it for any particular motif) needs to be rejected, not because individual motifs lack understanding or coherence but because the communication of the saving message of the cross must be received personally,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf285.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
