<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt24h2d1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Nowhere in the Middle Ages</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LOCHRIE</surname>
               <given-names>KARMA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780812248111</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812292855</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0812292855</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bmzkpm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Literary and cultural historians typically cite Thomas More's 1516<italic>Utopia</italic>as the source of both a genre and a concept. Karma Lochrie rejects this origin myth of utopianism along with the assumption that people in the Middle Ages were incapable of such thinking. In<italic>Nowhere in the Middle Ages</italic>, Lochrie reframes the terms of the discussion by revealing how utopian thought was, in fact, "somewhere" in the Middle Ages. In the process, she transforms conventional readings of More's<italic>Utopia</italic>and challenges the very practice of literary history today.</p>
         <p>Drawing on a range of contemporary scholarship on utopianism and a broad premodern archive, Lochrie charts variant utopian strains in medieval literature and philosophy that diverge from More's work and at the same time plot uncanny connections with it. Examining works such as Macrobius's fifth-century<italic>Commentary on the Dream of Scipio</italic>,<italic>Mandeville's Travels</italic>, and William Langland's<italic>Piers Plowman</italic>, she finds evidence of a number of utopian drives, including the rejection of European centrality, a desire for more egalitarian politics, and a rethinking of the division between animals and humans.<italic>Nowhere in the Middle Ages</italic>insists on the relevance and transformative potential of medieval utopias for More's work and positions the sixteenth-century text as one alternative in a broader historical phenomenon of utopian thinking. Tracing medieval utopianisms forward in literary history to reveal their influences on early modern and modern literature and philosophy, Lochrie demonstrates that looking backward, we might extend future horizons of utopian thinking.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>No Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2004 Lee Edelman published his controversial critique of the “reproductive futurism” that drives American politics, in his view. The title of his book,<italic>No Future</italic>, embraced a mantra of queer resistance to this futurism figured in the Child, and with it, all its attendant linear histories, narratives, and presentsustaining effects. The title of my introduction cites Edelman’s book not by way of advocating a rejection of the past, as one might expect of such a citation, but rather, of marking the problem this book seeks to remedy. Utopianism as we have come to know and theorize it since Thomas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Nowhere Earth:</title>
                     <subtitle>Macrobius’s Commentary on the Dream of Scipio and Kepler’s Somnium</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This story of utopia begins in reverie and cosmography. The last chapter of Cicero’s treatise,<italic>De republica</italic>, recounts Scipio Africanus’s dream that he is transported from his native Rome and earth to the heavenly spheres. From this interstellar perch he is transported again, only this time, affectively, by wonder at the grandeur of the heavenly spheres and shame at the comparative meanness of earth and diminution of Rome’s imperial reach. Scipio’s humility becomes the prerequisite for the text’s meditation on a world dedicated to justice and service of the commonwealth. Johannes Kepler, too, in his<italic>Somnium, sive astronomia lunae, Dream,</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Somewhere in the Middle Ages:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Land of Cokaygne, Then and Now</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Everyone living at the end of the Middle Ages had heard of Cokaygne at one time or another,” writes Herman Pleij about the Dutch tradition of the Land of Cokaygne.¹ If this is true, medieval Europeans would have known it by its different names, “Cokaygne” (British Isles), “Bengodi” (Italy), “Cucagna” (France) “Jauja” (Spain), “Schlaraffenland” (Germany), and “Luilekkerland” (the Netherlands). With respect to the utopian tradition, however, as A. L. Morton, the Marxist scholar of English utopianism, wrote, the Land of Cokaygne survives “as an almost secret tradition under the surface, while the mainstream of utopian thought passed through other channels.”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Provincializing Medieval Europe:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mandeville’s Cosmopolitan Utopianism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world of John Mandeville is far removed from the land of Cokaygne’s island paradise except insofar as it provides a narrative account of his travels to distant and fabulous places. Its utopianism, oddly enough, has more in common with the<italic>Dream of Scipio</italic>and Macrobius’s<italic>Commentary</italic>than it does with the<italic>Land of Cokaygne</italic>, because of its cosmopolitanism, which bears a kinship with that “geography of reduced significance” in the dream. Mandeville’s cosmopolitanism shares with Cicero’s text and Macrobius’s commentary the desire to dismantle the geopolitical “centrisms” of their times, if you will—of Rome in Scipio’s dream and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>“Something Is Missing”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Utopian Failure, Piers Plowman, and The Dream of John Ball</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fredric Jameson’s assertion that utopia’s deepest subject is its own inconceivability—its own failure of imagination, in a sense—baldly contravenes a positivist utopian tradition characterized precisely as the full-fledged blueprint of an alternative, more perfect society. Jameson’s negative utopianism embraces this aspect of failure, but it is important to understand that this failure is not simply the commonplace fatality of a compromised individual or authorial imagination. It is, instead, what Jameson calls “the systemic, cultural, and ideological closure of which we are all in one way or another prisoners.”¹ Despite Thomas More’s inspiration for, and association with, utopianism of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Reading Forward:</title>
                     <subtitle>More’s Utopia Unmoored</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Utopia, for all its playful allusiveness to “no-place,” comes from someplace, or rather from some places and not others. Like the chimerical centaur, it is a complex idea composed of an assemblage of other ideas and, at the same time, it engages with and responds to historical realities. But it is also entirely new, and the fact that Thomas More coined a self-canceling name for the island and the political idea associated with it tends to function somewhat like King Utopus’s moat, cordoning off that idea from the continent from which it might have come, either directly or indirectly. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkpm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
