<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Citizenship in Heaven and on Earth</book-title>
         <subtitle>Karl Barth's Ethics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Massmann</surname>
               <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451478143</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451478143</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401461</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401465</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155j39h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While Karl Barth is one of the most significant theologians of the twentieth century, his contribution to ethics is less well known and subject to controversy among interpreters. Barth combined his commitment to the church and its particular task in faith and theology with a concern for ethics and politics in wider society. By examining the historical development of Barth’s ethics, this study traces the vital influences and considerable shifts in Barth’s understanding of the ethical task, situating him within his political context. Alexander Massmann provides a comprehensive explication and assessment of the full scope of Barth’s ethics, from the first edition of the Romans commentary to the final volume of the Church Dogmatics. General questions of Barth’s methodology in ethics and case studies in applied ethics are both analyzed in their intricate connection to his dogmatic thought. The study highlights how an ethical approach emerged in which the freedom of the gospel allows for considerable openness to empirical insights from other disciplines. The author reevaluates Barth’s ethics in a constructive vision of the role of the church in the quest for a just society.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to get a sense of the multifaceted nature of Karl Barth’s ethics, one thing to do is to conjure up before the inner eye images that western societies commonly associate with a long interval of the twentieth century such as the years between 1932 and 1967. This was the time it took Barth to publish his multi-volume<italic>Church Dogmatics (CD),</italic>¹ which comprises both theology and ethics. Moreover, the various social, ecclesial and political contexts of his work are reflected in the fact that the critical edition of Barth’s works includes five volumes of individual smaller texts, written for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Development of Barth’s Ethics from the First Epistle to the Romans to Church Dogmatics I/1</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Barth’s early thought, two major aspects are of particular ethical significance. To begin with, Barth attributes great significance to the notion of sacrifice and repentance, which the literature on Barth has not sufficiently noted.¹ In order to keep this critical, negative dimension from dominating ethics, Barth eventually developed the actualistic concept of revelation.² This is the roadmap for this chapter’s discussion of Barth’s major works from the first edition of<italic>The Epistle to the Romans</italic>(henceforth<italic>Rom</italic>I) to<italic>CD</italic>I/1.</p>
                     <p>The emphasis on sacrifice in Barth’s early work is part of a charged issue in the political contexts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Ethics of the Doctrine of God in Church Dogmatics II/2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Judgment<italic>and</italic>grace, condemnation<italic>and</italic>beatification—these are always the implications of this event, of God’s command in its revelation. It encounters me thus, killing me and making me alive.”¹ As the ethics lectures highlighted especially the aspect of judgment in discussing God’s command, the notion that moral obligation is constituted by the gospel did not attain full force—on the contrary. Even to the extent that the gospel rather than the law ultimately determined the sinner’s status before God, Barth drew attention to this relation<italic>coram Deo</italic>rather than to the moral reality of an ethos, of actions and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Ethics of the Doctrine of Creation in Church Dogmatics III/4</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The discussion of<italic>CD</italic>II/2, chapter 8 detected a significant contradiction between ethical actualism on the one hand and the priority of the gospel over the law or the doctrine of election on the other. The ensuing volumes of<italic>CD</italic>III deal with the doctrine of creation. The subvolume discussing the ethical aspects of the doctrine of creation,<italic>CD</italic>III/4, discusses those ethical questions that arise with regard to God’s work as Creator. In part, Barth explicitly retains the actualistic concept of ethics, especially at the beginning. Yet at the same time, he engages in the discussion of empirical phenomena,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Foundations of Ethics in the Doctrine of Reconciliation in Church Dogmatics IV</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Barth’s doctrine of reconciliation in<italic>CD</italic>IV highlights the contingent event of reconciliation as the “centre of all Christian knowledge.” Barth announces that no other topic is of such crucial importance; all theology stands or falls with the fundamental decisions made at this point: “To fail here is to fail everywhere. To be on the right track here makes it impossible to be completely mistaken in the whole.”¹ This implies that Barth’s theological interpretation of the reconciliation in Christ is fundamental also for his ethics. It will turn out, however, that matters are not as simple as Barth suggests when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Perspectives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Responsibility and Faith in the Triune God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After discussing Barth’s the ethical dimension of Barth’s works from<italic>Rom</italic>I to<italic>CD</italic>IV, the task of this chapter is to look back, recall some of the main results, and feed them into a constructive effort to learn from Barth’s ethical reflections for today’s Christian ethics.</p>
                     <p>The historico-genealogical and systematic reconstruction of Barth’s concept of gospel and law has been a continuing theme in this discussion. Referencing “GL” and<italic>CD</italic>II/2, chapter 8, Barth himself called it “the basic substance” of<italic>CD</italic>.¹ An important question pursued in the current interpretation was if this subordination of the law is authoritarian,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>483</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j39h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>534</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
