<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kw2849</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>How to Do Comparative Theology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CLOONEY</surname>
               <given-names>FRANCIS X.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VON STOSCH</surname>
               <given-names>KLAUS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITORS</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823278404</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823278435</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823278433</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr5zg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For a generation and more, the contribution of Christian theology to interreligious understanding has been a subject of debate. Some think of theological perspectives are of themselves inherently too narrow to support interreligious learning, and argue for an approach that is neutral or, on a more popular level, grounded simply open-minded direct experience. In response, comparative theology argues that theology, as faith seeking understanding, offers a vital perspective and a way of advancing interreligious dialogue, aided rather than hindered by commitments; theological perspectives can both complement and step beyond the study of religions by methods detached and merely neutral. Thus comparative theology has been successful in persuading many that interreligious learning from one faith perspective to another is both possible and worthwhile, and so the work of comparative theology has become more recognized and established globally. With this success there has come to the fore new challenges regarding method: How does one do comparative theological work in a way that is theologically grounded, genuinely open to learning from the other, sophisticated in pursuing comparisons, and fruitful on both the academic and practical levels?</p>
         <p>How To Do Comparative Theology therefore contributes to the maturation of method in the field of comparative theological studies, learning across religious borders, by bringing together essays drawing on different Christian traditions of learning, Judaism and Islam, Hinduism and Buddhism, the wisdom of senior scholars, and also insights from a younger generation of scholars who have studied theology and religion in new ways, and are more attuned to the language of the "spiritual but not religious." The essays in this volume show great diversity in method, and also-over and again and from many angles-coherence in intent, a commitment to one learning from the other, and a confidence that one's home tradition benefits from fair and unhampered learning from other and very different spiritual and religious traditions. It therefore shows the diversity and coherence of comparative theology as an emerging discipline today.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clooney</surname>
                           <given-names>Francis X.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Stosch</surname>
                           <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fifteen essays collected in<italic>How to Do Comparative Theology</italic>are the fruits of an August 2014 conference in Paderborn, Germany, which itself was part of a larger conversation involving senior and junior scholars in the field over the five years before that. The conference brought together scholars in the field of comparative theology in the United States and Eu rope to share their work in this emerging field, and to reflect together on the nature and best methods current today by listening to how each of us actually does it.</p>
                     <p>Comparative theology is, after all, a challenging endeavor: From</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Choice in Comparative Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cornille</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The discipline of comparative theology is steadily growing and diversifying. While it is often seen as originating within Christian, and predominantly Roman Catholic, theological circles, it is increasingly practiced by Christians of other denominations and by other religious traditions. And comparative theologians of any one tradition are presented with a seemingly endless possibility of choice in terms of which tradition, which text, or which aspect of that tradition to engage in comparative work. Once other religions are recognized as possible resources for constructive religious reflection and insight, there is no limit to where such truth or insight might manifest itself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Reflecting on Approaches to Jesus in the Qur’ān from the Perspective of Comparative Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Stosch</surname>
                           <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first issue to which comparative theology must respond when its methodology is questioned is choosing a topic for discussion. As religions offer such great variety of starting points for discussion, these points should not be chosen only according to the preference of the researcher or institution, if comparative theology wants to show its relevance to the Church and society. In my opinion, theology, like any other science, should try to solve problems and to respond to contemporary issues. Therefore, I see three legitimate starting points for comparative theology: problems of society, problems of theology, and problems that arise out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Moment of Truth:</title>
                     <subtitle>COMPARATIVE AND DOGMATIC THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Langenfeld</surname>
                           <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In European theological discourse, the various projects of comparative theology often are confronted with two reproaches: first, that they are not distinguishable from a pluralistic theology of religions,¹ and second, that they are not distinguishable from some types of religious studies.² The interesting point is that both assertions are traceable to the same fundamental critique, even if they obviously diverge in its specific interpretation. This criticism addresses the apparent relativization of Christology as the dogmatic normative core of all Christian theology. Confronting this objection against the comparative projects, in the first part of the paper I will address comparative and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Rhetorics of Theological One-Upsmanship in Christianity and Buddhism:</title>
                     <subtitle>ATHANASIUS’S POLEMIC AGAINST THE ARIANS AND VASUBANDHU’S REFUTATION OF PUDGALAVĀDA BUDDHISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nicholson</surname>
                           <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The name of our discipline contains a methodologically significant ambiguity. As David Tracy remarked a number of years ago in his encyclopedia article on “Comparative Theology,” “theology” in this designation can refer either to the object or the subject of the activity of comparison.¹ To the extent that theology forms the<italic>object</italic>of comparison, Comparative Theology represents a subfield or a specific focus within Comparative Religion or the History of Religions (for my present purposes, I consider these two designations to be roughly equivalent). That is, Comparative Theology in this sense denotes the study of the intellectual or doctrinal dimension</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“An Interpreter and Not a Judge”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Insights into a Christian-Islamic Comparative Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Takács</surname>
                           <given-names>Axel Marc Oaks</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dialogue between Muslims and Christians has a long, rich, and complex history. Long, in that the first extant<italic>theological</italic>encounter between a Christian and a Muslim occurred over 1,200 years ago between Mar Timothy I (728–823), the Catholicos of the Church of the East at the time, and the ruling caliph, al-Mahdi (who ruled from 775–785); this excludes any sort of early exchanges that may have occurred among Muhammad, his companions, and Christian tribes in the Arabian peninsula, possible interreligious engagement among Christian ascetics and proto-ṣūfī’s, and statements in the Qur’ān that explicitly address Christian theology, such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>On Some Suspicions Regarding Comparative Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Willis</surname>
                           <given-names>Glenn R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If theological comparisons do not connect themselves to the concerns of actual religious communities, it is not clear how comparison can be theological at all, given that theologies must implicate the writer in some community of practice. This essay addresses several quiet but sustained suspicions about theological comparison as a religiously relevant project. There seems little reason to deny that comparisons are often subject to an “ingrained resistance,”¹ particularly among theologians.² In what follows, I first deepen several fundamental critiques of comparison, emphasizing that theologies must offer more than virtuoso interreligious vision, before suggesting some ways in which comparison can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Embodiment, Anthropology, and Comparison:</title>
                     <subtitle>THINKING-FEELING WITH NON-DUAL SAIVISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roberts</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle Voss</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Imagine the constructive theologian as a beachcomber. She attentively picks her way through the landscape of the Christian theological heritage, salvaging treasures that sparkle unexpectedly in the sun of the contemporary moment. From this or that angle, a dusty practice or neglected doctrine takes on new beauty. The theologian’s tools of detection sound the alert: There is something relevant here, something useful, something true! The detectors include sensors for scriptural soundness, doctrinal fidelity, rational coherence, and con temporary resonance. Many different tools can be used to look and to dig.</p>
                     <p>Comparison belongs to the toolkit of constructive theology, although it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Comparative Theology After the Shoah:</title>
                     <subtitle>RISKS, PIVOTS, AND OPPORTUNITIES OF COMPARING TRADITIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moyaert</surname>
                           <given-names>Marianne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Shoah, insofar as it forms the climax of a longstanding tradition of anti-Jewish discrimination, contains one of the most important inducements for the revolutionary change in the Church’s attitude vis-à-vis Israel. After the Shoah, the Second Vatican Council (1962–65), and in particular the promulgation of the document<italic>Nostra Aetate</italic>, brought about a turning point in Jewish-Christian relationships. Later such documents as the<italic>Guidelines</italic>(1974),<italic>Notes</italic>(1985),<italic>We Remember</italic>(1998), and<italic>The Jewish People and their Sacred Scriptures in the Christian Bible</italic>(2001), together with various dialogical initiatives, affirmed the Church’s determination to break away from the “teaching of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Using Comparative Insights in Developing Kalām:</title>
                     <subtitle>A PERSONAL REFLECTION ON BEING TRAINED IN COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tatari</surname>
                           <given-names>Muna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I started working on my dissertation in Paderborn in 2010, I was already quite familiar with Islamic theology.¹ I had graduated University with a degree in Islamic studies, a subject quite separate and apart from Islamic theology. I was also a visiting student at an Islamic theological faculty in Jordan for three semesters, and finally studied Islamic theology at a private institute in Hamburg for six semesters. From 1996 to 2010, I worked as a freelance facilitator in the field of inter-religious dialogue. I regularly trained teachers and vicars and co-developed teaching materials with groups of Muslims, Christians, Buddhists,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Difficult Remainders:</title>
                     <subtitle>SEEKING COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY’S REALLY DIFFICULT OTHER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clooney</surname>
                           <given-names>Francis X.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Christian comparative theological engagement with other faith traditions is most often driven by attention to select themes, images, and practices already somewhat familiar, even if inexactly, in Christian tradition. This approach makes sense and is fruitful. The preference for the familiar risks an evasion of the more difficult realm of the unfamiliar, and reducing the great texts of other traditions to compendia of ideas available for selective consideration as desired. Comparisons are often asymmetrical, too. Christian comparativists at their best work with a rich sense of the completeness of Christian faith, and of the organic coherence of Christian doctrine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Sagi Nahor—Enough Light:</title>
                     <subtitle>DIALECTIC TENSION BETWEEN LUMINESCENT RESONANCE AND BLIND ASSUMPTION IN COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gordon-Guedalia</surname>
                           <given-names>Shoshana Razel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay, titled, “<italic>Sagi Nahor</italic>¹—Enough Light: Dialectic Tension Between Luminescent Resonance² and Blind Assumption in Comparative Theology,” engages in comparative theological examination of two ritual-legal systems,<italic>Mīmāṃsaka</italic>and<italic>Rabbinic</italic>, which,<italic>prima facie</italic>, share “measures” of hermeneutic reasoning—tools for culling ritual law from respective Urtext, each expanding into vast commentarial corpora, each yielding distillation into terse legal codes in the medieval period. Proper comparison yields illumination, while sheer conflation blinds. Even as we study test cases, seeking to delineate each system-specific matrix with regards to ritual efficacy and agency, concerns loom: Can one suspend current sensibilities when exploring cosmologies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Methodological Considerations on the Role of Experience in Comparative Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Donnell</surname>
                           <given-names>Emma</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The still relatively new field of comparative theology has made great strides in the past few decades, growing into an internationally recognized field with departments in major universities. Throughout this growth, comparative theology has engaged a wide range of religious traditions and has addressed a similarly diverse range of topics within religious thought and practice. Yet, reflecting a wider phenomenon in theology more broadly defined, comparative theology has consistently remained a largely textual venture, based in the comparative reading of religious texts.</p>
                     <p>It is not a stretch to argue that comparative theology has defined itself as a practice of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Incarnational Speech:</title>
                     <subtitle>COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY AS LEARNING TO HEAR AND PREACH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bannon</surname>
                           <given-names>Brad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How—and why—does one do comparative theology? As the essays in this volume demonstrate, there are as many answers to these questions as there are comparative theologians. One’s method and purpose even tends to vary from one project to the next.¹ In part, this is because theology is often driven by questions. Differing questions require differing methods of inquiry. Because comparative theologians delve deeply into more than one religious tradition, we are often compelled by more than one question at a time. Because this anthology addresses<italic>how to do comparative theology</italic>, I begin by reflecting on how I formulate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Living Interreligiously:</title>
                     <subtitle>ON THE “PASTORAL STYLE” OF COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barnes</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Comparative Theology commends an imaginative entry into another religious world. In so doing it raises some difficult questions about what it means to live and act “interreligiously.” How to recognize continuities, acknowledge discontinuities, build creative analogies, without getting stuck into some sort of self-serving colonizing of the other? How to ensure that the complex business of mediating across religious borders does not ignore the demands of truth—and justice? How to keep alive the discipline of obedience that arises from the hearing of the Word while yet taking seriously the myriad words that are inseparable from life in a thoroughly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Theologizing for the Yoga Community?</title>
                     <subtitle>COMMITMENT AND HYBRIDITY IN COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corigliano</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>324</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Comparative theology is a transformative academic pursuit. To name but a few examples, James Fredericks, Paul Knitter, Catherine Cornille, and Francis X. Clooney all argue in different ways that comparative theology is a study that begins with a theologian who is rooted in a particular faith tradition. In this way, the learning about and from another tradition, as Knitter describes, is an act of passing over, which necessarily entails a passing back, or return to one’s home tradition.¹</p>
                     <p>This essay questions the idea that an explicit faith commitment is a necessary criterion for comparative theology. Conversely, I propose that for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5zg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
