<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD161.K53 1986</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Piaget, Jean, 1896–1980</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in theory of knowledge</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge, Theory of</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Piaget's Theory of Knowledge</book-title>
         <subtitle>Genetic Epistemology and Scientific Reason</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KITCHENER</surname>
               <given-names>RICHARD F.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>1986</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300035797</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237863</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1986</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3sbd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Best known as a child psychologist, Jean Piaget considered himself primarily an epistemologist who was engaged in empirical research on the development of knowledge. In this book, philosopher and psychologist Richard F. Kitchener provides the first comprehensive study in English of Piaget's genetic epistemology, or his theory of knowledge. Drawing largely on a careful perusal of Piaget's untranslated works, Kitchener presents little-known aspects of Piaget's thought and argues that, in fact, Piagest has been misunderstood and was completely justified in his claim to be an epistemologist rather than a psychologist.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="230"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If one were to name the most significant psychologists of the twentieth century, Sigmund Freud would surely head the list. But who would come after him in importance? Opinions would probably differ here, with serious consideration begin given to B. F. Skinner and Ivan Pavlov. But Jean Piaget would also most assuredly be mentioned. By universal consensus Piaget is counted as one of the two or three most significant figures in twentieth-century psychology. In fact, he is generally taken to be the most significant child or developmental psychologist in the history of psychology. He has studied scores of children busily</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Piaget’s Theory of Cognitive Development</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although Piaget is a genetic epistemologist, he is more widely known for his theory of cognitive development—his epistemological psychological theory concerning the development of epistemic cognition in the individual. This theory is often taken to be a pure psychological theory about child development, a scientific theory of psychological development that makes factual claims about what happens in the course of development, claims backed to some degree by scientific evidence.</p>
                     <p>Although this “empirical” interpretation of Piaget’s theory of psychological development is partially correct-for example, his theory purports to be scientific-it is also misleading in several important respects. This is largely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Piaget’s Theory of Knowledge:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Overview</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In discussing Piaget’s epistemology, a very natural starting point is the question, what is Piaget’s basic epistemological outlook, and how does it differ from traditional philosophical epistemology? Philosophers from the Greeks-to the twentieth century have advanced numerous theories of knowledge—for example, that knowledge comes from the senses and is reducible to a collection of sense impressions, or that knowledge comes from the creative activity of the rational mind. Traditionally they have also discussed questions of a more abstract, reflective kind: What problems should epistemology investigate? What are the limits of our knowledge? What method(s) should one employ in epistemology?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Piaget’s Epistemological Constructivism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Piaget’s theory of knowledge is fundamentally concerned with the question, how (developmentally) is a certain epistemic fact or property possible? How is it possible, for example, for the necessary truths contained in logic and mathematics to result from the contingent ones the child first encounters?¹ How is it possible for the epistemic objectivity of adulthood to develop from the subjectivity and egocentrism of childhood? How is it possible for objective social structures, containing properties ofjustice, fairness, and reciprocity, to develop from individual behavior patterns lacking these features? How is it possible for scientific knowledge to have developed from earlier modes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Piaget’s Theory of Epistemology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We know things, Piaget claims, because we construct epistemic structures, which function as necessary conditions for knowledge. In this process our epistemic structures become progressively more adequate. This constructivism, whatever conceptual flaws it may have, lies at the heart of Piaget’s theory of knowledge. An attempt to provide such a theory of knowledge we labelled “epistemology proper” or “normative epistemology.” Piaget’s constructivism, I suggested, is a theory about how we actually know. Constructivism can be viewed as an answer to the earlier (transcendental) question; how is it possible (developmentally) for us to have the knowledge we have? Piaget answers that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Nature and Scope of Genetic Epistemology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most controversial aspects of Piaget’s genetic epistemology concerns the claim that epistemology can and must be investigated empirically by using appropriate scientific methods coupled with conceptual theorizing. Although such an empirical epistemology will employ the standard scientific method, it will focus on the development of knowledge, hence it will employ certain auxiliary methods, notably the genetic method, which attempts to understand the development of knowledge.</p>
                     <p>Definition of Genetic Epistemology</p>
                     <p>Epistemology, according to Piaget, must take a dynamic turn and become a genetic epistemology. At least three different (but overlapping) characterizations of genetic genetic epistemology can be found</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Genetic Epistemology &amp; Historicist Philosophy of Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Genetic epistemology, as I have argued, is not some kind of cleverly disguised genetic psychology. It is precisely what its name indicates-an epistemology oriented towards the genesis and development of knowledge. But as we have seen, it has a complex domain, including the growth of knowledge both in the individual person and in the history of science. As such, it is not merely an epistemology but also a philosophy of science. For, after all, if the philosophy of science is taken to be the epistemology of science-an assumption widely accepted-and if genetic epistemology is concerned with the epistemology of scientific</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sbd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
