<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.W3F38 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War and society</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>War at a Distance</book-title>
         <subtitle>Romanticism and the Making of Modern Wartime</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Favret</surname>
               <given-names>Mary A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691144078</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691144079</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400831555</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7t6rs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What does it mean to live during wartime away from the battle zone? What is it like for citizens to go about daily routines while their country sends soldiers to kill and be killed across the globe? Timely and thought-provoking,<italic>War at a Distance</italic>considers how those left on the home front register wars and wartime in their everyday lives, particularly when military conflict remains removed from immediate perception, available only through media forms. Looking back over two centuries, Mary Favret locates the origins of modern wartime in the Napoleonic era and describes how global military operations affected the British populace, as the nation's army and navy waged battles far from home for decades. She reveals that the literature and art produced in Britain during the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries obsessively cultivated means for feeling as much as understanding such wars, and established forms still relevant today.</p>
         <p>Favret examines wartime literature and art as varied as meditations on the<italic>Iliad</italic>, the history of meteorology, landscape painting in India, and popular poetry in newspapers and periodicals; she locates the embedded sense of war and dislocation in works ranging from Austen, Coleridge, and Wordsworth to Woolf, Stevens, and Sebald; and she contemplates how literature provides the public with methods for responding to violent calamities happening elsewhere. Bringing to light Romanticism's legacy in reflections on modern warfare, this book shows that war's absent presence affects home in deep and irrevocable ways.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PRELUDE</title>
                     <subtitle>A Winter’s Evening</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a winter’s evening, a man looks into the fireplace and contemplates a world at war.</p>
                     <p>It is February of 2003; the poet has just turned off the evening news. The buildup to the U.S.-led invasion of Iraq goes without saying. Sleet is “slashing” outside on this “bitter evening,” while C. K. Williams’s attention wanders to the hearth.¹ There he sees a plastic coffee cup teetering “on a log for a strangely long time, / as though uncertain what to do” (7–8). The hesitation and subsequent collapse of this strange “creaturely” thing calls forth a series of meditations on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Sense of War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book considers how war becomes part of the barely registered substance of our everyday, an experience inextricable from sitting at home on an evening, recalling absent friends, staring at a fire, gazing out a window. As it looks back over two centuries,<italic>War at a Distance</italic>tells how military conflict on a global scale looked and felt to a population whose armies and navies waged war for decades, but always at a distance. For those at home, the task was to find sentient ground for what often appeared a free-floating, impersonal military operation, removed from their immediate sensory perception.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Telling Time in War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter extends the thought that the experience of war at a distance, of a mediated war, is fundamentally dislocating, and that such dislocation expresses itself most frequently and forcefully through our sense of the movement (or stasis) of time, through temporalities. Thus the wartime poems set on a winter’s evening, considered in the prelude, elaborate the simplest markers of time (winter, evening) into channels of memory and prophecy, avenues of recursivity and nodes of stillness. Wartime in modernity refers not to a single temporal mode—<italic>the</italic>time of war. Rather it houses many temporalities, each one, as we will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTERLUDE</title>
                     <subtitle>Still Winter Falls</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Wartime summons winter. It would perhaps be best for this interlude to be read as it was written—at the darkest time of the year, in weather able to chill the blood, numb the body, and halt the movement of clocks. Were it presently December in London, or William Cowper’s Olney, the sun would not rise before 8:00 a.m.; it would illuminate the sky for fewer than eight hours. Imagine the length of the cold night before electricity. Imagine your dependence on the fire you built, before which you now sit, reading about a world at war. What makes you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>War in the Air</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poets of the late eighteenth century ask us to see in the snows of winter a history of warfare, with its anesthetizing threat to both history and writing. They conjure prospect poems where the view looks out upon total annihilation. Yet in their mining of the literary tradition and the resources of figuration, they disrupt that prospect, insisting that beneath and within the snow we recognize something still surviving. So much is written into the snow that these poems suggest the value of, indeed the need for a wartime rereading of that most romantic trope, the weather. To the precise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Everyday War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Perhaps, these lyric poems propose, the weather can serve as a forceful wartime medium, broadcasting the voices or at least the sounds of distant violence, carrying in its currents an audible, palpable sense of suffering elsewhere. This was one way war at a distance could invade—affectively and effectively—the home front. An air-borne sense of suffering, however, escaped like involuntary sighs or moans from a growing, more rationalized understanding of global weather and global war. The new meteorology aimed to regularize violent extremes into an intelligible system, less felt than observed, and predicated on a predictable and continuous nature.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTERLUDE</title>
                     <subtitle>A Brief History of the Meaning of War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understanding war. This book has been asking what war meant to a population whose experience and memory were shaped by warfare, a population whose armies and navies were almost constantly engaged in military conflict across the globe, though rarely, if ever, on home ground. It has asked how war was understood by those who were, at least as subjects of a sovereign state, often at war, though never actually in battle. But it has not yet asked what it meant to make war an object of understanding.</p>
                     <p>What if war is and was meaningless? A trip to the<italic>Oxford English</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Viewing War at a Distance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Henri Lefebvre looks at the everyday and finds there a truth “waiting for us, besieging us on all sides”; when Sigmund Freud imagines the frail organism “suspended in the middle of an external world” that attacks it with “stimuli,” they demonstrate the figurative power of the siege well into the twentieth century.¹ The siege concentrates warfare, bringing it home in the most immediate and violent way. The siege marks therefore the end of war at a distance. It is thus appropriate to conclude with a meditation on sieges, or at least on the representational work sieges may perform. Even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CODA</title>
                     <subtitle>Undone</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book began with the problem of modern wartime, that is, the problem of coordinating an awareness of violence elsewhere with everyday movements here, at a distance from the fighting. The book ends with the problem of cosmopolitanism. Another way of characterizing this trajectory would be to say it looks from the familiar scene at hearth and home to the more foreign scene of a suspension bridge set in a distant land—then looks back again. Holding together these two scenes is difficult: in one you might sit as a violent world comes to you; in the other you might</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7t6rs.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
