<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E185.615 .M3537 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African Americans</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Violence against</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African Americans</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Violence against</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bereavement</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Grief</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Race relations</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mourning in America</book-title>
         <subtitle>Race and the Politics of Loss</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McIvor</surname>
               <given-names>David W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781501704956</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781501706189</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ITHACA; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cornell University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctt1d2dmt4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Recent years have brought public mourning to the heart of American politics, as exemplified by the spread and power of the Black Lives Matter movement, which has gained force through its identification of pervasive social injustices with individual losses. The deaths of Sandra Bland, Michael Brown, Freddie Gray, Trayvon Martin, Tamir Rice, Walter Scott, and so many others have brought private grief into the public sphere. The rhetoric and iconography of mourning has been noteworthy in Black Lives Matter protests, but David W. McIvor believes that we have paid too little attention to the nature of social mourning-its relationship to private grief, its practices, and its pathologies and democratic possibilities.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Mourning in America</italic>, McIvor addresses significant and urgent questions about how citizens can mourn traumatic events and enduring injustices in their communities. McIvor offers a framework for analyzing the politics of mourning, drawing from psychoanalysis, Greek tragedy, and scholarly discourses on truth and reconciliation.<italic>Mourning in America</italic>connects these literatures to ongoing activism surrounding racial injustice, and it contextualizes Black Lives Matter in the broader politics of grief and recognition. McIvor also examines recent, grassroots-organized truth and reconciliation processes such as the Greensboro Truth and Reconciliation Commission (2004-2006), which provided a public examination of the Greensboro Massacre of 1979-a deadly incident involving local members of the Communist Workers Party and the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface:</title>
                     <subtitle>MOURNING IN AMERICA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE POLITICS OF MOURNING IN AMERICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Greensboro Massacre to the Greensboro Truth and Reconciliation Commission</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the late morning on Saturday, November 3, 1979, a caravan of Ku Klux Klansmen steered its way through the streets of Greensboro, North Carolina. The thirty-five individuals packed into nine automobiles were on their way to disrupt a scheduled rally in a black public-housing neighborhood that had been planned by the Communist Workers Party (CWP), which had been organizing mill and cafeteria workers along with the Greensboro Association for Poor People (GAPP). Ostensibly, this disruption was to be limited to throwing eggs and making speeches, but the pistols and shotguns packed into the Klansmen’s vehicles bespoke other possibilities. As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>TO JOIN IN HATE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Antigone and the Agonistic Politics of Mourning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In scanning the history of mourning’s public expression and political appropriations, we see that the politics of mourning are both mobile—they move across the political spectrum and across cultural contexts—and historically variable.¹ Nevertheless, certain images and ideas are so frequently associated with the political expression of mourning that they have come to dominate the interpretive field. This field, in effect, is prepopulated by figures that shape expectations of what the politics of mourning looks like, the kinds of actions it involves, and the affective registers through which it is filtered. In this chapter and chapter 3, I explore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE IMAGINARY CITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Consensual Mourning form Pericles to John Rawls</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Antigone provides the figure for a style of mourning politics in which claims for recognition disrupt the disavowals and silences of the status quo. Unruly, mournful voices mobilize on the basis of shared grief in order to challenge the norms that have made their suffering unrecognizable or their lives impossible. Yet these insistent mourning voices circulate within, attempt to influence, and implicitly acknowledge a broader struggle of narration over the meaning of historical suffering and enduring traumas.¹ Here the most prominent voices are often the official discourses and rituals that seek to memorialize the past in ways that reinforce common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>“THE IS TROUBLE HERE. THERE IS MORE TO COME”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Greek Tragedy and the Work of Mourning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I begin to sketch out in more detail the constitutive aspects of what I am calling the democratic work of mourning. The democratic work of mourning involves the public spaces and practices by which the traumas of collective life are publicly worked through in ways that enliven social struggles for recognition while mitigating denial, disavowal, and distrust. In articulating this concept, I lean heavily on the work of object relations psychoanalysis and, in particular, the approach to mourning found in Melanie Klein and D. W. Winnicott. Klein’s concepts of the depressive position and the good object, supplemented</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>A SPLINTERING AND SHATTERING ACTIVITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Truth, Reconciliation, Mourning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 4, I argued that the Greek tragic festival marked a psychopolitical innovation in Athens of the fifth century BCE. The Great Dionysia provided a space within which the members of the polis could work through public traumas and intense anxieties by facing down the ambivalence of self and other and by advancing simultaneous moral and tragic narratives about the political project in which they were engaged—including an awareness of this project’s fragility, contingency, contestability, and susceptibility to radical rupture. The Great Dionysia was a Kleinian good object, shaped by psychosocial defenses such as idealization and omnipotence that offered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>BLACK LIVES MATTER AND THE DEMOCRATIC WORK OF MOURNING</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If Freddie Gray spent any time during his twenty-five years imagining his own funeral, it seems unlikely that he could have predicted the hours-long event that took place on April 27, 2015, at the New Shiloh Baptist Church in West Baltimore. Thousands of mourners were in attendance, including a U.S. cabinet secretary, a member of the U.S. House of Representatives, and multiple civil rights movement icons—not to mention a dozen or so television crews and even more newspaper and magazine journalists. The funeral took place just over a week after Gray’s death as a result of injuries sustained while</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dmt4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
