<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbsk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PM218.B67 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Languages</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Translating</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indian literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">North America</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Translations into English</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Born in the Blood</book-title>
         <subtitle>On Native American Translation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited and with an introduction by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Swann</surname>
               <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803267596</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803235410</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803235410</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1df4gp3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since Europeans first encountered Native Americans, problems relating to language and text translation have been an issue. Translators needed to create the tools for translation, such as dictionaries, still a difficult undertaking today. Although the fact that many Native languages do not share even the same structures or classes of words as European languages has always made translation difficult, translating cultural values and perceptions into the idiom of another culture renders the process even more difficult.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Born in the Blood</italic>, noted translator and writer Brian Swann gathers some of the foremost scholars in the field of Native American translation to address the many and varied problems and concerns surrounding the process of translating Native American languages and texts. The essays in this collection address such important questions as, what should be translated? how should it be translated? who should do translation? and even, should the translation of Native literature be done at all? This volume also includes translations of songs and stories.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="488"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swann</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Translating Native American languages is a very different process from translating European languages. For one thing, the translation of European languages does not usually present real physical and spiritual dangers.¹ For another, there are the complexities of collaboration between non-Native academics and Native American culture-bearers, formerly “informants.” Moreover, translators have to decide how to transform oral expression into a written form, and in addition they may have to produce their own grammars and dictionaries, as part of what Julie Brittain and Marguerite MacKenzie in this volume term “a unique constellation of factors.” This constellation can also include “the interaction of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Should Translation Work Take Place?</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethical Questions Concerning the Translation of First Nations Languages</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dyck</surname>
                           <given-names>Carrie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many First Nations communities, translation represents a “sea change”: while all languages are passed on through word of mouth, only a subset of languages have writing systems, and even fewer are regularly translated. Many First Nations languages (and many other languages) are primarily oral; writing and translation are recent additions. Writing, literacy, and translation work potentially leads to great changes in a language community, and their introduction raises a host of ethical questions.</p>
                     <p>This chapter outlines the potential benefits and disadvantages of translating Cayuga, an Iroquoian language. It also describes the context of translation: the people who speak Cayuga,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Reading a Dictionary:</title>
                     <subtitle>How Passamaquoddy Language Translates Concepts of Physical and Social Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leavitt</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I sat down to proofread the thousands of entries in<italic>A Passamaquoddy-Maliseet Dictionary</italic>¹ (Francis and Leavitt 2008), I expected to endure a long, tedious chore, compensated only by seeing the broad scope of the words David A. Francis and I, working with dozens of Passamaquoddy and Maliseet contributors, had compiled. But an unexpected pleasure awaited. In the words themselves and the example sentences, the Passamaquoddy world of the past hundred years came welling up from the pages. I could sense what speakers mean when they say that the language is “a unique mindset, in which I feel completely at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Translating Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Dialogue on Hopi Experiences of the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Colwell-Chanthaphonh</surname>
                           <given-names>Chip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Koyiyumptewa</surname>
                           <given-names>Stewart B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter takes as its focus the question of how Hopi feelings, experiences, and knowledge of the past are, or can be, translated. Our motivation for this chapter grew out of our work together and conversations about the first author’s own (non-Pueblo) experiences at ancient sites compared to how the second author perceives the role of the past in his own life and more broadly in Hopi society. From our exchanges we have to come to believe that addressing the ways in which these two disparate affinities for the material past—and ultimately closing the gap between non-Pueblo and Pueblo</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Hopi Place Value:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translating a Landscape</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whiteley</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Hopi discourse, important ideas and processes involving cultural and historical order are localized and commemorated in the landscape and are indexed by place-names. Events happened at particular places: in Hopi oral history, knowing<italic>where</italic>something happened is an important part of knowing<italic>that</italic>it happened. As texts, some named places are interconnected, while others are more independent (on related Pueblo geographic sensibilities, see, e.g., Harrington 1916; Ortiz 1969, 1972; Silko 1999). Some texts are sociological, others historical, some mythological, others political, economic, religious, or ecological (cf. Thornton 2008 on Tlingit place-names). Like Hopi personal names, Hopi place-names individuate (see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Related-Language Translation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Naskapi and East Cree</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jancewicz</surname>
                           <given-names>Bill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While some theorists have suggested that translation is impossible (Payne 1971), to a large degree Western civilization and culture has depended upon translated documents originally written in one language into some other, usually more common, language. A large portion of our current understanding of philosophy, history, mythology, and religion comes to us through translated documents. What could we know of Aristotle, Plato, Moses, or Muhammad without contemporary translations of their writings into our mother tongue? From the philosophy of Immanuel Kant to the literature of Victor Hugo, the breadth of human knowledge is inextricably linked to the translation of documents</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Performative Translation and Oral Curation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ti-Jean/Chezan in Beaverland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ridington</surname>
                           <given-names>Amber</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ridington</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1999, as Amber Ridington was preparing to enter the ma program in folk studies at Western Kentucky University, her father, anthropologist Robin Ridington, recorded a French folktale told by Sammy Acko, a talented Dane-z̲aa storyteller (for the full text of this story see appendix A). The Dane-z̲aa, also known as the Beaver Indians (or Dunne-za in earlier publications), are subarctic hunting-and-gathering people who live in the Peace River region of northeastern British Columbia, Canada, close to the town of Fort St. John, where Amber was born. For almost fifty years, since Robin began his fieldwork in the area, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Translation and Censorship of Native American Oral Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clements</surname>
                           <given-names>William M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One decision confronting translators of orally performed American Indian verbal art concerns what to do with material that is regarded as questionable by one of the several persons who may figure into the process that begins with oral performance and ends with the publication of a written representation of that performance. The performer, the ethnographer who documents the performance, the translator, an editor, or a publisher may decide that a feature of a story or song should be withheld or transformed, usually to protect someone or something from moral or spiritual contamination. Under ideal conditions, the performer should not feel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>In the Words of Powhatan:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translation across Space and Time for The New World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rudes</surname>
                           <given-names>Blair A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the numerous screen and stage events staged to celebrate the four hundredth anniversary of the founding of the first permanent English colony in the Americas at Jamestown, Virginia, in 1607, perhaps the most ambitious and widely seen was the film<italic>The New World</italic>(New Line Cinema 2005). The film’s screenwriter and director, Terrence Malick, used the legendary romance of Pocahontas and John Smith to depict the impact that the settlement of Jamestown had on both the English and the native Virginia Algonquian people. Despite the questions that surround the authenticity of the Pocahontas story, Malick wanted to provide as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Ethnopoetic Translation in Relation to Audio, Video, and New Media Representations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ridington</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ridington</surname>
                           <given-names>Jillian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hennessy</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib5" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ridington</surname>
                           <given-names>Amber</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter describes our use of video and Web-based media to present an electronic equivalent of “interlinear” translations of ethnographic texts. The initial tape recordings of elders of the Dane-z̲aa of northeastern British Columbia were made by Robin Ridington in the 1960s. Jillian Ridington and Howard Broomfield joined the work in the 1970s and 1980s, and Jillian continues to be a partner in the projects. In recent years, Robin has added video recordings to the collection. The entire audio archive has been cataloged and digitized and is available to members of the Danez̲aa community. More recently the Doig River First</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Translating Algonquian Oral Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brittain</surname>
                           <given-names>Julie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacKenzie</surname>
                           <given-names>Marguerite</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we discuss a number of issues pertinent to the translation of Canadian Aboriginal oral literature, specifically that of the Algonquian peoples of the Quebec-Labrador peninsula (eastern Canada). Our discussion focuses on a collection of “oral texts” (the Innu-Naskapi collection) with which we have been involved as translators since 1985 (MacKenzie) and 1996 (Brittain).¹ Working collaboratively with native speakers of the Aboriginal language, we have now published English translations of several stories from this collection (e.g., MacKenzie 2004; Brittain and Mac-Kenzie et al. 2004, 2005). The Innu-Naskapi collection was recorded on cassette tape in 1967 and 1968. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Translating the Boundary between Life and Death in O’odham Devil Songs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kozak</surname>
                           <given-names>David L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lopez</surname>
                           <given-names>David I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I do not think it a stretch to say that translating Native verbal arts occupies an unseen boundary with its comings and goings between what is actually said, what is interpreted, then invented out of those words, and the written text that is presented as a faithful rendition of what was originally stated or sung. And while translation is of course reliant upon getting the words straight, I think the heart of translation is centrally about re-expressing the rhythms and movements expressed by those words. As we are all very much aware, words have the ability to move us. And</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Revisiting Haida Cradle-Song 67</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederick H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The significant development concerning traditional Native American literature and Native American cultural research has invoked attention to the intricacies of Native languages that previously had been ignored, if even considered at all (Basso 1984; Bringhurst 1999; Hymes 1981; Kroeber 1981; Kroskrity 1986; Swann 1992; Tedlock 1972). This attention has sparked a review of the volumes amassed during the early part of the twentieth century by the premier anthropologist Franz Boas and his protégés (1911, 1922). This return—to the texts gathered by Boasians as well as other collections—is replete with stories and songs of the tribes of North America.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Translating Tense and Aspect in Tlingit Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dauenhauer</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dauenhauer</surname>
                           <given-names>Nora Marks</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So I am in the eighth grade and I am assigned this book report and I write about Damon Runyon short stories and I begin it like this: “I am in the library last week and I see this book and I check it out.”¹ My book report was severely red-penciled by my teacher, although she lightened up at the end when she saw what I was trying to do. I learned from the experiment not to mix genre and style, but to use the style appropriate to the genre and level of formality. This is a message that comes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Translating Performance in the Written Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>Verse Structure in Dakota and Hocák</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burley</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>326</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We all know someone who can really tell a story—a person whose voice commands our attention, who encourages us to lean closer, waiting for the next detail, the next twist in the story. This person’s talent may be learned or intuitive, but part of the artistry he or she displays comes from our expectations of a story, our Western culture that dictates how a story is to be told and how a story is to unfold. We learned about stories long before we started school, in our nursery tales, our fairy tales, our children’s books, and while the stories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Toward Literature:</title>
                     <subtitle>Preservation of Artistic Effects in Choctaw Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haag</surname>
                           <given-names>Marcia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>348</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The central problem of translation, namely, the competition between faithfulness to meaning and preservation of form, grows more attenuated as translation moves from simple conveyance of information to artistic forms. Generally, in working with translations among European languages, the translator struggles with word choices when one language contains a particular word that denotes or connotes an idea that the other language does not. Then the translator seeks synonyms, or may resort to a phrase that more completely captures the sense intended. The translator may also have to deal with problems of grammatical structure: a language may lack a particular verbal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Translating an Esoteric Idiom:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Aztec Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bierhorst</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>370</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A typical Cherokee “sacred formula”—better,<italic>i:gawé:sdi</italic>‘to say, one’—begins with the words:</p>
                     <p>Ha! White Sparrow Hawk! You live Above. You have just come to scream: “Your soul has just been separated!”</p>
                     <p>Ha! Blue Mourning Dove!¹</p>
                     <p>Similarly, out of the cryptic literature of the Yucatec Maya, the compilation known as<italic>Ritual of the Bacabs</italic>gathers up incantations put together with such blind phrases as:</p>
                     <p>Who is its mother? O glyphs in the skies, O glyphs in the clouds, for you are always in skies, for you are always in clouds. Throw it down!²</p>
                     <p>Mystifying in much the same way,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Translating Context and Situation:</title>
                     <subtitle>William Strachey and Powhatan’s “Scorneful Song”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clements</surname>
                           <given-names>William M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>398</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the earliest references to singing among North American Natives appears in a chronicle of Hernando de Soto’s exploratory expedition of La Florida, during which he and his Spanish cohorts ventured as far west as the Mississippi River after passing through much of what is now the southeastern United States. Soto’s party made their journey between 1539 and 1543. Inevitably, they would have encountered verbal art in the form of oratory as a component of diplomatic courtesies from the Indians they encountered, and they also experienced their singing. As reported by the chronicler Garcilaso de la Vega—known as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>A Life in Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Preston</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was a child, I made about thirty solitary trips between my divorced parents, one in Chicago, the other in Fort Collins, Colorado, on the Union Pacific Streamliner<italic>City of Denver</italic>. Each trip was a thousand miles all by myself, and they were great adventures that I looked forward to eagerly. And at night, in an upper bunk, I would slide open the small window and look out through the darkness rushing by, and see in the distance a house, visible only by a lighted window or two. I used to wonder what it was like, living in those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Memories of Translation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Looking for the Right Words</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thompson</surname>
                           <given-names>M. Terry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thompson</surname>
                           <given-names>Laurence C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>446</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is not a technical essay on the sport of translation. It is some reminiscences about the experiences of a pair of linguists while studying several of the twenty-three Salishan languages of the Pacific Northwest during the active working years of our lives, between 1960 and 1995. We realize how very fortunate we were to be able to work with elders of the Lummi, Lushootseed, Thompson River Salish, Klallam, and Tillamook.</p>
                     <p>As linguists working on dying unwritten languages, where much if not all of the traditional culture survives only in the memory of elderly speakers, it is hard to translate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>461</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4gp3.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
