<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z8vf</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR4487.A35M37</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Coleridge on the Language of Verse</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marks</surname>
               <given-names>Emerson R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400886401</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400886406</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1981</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1m3nvnr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Drawing on the entire corpus of Coleridge's prose, Emerson Marks shows how the poet's rationale was grounded in the mimetic theory that informed his distinction between a copy and an imitation which Coleridge himself labeled the universal principle of the fine arts."</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1981.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback and hardcover editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="134"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>E.R.M.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I</label>
                     <title>Coleridge on Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The prolific Coleridge scholarship</italic>of recent years has strangely slighted that aspect of the poet’s literary theory which he himself thought centrally important and which, perhaps uniquely, owes little or nothing to any German “source”: his conception of poetic diction. What little attention it has received is largely confined to how and wherein his opinions on the subject differ from Wordsworth’s, with only perfunctory accounts, if any, of the theoretical grounds of the difference. Yet the first paragraph of<italic>Biographia Literaria</italic>lists “a settlement of the long-continued controversy concerning the true nature of poetic diction” among the book’s chief aims.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>II</label>
                     <title>The Language of Heaven</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>It is not hard</italic>to account for the note of barely restrained impatience audible in Coleridge’s refutation of Wordsworth’s notions of poetic language and form. In the Preface to<italic>Lyrical Ballads</italic>the almost casual dismissal of meter and related aspects of prosodic structure affronted Coleridge’s dearest experiences as reader and poet as much as they clashed with his reasoned ideas about poetry. No aspect of the poet’s art interested him more than its technique. Virgil, whose versification he admired “beyond measure,” delighted him for that reason alone. To his rapt young audience at Highgate he complained of the neglect of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III</label>
                     <title>The Universal Principle</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Of Wordsworth’s declarations</italic>that the language of good poetry is ideally derived from rustic speech, and that there is no essential difference between the languages of poetry and prose, Coleridge provided the readers of the<italic>Biographia Literaria</italic>with a bi-level refutation. On the first level, which has received the bulk of critical attention since, are several more or less direct denials of these assertions themselves or of assumptions they seem to entail. Thus he retorts that the best part of any language comes not from the countryman’s daily communion with nature but from the intellectual and imaginative activity of educated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV</label>
                     <title>Organic Mimesis and Poetic Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although this passage from<italic>Table Talk</italic>is probably his most succinct definition of the “universal principle,” the central role it plays in his poetics becomes clear only when he applies it to the other arts. Besides the illustrations already noted (from opera, stage scenery, and landscape painting), there is another from an art which had its heyday in the previous century. In the pleasure we experience at the sight of a fine landscape garden, he sees the type of that mimetic restructuring of reality which we enjoy in a good drama.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>“How natural!” we say; but the very wonder that</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>V</label>
                     <title>Tamers of the Chaos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>That Coleridge</italic>has been so little recognized as an intellectual ancestor by even the most distinguished proponents of structuralist poetics, European and American alike, at first seems odd. Yet it is possible that some of them, thinking of him chiefly as one of the leading British Romantic poets, left his prose largely unread. Others, perhaps taking their cue from the long indifference of Coleridge’s own countrymen to the signal achievement of the<italic>Biographia Literaria</italic>, may have assumed it to be like the bulk of pre-World War I poetics devoid of the analytical precision of their own Saussurean reasoning and therefore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nvnr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
