<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f89hm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The War of 1948</book-title>
         <subtitle>Representations of Israeli and Palestinian Memories and Narratives</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sela</surname>
               <given-names>Avraham</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kadish</surname>
               <given-names>Alon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253022424</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253023414</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253023416</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005tc4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The 1948 War is remembered in this special volume, including aspects of Israeli-Jewish memory and historical narratives of 1948 and representations of Israeli-Palestinian memory of that cataclysmic event and its consequences. The contributors map and analyze a range of perspectives of the 1948 War as represented in literature, historical museums, art, visual media, and landscape, as well as in competing official and societal narratives. They are examined especially against the backdrop of the Oslo process, which brought into relief tensions within and between both sides of the national divide concerning identity and legitimacy, justice, and righteousness of "self" and "other."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="242"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sela</surname>
                           <given-names>Avraham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kadish</surname>
                           <given-names>Alon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Israeli and Palestinian Memories and Historical Narratives of the 1948 War—An Overview</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sela</surname>
                           <given-names>Avraham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kadish</surname>
                           <given-names>Alon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume consists of a collection of studies of Israeli representations, both Jewish and Palestinian, of memory and historical narratives of the 1948 War. The studies map and explain some Israeli-Jewish and Israeli-Palestinian perspectives of the 1948 War as represented in literature, historical museums, art, visual media, and landscape, as well as in competing official and societal narratives. They are examined especially against the backdrop of the Oslo process, which had strongly brought into relief tensions within and between both sides of the national divide concerning identity and legitimacy, justice, and righteousness of “self” and “other.” Five chapters represent varied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The 1948 Palestine War on the Small Screen:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Comparative Analysis of Its Representation in Two Israeli Television Series</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garami</surname>
                           <given-names>Bosmat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Televised history has become the focus of growing academic research, which examines its uniqueness compared to the tradition of written history, and emphasizes its significant role in shaping collective memory. Film and television became central mechanisms of memory construction during the second half of the twentieth century and Western scholarship has long been emphasizing the power of fictional as well as documentary film in the representation of history¹ and defending television’s capabilities to “mediate” history successfully against those who doubt it.² According to Edgerton, televisual characteristics such as immediacy, dramatization, personalization, and intimacy, all shape the medium’s interaction with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Israel’s Publications Agency and the 1948 Palestinian Refugees</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nets-Zehngut</surname>
                           <given-names>Rafi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nations involved in an intractable conflict usually present a biased<italic>official memory</italic>of the conflict. To fit their interests, such memory portrays these nations positively and their rivals negatively. As such, it plays an important role in the conflict by affecting the psychological and behavioral reactions of the parties toward their rivals. Therefore, such memory is of importance for scholarly research as attested by the blooming research literature in recent years on memory, especially in the context of conflict, war, and peace.¹</p>
                     <p>Israel’s intractable conflict with the Palestinians and the Arab states is by no means exceptional in Israel’s quest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The War of Independence Exhibited:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Study of Three Israeli Museums</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boord</surname>
                           <given-names>Ofer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the past three decades, Israel’s history museums have gradually started to gain an important role within the public arena. Museums have attempted to compete with the teaching of history in schools, with the textbooks, as well as with TV programs and contents obtained through the Internet, by including short and focused captions, historic photographs, original items, reconstruction of buildings, and films. Many museums are currently successful in illustrating “boring” and distant historic issues in a captivating manner, and are thus a factor to be taken into consideration. The large number of museums as well as the scope of their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Contested Urban Memoryscape Strategies and Tactics in Post-1948 Haifa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kolodney</surname>
                           <given-names>Ziva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Haifa’s Memorial Garden (Gan ha-Zikkaron) was the subject of an architectural competition immediately after the 1948 War. It was a main urban open space, situated at the heart of the city’s current municipal center along the confrontation seam between the pre-1948 Arab quarter of Haifa’s downtown area and the Jewish neighborhood of Hadar ha-Carmel. Today, the garden overlooks the long-gone Old City area of Haifa, which was demolished during the Shikmona Operation in 1948–49. Along with concrete and imagery landscape memory production practices (memoryscape) of street re-naming, war monuments and memorials construction in the urban fabric in the early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Making of a Myth:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Story of Kfar Etzion in Religious Zionism 1948–1967</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Greenblum</surname>
                           <given-names>Dror</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 1948 and 1967 the story of Kfar Etzion, one of the best-known cases of heroism in Israel’s War of Independence, became the defining myth in religious Zionism. No other story or single event in the history of religious Zionism has attained such mythical proportions and had so much influence on religious Zionists. The essence of religious-Zionist belief, how to live a life of purity and holiness and how to die a hero’s death, all for the sanctification of God’s name (<italic>kiddush ha-shem</italic>) is an integral part of this story.</p>
                     <p>Kfar Etzion was one of the four kibbutzim (the others</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Descending the Khazooq:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Working Through” the Trauma of the Nakba in Emile Habibi’s Oeuvre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Peled</surname>
                           <given-names>Assaf</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many Palestinian intellectuals have written about the harsh realities of their people following the<italic>Nakba</italic>, but only a few of them have critically dealt with the traumatic facets of the event and their present repercussions. Literature on the<italic>Nakba</italic>represents a salient effort to serve the Palestinian people’s struggle for their natural rights. While this focus on the injustices perpetrated against the Palestinians and the need for restitution is tempting, it leaves little room for critical reflection on the experience itself. As its point of reference is external, it dooms the writer to act out¹ the past.² In recent years</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Wa-Ma Nasayna (We Have Not Forgotten):</title>
                     <subtitle>Palestinian Collective Memory and the Print Work of Abed Abdi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ben-Zvi</surname>
                           <given-names>Tal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Palestinian art created within Israel’s 1948 borders possesses unique characteristics deriving from its being part of the visual culture of the Palestinian minority in Israel. In this artistic-national construct, artist, graphic designer, and printmaker Abed Abdi played a leading role as a consequence of his work over the decade between 1972 and 1982 as graphics editor of the publications of the Communist Party and its successor, the Democratic Front for Peace and Equality, the Arabic language journal<italic>Al-Ittihad</italic>, and the<italic>Al-Jadid</italic>literary journal. Additionally, many of his works were also published in the Communist Party’s Hebrew language paper,<italic>Zo Haderekh</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Palestinian Exile—Drama Shapes Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kabha</surname>
                           <given-names>Mustafa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapter attempts to link memory to history through the genre of “historical drama,” where the collective memory of a people is presented through the story of certain groups of this people at a defined point in time.</p>
                     <p>The question “What is memory to history?” has occupied and continues to occupy many historians. In the opinion of Pierre Nora, history is a problematic and incomplete reconstruction of what is no more, while memory is always relevant. Memory is life, borne constantly by living groups, and is therefore constantly developing, open to a dialectic of remembrance and forgetting, sensitive to all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Post-Oslo Israeli and Palestinian History and Memory of 1948</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sela</surname>
                           <given-names>Avraham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caplan</surname>
                           <given-names>Neil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapters in this volume have discussed various Israeli and Palestinian approaches to, and perceptions of, 1948 commonly represented in historiography, literature, films, and other public realms of culture and knowledge. In presenting their case studies, the authors have made valuable contributions to a field increasingly marked by perceptive interpretations of the nature and fluctuating trends among Israelis and Palestinians as they remember and narrate their respective histories.</p>
                     <p>These in-depth studies underline the rigid nature of collective memory and identity, especially in intractable ethno-national conflicts such as the Israeli-Palestinian one. At the same time, however, they also demonstrate the dynamic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tc4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
