<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9dgg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HV8699.U5H374 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Capital punishment</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Crime</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Debates and debating</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Colonial period, ca. 1600–1775</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1783–1865</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Executing Democracy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Volume One: Capital Punishment &amp; the Making of America, 1683-1807</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hartnett</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780870138690</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609172077</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Stephen John Hartnett</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt7zt9dq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Executing Democracy: Capital Punishment &amp; the Making of America, 1683-1807</italic>is the first volume of a rhetorical history of public debates about crime, violence, and capital punishment in America. This examination begins in 1683, when William Penn first struggled to govern the rowdy indentured servants of Philadelphia, and continues up until 1807, when the Federalists sought to impose law-and-order upon the New Republic.This volume offers a lively historical overview of how crime, violence, and capital punishment influenced the settling of the New World, the American Revolution, and the frantic post-war political scrambling to establish norms that would govern the new republic.By presenting a macro-historical overview, and by filling the arguments with voices from different political camps and communicative genres, Hartnett provides readers with fresh perspectives for understanding the centrality of public debates about capital punishment to the history of American democracy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Rhetorical History of “A Very Hard Choice”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus the news from Andrew Bradford’s<italic>American Weekly Mercury</italic>on 7 July 1737. The second regularly published newspaper in the New World and the most important newspaper in Philadelphia at the time, the<italic>American Weekly Mercury</italic>offers a window into the complicated choices of colonial life. The block of text quoted above appears on page 3, immediately above notices of ships having arrived from and departed for Jamaica, Boston, Cadiz, Barbados, and Bristol; it is three short blocks of text removed from an advertisement for Archibald Cummings’s<italic>The Danger of Breaking Christian Unity: In Two Sermons Preached at Christ’s Church</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Settler Debauchery, Capital Punishment, and the Theater of Colonial (Dis)Order, 1683–1741</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1758 English troops stormed Senegal, seizing property valued at more than £250,000. According to Peter Linebaugh, one of the seamen who fought for the Crown in the battle, John Ward, was soon thereafter “hanged [in London] for stealing a watch.” Linebaugh thus shows how empires plunder and pillage with impunity while working stiffs, including those trained in the ways of violence by the Crown, are hanged for committing the most trifling crimes. Ward would appear to have been particularly unlucky, for Eric Williams observes that “in 1745 transportation [the euphemism for banishing convicts] was the penalty for the theft</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Paradox of a Republican Revolution Using Executions as Pedagogy, 1768–1784</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historians have long recognized a paradox within the American Revolution: while the leaders of the uprising marshaled the revolutionary rhetoric of liberty and equality to discredit a (supposedly) tyrannical king and to rally the masses to the cause of independence, they maintained a vision of political leadership that was more aristocratic than republican. As Henry Steele Commager and Richard B. Morris note, the Revolution’s leaders were “elitist, prosperous, and essentially conservative”; Gordon Wood echoes this argument, noting that the new nation’s leaders were “habituated . . . to monarchical hierarchy and desirous of stability and continuity.” Nonetheless, the masses could</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Hanging of Abraham Johnstone and the Turning of Terror into Hope, 1797</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I argued in chapter 2 that post-Revolutionary America experienced a backlash against too-damned-much-democracy: revolutionary impulses needed to be curtailed, so elites thought, to prevent the young nation from succumbing to what founding father Benjamin Rush diagnosed as the disease of “anarchia” and from sliding into what the Connecticut Wits portrayed in<italic>The Anarchiad</italic>as a coming age of democracy run wild. Part of this backlash against those who took the words of the Declaration of Independence too literally—for of course all men were not created equal and happiness was not a natural right—entailed the use of state-sanctioned violence,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Enlightenment, Republicanism, and Executions, 1785–1800</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Delivering a July Fourth oration in Boston in 1785, John Gardiner, an Episcopal minister and “perhaps Boston’s most distinguished man of letters,” offered this observation on the relationships among the different forms of government and their corresponding stages of Enlightenment:</p>
                     <p>The introduction and progress of<italic>freedom</italic>have generally attended the introduction and progress of<italic>letters and science</italic>. In despotick governments the people are mostly illiterate, rude, and uncivilized; but in states where CIVIL LIBERTY hath been cherished, the human mind hath generally proceeded in improvement, learning and knowledge have prevailed, and the arts and sciences have flourished.</p>
                     <p>Thus expressing a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Hanging of John M’Kean and the Perils of Sinning in an Age of Reason</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A hard-drinking Irishman who emigrated to Philadelphia in 1783, John M’Kean was a notorious wife beater. He apparently hit his wife daily, sometimes for no reason, sometimes for trifling reasons, sometimes just because he was drunk and was in the habit. One wonders what his neighbors were doing during these constant batterings; nonetheless, when he finally killed his wife and was hanged for it, one observer ventured that “the safety of society requires it.” But it would seem that<italic>society</italic>was not threatened, just his<italic>wife</italic>—which means that some intervention was needed before, not after, she was beaten to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt9dq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
