<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P301.F37 1993</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reason</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Norms of Rhetorical Culture</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Farrell</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1993</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300053852</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237818</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1993</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3sn2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Rhetoric is widely regarded by both its detractors and advocates as a kind of antithesis to reason. In this book Thomas B. Farrell restores rhetoric as an art of practical reason and enlightened civic participation, grounding it in its classical tradition-particularly in the rhetoric of Aristotle. And, because prevailing modernist world views bear principal responsibility for the disparagement of rhetorical tradition, Farrell also offers a critique of the dominant currents of modern humanist thought.Farrell argues that rhetoric is not antithetical to reason but is a manner of posing and answering questions that is distinct from the approaches of analytic and dialectical reason. He develops this position in a number of ways: through a series of bold reinterpretations of Aristotle's<italic>Rhetoric</italic>; through a detailed appraisal of traditional rhetorical concepts as seen in modern texts from the Army-McCarthy hearings to Edward Kennedy's memorial for his brother, Mario Cuomo's address on abortion, Betty Friedan's<italic>Feminine Mystique</italic>, and Vaclav Havel's inaugural address; and through a fresh appraisal of theories on the character of language and discourse found in contemporary philosophy, literary criticism, anthropology, deconstructionism, Marxism, and especially in Habermas's critical theory of communicative action.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="374"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A rhetorical culture is an institutional formation in which motives of competing parties are intelligible, audiences available, expressions reciprocal, norms translatable, and silences noticeable. It may seem odd, even confounding, to introduce certain norms or “goods” where the notoriously crafty business of rhetoric is concerned. Today we have spin doctors and image consultants, audience-manipulators of every ideological stripe—hence the much discussed flight of audiences from the public arena. But this is not really so surprising. Rhetoric has always been a practiced imperfection, the worst fear of idealized reason and the best hope for whatever remains of civic life. This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Rhetoric and Dialectic as Modes of Inquiry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Asking questions is a curious business. The larger the question, the less likely the questioners are to be satisfied with the answer. And<italic>rhetorical</italic>questions seem the most elusive of all. They are questions in name only, introduced for effect; questions for which we already have answers. Still, they continue to provoke us.¹ Earlier this century, two fascinating public figures struggled with that strange amalgam of power, suspicion, and curiosity that is implied by the thoughtful question. The figures were as different from one another as the questions that engaged them. One was a formidable intellectual, a political revolutionary, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Rhetorical Reflection:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward an Ethic of Practical Reason</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even earlier in the twentieth century, the public agenda seemed lost or abandoned. In an atmosphere of crisis, civic institutions could only repeat empty symbolic reassurances. The symbols were in fact empty, because there appeared to be no learned experience except failure for them to rest on. Resignation, cynicism, and hopelessness had become the order of the day. In the midst of this material and symbolic dispossession it seems almost fanciful to imagine a creative ethical option for speech. Around the world oratory flourished; but it was hardly the sort to revive hopes for participatory democracy. Imagine now a public</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>In the Horizon of Necessity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tragic Rhetoric and Public Character</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most of the time we are unlikely to consider modern political life as supplying us with the materials for an<italic>art</italic>. Caricature, perhaps, as in the political cartoon or the made-for-television cartoons we know as docudramas. But the high drama and oracular vision once associated with the grand art of statecraft seem today as far from our experience as hooped skirts and horse-drawn carriages. Perhaps this is as it should be in an age that is suspicious of grand designs. But not so terribly long ago it was otherwise. A patriarchal aesthetic of politics exuded grace, poise, and propriety; it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>After Rhetorical Culture:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Spectacle of Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a fact that not all stories are told. And if they could all be told, there is no imaginable forum that could encompass all the needs, themes, and moral concerns which deserve expression. Even if, as some of us once thought, the whole world is watching, its attention span seems limited to one thing at a time. This is, in less humble language, the modernist dilemma. It is all too easy to universalize wants, needs, interests, and norms. In a world of unequal chances, such categories exist only as a fragile language of development begging for yet another</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Universal Pragmatics and Practical Reason:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Deformation to Reformation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Proclamations of reason’s eclipse, like many a categorical dismissal, have shown themselves to be a bit hasty. Perhaps the life of practical reason, as a mode of reflection open to the collectivity, may be thought of as a generational phenomenon.¹ In any historical period, there are likely to be cultures in which reason and rhetoric have been poisoned. But it seems premature to pronounce any state of affairs, however extreme, as having eliminated forever the prospects for recovery. In the retrospection of dark times, utopian thought can appear foolish. But some such thought may be necessary if possibilities for reflection</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Rhetorical Coherence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Refiguring the Episodes of Public Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nobody admits to liking rhetoric very much. But almost everyone admits to having occasionally been seized and transported by a discourse which changed or influenced their life and priorities. It is a commonplace that such discourse is rare, the exception that proves our (usually untested) rule. But all practices need to have outstanding exemplars, touchstones of accomplishment. And virtually by definition, such outstanding cases will be rare. It is probably not possible to determine whether great or eloquent rhetoric is rarer now than it was in the various golden ages of the past. Nor do I think that the determination,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Criticism, Disturbance, and Rhetorical Community:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reanimating the Occasions for Rhetoric</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eloquence deepens and distinguishes the contours of a practice, as do all noble exceptions, the few showing the many what might be accomplished. But for the pedestrian art of rhetoric, these “many” are more than also-rans in the parade; they are also the constitutive stuff of the art. Ours has been the century of Mahler and Shostakovich and of Elvis, Janis, and Chuck Berry as well. Rhetoric works its magic inconspicuously, in small successes as well as noble failures. Above all, it works<italic>both</italic>sides of the street. In this chapter, I address a problem which haunts contemporary practice: namely,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sn2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
