<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Scripture with the Saints</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Black</surname>
               <given-names>C. Clifton</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Fowl</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893804</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718843458</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>C. Clifton Black</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdw89"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Reading Scripture with the Saints is a small museum. On its pages hang portraits of Christianity’s “masters of the sacred page": Gregory of Nyssa, Augustine of Hippo, Benedict of Nursia, Maximus Confessor, Thomas Aquinas, Martin Luther and Charles Wesley. Other, surprising figures also appear, such as Shakespeare, Washington and Lincoln. How did these figures from history interpret Scripture? What might their diverse approaches teach today’s readers of the Old and New Testaments? What is missing in contemporary biblical interpretation that an awareness of the history of exegesis might complete? Join C. Clifton Black as he traverses the Bible, Church History, systematic theology, Elizabethan drama and American politics. Reading Scripture with the Saints retrieves pre-modern insights for a post-modern world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="290"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF TABLES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fowl</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the very first tasks I took up as a newly minted PhD was a review of Clifton Black’s<italic>The Disciples According to Mark: Markan Redaction in Current Debate</italic>. I do not recall why I was asked to review the book or why I even agreed to do it, since I am not a specialist in Mark. The book was an absolute delight to read. Even though the material was quite technical, Black had a graceful writing style that made the material accessible without oversimplifying and distorting it. The book is a gentle but devastating criticism of the attempts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>C.C.B.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>WELCOME</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The book you are holding is a small museum. That should be obvious by thumbing its pages. Study the portrait of disciplined, gentle Abbot Benedetto—Benedict—patron saint of Europe and of students. Nearby, in the center of things, is Maximus the Confessor, lifting his right hand before it was hacked off for his allegedly heretical writings. That verdict was overturned by the Sixth Ecumenical Council (680–81), two decades after his death: a grim reminder that the church has a history of getting things terribly wrong before God helps it put them right. Turn a few more pages: there’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>TRINITY AND EXEGESIS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That claim,¹ or something like it, unites most Christians who consider themselves orthodox. The God whom Christian worship is one God, who has revealed himself to believers as an intrinsically relational tri-unity of Father and Son and Holy Spirit. Historically, the church has based that claim on Scripture itself:²</p>
                     <p>“Hear, O Israel: The LORD our God, the LORD is one; and you shall love the LORD your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your might.” (Deut 6:4–5)</p>
                     <p>The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ and the love of God and the communion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>SERVING THE FOOD OF FULL–GROWN ADULTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If remembered at all, Augustine of Hippo (354–430) is associated with original sin, predestination, and other ideas consigned by many to a theological flea market. I shall not play the apologist for Augustine’s thought, even less attempt his rehabilitation among present-day skeptics.¹ Though astonishingly prolific, he enjoyed no ivory tower. His pivotal masterpieces—<italic>Confessions, The Trinity, The City of God</italic>, to name but three—were written on his career’s margins, from 396 until his death, as a diligent bishop in Hippo Regius, a scruffy African harbor-town. In those days a bishop was not the diocesan administrator that some modern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>LISTEN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Rule</italic>of Benedict of Nursia (480–547) is widely considered the primary monastic code, the sun around which western monasticism came to revolve from the early Middle Ages to the present day. Doubtless Benedict, who prepared “this little rule … for beginners” (<italic>RB</italic>73.8b),¹ would have eschewed being regarded the center of anything. God, however, has always displayed a knack for elevating the humble (Ps 149:4; Luke 1:52). The Benedictine way continues to offer a vital alternative to the duplicities and delusions of our own era: a starkly countercultural way of life grounded in Jesus Christ, instead of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>TRANSFIGURED EXEGESIS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Moses’ encounter with the LORD on Mount Sinai is critically important among Jews and Muslims. Its distinctively Christian counterpart is Jesus’ transfiguration, appearing in the Synoptic Gospels according to Matthew (17:1–8), Mark (9:2–8), and Luke (9:28–36). Since the nineteenth century historical criticism’s treatment of this narrative has traveled some well-worn grooves:</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Tradition-critically</italic>, the story is considered a Christian midrash on similar mountain-top experiences of Moses and Elijah (Exod 24:12–18; 1 Kgs 19:1–18)—the figures who, by more than sheer coincidence, attend Jesus at his transfiguration. Tradition critics hear reverberations of Ps 2:7 and Deut 18:15</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>DOUBTLESS THOMAS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because of his monumental<italic>Summa theologiae</italic>(1265–74), few remember that Thomas Aquinas (1225–1274) was employed as a biblical scholar.¹<italic>As magister in sacra pagina</italic>at Paris, Naples, Orvieto, and Rome, his principal duties were lecturing on biblical books, oversight of scholastic disputations on scriptural exegesis, and preaching the Word of God to clergy and laity.² From among his prodigious exegetical writings, Thomas’s lectures on the Gospel of John (<italic>Super Evangelium S. Ioannis Lectura</italic>) are esteemed as of the highest caliber.³ In this chapter we shall concentrate our attention on his handling of a crucial NT text, John 1:1–</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>LUTHER TIMES THREE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most standard treatments of Martin Luther’s (1483–1546) biblical commentary move deductively: general propositions are enunciated (e.g., holy Scripture as its own interpreter; all correct interpretation standing under the rule of the analogy of faith, construed christocentrically) and are then bolstered by extracts from the<italic>Weimar Ausgabe</italic>or<italic>Luther’s Works</italic>.¹ Though such a procedure can be instructive, its total effect is a rather flat presentation of Luther’s exegesis. Perhaps some of the subject’s dimensions—its unity and diversity, constancy and development—would become clearer by adopting a more inductive procedure: examining, comparing, and contrasting three different specimens of Luther’s exposition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“NOT OF AN AGE, BUT FOR ALL TIME”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the slender space of twenty years not one but two corpora exploded the course of English language and literature. Two centuries separate Goethe (1749–1832) from Luther’s Bible (1534). Pushkin (1799–1837) consolidated Russia’s vernacular a century after East Slavic’s push and pull between Church Slavonic and Peter the Great (1672–1725). From 1590 to 1611 England witnessed the emergence of<italic>both</italic>Shakespearean poetry<italic>and</italic>the King James Bible. The world has never been the same since. The Bard of Avon is now regarded as the preeminent dramatist on the world’s stage; no book has been published more often,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>SEARCHER OF THE ORACLES DIVINE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles Wesley (1707–1788), John’s younger brother, was Methodism’s unofficial poet laureate. By the most conservative reckoning, Charles penned some 6,500 hymns, perhaps hundreds more sacred poems,¹ many of which propelled Methodist worship and evangelism in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. More controversial is whether Wesley’s hymns² are “theological works” as such.³ Less debated—only for being more neglected—are the character and quality of biblical exegesis in Wesley’s poetry. This chapter attempts some soundings of that subject.</p>
                     <p>Interpreting Scripture, on what premises did Wesley proceed? Happily, we do not have to guess. He told us, in versified explanations.</p>
                     <p>When</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>AMERICAN SCRIPTURES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>George Washington’s (1732–1799) farewell address and Abraham Lincoln’s (1809–1865) second inaugural are among the very few specimens of American statecraft now accorded iconic status. This chapter considers them as<italic>theological</italic>statements. As counter-intuitive as that may seem, the pudding’s proof awaits its tasting.</p>
                     <p>“He was a virtuoso of resignations. He perfected the art of getting power by giving it away.”¹ Though unlikely to have been consciously motivated by John 10:17–18 or Phil 2:5–11, George Washington’s<italic>modus operandi</italic>was curiously Christ-like in effect.</p>
                     <p>News that Washington had resigned his commission as commander of America’s Continental Army (23</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>UNTIL LATER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our tour has reached its end. Are there any last questions?</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>What may the figures we have considered teach biblical interpreters in our very different era?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Generally speaking, several things. Most of them model an aptitude and imagination for those who care about theologically sensitive exegesis that guides the church’s life.¹ Return to Crivelli’s portrait of Thomas Aquinas in chapter 6. The saint’s right hand holds the church; in his left are Scripture’s opened pages. Each is held in balance with the other, although the Bible appears heavier, counterweighting an edifice with heavenly aspiration. A radiant medallion throws sunlight on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX 1</title>
                     <subtitle>WASHINGTON’S FAREWELL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX 2</title>
                     <subtitle>LINCOLN’S SECOND INAUGURAL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdw89.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
