<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z8vf</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3565.C57Z725 1986</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">O’Connor, Flannery</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apocalyptic literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Flannery O'Connor and the Language of Apocalypse</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KESSLER</surname>
               <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400886012</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400886015</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1986</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRESS</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1m323xn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Seeing Flannery O'Connor in the company of poets, rather than realistic prose writers, this work shows how she uses recurring figures of speech to transform or re-create the external world.</p>
         <p>Originally published in .</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback and hardcover editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="180"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Flannery O’Connor chose to keep within the boundaries of fiction, even as she “seemed to contemplate,” like her character Mrs. Shortley, “the tremendous frontiers of her true country.” Although some apologists have written as if her fiction is theology in disguise, her stories a series of illustrations of Grace, O’Connor continually stressed that she was writing fiction, not religious tracts. Some other commentators have attempted to explain her narratives in terms of her “real” Southern world, but by now the writer’s rejection of “realism” has become well-known. In either case, the aim has been to strip her of her various</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I</label>
                     <title>THE VIOLENCE OF METAPHOR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even though interpretation demands that we limit textual meaning, the direction of the interpretive movement can be questioned: away from language toward extrinsic knowledge, of whatever sort, or deeper into the labyrinth of words? Believing that language possesses its own reality, I intend to follow, in O’Connor’s phrase, “words moving secretly toward some goal of their own.” Her metaphors are rarely simple resemblances or satisfying correspondences between man and a natural order, as those of Eudora Welty and Wallace Stevens often are. An apocalyptic poet like T. S. Eliot, O’Connor finds limited value in analogies with the physical world and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>II</label>
                     <title>THE VIRTUE IN AS IF</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After Caroline Gordon read the manuscript of<italic>The Violent Bear it Away</italic>, she suggested that O’Connor attend to certain verbal mannerisms, “technical imperfections” that had become habitual. O’Connor was eager to comply, but she wrote to a friend: ”I have just corrected the page proofs and I spent a lot of time getting<italic>seems</italic>and<italic>as if</italic>constructions out of it. It was like getting ticks off a dog. I was blissfully unaware of all this while I was writing it. ...” The stylistic tic remained, however, despite the writer’s conscious efforts, and even in the typescript of a very</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III</label>
                     <title>SEEING INTO MYSTERY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>O’Connor’s metaphors, particularly her characteristic<italic>as if</italic>, release a power, often violent and threatening, that demands the death of the understanding before the reader can begin to evolve a new consciousness. The power exists in man and in external nature, but it remains hidden to those who see<italic>as</italic>and not<italic>as if</italic>. Onnie Jay Holy, in<italic>Wise Blood</italic>, could represent all those literalists who cling to the assurance of the understanding: “You don’t have to believe nothing you don’t understand and approve of. If you don’t understand it, it ain’t true, and that’s all there is to it. Nojokers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV</label>
                     <title>MAKING AN END</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her story “Greenleaf,” Flannery O’Connor created one of her typical matriarchs, fearful of the unknown and resolutely determined to make her earthly “place” secure. Mrs. May sees herself as a good person, whose virtue shows in the charitable works she performs for others, particularly the Greenleaf family. She speculates that it would be ironic if, after all her efforts, one of the Greenleaf children should sue her for injuries his father suffered on her farm: “she thought of it almost with pleasure as if she had hit on the perfect ending for a story she was telling her friends.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In company with other Southern writers, notably the Agrarians, who aspire to embrace a lost tradition and look on history as a repository of value, Flannery O’Connor seems a curious anomaly. She wrote of herself: “I am a Catholic peculiarly possessed of the modern consciousness, that Jung describes as unhistorical, solitary, and guilty.” Likewise her characters comprise a gallery of misfits isolated in a present and sentenced to a lifetime of exile from the human community. In O’Connor’s fiction, the past neither justifies nor even explains what is happening. If she believed, for example, in the importance of the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m323xn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
