<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z8sj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN491.5.S49 2000</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Minority authors</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Immigrants’ writings</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Multiculturalism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Writing Outside the Nation</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SEYHAN</surname>
               <given-names>AZADE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691050997</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691050996</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400823994</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7s8h3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Some of the most innovative writers of contemporary literature are writing in diaspora in their second or third language. Here Azade Seyhan describes the domain of transnational poetics they inhabit. She begins by examining the works of selected bilingual and bicultural writers of the United States (including Oscar Hijuelos, Maxine Hong Kingston, and Eva Hoffman) and Germany (Libuse Moníková, Rafik Schami, and E. S. Özdamar, among others), developing a new framework for understanding the relationship between displacement, memory, and language. Considering themes of loss, witness, translation, identity, and exclusion, Seyhan interprets diasporic literatures as condensed archives of cultural and linguistic memory that give integrity and coherence to pasts ruptured by migration.</p>
         <p>The book next compares works by contemporary Chicana and Turkish-German women writers as innovative and sovereign literary voices within the larger national cultures of the United States and Germany. Seyhan identifies in American multiculturalism critical clues for analyzing new cultural formations in Europe and maintains that Germany's cultural transformation suggests new ways of reading the American literary mosaic. Her approach, however, extends well beyond these two literatures. She creates a critical map of a "third geography," where a transnational, multilingual literary movement is gathering momentum.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Writing Outside the Nation</italic>both contributes to and departs from postcolonial studies in that it focuses specifically on transnational writers working outside of their "mother tongue" and compares American and German diasporic literatures within a sophisticated conceptual framework. It illustrates how literature's symbolic economy can reclaim lost personal and national histories, as well as connect disparate and distant cultural traditions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Neither Here/Nor There: The Culture of Exile</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The words of the eighteenth-century German Romantic poet Novalis (Friedrich von Hardenberg) resonate beyond the boundaries of their history and geography and are poignantly rearticulated by a contemporary master of the arts of memory. Salman Rushdie’s critical sentiment stands as a testimony to the labor of remembrance that reclaims the lost experience of another time and place in language and imagination. The work of commemoration is often the only means of releasing our (hi)stories from subjugation to official or institutionalized regimes of forgetting. Remembering is an act of lending coherence and integrity to a history interrupted, divided, or compromised by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Geographies of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How many people today live in a language that is not their own? Or no longer, or not yet, even know their own and know poorly the major language that they are forced to serve? This is the problem of immigrants, and especially of their children, the problem of minorities, the problem of a minor literature, but also a problem for all of us: how to tear a minor literature away from its own language, allowing it to challenge the language and making it follow a sober revolutionary path? How to become a nomad and an immigrant and a gypsy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Autobiographical Voices with an Accent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Migrancy, Culture, Identity</italic>, Iain Chambers presents a well-orchestrated medley of personal memory, philosophical reflection, anthropological and literary theory, cultural criticism, social commentary, well-positioned quotations, and photographs to communicate how notions of identity and geography shift and shape as they travel through myriad languages and cultures, across borders and histories. At one level, this book can be read as the long version of Chambers’s curriculum vitae, his own<italic>Bildungsroman</italic>. Evocative of early German romanticism’s<italic>Bildungsroman</italic>that recounts the protagonist’s<italic>Bildung</italic>through different stations of his journey in prose, poetry, song, anecdote, letter, philosophical reflection, and free associations of dream and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>At Different Borders/On Common Grounds</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An active European site of fiery debates, where stakes in labor migration, immigration, patriation, and national and ethnic identity politics are very high, is the reunified German state. At this historical juncture, over six million foreigners, including Gastarbeiter (guest workers), refugees, asylum seekers, writers, artists, and professionals are permanently settled in Germany. In the embattled Europe of the post-cold-war era, Germany, with its economic power, political stability, generous welfare system, and what until recently were very flexible asylum laws, has become, perhaps quite unwittingly and unwillingly, the destination for a growing body of dis- placed peoples. This unprecedented presence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Writing Outside the Nation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether removed from the subject by one or more generations, several decades, or a few years, the memory and images of nation continue to inhabit the exilic imagination. The symbolic registers of the nation usually increase proportionately to the length of time spent outside the nation, and the loyalties that bind the “imagined community” (Anderson) diverge into smaller communities bound by gender, class, caste, religion, home region, profession, language, and dialect. The concept of a sacred mythical originary nation, Aztlán, developed at the height of the Chicano movement as a source of identification and identity formation in a diasporic community</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                     <subtitle>Pedagogical Gains</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The transnational and “bilingual” narratives of the present study foster an awareness of the contingencies of power structures and value systems in history. Consequently, they guide the reader away from narrowly defined or unreflected positions of interpretation. “As other histories emerge from the archaeology of modernity to disturb the monologue of History,” writes Iain Chambers, “we are reminded of the multiple rhythms of life that have been written out and forgotten.”¹ Benjamin’s reflections on history suggest that the narratives of the powerful are remembered as history, but those of the disenfranchised need to be “wrested away” as memory from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7s8h3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
