<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GE140.M68 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Environmental degradation</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ecological disturbances</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Global environmental change</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Grief</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Loss (Psychology)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Environmental Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mourning Nature</book-title>
         <subtitle>Hope at the Heart of Ecological Loss and Grief</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CUNSOLO</surname>
               <given-names>ASHLEE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LANDMAN</surname>
               <given-names>KAREN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773549357</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773549358</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Chicago</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1w6t9hg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>We are facing unprecedented environmental challenges, including global climate change, large-scale industrial development, rapidly increasing species extinction, ocean acidification, and deforestation – challenges that require new vocabularies and new ways to express grief and sorrow over the disappearance, degradation, and loss of nature. Seeking to redress the silence around ecologically based anxiety in academic and public domains, and to extend the concepts of sadness, anger, and loss, Mourning Nature creates a lexicon for the recognition and expression of emotions related to environmental degradation. Exploring the ways in which grief is experienced in numerous contexts, this groundbreaking collection draws on classical, philosophical, artistic, and poetic elements to explain environmental melancholia. Understanding that it is not just how we mourn but what we mourn that defines us, the authors introduce new perspectives on conservation, sustainability, and our relationships with nature. An ecological elegy for a time of climatic and environmental upheaval, Mourning Nature challenges readers to turn devastating events into an opportunity for positive change. Contributors include Glenn Albrecht (Murdoch University, retired); Jessica Marion Barr (Trent University); Sebastian Braun (University of North Dakota); Ashlee Cunsolo (Labrador Institute of Memorial University); Amanda Di Battista (York University); Franklin Ginn (University of Edinburgh); Bernie Krause (soundscape ecologist, author, and independent scholar); Lisa Kretz (University of Evansville); Karen Landman (University of Guelph); Patrick Lane (Poet); Andrew Mark (independent scholar); Nancy Menning (Ithaca College); John Charles Ryan (University of New England); Catriona Sandilands (York University); and Helen Whale (independent scholar).We are facing unprecedented environmental challenges, including global climate change, large-scale industrial development, rapidly increasing species extinction, ocean acidification, and deforestation – challenges that require new vocabularies and new ways to express grief and sorrow over the disappearance, degradation, and loss of nature. Seeking to redress the silence around ecologically based anxiety in academic and public domains, and to extend the concepts of sadness, anger, and loss, Mourning Nature creates a lexicon for the recognition and expression of emotions related to environmental degradation. Exploring the ways in which grief is experienced in numerous contexts, this groundbreaking collection draws on classical, philosophical, artistic, and poetic elements to explain environmental melancholia. Understanding that it is not just how we mourn but what we mourn that defines us, the authors introduce new perspectives on conservation, sustainability, and our relationships with nature. An ecological elegy for a time of climatic and environmental upheaval, Mourning Nature challenges readers to turn devastating events into an opportunity for positive change. Contributors include Glenn Albrecht (Murdoch University, retired); Jessica Marion Barr (Trent University); Sebastian Braun (University of North Dakota); Ashlee Cunsolo (Labrador Institute of Memorial University); Amanda Di Battista (York University); Franklin Ginn (University of Edinburgh); Bernie Krause (soundscape ecologist, author, and independent scholar); Lisa Kretz (University of Evansville); Karen Landman (University of Guelph); Patrick Lane (Poet); Andrew Mark (independent scholar); Nancy Menning (Ithaca College); John Charles Ryan (University of New England); Catriona Sandilands (York University); and Helen Whale (independent scholar).</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue:</title>
                     <subtitle>She Was Bereft</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CUNSOLO</surname>
                           <given-names>ASHLEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2011, I was bereft. I was at a loss intellectually and emotionally. I felt adrift in waves of sadness, grief, loss, and pain, unanchored from my life, isolated from those around me, and unsure of how to process what I was experiencing. It was a sense of almost abyssal sorrow, without an idea of how to move forward, or how to see beyond the edges, the fringes of these feelings. It was a grief I did not expect or anticipate. Yet it was there waiting for me in the morning when I awoke, there at night as I drifted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>To Mourn beyond the Human</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CUNSOLO</surname>
                           <given-names>ASHLEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection is about loss. It is about grief. And it is about mourning. But it is also about understanding absence, sense of place, and the spectral haunting that comes from more-than-human loss. It is about elegies and auguries, melancholy and transformation, and about different ways of knowing and being in the world that stretch beyond solely human bodies into the sensuous experiences of the more-than-human world(s). It is about traces and memories and awareness beyond the human. It is about decentring subjectivities, healing environmental grief, and living connectivity and interdependency. It is about mourning that resists the artificial separation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Mourning the Loss of Wild Soundscapes:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Rationale for Context When Experiencing Natural Sound</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KRAUSE</surname>
                           <given-names>BERNIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historically, natural soundscapes have been recorded in fragmented, decontextualized formats, the emphasis focused on the abstraction of single species’ animal voices intentionally removed from their more holistic and informative acoustic fabric. This older model, first expressed in the late nineteenth century when recording technologies were in their infancy, became an act of faith by the 1930s when ornithologists first applied the parabolic dish primarily to the capture of bird song and calls. The 1935 recording of the ivory-billed woodpecker in a Georgia swamp by Arthur Allen and Peter Kellogg from Cornell’s Macaulay Library of Natural Sound fixed a course that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Environmental Mourning and the Religious Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MENNING</surname>
                           <given-names>NANCY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We don’t grieve abstractly; we mourn particular losses of people, places, animals, objects, and ideas to whom and to which we are attached. These losses range from the most direct to those grasped only in the historical imagination. The death of a pet, the paving over of a favourite childhood playsite, the roadside body of the deer we just hit with our car, river gorges obliterated by dam-building projects, mountaintops removed by mining, once-familiar landscapes permanently transformed by nuclear contamination, night stars obscured by light pollution, and the absence of buffalo moving freely across the Great Plains are all grievable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Mourning Ourselves and/as Our Relatives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Environment as Kinship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRAUN</surname>
                           <given-names>SEBASTIAN F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to begin this exploration with three statements about mourning and the environment. The first two are related to the longstanding discussion about buffalo in Yellowstone National Park. Because they are suspected of being exposed to brucellosis, the state of Montana has engaged in a variety of plans and strategies to kill these buffalo upon entering its territory. Activists, both Native and non-Native, have long protested these practices. As part of their argument for better treatment of the buffalo, they have been portraying the buffalo in ways that show similarities in these animals to human behaviour. One buffalo behaviour</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>In the Absence of Sparrows</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WHALE</surname>
                           <given-names>HELEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GINN</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANKLIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Colourful flocks and feathered shapes make their way across a page. They are moving yet motionless, left to hang forever from a branch, their trajectory of flight suspended in time. The illustrations are from Hume and Walters’s 2012<italic>Extinct Birds</italic>, said to be the first study to document every avian species’ demise to have occurred over the last thousand years. As this volume demonstrates, extinction haunts our time as never before. The extinction that pervades popular nature-writing and the environmental sections of our newspapers, and which confronts us through screens, is not about the past. The blurry shot of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Where Have All the Boronia Gone?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Posthumanist Model of Environmental Mourning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RYAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN CHARLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scented or brown boronia (<italic>Boronia megastigma</italic>) is a slender shrub endemic to the South-West corner of Western Australia. Said to possess a “heady, sentimental perfume” (Parker 1962, 4), the fragrant blossom is found in the heath lands and eucalypt forests between Busselton and Albany, south of the capital city Perth. Bearing small brown and yellow flowers toward the end of winter (late July–September in Western Australia), boronia was collected in the wild, shipped by train, and sold as an ornamental by Perth streetsellers in the early to mid-1900s. In 1947, novelist and columnist James Pollard (1900–1971) wrote of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Losing My Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>Landscapes of Depression</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANDILANDS</surname>
                           <given-names>CATRIONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In June 2010 my marriage ended; in November my mother died (both my mother and my marriage had been suffering significant decline for some time). In February 2011 I sold my little house on the Niagara Escarpment; at the end of June, my daughter and I moved into a nice townhouse in the west end of Toronto. The first thing I did was plant a garden, only a fragment of what we had had in the country but a good gesture toward the possibility of taking root in this new place. I transplanted some of my favourite herbs and flowers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Climate Change as the Work of Mourning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CUNSOLO</surname>
                           <given-names>ASHLEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was five, a pond and thicket area down the street from my house was filled in and levelled while I was away. I remember coming home and finding my beloved ecosystem denuded of all greenery, and completely empty of the beavers and their dam, the minnows, the birds, and the countless rabbits and squirrels that had been a comforting and valued presence. I was devastated, consumed and overcome by grief and loss. I did not want to eat, or play, or go to school. I felt as though I had lost something deeply important, and intimately a part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Auguries of Elegy:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Art and Ethics of Ecological Grieving</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARR</surname>
                           <given-names>JESSICA MARION</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the trailer for artist Chris Jordan’s film<italic>Midway</italic>, viewers are invited to “Come … on a journey through the eye of beauty, across an ocean of grief … and beyond” (2013) as he documents the trash-filled bellies of baby albatrosses, dead after being fed plastics from the Pacific “Gyre” by their unwitting parents. Jordan further states that “<italic>Midway</italic>explores the plight of the Laysan albatross plagued by the ingestion of our plastic trash. Both elegy and warning, the film explores the interconnectedness of species, with the albatross on Midway [Island] as a mirror of our humanity” (2013). Jordan is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Making Loss the Centre:</title>
                     <subtitle>Podcasting Our Environmental Grief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARK</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DI BATTISTA</surname>
                           <given-names>AMANDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As members of a large interdisciplinary environmental studies faculty at York University, we are continually confronted by the devastating effects of environmental loss and by the inability of our community of scholars, students, and activists to grieve for these losses in meaningful ways. In our teaching practices, we uncover systemic forms of violence against both humans and the more-than-human world and risk encouraging abject despair as we struggle to resist hegemonic Western capitalist narratives of progress. While the extinction of species across the globe, the violence of resource extraction, and the consequences of our daily consumptive practices are inscribed on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Emotional Solidarity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ecological Emotional Outlaws Mourning Environmental Loss and Empowering Positive Change</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KRETZ</surname>
                           <given-names>LISA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ecological crisis provides no shortage of evidence for justified mourning. For a non-exhaustive list, consider the following: overpopulation (more than 200,000 people added every day); global warming (global ice cap melting, sea level rise, increasing catastrophic natural disasters); deforestation (32 million acres annually); unsustainable agriculture¹ (the abominable treatment of non-human animals aside, current farming practices are responsible for 70 per cent of the pollution of United States rivers and streams); unsustainable transportation (a single car emits 12,000 pounds of carbon dioxide every year in the form of exhaust; in the United States cars emit roughly the same amount of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Solastalgia and the New Mourning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALBRECHT</surname>
                           <given-names>GLENN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the global environment changes at an exponential rate, we need novel Earth-related concepts to give expression to our feelings about such change. I have created a psychoterratic (psyche-earth) typology of Earth-related emotions and feelings that captures the field as it has evolved in past and contemporary nature and place writing (Albrecht 2012a; Albrecht 2013). I have now located my concept of solastalgia (Albrecht 2005) within this psychoterratic typology. Solastalgia was created by me to fill a gap in our language of Earth-related emotions where people experience a deep form of existential distress when directly confronted by unwelcome change in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Wild Creatures</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANE</surname>
                           <given-names>PATRICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>316</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is sixty-five years ago, you’re ten years old and sitting on an old, halfblind grey horse.</p>
                     <p>All you have is a saddle blanket and a rope for reins as you watch a pack of dogs rage at the foot of a Ponderosa pine. High up on a branch a cougar lies supine, one paw lazily swatting at the air. He knows the dogs will tire. They will slink away and then the cougar will climb down and go on with its life in the Blue Bush country south of Kamloops.</p>
                     <p>It is a hot summer day. There is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1w6t9hg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
