<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3555.I78Z55 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Eiseley, Loren C., 1907–1977</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ecocriticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Biological Sciences</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Artifacts and Illuminations</book-title>
         <subtitle>Critical Essays on Loren Eiseley</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited and with an introduction by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LYNCH</surname>
               <given-names>TOM</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MAHER</surname>
               <given-names>SUSAN N.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803234031</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803240490</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">080324049X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska Paperback</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d9nqjg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Loren Eiseley (1907-77) is one of the most important American nature writers of the twentieth century and an admired practitioner of creative nonfiction. A native of Lincoln, Nebraska, Eiseley was a professor of anthropology and a prolific writer and poet who worked to bring an understanding of science to the general public, incorporating religion, philosophy, and science into his explorations of the human mind and the passage of time.</p>
         <p>As a writer who bridged the sciences and the humanities, Eiseley is a challenge for scholars locked into rigid disciplinary boundaries.<italic>Artifacts and Illuminations</italic>, the first full-length collection of critical essays on the writing of Eiseley, situates his work in the genres of creative nonfiction and nature writing. The contributing scholars apply a variety of critical approaches, including ecocriticism and place-oriented studies ranging across prairie, urban, and international contexts. Contributors explore such diverse topics as Eiseley's use of anthropomorphism and Jungian concepts and examine how his work was informed by synecdoche. Long overdue, this collection demonstrates Eiseley's continuing relevance as both a skilled literary craftsman and a profound thinker about the human place in the natural world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LYNCH</surname>
                           <given-names>TOM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHER</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Acknowledged as one of the most important twentieth-century American nature writers, Loren Eiseley was a widely admired practitioner of creative nonfiction, a genre that, in part due to his example, has flourished in recent decades. Contemporary nature writers regularly cite Eiseley as an inspiration and model. General readers, as well, appreciate Eiseley’s eloquent, complex, and informative essays; devoted readers have helped keep Eiseley continuously in print since his books first began appearing more than a half century ago. Clearly, Eiseley is a writer who matters.</p>
                     <p>As many observers lament, current environmental and other problems require a public and media that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“The Bay of Broken Things”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Experience of Loss in the Work of Loren Eiseley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HANSON</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When he was a boy, Loren Eiseley recalls in<italic>All the Strange Hours</italic>, he for a time had the habit of whittling small crosses out of wood, decorating them with liquid gilt, and then erecting them atop the graves of birds he’d buried in the lot behind his house. He even went so far as to inter the printed obituaries of people who had died in heroic or tragic circumstances. These graves, too, were marked with a golden cross. “One day,” he writes, “a mower in the empty lot beyond our backyard found the little cemetery and carried off all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“Never Going to Cease My Wandering”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley and the American Hobo</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOWNS</surname>
                           <given-names>M. CATHERINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1926 or thereabouts, young Loren Eiseley and his friends from high school hopped a freight in California (Christianson,<italic>Fox</italic>50–54).¹ One of their number was, in the slang of Eiseley-the-boy’s favorite author Jack London, a<italic>profesh</italic>, a boy who had jumped trains in previous acts of derring-do. Perhaps in earlier years he had enticed Eiseley on short runs from the freight yards of Lincoln, Nebraska, where they were living, to the next town, but this California trip was a real adventure. Their trip had the hallmarks of boys’ rough play and concomitant bad planning. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“The Places Below”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mapping the Invisible Universe in Loren Eiseley’s Plains Essays</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHER</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the 1940s and 1950s, essayist Loren Eiseley was conscious that he was inventing a new form of nonfiction essay, one that could embrace the depths of time that geology, evolutionary biology, and astrophysics had revealed to the modern world. Trained in anthropology, with expertise in paleontology and archaeology, Eiseley often finds himself pondering the mysteries of time and space, the shifting landscapes of epic gestation, the “strange transmutation” of cartographic imagination, and “the inner forest” of the collective unconscious (<italic>Night</italic>206, 207). Positioning himself within a literary line of descent that commences with Thoreau, Eiseley aligns himself to a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Unearthing Urban Nature:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley’s Explorations of City and Suburb</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRYSON</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Loren Eiseley used the compelling landscapes of his native Great Plains as well as the arid West as both setting and subject for his poetic yet scientifically rigorous explorations of evolution, natural history, and the human condition. But as a literary naturalist, Eiseley also mined the urban environment for inspiration and recognized the importance of analyzing nature close at hand in city and suburb in a rapidly urbanizing world, in which more than 50 percent of the world’s population now lives in cities.</p>
                     <p>This essay explores how the physical environment and natural history of city and suburb serve multiple (and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Anthropomorphizing the Essay:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley’s Representations of Animals</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOARDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHLEEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>“Anthropomorphizing</italic>: the charge of my critics.” With these abrupt words, Loren Eiseley began a one-paragraph notebook entry defending his representations of animals and animal-human relationships from the attacks of real and imagined detractors. On the day of the entry — January 22, 1970 — Eiseley was in the midst of a productive late-career period:<italic>The Unexpected Universe</italic>had recently been published,<italic>The Invisible Pyramid</italic>was about to appear, and no doubt Eiseley was in the process of assembling and revising the essays — most of them previously published — that would compose<italic>The Night Country</italic>. In addition, he was drafting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“The Borders between Us”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley’s Ecopoetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LYNCH</surname>
                           <given-names>TOM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Loren Eiseley’s literary reputation today rests almost exclusively on the significance of his nonfiction nature essays, which deservedly stand as influential exemplars of creative nonfiction science and nature writing. However, in his early years as an undergraduate at the University of Nebraska, Eiseley had the reputation as an important and promising poet, and he published poetry in a range of literary journals. Most notably, his work appeared in the earliest editions of<italic>Prairie Schooner</italic>, whose editorial staff he joined in 1927, the year after it began publication. And, not limited to his own school’s journal, he published in a variety</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Lessons of an Interdisciplinary Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley’s Rhetoric of Profundity in Popular Science Writing and “Two Cultures” Pedagogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOSSIN</surname>
                           <given-names>PAMELA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From an early age, Loren Eiseley lived his life betwixt and between various kinds of “two cultures” experiences: the two linguistic worlds of his parents’ disparate communication styles; the distinct realms of private thought and public expression; the separate but concentric spheres of personal and professional discourses; and the two intellectual and academic domains traditionally described as “<italic>the</italic>two cultures” — the poetic, imaginative, and humanistic versus the technical, rational, and scientific.¹ Driven to explore both sides of such cultural differences, Eiseley observed, valued, and experimented with each approach separately. Over time, he developed vital skills of empathy and analysis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Artifact and Idea:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley’s Poetic Undermining of C. P. Snow</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PITTS</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY ELLEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Loren Eiseley often scrawled questions and poems in the margins of texts that he read. Indeed, two years before the publication of Thomas S. Kuhn’s<italic>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</italic>, which footnotes<italic>The Firmament of Time</italic>, Eiseley wrote that “the intellectual climate of a given period may unconsciously retard or limit the theoretical ventures of an exploring scientist” (<italic>Firmament</italic>61). Keenly aware of the limitations imposed by a worldview, Eiseley responded formally in “The Illusion of the Two Cultures” to C. P. Snow’s pronouncement that scientific and literary cultures are so polarized that they fail utterly to communicate. Thus began</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Spirit of Synecdoche:</title>
                     <subtitle>Order and Chaos Contend in the Metaphors of Loren Eiseley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CASON</surname>
                           <given-names>JACQUELINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The way we read the past shapes our present and future, and the genius of Loren Eiseley’s evolutionary metaphors remains relevant to current cultural and ecological issues. William Zinsser describes the sixties as the “golden era of nonfiction” (56). Eiseley’s books sold well after World War II, when the reading public developed an appetite for works that dealt directly with reality, preferring nonfiction to novels and short stories. W. H. Auden read everything of Eiseley’s he could lay his hands on (15). Yet in spite of a loyal and diverse following, Eiseley has yet to receive critical attention commensurate with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>In a Dark Wood:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dante, Eiseley, and the Ecology of Redemption</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LIOI</surname>
                           <given-names>ANTHONY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a midsummer night in 1985, I sit around a campfire with a dozen other high school students on the beach of Hardwood Island in the Bay of Maine, listening to professors from Case Western and the Yale School of Forestry read an essay: “The Star Thrower,” by Loren Eiseley. Eiseley, we learn, was an anthropologist who moonlighted as one of the finest nature writers of the twentieth century. Natural history is important to us. For the last two weeks, we have been through ecology boot camp all over Maine. We have caught the stench of anaerobic decomposition in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Emerson and Eiseley:</title>
                     <subtitle>Two Religious Visions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEIDENBAUM</surname>
                           <given-names>JONATHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Central to Emerson and the transcendentalists is a sense of sheer astonishment in the face of existence, a receptivity to nature as fresh and original as “Adam early in the morning” — to steal a phrase from Whitman (<italic>Leaves</italic>95). The invitation to witness the universe “with new eyes” was not lost on Emerson’s countless literary and philosophical progeny (<italic>Essential</italic>39). Chief among these is Loren Eiseley, the anthropologist, author, and bone hunter who perceived his whole life to be a religious pilgrimage and who saw “deep mystery in the heart of a simple seed” (<italic>All</italic>141;<italic>Firmament</italic>8). The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Epic Narratives of Evolution:</title>
                     <subtitle>John Burroughs and Loren Eiseley</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MERCIER</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1961 Loren Eiseley was awarded the prestigious John Burroughs Medal for<italic>The Firmament of Time</italic>, joining the ranks of distinguished authors of natural history such as Ernest Thompson Seton, Rachel Carson, Joseph Wood Krutch, and Roger Tory Peterson. Indeed, both Burroughs (1837–1921) and Eiseley (1907–77) belong to a long list of writers who imaginatively delve into environmental explorations, forging connections to ecological and evolutionary dynamics. Surely, their writings cannot escape influences from a long history of previous nature works, from Gilbert White’s discursive firsthand observations on his beloved Selbourne, to Charles Darwin’s profound theories of evolution, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Eiseley and Jung:</title>
                     <subtitle>Structuralism’s Invisible Pyramid</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NIZALOWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his essay “Loren Eiseley’s<italic>Immense Journey</italic>,” Andrew J. Angyal celebrates the revered nature writer’s unconventional public stance: “As Eiseley warns his readers repeatedly, he is not a spokesman for conventional science. Instead, he is a poet-shaman, a wizard-alchemist who adopts the disguise of a changeling” (70). The roots of this unorthodox self-definition are found in the depth psychology of Carl Jung. There are two central tenets of Jung’s philosophical system that range throughout Eiseley’s writing: the importance of the collective unconscious in shaping the structures of human intelligence and the essential dualism of human culture and experience.</p>
                     <p>Beginning with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>From the American Great Plains to the Steppes of Russia:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loren Eiseley Transplanted</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRESCHINSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>DIMITRI N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Loren Eiseley was born in Lincoln, Nebraska, under the open skies of the Great Plains, and except for a brief business trip to England in 1951, never left the American mainland (see Christianson,<italic>Fox</italic>298). Had he traveled to the steppes of southern Russia, he would probably not have felt out of place, recognizing in the gently rolling hills of the countryside the flat, treeless terrain of his childhood. The difference between the Plains and the steppes is to a large extent linguistic.</p>
                     <p>The reference to transplantation in the title of this essay is, of course, a metaphor for literary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9nqjg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
