<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>French Philosophy Today</book-title>
         <subtitle>New Figures of the Human in Badiou, Meillassoux, Malabou, Serres and Latour</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WATKIN</surname>
               <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474414739</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474414746</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1474414745</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Christopher Watkin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1bh2hjp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Alain Badiou, Quentin Meillassoux, Catherine Malabou, Michel Serres and Bruno Latour: this comparative, critical analysis shows the promises and perils of new French philosophy's reformulation of the idea of the human.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>French philosophy today is laying fresh claim to the human. This is not to be mistaken for an exercise in winding back the clock, nor is it a return to previous ideas of the human, much less a coordinated ‘human turn’. It is a series of fundamentally independent and yet strikingly simultaneous initiatives arising across the diverse landscape of French thought to transform and rework the figure of the human. Whereas the latter decades of the twentieth century adopted a decidedly critical and cautious approach to the question of ‘the human’, imprisoning it within the iron bars of scare quotes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Alain Badiou:</title>
                     <subtitle>Formalised Inhumanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Alain Badiou the twentieth century was ‘haunted by the idea of changing man, of creating a new man’ (<italic>S</italic>20/<italic>Cen</italic>8) with communism and fascism, humanism and antihumanism each offering its vision of a transformed humanity. At the beginning of the twenty-first century Badiou offers us his own account of transformation that both remains (or so he claims) within a materialist frame and yet dusts off and reworks motifs seemingly from a bygone religious age: immortality, grace, resurrection and miracle. If, as these terms already hint, Badiou’s reworking of the human is not a simple case of either accepting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Quentin Meillassoux:</title>
                     <subtitle>Supreme Human Value Meets Anti-anthropocentrism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading the philosophy of Quentin Meillassoux gives one an appreciation of what it must be like to ride a donkey in a state of inebriation: in the attempt not to fall off on one side it is very easy to find oneself sliding down the other. It is easy to think, on the one hand, that Meillassoux’s arguments are all spectacular, unheard-of and revolutionary, or to assume, on the other hand, that he is playing a game with his reader, and cannot possibly mean what he says in earnest. Neither of these readings is true or fair, and Meillassoux’s approach</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Catherine Malabou:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Plastic Human</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first two chapters we saw that Badiou and Meillassoux each make a particular, determinate human capacity the gatekeeper of full-orbed humanity: for Badiou it is the capacity for affirmative thought and for Meillassoux it is the capacity to think the eternal principle of factiality. Such host capacity² accounts of the human struggle both with defining humanity so as not to exclude some of those least able to raise their voices in protest and also with the subtleties of an anthropocentrism from which they consider themselves freed. We also saw that, despite their claims to materialism, neither Badiou nor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Catherine Malabou:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Epigenetic Human</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This second of two chapters on neurological transformations of the human will focus on epigenesis, a particularly fruitful notion for the elaboration of a non-reductive materialist account of the self. At the end of the previous chapter I drew a distinction between the mind–brain problem and the self–brain problem; in the present chapter I will take up that distinction in order to pursue the question of the identity of self (rather than the mind or brain) over time. In the previous chapter I considered how Malabou can overcome the tethering of the question of humanity as such to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Michel Serres:</title>
                     <subtitle>Universal Humanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Chapter 4 we saw how Malabou in<italic>Avant demain</italic>opens the door to the possibility of an eco-synaptic account of personhood and selfhood which moves beyond the problematic way in which her earlier work tethers the human to the ‘host substance’ of the brain. Furthermore,<italic>Avant demain</italic>moves towards a more situated, complex figure of the human being taking into account the various co-written narratives in which each human being is entangled, as well as (and on equal terms with) the synaptic encoding of memories and the allied capacity for recall. This move towards a more situated, ecological notion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Bruno Latour:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translating the Human</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the universal humanism of Michel Serres we saw both a development and a change of direction from the accounts of the human elaborated by Badiou, Meillassoux and Malabou. Whereas the figure to emerge in the thought of Badiou and Meillassoux relies on the host capacity of thought, Malabou moves away from determinate capacities but, in her early work at least, seems to favour a host cerebral substance of human personhood. Serres’s account of the human, by contrast, is multi-modal: he combines de-differentiation with a recognition of determinate capacities, and also develops a narrative account of humanity as part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any attempt to draw links between and comparatively evaluate such a diverse range of thinkers as those I have discussed in this volume must necessarily be partial, both in the sense of incomplete and also in the sense of motivated by particular commitments and ideas at the expense of others. The analysis in this book has indeed been partial, although in its defence the main target of its critique has been partiality. The foregoing analysis has sought to expose and remedy the partiality of those accounts of the human which rest, in the final analysis, on a determinate host capacity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2hjp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
