<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">N8217.D94L39 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dwellings in art</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dwellings</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Art, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Unmaking of Home in Contemporary Art</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LAUZON</surname>
               <given-names>CLAUDETTE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442649828</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781487514679</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1whm8v6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In a world where the notion of home is more traumatizing than it is comforting, artists are using this literal and figurative space to reframe human responses to trauma. Building on the scholarship of key art historians and theorists such as Judith Butler and Mieke Bal, Claudette Lauzon embarks upon a transnational analysis of contemporary artists who challenge the assumption that ‘home’ is a stable site of belonging. Lauzon’s boundary-breaking discussion of artists including Krzysztof Wodiczko, Sanitago Sierra, Doris Salcedo, and Yto Barrada posits that contemporary art offers a unique set of responses to questions of home and belonging in an increasingly unwelcoming world. From the legacies of Colombia’s ‘dirty war’ to migrant North African workers crossing the Mediterranean, The Unmaking of Home in Contemporary Art bears witness to the suffering of others whose overriding notion of home reveals the universality of human vulnerability and the limits of empathy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Unmaking Home</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Picture two steel barricades, the kind you might expect to see blocking access to a street or public area during a political rally. The barricades are approximately twenty feet apart, and strung between them are two rows of twelve cords, one row at calf height and the other about four feet off the ground. The first impression might be of an enormous institutional cot whose frame and mattress have ominously disappeared, except that the cords are festooned like clotheslines with everyday household objects connoting a kind of itinerant domesticity (dish towels, a rug, a stuffed bunny, battered suitcases, a bedroll,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>An Unhomely Genealogy of Contemporary Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fifteen years ago, historian Kerwin Lee Klein issued a scathing report on what he termed the advent of the “memory industry” – the exponential growth of memory as a key vector of concern in the arts and humanities. And indeed, a collective turn to memory – variously referred to as an industry, a boom, an avalanche, and a crisis – undeniably began to materialize in both Western culture and critical discourse in the late 1990s.¹ As elaborated by Andreas Huyssen, this turn can be mapped along three trajectories: the rejection of modernity’s blind trust in progress and development, the articulation of anxiety around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Art of Longing and Belonging</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In New York in 2003, Polish-American artist Krzysztof Wodiczko exhibited<italic>Dis-Armor</italic>, a high-tech wearable communications instrument equipped with video camera, microphone, speakers, and LCD screens broadcasting stories of alienation and cultural displacement, designed to facilitate public testimony and eventual (re)integration into the social body. The same year, Mexico City–based Spanish artist Santiago Sierra represented Spain at the 50th Venice Biennale with<italic>Wall Enclosing a Space</italic>and<italic>Covered Word</italic>, an installation that saw the national pavilion bricked in and accessible only through the back entrance, and only to those who presented a Spanish passport. In their diverse art practices, both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Unhomely Archives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lida Abdul’s video<italic>Housewheel</italic>(2003) follows the Afghani artist as she walks and runs through the streets of inner-city Los Angeles, dragging a doll-sized white plaster house behind her with a rope. As it is jolted along, the house becomes dented, chipped, and battered; within minutes, it is reduced to scattered, abandoned pieces. Created during the Taliban regime while Abdul was living in exile, the work is a poignant performance of Gaston Bachelard’s observation that homes “are in us as much as we are in them.”¹ As much as we consider (or long for) home as a space that we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Biennial Culture’s Reluctant Nomads</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In October 2007, Doris Salcedo performed another sort of archaeological dig when she occupied the massive space of the Tate Modern’s Turbine Hall with<italic>Shibboleth</italic>, a 548-foot fissure that snakes its way along the length of the floor, beginning as a hairline crack and at times gaping to expose what appears to be a bottomless crevasse, lined with concrete and chain-link fencing. A complex meditation on the experience of immigration that simultaneously evokes the often treacherous experience of crossing borders and the “negative space” occupied by migrants within the increasingly policed borders of the European Union, the work seems determined</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1whm8v6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
