<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h097q</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8007.F87 1987</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Future Indicative</book-title>
         <subtitle>Literary Theory and Canadian Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited and with an Introduction by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moss</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1987</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615998</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615998</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1987</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6t2m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Description not available.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="258"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Presence of Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOSS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Future Indicative: Literary Theory and Canadian Literature. University of Ottawa Symposium. April 25 to 27, 1986. The title worked well—as a rubric under which to gather; as a non-proscriptive label of activities; as a summary of the symposium’s achievement. As a book title it works well, too. The implications it carries of change, commitment, and the prophetic are, perhaps, even more appropriate to a book.</p>
                     <p>Book titles are important. They provide the parentheses within which we read as an activity separable in mind from other things. The symposium relayed its title to the book and here we are. Do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Writer Writing, Ongoing Verb</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOWERING</surname>
                           <given-names>GEORGE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KROETSCH</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>EDITED BY</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHELLENBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>BETTY A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Things feel right tonight. We’re at the midway point between writing papers and polishing them into a book. This is the best part, gathering together, listening to each other, having a good time. I don’t think I need to introduce George Bowering and Robert Kroetsch. They will speak for themselves.</p>
                     <p>Kroetsch and I are in similar positions, in that we’re both academics and we’re both writers, and so we have the problem that in recent years we’ve heard the terminology of theory used, and we’ve read it, and we’ve heard our students using it, and we’ve had to learn it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Structuralism/Post-Structuralism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language, Reality and Canadian Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GODARD</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My dilemma is that of Scheherazade, for I speak under the threat of forced closure. Like hers, mine is an endless tale, the saga of the “new new criticism” of Canadian literature. Such is the evolving nature of my subject that, even as I speak, it slips away from me. The thread of my narrative will be unravelled when I stop. Presenting their poststructuralist readings of Canadian literature, other critics will add new episodes to chapters or introduce new characters and new points of view. Such is the fate of a historical narrative about a contemporary phenomenon. Endings are elusive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Question of the Corpus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethnicity and Canadian Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LORIGGIO</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCESCO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are, of course, many reasons why ethnic writing should interest anyone whose field is literature, even before he or she makes the association with the Chinatowns or the Little Italys or the native groups that are or may be part of his or her everyday life. To start with, ethnic texts exist. They are published, appear, in journals, anthologies, are reviewed. And in literature, no less than in any other domain, phenomena have a way of enduring. They call for recognition, and sooner or later we cannot avoid stumbling on them.</p>
                     <p>This most elementary of gestures—mere acknowledgment—would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reading for Contradiction in the Literature of Colonial Space</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MURRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>HEATHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have been writing of cadence as though one merely had to hear its words and set them down. But that’s not true, at least not in my experience. There is a check on one’s pen which seems to take hold at the very moment that cadence declares itself. Words arrive, but words have also gone dead.</p>
                     <p>To get at this complex experience we must begin from the hereness, the local nature of cadence. We never encounter cadence in the abstract; it is insistently here and now. Any man aspires to be at home where he lives, to celebrate communion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Signs of the Themes:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Value of a Politically Grounded Semiotics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOLDIE</surname>
                           <given-names>TERRY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a number of years I have been researching the images of native peoples in Canadian, Australian, and New Zealand literatures. I was surprised by the uniformity of these images, both across different cultures and across time. At first I thought this primarily a reflection of genre. But then I recognized that the image of the indigene represents a much larger issue.</p>
                     <p>From the beginning to the present, the image of the Indian and Inuk in Canadian culture exists within a limited semiotic field, in which the image, the signifier, has at best a tenuous relationship with the implied signified,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Importing Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>Feminist Theory and Canadian Women Writers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NEUMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>SHIRLEY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Leaving Regent’s Park, Peter Walsh blames Clarissa Dalloway for “what she had reduced him to—a whimpering, snivelling old ass. But women, he thought, shutting his pocket-knife, don’t know what passion is” (Woolf 1964, 89). At this moment, when his knife cuts so decisively through the question of women and passion and refolds within its sheath, a voice singing at the entrance to Regent’s Park Tube Station interrupts Peter’s anger. It sings “weakly,” and “shrilly,” a “voice of no age or sex” and “with an absence of all human meaning” (90). But, as the narrator’s consciousness displaces Peter Walsh’s, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Listen to the Voice”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dialogism and the Canadian Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRACE</surname>
                           <given-names>SHERRILL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The importance of Mikhail Bakhtin for literary scholarship does not reside in his often carelessly applied notions of carnival and polyphony. Bakhtin’s primary significance lies in his dialogism, that theory of discourse which enables him to establish, chart, and identify so many of the ways in which literary forms coincide with other diachronic systems of human communication. His theory of discourse is, in fact, an epistemology, even an ontological category (“<italic>To be,</italic>” writes Bakhtin, “means<italic>to communicate,</italic>” 1984, 287),¹ and it is a vital method for analyzing, not only texts, but concepts of literary canon, language acquisition, social identity, culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lacan:</title>
                     <subtitle>Implications of Psychoanalysis and Canadian Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMERON</surname>
                           <given-names>BARRY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper is an enactment of theory. It constitutes a series of beginnings about the implications and appropriations of theory: the implications of the relationship between psychoanalysis and (Canadian) literature, the ways in which each of these discourses—concerned as they both are with seeking meaning through narration and with the construction of the subject in and by language/discourse/culture—is implicated in the other as its “<italic>otherness-to-itself,</italic>its<italic>unconsciousness</italic>” (Felman 1982, 10), and my appropriations of theory and theorists. It is a paper everywhere traversed by other languages, other critical texts/discourses/scenes, other rhetorical strategies. Of necessity, too, my text is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reconstructing Structuralism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Theme-Text Model of Literary Language and F. R. Scott’s “Lakeshore”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STEELE</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Theme-Text model of literary structure, a theory developed by Alexander Zholkovsky and Ju. K. Sčeglov, combines certain traditional critical concepts—rigorously redefined—with a set of systematic postulates for their practical use. In recent years, arguments and counterarguments advanced by structuralists and post-structuralists have indicated that neither the superimposition of pre-conceived structures on literary texts nor the sceptical rejection of the meaning of literary conventions offers a sound basis for literary theory. The Theme-Text model rests, as it were, on a more productive middle ground. Its main premise is that the artistic message of any TEXT¹ has a structure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>History and/as Intertext</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HUTCHEON</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The context of this examination of history and/as intertext is what I see as the paradoxes, not to say contradictions, of what we seem to want to call “postmodernism” in both artistic practice and theoretical discourse. Postmodernism in both areas is fundamentally paradoxical: in both, we find masterful denials of mastery, totalizing negations of totalization. The conventions of discourse are used and abused, inscribed and subverted, asserted and denied. This is the context in which I want to look at what I see as the literary equivalent of postmodern architecture. What we usually label as postmodernist in literature today, though,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Language and Silence in Richardson and Grove</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TURNER</surname>
                           <given-names>MARGARET E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Settling and writing the New World means coming to terms with its ontological status and constructing its discourse. There is a pause or stillpoint in the migration from the fixed and placed culture of Europe to the new setting, in this case Canada—a moment which is disconnected from the Old World and as yet unconnected to the New. That stillpoint between cultures is charged with questions of structure and meaning, and finds a reflection in literature, in language, in human being itself. Absence and silence accompany the migrant suspension between cultures, and underlie the writing of this continent.¹</p>
                     <p>John</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rewriting Roughing It</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THURSTON</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Susanna Moodie did not write<italic>Roughing It in the Bush.</italic>In fact,<italic>Roughing It in the Bush</italic>was never written. Susanna Moodie and<italic>Roughing It in the Bush</italic>are interchangeable titles given to a collaborative act of textual production whose origin cannot be limited to one person or one point in time. This activity is ongoing. It is not merely a matter of the interpretation or reception of<italic>Roughing It.</italic>The process for which this text is the focus involves its actual production. Susanna Moodie’s is only one hand among the many involved in this collaborative activity. In this paper,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bakhtin Reads De Mille:</title>
                     <subtitle>Canadian Literature, Postmodernism, and the Theory of Dialogism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAVELL</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A number of Canadian critics—Frank Davey, Bruce Powe, and Paul Stuewe among them—have recently argued that Canadian criticism has reached an impasse. While the thematic criticism which has characterized writing on Canadian literature is acknowledged to have played a necessary part in the articulation of a Canadian literary identity, that criticism has been unable to respond adequately to the formal nature of the texts about which it seeks to speak (as Russell Brown, among others, has argued). As a solution to this impasse, these critics have proposed a re-orientation towards formalism—towards “literature as language and . .</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Reader as Actor in the Novels of Timothy Findley</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SEDDON</surname>
                           <given-names>ELIZABETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the novelist experiments with narrative techniques the reader, necessarily, becomes actively engaged in the process of discerning patterns and perceiving meanings. Within the context of reader response theory this paper explores the narrative layering in the novels of Timothy Findley and the structuring of texts that consciously anticipate the role of the reader. Implicit in this reading of Findley’s work is a tripartite model of reader response theory that includes a self-consciously constructing writer, a self-referentially deconstructing reader, and the enigmatic text of their mutual exchange. While the theory of the reader’s response has tended to be based on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Blown Figures and Blood:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Feminist/Post-Structuralist Reading of Audrey Thomas’ Writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DORSCHT</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN RUDY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Blank pages, comic strips, quotations, jokes, dreams, rhymes, newspaper clippings, ads, etymologies, multiple selves, silence: what we have traditionally referred to as the writing of Audrey Thomas is obsessed with the contextual, contradictory meanings, and meaninglessnesses, of words, with the ways subjectivity is represented, in fact present only, in and as language. When I say “the writing of Audrey Thomas” then, I mean to point out the duplicity of the phrase. The words “the writing of Audrey Thomas” may refer to those texts which, because of our particular ideology of literary production, we say have been written by Audrey Thomas,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reconstructing the Deconstructed Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Reading of Robert Kroetsch’s What the Crow Said</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOEPPNER</surname>
                           <given-names>KENNETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do we read a novel which is self-consciously post modern? If, as Paul de Man suggests, “a literary text simultaneously asserts and denies the authority of its own rhetorical mode, and . . . poetic writing is the most advanced and refined mode of deconstruction” (1979, 17) then, as Leitch says, “<italic>literary</italic>texts deconstruct themselves; they are always already deconstructed whether the author (or critic) realizes it or not” (1983, 187). Kroetsch’s<italic>What the Crow Said</italic>(1979), generally read as an example of the already deconstructed narrative “eroding the old forms and certainties” (MacKendrick 1979, 137), or as “an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Present Tense:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CLOSING PANEL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCOBIE</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOWERING</surname>
                           <given-names>GEORGE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HUTCHEON</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KROETSCH</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The function, I suppose, of a final panel, at the end of a conference, is to have the last word. But if there’s one thing that we can learn from contemporary movements in theory, from that moment of theory in which we now find ourselves, it is that there’s no such thing as the last word: no summation, no totalizing formula, no closure. And the reason that there’s no last word is that there’s no first word either: no source, no origin, no In Principio Erat Verbum. Instead, we’re all stuck somewhere in between, in the process of translation, trying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6t2m.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
