<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8btr</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3279. H94 G3613 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Husserl, Edmund, 1859-1938</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Heidegger, Martin, 1889-1976</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hermeneutics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Life</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Self-Understanding and Lifeworld</book-title>
         <subtitle>Basic Traits of a Phenomenological Hermeneutics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GANDER</surname>
               <given-names>HANS-HELMUTH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">TRANSLATED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DRAKE</surname>
               <given-names>RYAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RAYMAN</surname>
               <given-names>JOSHUA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253025555</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253026071</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253026075</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005w6h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What are the foundations of human self-understanding and the value of responsible philosophical questioning? Focusing on Heidegger's early work on facticity, historicity, and the phenomenological hermeneutics of factical-historical life, Hans-Helmuth Gander develops an idea of understanding that reflects our connection with the world and other, and thus invites deep consideration of phenomenology, hermeneutics, and deconstruction. He draws usefully on Husserl's phenomenology and provides grounds for exchange with Descartes, Dilthey, Nietzsche, Gadamer, Ricoeur, and Foucault. On the way to developing a contemporary hermeneutical philosophy, Gander clarifies the human relation to self in and through conversation with Heidegger's early hermeneutics. Questions about reading and writing then follow as these are the very actions that structure human self-understanding and world understanding.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="430"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TRANSLATORS’ INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>R. D.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>J. R.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Self-Understanding and Lifeworld: Basic Traits of a Phenomenological Hermeneutics</italic>, Hans-Helmuth Gander’s Gadamerian orientation leads him to think seriously about what is typically ignored or neglected in the current state of phenomenology, namely, our hermeneutic experience of reading. Phenomenological inquiry is most often directed to our experience of the world, to sense experiences, to questions of reality and knowledge, and to a lesser extent to thinking and understanding. But when we, as philosophers trained in or engaged with the continental tradition, are steeped so heavily in the reading of texts, this experience of reading demands its own proper explication as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Actually abiding philosophy can only become the true philosophy of its time, i.e., is powerful [<italic>mächtig</italic>] over its time.”¹ With this reflection, in which Martin Heidegger expresses a maxim of his thinking, he binds himself to a tradition within which Aristotle as much as Augustine, Kant, Hegel, Kierkegaard, or Nietzsche can be named. They all found themselves challenged in their thinking by the questions of their time to a type of critical contemporaneity, which sought to posit a diagnosis of their respective historical situations with the means of philosophy. Even if the boundaries are fluid and overstepping them appears unavoidable,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART ONE Introductions]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One is to write one’s first sentence in such a way that the reader will want, without fail, to read the second sentence. So reads the advice that William Faulkner imparted to anyone who wishes to embark on the adventure of writing a text. Truthfully, this is no easy demand to fulfill, especially if one considers that—regarded from outside—at first something entirely arbitrary belongs to every beginning. And if it is adequate to satisfy the Faulknerian precept, it thus remains that such a beginning in every case possesses something compelling or seductive, though not compulsory in the strict</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>ON THE SEARCH FOR THE CERTAINTY OF THE ‘I’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to disclose the problem area of self-understanding in a more farreaching way, in the following the ground that founds and bears all knowing, and presents in the concept of the<italic>lifeworld</italic>one of the central challenges for philosophical thinking, is shown. According to Kant’s famous formula, philosophical thinking—and in this sense, philosophy—is “<italic>rational knowledge from concepts</italic>.”¹ From a hermeneutical perspective it is to be noted, however, that the philosophical analysis of concepts to follow is defined by what Manfred Riedel calls “the aim of clarifying the contents of experience and sense, which are already laid out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>ON LIFE IN LIFEWORLDS:</title>
                     <subtitle>CRITICAL CONSIDERATIONS OF HUSSERL’S PHENOMENOLOGY OF THE LIFEWORLD</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The understanding of reality brought into our approach orients itself to that which has long since become indigenous to philosophy in the concept of the lifeworld.¹ If Gadamer’s dictum applies, that a statement is “always an answer,”² the enormous resonance that this coinage has—in such a way that the concept after all became, without further ado, a part of our everyday and common language—offers a material indication of a constellation of problems in the air, as it were, and focusing itself in it as in a burning lens.³</p>
                     <p>The high “value of sympathy”⁴ that the expression ‘life world’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>THE HERMENEUTICAL TURN:</title>
                     <subtitle>HEIDEGGER’S CRITICAL DIALOGUE WITH HUSSERLIAN PHENOMENOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The lifeworld as the pretheoretical world in which we live—with a view to the question of human self-relations, how are we to make it adequately accessible to a philosophical thematization? This question is all the more urgent insofar as the critical objections that have arisen in the course of the discussion of Husserl’s last great transcendental meditation are taken as valid. That the objection against the Husserlian conception shows itself to be more than a facile detection of mistakes is something of a triviality in the face of the circumstance that here the high road of modern philosophy has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>THE EXPERIENTIAL STRUCTURE OF THE SELF:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARD A HERMENEUTICS OF FACTICAL HISTORICAL LIFE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To gain the philosophical attitude that appears necessary from out of the hermeneutical turn of phenomenology for an analysis of determinate human life as facticity means, to begin with, as Pöggeler puts it, “to break away from or shut off the machinery of Husserl’s phenomenological reductions.”¹ Instead of wanting to penetrate into a deep layer of the immutable ideal “I” on the path of reductions, phenomenological hermeneutics forms its approach by recurring to<italic>pretheoretical experiences,</italic>from which it works on its ontological analysis of structure by means of the interpretation of concrete appearances. In the context of discussions of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>APPLICATION—DESTRUKTION—HISTORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>HERMENEUTICAL SKETCHES OF A PHILOSOPHY OF THE SITUATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a hermeneutical problem of utilization [<italic>Anwendung</italic>], the application [<italic>Applikation</italic>] forms its own ontological sense of contribution of historical hermeneutics. Hans-Georg Gadamer in particular has stressed this with a view to the task of textual interpretation in this sense and he has exemplarily developed it in regard to its function in legal hermeneutics.¹ In the given context, to introduce this application structure in the discussion of the hermeneutics of facticity does not mean simply wanting to interpret Heidegger by way of Gadamer. Rather, as we shall see, a structural comportment is explicated, which, even though it is not made explicit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>OPEN END</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the hermeneutical demonstration that our never other than life worldly situated self-understanding is always already historical at the origin of its self-worldly significance, the factual analysis of Heidegger’s early work comes to an end, in that for one thing, it makes explicit the point of departure of phenomenological hermeneutics of factical historical life in the wealth of its structures. For another, beyond the fact of placing the starting point in life, the central question of his early work illuminates at the same time how “factical life-experience belongs in a wholly originary sense to the problematic of philosophy,”¹ in that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SUBJECT INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF NAMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>409</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005w6h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
