<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Facing the Other</book-title>
         <subtitle>John Paul II, Levinas, and the Body</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
               <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>de Malherbe</surname>
               <given-names>Brice</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175705</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905289</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Nigel Zimmermann</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf9gn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What is the significance of the body? What might phenomenology contribute to a theological account of the body? And what is gained by prolonging the overlooked dialogue between St. John Paul II and Emmanuel Levinas? Nigel Zimmermann answers these questions through the agreements and the tensions between two of the most important thinkers of the twentieth century. John Paul II, the Polish pope, philosopher, and theologian, and Emmanuel Levinas, the French-Jewish philosopher of Lithuanian heritage, were provocative thinkers who courageously faced and challenged the assumptions of their age. Both held the human person in high regard and did their thinking with constant reference to God and to theological language. Zimmermann does not shirk from the challenges of each thinker and does not hide their differences. However, he shows how they bequeath a legacy regarding the body that we would overlook at significant ethical peril. We are called, Zimmermann argues, to face the other. In this moment God refuses a banal marginalisation and our call to responsibility for the other person is issued in their disarming vulnerability. In the body, philosophy, theology, and ethics converge to call us to glory, even in the paradox of lowly suffering.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Malherbe</surname>
                           <given-names>Brice</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Should something be remembered about John Paul II three hundred years from now, it will surely be his anthropology and theology of the body.” These were Angelo Scola’s words when he taught us in the early nineties at the Pontifical John Paul II Institute for Studies on marriage and Family in the Lateran University in rome. The then-bishop of Grossetto, tuscany (at present Cardinal Archbishop of milan) spoke in his capacity as a thorough investigator of past and contemporary global culture, following in the steps of don Luigi Giussani’s eagerness to establish a solid dialogue between faith and culture. Both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book adds to a litany of works in recent years that argue for a theological significance of the body. It shares the sentiment of Matthew’s gospel that the theological meaning of the body exceeds outer apparel, even the language used to describe it or the metaphors with which it is dressed. It is indeed “more than clothes.” However, this book resists the temptation to merely propose a carnivalesque or reductionist postmodern account of the human person in which goodness and truth are tied to the pleasures of the body. Rather, the approaches of two notable twentieth-century thinkers are teased</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>John Paul II and Emmanuel Levinas:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Overlooked Dialogue of the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John Paul II has been declared a saint. With this declaration of extraordinary holiness, the Catholic Church calls for reflection upon the many contributions that John Paul II (Karol Wojtyla) made to various problems of the age in which he lived, which in the case of the twentieth century is a time of much war, blood, and conflict. Of the examples of friendship and dialogue in which Wojtyla engaged, an overlooked discourse is that which he held with Emmanuel Levinas, a Lithuanian-born French-Jewish intellectual. This particular dialogue cannot be understood without reference to religion, phenomenology, and postmodernity. Moreover, key publications</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>John Paul II’s Theology of the Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The place of the body in the thought of John Paul II is situated within a prolific literary legacy for philosophy and theology.¹ Here, his original contribution to theological anthropology will be of interest, specifically his development of a theology of the body.² This chapter has three sections. The first is on the formative influences upon the younger Karol Wojtyla, the second outlines his theological framework which accentuated his thought as Bishop of Rome, and the third looks closely at<italic>Man and Woman He Created Them</italic>. The latter was written while Wojtyla was Archbishop of Krakow, but presented and published</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Levinas, Alterity, and the Problem of the Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The place of the body is a problematic feature in the thought of Emmanuel Levinas. Here, it will be considered in light of his Jewish tradition and the ambiguity of the term “God” in his writings, as well as some theological responses. In both his major works,<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>and<italic>Otherwise Than Being</italic>, Levinas refers often to the body. In the former, he offers a concise description of its dual nature: “<italic>To be a body</italic>is on the one hand<italic>to stand</italic>[<italic>se tenir</italic>], to be master of oneself, and, on the other hand, to stand on the earth,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Eros and the Desirous Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A pressing contemporary problem is that of the relationship between<italic>eros</italic>and desire in the body. How does the dialogue between John Paul II and Levinas shed light on this problem? First, the problems of<italic>eros</italic>, desire, and sexual ethics are described in relation to the place of the body in these two theorists. Next, the sexual person will be studied as a realm of concrete problems for the body; and finally the problem of the body will be explored in light of Jean-Luc Marion’s thought, who crosses the boundaries between philosophy and theology. Marion owes a significant debt to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>On What is Given:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Gift-Logic of the Body</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The place of the body in John Paul II and Levinas has been studied in detail, as well as major themes that emerge from both, especially<italic>eros</italic>and sexual desire. It has been seen how the problematic understanding of the body in postmodern thought might be theologically situated. While consideration was given to that which is<italic>desired</italic>in the body, this chapter considers what is<italic>given</italic>in the body. In addition to the dialogue between John Paul and Levinas, the work of Jean-Luc marion will be considered further, whose work explicitly crosses the divide between philosophy and theology. Marion’s “saturated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards a Theology of Embodied Alterity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three concluding judgments can be made based on the study of the place of the body in Karol Wojtyla/John Paul II and Levinas. First, that the fruitful dialogue between John Paul and Levinas has been largely overlooked. Second, John Paul and Levinas’ approaches to the body are discordant (more on this below). Third, John Paul’s account of the body is a positive theological development that is made clearer and enhanced by reading Levinas. In consideration of these three judgments, a way is opened up that indicates how a theological approach to the body can be fruitfully developed. In fact, John</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9gn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
