<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX1795.P47 T44 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church and philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Faith and reason</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Theology Needs Philosophy</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lamb</surname>
               <given-names>Matthew L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813228396</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813228402</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d2dp79"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Theology Needs Philosophy brings together essays by leading theologians and philosophers on the fundamental importance of human reason and philosophy for Catholic theology and human cultures generally. This edited collection studies the contributions of reason, with its acquired wisdom, science, and scholarship, in five sections. Those sections are: (1) the inevitable presence and service of philosophy in theology; (2) the metaphysics of creation, nature, and the natural knowledge of God; (3) the history of Logos as reason in the fathers, in St. Thomas Aquinas, and Medieval Biblical commentaries; (4) the role of reason in Trinitarian theology, Christology, and Mariology; and finally (5) reason in the theology of Aquinas.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Need for Reason in Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAMB</surname>
                           <given-names>MATTHEW L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The studies in this book indicate the influences of human reason throughout Christian theological reflections on the teachings of Christian faith. The universality of this faith—proclaiming salvation to all races and peoples—requires that reflection on it draw upon the universality of the God-given light of human reason. Pope Francis in his first encyclical,<italic>Lumen Fidei</italic>, has taken up the theme of his predecessors in stating that the light of faith heals and elevates the light of reason.¹ Saint John Paul II and Pope Emeritus Benedict XVI learned from great Catholic minds, like those of Augustine and Aquinas, how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>All Theologians Are Philosophers, Whether Knowingly or Not</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOREROD</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theologians have many debts of gratitude owed to the life and prodigious work of Professor Ralph McInerny. He called attention to the need for a genuinely philosophical formation for any theologian committed to the truth of our Catholic faith and teaching. In this he was echoing many a papal warning.</p>
                     <p>Philosophers may live in their little world, but—as artists also do—they feel and influence their culture. Philosophy has some influence on what everybody thinks. Who would have suspected, at the beginning of the eighteenth century, how deeply the Enlightenment philosophers would change the world over the next decades?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Videtur quod non sit necessarium, praeter theologicam disciplinam, aliam doctrinam haberi:</title>
                     <subtitle>Legitimacy of Philosophy as an Autonomous Discipline and Its Service to Theology in Aquinas and Ralph McInerny</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’CALLAGHAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A volume on the importance of philosophy for faith and theology is certainly a legacy of my teacher and friend Ralph McInerny. I hope that I can do honor to him, not just as a friend or teacher, but as a colleague precisely on a topic of such great moment in McInerny’s thought, the role of philosophy in the life of faith. One of his last books,<italic>Praeambula Fidei</italic>, was a spirited defense of philosophy and the good it achieves in the life of faith, and thus for theology as reasoned reflection upon God’s revelation, what Aquinas called “<italic>sacra doctrina</italic>.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Theology and the Metaphysics of Creation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEWAN</surname>
                           <given-names>LAWRENCE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has for its general theme: the need of philosophy in theology.¹ My article invokes the legacy of a recently deceased colleague and friend, Ralph McInerny, one of whose last books was, in his own words, “a defense of a robust understanding of the teaching of St. Thomas Aquinas and of the Magisterium on<italic>Praeambula Fidei</italic>.”² By the “<italic>praeambula fidei</italic>” he means those truths concerning God, and first of all the truth of his very existence, which can be demonstrated by philosophy, and which are essential for the life of supernatural faith.</p>
                     <p>In proposing to speak about the importance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Concept of Nature:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophical Reflections in Service of Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOTERSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are numerous ways in which philosophy can be of service to theological education. There is something invaluable, for instance, in the art of making distinctions, and among the many ways of acquiring such facility, this skill is especially promoted by training in logic, philosophy of nature, and metaphysics. It is not just a matter of avoiding arbitrary distinctions without a basis in real differences but of devising distinctions that make their cuts between diverse natural kinds. Crucial to the theoretical justification for this activity is the notion that things have real natures that can be discovered by human inquiry.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>On Natural Knowledge of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aquinas’s Debt to Aristotle</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LONG</surname>
                           <given-names>STEVEN A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Here I will elaborate the Aristotelian foundations of the metaphysics and natural theology of St. Thomas Aquinas. In any consideration of the debt owed by Aquinas to Aristotle, the controverted question must necessarily arise as to what Aristotle himself accomplished. This has not infrequently been answered in the negative. That is, those who do not consider metaphysics to be a naturally knowable discipline with conclusions regarding God and the soul subject to demonstrative reason as such, apart from advertence to any revealed premise, will find it impossible to credit Aristotle as having so much as adverted to God rather than</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Logos as Reason and Logos Incarnate:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophy, Theology, and the Voices of Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DALEY</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of Pope Benedict XVI’s first serious clashes with the “chattering classes” represented by today’s media was his now-famous lecture to academic faculties of the University of Regensburg, in September of 2006. As you doubtless remember, that lecture was widely interpreted as a strong critique of Islam on religious grounds, and it inspired heated reactions—against him and against Christian institutions in general—all over the Muslim world. Actually, though, it was not a lecture on Islam and Christianity at all, but a subtle and carefully constructed discussion of faith and human reason. More explicitly, Benedict was really talking about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Are Aristotelian-Thomists Rationalists?</title>
                     <subtitle>On Thomism, the Praeambula Fidei, and Theological Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NUTT</surname>
                           <given-names>ROGER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I came to know Ralph McInerny through my participation in the conferences of the American Maritain Association. I always enjoyed the filial piety with which he spoke of his great teacher, Charles De Koninck. So I will move into my topic by considering some foundational insights from both De Koninck and McInerny. De Koninck begins an essay (translated into English by McInerny) with the words of an unnamed modern author who “wrote that he could not understand how some of the most intelligent people of his acquaintance could still believe the most<italic>afflicting foolishness</italic>they are taught by the Catholic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Philosophical Starting Points:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reason and Order in Aquinas’s Introductions to the Posterior Analytics, De Caelo, and Nicomachean Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WHITE</surname>
                           <given-names>KEVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To go by the first article of Aquinas’s<italic>Summa theologiae</italic>, as well as by the traditional order of seminary courses, the place of philosophy in theological education would seem to be before, or at least at, the beginning. To go by the<italic>Summa</italic>as a whole, and by the way in which theology is customarily taught, philosophy permeates theological education from beginning to end, although it is changed in doing so. Philosophy in theological education is a<italic>principium</italic>in two senses: it is both a point of departure and a continuing resource.</p>
                     <p>Philosophy is inquiry into the principles of things,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Tunc scimus cum causas cognoscimus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Medieval Endeavors to Know Scripture in Its Causes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BELLAMAH</surname>
                           <given-names>TIMOTHY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the outset of the<italic>Metaphysics</italic>, Aristotle says that “all men suppose what is called wisdom (<italic>sophia</italic>) to deal with the first causes (<italic>aitia</italic>) and the principles (<italic>archai</italic>) of things,” and that it is these causes and principles that he proposes to study in this work.¹ During the thirteenth century the recent recovery of Aristotle’s works of natural philosophy (<italic>Physics, Metaphysics, De anima, Meteora</italic>), resulted in an evolution of the understanding of causality, which in turn resulted in remarkable developments in biblical interpretation.² Especially at the universities of Paris and Oxford commentators reevaluated conventional anthropological presuppositions and reassessed the human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Ad aliquid:</title>
                     <subtitle>Relation in the Thought of St. Thomas Aquinas</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EMERY</surname>
                           <given-names>GILLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Relation occupies a position of paramount importance in the thought of St. Thomas Aquinas. Several central themes of his theology are based on his use of the category of relation, such as his theology of the Trinity (the divine person as subsistent relation), creation (the relation of God to the world), and the Incarnation (the relation of the divine and the human natures in Christ). Relation receives attention of a philosophical and a theological order.¹ The philosophical approach is well attested in Aquinas’s commentaries on the<italic>Physics</italic>and the<italic>Metaphysics</italic>of Aristotle. The theological interest explains why the most developed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Aquinas on the Procession of the Holy Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOYLE</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his memoir,<italic>I Alone Have Escaped to Tell You</italic>, Ralph McInerny spoke to the current state of philosophy, especially in Catholic institutions:</p>
                     <p>This habit of prescribing more of what has caused the problem is a mark of our age. Philosophers, aware that something has gone wrong in their discipline, do not see the need for a 180-degree turn. What are considered radical solutions, merely plunge us deeper into nihilism and relativism. In short, the culture and its philosophy have grown worse since 1879, and the remedy Leo XIII proposed remains the only cure. The human mind must again be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Christology of Disclosure in Robert Sokolowski</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MANSINI</surname>
                           <given-names>GUY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter seeks to honor the esteemed Ralph McInerny by exploring what Robert Sokolowski has to say about the role of philosophy in theology and theological education. He has addressed this issue many times, in many ways. I begin with some evidently sensible advice that he has given to seminary educators about philosophy. There follows a description of what he calls the “theology of disclosure.” Third, I gather up some of the “disclosures” he has made in Christology. Last, I try to press things just a little further in one or two matters Christological.</p>
                     <p>I will begin with an essay</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Ego sapientia:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Mariology of Laval Thomism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CESSARIO</surname>
                           <given-names>ROMANUS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter aims to illuminate the intercession of the Blessed Virgin Mary. It views what the Church holds about her maternal mediation as an application of Aristotelian efficient instrumental causality within the order of grace. Specifically, the chapter evokes the notion of “physical causality” that the grand Thomist tradition employs when speaking about the sacraments. While the crisis over instrumental causality reaches beyond the theology of the sacraments, one nonetheless recognizes it rather acutely there. This crisis stems from several sources, such as developments in both natural philosophy and theological method. It is wondrous to observe that several approaches to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Reflections on Ralph McInerny’s Dante and the Blessed Virgin Mary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLANNERY</surname>
                           <given-names>KEVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the second semester of the academic year 2005–6, Ralph McInerny was the Joseph Visiting Professor in the Faculty of Philosophy at the Gregorian University. The course was entitled<italic>Praeambula fidei</italic>and was basically an exposition of the book of the same title that came out later that year.¹ For at least a couple of years prior to that, Fr. Paul Mankowski and I had been meeting on Sunday evenings in order to translate<italic>The Divine Comedy</italic>to (or at!) each other, one canto per sitting; so, knowing of McInerny’s interest in Dante, we invited him to join us,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>Moderating the Magnanimous Man:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aquinas on Greatness of Soul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GUERRA</surname>
                           <given-names>MARC D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a still-influential book published sixty-three years ago, Harry Jaffa argued that St. Thomas Aquinas “mistakes Aristotle’s intention,” and for that reason Thomas endeavors to “save” the character of the<italic>Nicomachean Ethic</italic>’s magnanimous man “in accordance with what Thomas evidently considers a higher standard of perfection.”¹ The higher standard of perfection Jaffa has in mind is “Christian ethics,” as revealed in an epigram from Winston Churchill that Jaffa uses to open his book: “It is baffling to reflect that what men call honor does not correspond always to Christian ethics.” Jaffa’s argument is not simply that Aristotle’s account of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Charles De Koninck and Aquinas’s Doctrine of the Common Good</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WALSHE</surname>
                           <given-names>SEBASTIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PRAEM</surname>
                           <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles De Koninck taught Prof. McInerny at the University of Laval in Quebec in the mid-1950s, and (as those of us who knew him can attest) McInerny considered himself a disciple of De Koninck. In later years, McInerny would express ever-increasing gratitude to De Koninck for the formation he received in Thomistic thought, and was even responsible for editing and publishing the works of his former teacher as an expression of his gratitude.</p>
                     <p>While De Koninck taught and wrote on virtually every subject that occupied the mind of St. Thomas Aquinas: the philosophy of nature and of the soul, ethics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>Reading Aquinas’s Commentary on Aristotle’s Nicomachean Ethics:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Reply to Mark D. Jordan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KACZOR</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Numerous questions arise in connection with St. Thomas Aquinas’s commentaries on Aristotle. Aquinas devoted a great deal of time to these commentaries through his professional responsibilities focused on commenting on Scripture. In terms of overall volume, they constitute about 13 percent of his entire corpus, roughly matching the 13.5 percent of the<italic>opera omnia</italic>devoted to commenting on the Bible. Should these works be construed as theology or philosophy? What were Aquinas’s goals in writing them? Were they notes in preparation for writing the moral parts of the<italic>Summa theologiae?</italic>Were they expositions to provide his brother Dominicans a guide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering a Genuine Lover of Wisdom: The Impressive Legacy of Ralph McInerny</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NOVAK</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am afraid I never think of Ralph as “gone.” I am reminded of this every time I fly, when our plane climbs through thick clouds and comes out behind them where the sun is as present as ever, brilliant and blinding. Ralph is as present as the sun, even on cloudy days.</p>
                     <p>Did you hear about the female collie that gave birth to four pups along the roadside, and was arrested for littering? Ralph’s presence sharpens in me every time I hear a pun. A bad pun or a good one, Ralph loved them both. Ralph called one of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dp79.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
