<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Love and its Critics</book-title>
         <subtitle>From the Song of Songs to Shakespeare and Milton’s Eden</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bryson</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Movsesian</surname>
               <given-names>Arpi</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781783743483</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783743506</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Open Book Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael Bryson</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Arpi Movsesian</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1sq5vd6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is a history of love and the challenge love offers to the laws and customs of its times and places, as told through poetry from the Song of Songs to John Milton’s Paradise Lost. It is also an account of the critical reception afforded to such literature, and the ways in which criticism has attempted to stifle this challenge. Bryson and Movsesian argue that the poetry they explore celebrates and reinvents the love the troubadour poets of the eleventh and twelfth centuries called fin’amor: love as an end in itself, mutual and freely chosen even in the face of social, religious, or political retribution. Neither eros nor agape, neither exclusively of the body, nor solely of the spirit, this love is a middle path. Alongside this tradition has grown a critical movement that employs a 'hermeneutics of suspicion', in Paul Ricoeur’s phrase, to claim that passionate love poetry is not what it seems, and should be properly understood as worship of God, subordination to Empire, or an entanglement with the structures of language itself – in short, the very things it resists. The book engages with some of the seminal literature of the Western canon, including the Bible, the poetry of Ovid, and works by English authors such as William Shakespeare and John Donne, and with criticism that stretches from the earliest readings of the Song of Songs to contemporary academic literature. Lively and enjoyable in its style, it attempts to restore a sense of pleasure to the reading of poetry, and to puncture critical insistence that literature must be outwitted. It will be of value to professional, graduate, and advanced undergraduate scholars of literature, and to the educated general reader interested in treatments of love in poetry throughout history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>California State University Northridge</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="576"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Sources and Languages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Love and Authority:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love Poetry and its Critics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Love has always had its critics. They range far and wide throughout history, from Plato and the Neoplatonists, to the Rabbinic and Christian interpreters of the Song of Songs, from the clerics behind the savage Albigensian Crusade, to the seventeenth-century English Puritan author William Prynne, who never met a joy he failed to condemn. Love has never lacked for those who try to tame it for “higher” purposes, or those who would argue that “the worst evils have been committed in the name of love”.¹ At the same time, love has always had its passionate defenders, though these have more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Channeled, Reformulated, and Controlled:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love Poetry from the Song of Songs to Aeneas and Dido</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Susan Sontag, in her now-classic essay “Against Interpretation”, protests against a form of criticism which reshapes texts like the Song of Songs into new and ideologically compliant forms:</p>
                     <p>Interpretation […] presupposes a discrepancy between the clear meaning of the text and the demands of (later) readers. It seeks to resolve that discrepancy. The situation is that for some reason a text has become unacceptable; yet it cannot be discarded. Interpretation is a radical strategy for conserving an old text, which is thought too precious to repudiate, by revamping it. The interpreter, without actually erasing or rewriting the text, is altering</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Love and its Absences in Late Latin and Greek Poetry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After Virgil and Ovid, the poetry of love begins to fade into the background of the literary scene. Many of the later Latin poets, like Claudian and Sidonius of the late fourth and the fifth centuries, follow Lucan rather than Ovid, in a poetic tradition that puts love aside entirely: “Lucan’s poem, programmatically, declares the absence of ‘love’ at the outset. The<italic>Bellum Civile</italic>has no ‘love’. It does not have an<italic>Iliadic</italic>part […] or an<italic>Odyssean</italic>part. It has only war”.¹ Lucan’s epic<italic>The Civil War</italic>(or<italic>Pharsalia</italic>) is a lengthy account of the defeat of Pompey the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>The Troubadours and Fin’amor:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love, Choice, and the Individual</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Erich Auerbach’s view, “for the Provençal poets and the [Italian] poets of the new style [<italic>dolce stil novovv</italic>], ‘high love’ was the only major theme”.¹ Speaking of<italic>die hohe Minne</italic>(what French scholars call<italic>amour courtois</italic>, and English scholars “courtly love”), Auerbach gives voice to a critical consensus that over the last century-and-a half has dominated our understanding of the origins and development of western love poetry. Both the consensus, and Auerbach, are wrong.</p>
                     <p>Start with adultery. Start, at least, with the idea of adultery. Breaking the rules, doing something you are not supposed to do. Doing some<italic>one</italic>you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Fin’amor Castrated:</title>
                     <subtitle>Abelard, Heloise, and the Critics who Deny</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The brief flowering of the troubadours helps us to understand the love story, in twelfth-century Paris, of Peter Abelard and Heloise d’Argenteuil, who lived the passions and the dangers often spoken of in the poetry of the age. The letters between Abelard and Heloise are among the world’s most vibrant embodiments of<italic>fin’amor</italic>,¹ as well as its most tragic testaments to the violence and determination of those who would prevent men and women from living and loving as they choose. Written around 1128, this Latin correspondence tells a story of love that is both of the body and the mind.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Albigensian Crusade and the Death of Fin’amor in Medieval French and English Poetry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the beginning of the thirteenth century, everything changed. In its earliest days, the mood in Provençe was ebullient and defiant. It radiates from the tale of<italic>Aucassin et Nicolette</italic>, which, though written in the northern dialect of Picardy, “gives a faithful picture”¹ of the attitudes held in Occitania—sensual, anticlerical, and fiercely independent:</p>
                     <p>In Paradise what would I do? I do not seek to enter there, but only wish for Nicolette, my sweet friend that I love so much. For no one goes to Paradise except the kinds of people I will tell you about now: there is where</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>The Ladder of Love in Italian Poetry and Prose, and the Reactions of the Sixteenth-Century Sonneteers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the changes that are beginning to appear in fourteenth-century England, by the same time in Italy the sublimation and spiritualization of love has long established itself as the dominant theme of European poetry, a theme that is exported to England in the sixteenth century, briefly sweeping aside much of the spirit we have seen developing in Chaucer. To understand how and why this happened, we will have to circle back and spend a little time with Plato.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps the single most basic element of Platonic metaphysical thought is the separation between the world we see and the world we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Shakespeare:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Return of Fin’amor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The true recovery of the troubadour tradition comes with Shakespeare, the poet and playwright who “towers like a mountain peak above the surrounding foothills, but is one substance and structure with them”.¹ Most truly “of the English strain”, Shakespeare’s sonnets are a reversing, even a mocking of the Petrarchan mode and the Neoplatonic sublimation of passion into worship that sometimes marks the poetry of Sidney. Rather than treating the individual as a means to an end, the lowest rung on the ladder of love, Shakespeare’s sonnets reverse this emphasis, valuing the individual as an end in itself, not a means</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Love and its Costs in Seventeenth-Century Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme of love as resistance to authority is transformed and amplified in the lyric poetry of John Donne and Robert Herrick. In work filled with a sense of the fragility and shortness of life, these poets contribute to an ethos that has come to be known by the name<italic>carpe diem</italic>, a phrase made famous by Horace, “who in Ode, I. xi, tells his mistress that […] life is short, so they must ‘enjoy the day’, for they do not know if there will be a tomorrow”.¹ Horace’s line, “carpe diem quam minimum credula postero”² (“Seize the day, put</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Paradise Lost:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love in Eden, and the Critics who Obey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To choose is not so easy as it sounds. “All choice is frightening, when one thinks about it: a terrifying liberty, unguided by a greater duty”.¹ Choices open some doors, while closing others. New lives, new possibilities, often come at the expense of other lives now foreclosed or lost. The wages of<italic>choice</italic>are death, as every life leads, eventually, to that ending that may be the only true universal of the human experience—not the understanding or the experience of the end, but the physical cessation itself, the transition from animate to inert, from you to it. Authority figures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue.</title>
                     <subtitle>Belonging to Poetry: A Reparative Reading</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over fifty years ago, Susan Sontag described “the project of interpretation” as “largely reactionary, stifling”, and placed it in the context of “a culture whose […] dilemma is the hypertrophy of the intellect at the expense of energy and sensual capacity”, before concluding that “interpretation is the revenge of the intellect upon art”.¹ The situation does not seem to have improved in the intervening half-century. As Martin Paul Eve has very recently observed, “traditional literary criticism<italic>always coerces</italic>texts into new narrative forms”, as “its practitioners [read] to seek case studies suited for exegetic purpose”.² To come back to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5vd6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
