<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8c0t</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E169.12 .Y33 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectuals</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Popular culture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Stereotypes (Social psychology)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Year's Work in Nerds, Wonks, and Neocons</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>EBURNE</surname>
               <given-names>JONATHAN P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SCHREIER</surname>
               <given-names>BENJAMIN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253026187</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253026873</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253026873</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt20060h2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What happens when math nerds, band and theater geeks, goths, sci-fi fanatics, Young Republican debate poindexters, techies, Trekkies, D&amp;D players, wallflowers, bookworms, and RPG players grow up? And what can they tell us about the life of the mind in the contemporary United States? With #GamerGate in the national news, shows like The Big Bang Theory on ever-increasing numbers of screens, and Peter Orzsag and Paul Ryan on magazine covers, it is clear that nerds, policy wonks, and neoconservatives play a major role in today's popular culture in America. The Year's Work in Nerds, Wonks, and Neocons delves into subcultures of intellectual history to explore their influence on contemporary American intellectual life. Not limiting themselves to describing how individuals are depicted, the authors consider the intellectual endeavors these depictions have come to represent, exploring many models and practices of learnedness, reflection, knowledge production, and opinion in the contemporary world. As teachers, researchers, and university scholars continue to struggle for mainstream visibility, this book illuminates the other forms of intellectual excitement that have emerged alongside them and found ways to survive and even thrive in the face of dismissal or contempt.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="378"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>WORKING IN AND ON NERDS, WONKS, AND NEOCONS, THIS YEAR AND TO COME</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EBURNE</surname>
                           <given-names>JONATHAN P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHREIER</surname>
                           <given-names>BENJAMIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It says a lot about your intellectual life if you remember being pushed around for wearing glasses and reading books as a kid—or if you remember pushing around kids who wore glasses and read books. Such persecutions may have faded to a distant memory or persist as a lingering ordeal. But what was the appeal—or the pathology—of glasses and books in the first place? Perhaps you were a Young Republican and flourished on the debating club; perhaps you were the manager for the varsity sports team, more comfortable with a clipboard than a sports bra or jockstrap.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>WONK MASCULINITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALLEN</surname>
                           <given-names>DENNIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sometime during the summer of 2013, Rick Perry, then governor of Texas, began wearing glasses. Now, these were not just any glasses but a pair of very big, very obvious, black-framed spectacles reminiscent of Clark Kent, which the media, with some consistency, referred to as “nerd glasses.” Since Perry’s general self-presentation had up until then run toward an extremely traditional “man’s man” image, this change prompted considerable speculation in the press. Ultimately, the pundits’ consensus was that after a disastrous performance in the 2011 Republican primary campaign, including a debate in which he forgot one of his main talking points</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>SURFACE WORSHIP, SUPER-PUBLIC INTELLECTUALS, AND THE SUSPICIOUSLY COMMON READER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAXWELL</surname>
                           <given-names>WILLIAM J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Young nerds may rule at last, as the title of this book implies, but their public intellectual moms and dads have never felt less regal. By this I don’t mean, Richard A. Posner–style, that it’s all been downhill for such intellectuals practically since Wilhelm von Humboldt forced seminars, laboratories, and departments on the learned gentlemen of Prussia. At the start of his millennial plaint<italic>Public Intellectuals: A Study of Decline</italic>(2001), Posner defines his subject as “academics’ writing outside their field,” and attributes the regular failures of professors courting a general readership to the successes of academic freedom and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>STRATIGRAPHIC FORM:</title>
                     <subtitle>SCIENCE FICTIONS OF THE PRESENT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LIU</surname>
                           <given-names>WARREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the spirit of the other chapters in this volume, I’m interested in exploring what it might mean to read “nerdily,” and to think about the possibly productive results that might result from such reading. The object of my attention, John McPhee’s<italic>Annals of the Former World</italic>, could certainly be described as an exemplary work of nerd-like obsession, one painstakingly pieced together over the course of twenty years and incorporating four separate volumes.¹ But I am less interested in qualifying McPhee as a nerd than I am in articulating how my encounter with McPhee’s text has provided unexpectedly insightful new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>OBSESSION, PATHOLOGY, AND JUSTICE:</title>
                     <subtitle>NERDS, BODIES, WINSOR MCCAY, AND THE 1893 CHICAGO FAIR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRANT</surname>
                           <given-names>NATHAN L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shortly before 1900, the growing ability of the weekly newspaper comic strip to bend the imagery of the everyday soon made it a staple of modern American life, as was the case with film. Beginning in 1895, Richard Outcault’s Sunday strip<italic>The Yellow Kid</italic>, depicting a bald, barefoot boy who, through the solecisms printed on his shirt, eventually helped to sell the idea of war with Spain to Americans, appeared in both William Randolph Hearst’s New York Journal and Joseph Pulitzer’s<italic>New York World</italic>, becoming wildly popular toward the end of the century. With his class-bound abuses of English grammar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE NEOCONSERVATIVE IMAGINATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLASER</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIFER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I struggled to finish a monograph on Jews, race, and writing, I couldn’t help but feel that I was futilely circling the point. Yes, Jewish writers were preoccupied with questions of race and racialization after the rise of civil rights in America. Yes, many of these same writers (and the intellectuals who influenced them) grappled with their anxiety by speaking in the cadences of more marginalized and racially marked others. But these arguments never felt like they fully encompassed the sometimes messy politics of race at the heart of postwar Jewish life. My project, like those of the Jewish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>CONSERVATIVE AND INTERNATIONALIST:</title>
                     <subtitle>GEORGE S. SCHUYLER’S PULP FICTION AND THE IMPERIALISM OF THE OPPRESSED</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARZIOLI</surname>
                           <given-names>SARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the eve of the Italian invasion of the Kingdom of Ethiopia in 1935, the journalist and novelist George Schuyler poked fun at the tendency for African Americans to become passionately concerned with the fate of the last independent African nation. In his weekly “Views and Reviews” column for the Pittsburgh<italic>Courier</italic>, he depicts this passion for a faraway land as both ridiculous and unbelievable, its motives both striking and performative—a gesture of disdain that epitomizes Schuyler’s own complex relationship to black internationalism and anticolonialism. Schuyler was, in fact, one of the most famous black conservative intellectuals of his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>THE TURING TEST AND OTHER LOVE SONGS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLAVEY</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction to<italic>The Most Human Human: What Artificial Intelligence Teaches Us about Being Alive</italic>, Brian Christian relates an embarrassing anecdote about being alive and intelligent. Looking for love in all the wrong places, a psychologist and author named Robert Epstein finds himself entangled in a long-distance relationship with a woman he met through an online dating service. Ivana lived thousands of miles away and her English was spotty, but the two spark a connection and begin an extended correspondence nonetheless. It is only after several months of evasive and oddball answers to his requests to meet in person,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>SEX AND THE SINGLE NERD:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SCHIZO SAGA OF GENES, GENIUS, AND FINALLY GETTING SOME</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROOF</surname>
                           <given-names>JUDITH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the latter half of the nineteenth century, Sir Francis Galton, halfcousin of Charles Darwin and most remembered for his advocacy of eugenics (he coined the term), worked to define scientifically the phenomenon of genius. Using surveys and developing statistical methods as the basis for his anthropometric studies, Galton published<italic>Hereditary Genius</italic>in 1869. In a 1874 lecture, “On Men in Science, Their Nature and Their Nurture,” Galton queried, “What then are the conditions of nature, and the various circumstances and conditions of life,—which I include under the general name of nurture,—which have selected that one and left</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>NERDS IN CAPES:</title>
                     <subtitle>COURTLY LOVE AND THE EROTICS OF MEDIEVALISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAYLOR</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At any moment at Bryn Mawr College, a women’s liberal arts college just outside of Philadelphia, one might encounter undergraduates involved in a game of Quidditch, overhear a group speaking like pirates, or see a few students wearing long capes. These students are known as “Capies,” and they constitute a small but visible subculture on campus, listed on Unigo (an online guide to American colleges and universities) as one of Bryn Mawr’s top-ten curiosities.¹ Even fellow Bryn Mawr students see them as oddities—as elusive and strange outsiders who are extraordinarily dedicated to their obscure hobbies, as a community that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>COMIC BOOK KID</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SMITH</surname>
                           <given-names>SCOTT T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent conversation about comics, a friend asked me how I was able to keep separate the different identities of scholar and fan. The question troubled me. I am a medievalist by training, but I also regularly teach undergraduate courses on comics. Was the implication that my academic work was professional (scholar), while my interest in comics was more casual (fan)? Must<italic>scholar</italic>and<italic>fan</italic>be exclusive categories—and do they describe “identities” at all? The alignment between<italic>comics</italic>and<italic>fan</italic>in my friend’s question certainly implied a value judgment, as well as a distinction between different kinds of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>WALKING SIMULATORS, #GAMERGATE, AND THE GENDER OF WANDERING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAGEN</surname>
                           <given-names>MELISSA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines a new kind of video game, the walking simulator, and how it stages a conflict between old “hardcore gamer” culture and a newer perception of gaming as fundamentally mainstream, artistic, and diverse. This conflict is exemplified by the #GamerGate controversy, which exploded in the gamer community in August 2014, either in response to a lack of journalistic ethics or because of an undercurrent of vicious misogyny in gaming, depending on whom you ask. Among other things, it was an attempt to police the borders of gamer identity in the face of changing demographics and complementary erosions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>THE FAN AS PUBLIC INTELLECTUAL IN “RACEFAIL ’09”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CARROLL</surname>
                           <given-names>SIOBHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“All men are intellectuals,” Gramsci famously declared, “but not all men have in society the function of intellectuals.”¹ For scholars writing in the wake of Edward Said’s influential<italic>Representations of the Intellectual</italic>, that function has mainly been to serve as a “critical commentator addressing a nonspecialist audience on matters of broad public concern.”² While writers on public intellectualism acknowledge that university credentials are not a prerequisite for this kind of enterprise, for the most part their discussions describe a “person trained in a particular discipline . . . who is on the faculty of a college or university.”³ While such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>AUTISM, NERDS, AND INSECURITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>CHLOE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>326</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In December of 2012, the US government effectively lost what newspapers referred to as a “ten year battle” to extradite a Scottish systems analyst named Gary McKinnon so that he could face charges for committing, in the words of prosecution attorneys, “the biggest military computer hack of all time.”¹ McKinnon maintained that he hacked into NASA and US military computers in order to locate suppressed evidence of UFOs, a special interest of his. He claimed that government agencies were concealing evidence of UFO crashes, effectively hiding knowledge of abundant, clean, alien energy sources of potential benefit to humanity. McKinnon has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>PROFESSORS WITHOUT CHAIRS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LECKLIDER</surname>
                           <given-names>AARON S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “anti-intellectualism” emerged in the United States in the early decades of the twentieth century, appearing in 1911 in the wellknown (if now largely forgotten) radical John Spargo’s book,<italic>Sidelights on Contemporary Socialism</italic>. Spargo argued passionately that the revolution needed to be guided by the proletariat, not only by a bunch of blithely theorizing intellectuals who undeservedly claimed ownership of a socialist movement over which they had no rightful claim. Yet Spargo also acknowledged that the proletariat could not truly understand their condition without well-equipped intellectual guides. In contrast to those poseurs fomenting anti-intellectualism—the “lawyers without clients, authors</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt20060h2.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
