<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Theology in Language, Rhetoric, and Beyond</book-title>
         <subtitle>Essays in Old and New Testament</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lundbom</surname>
               <given-names>Jack R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175118</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227904084</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jack R. Lundbom</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf54j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Theology in Language, Rhetoric, and Beyond' places before a broad audience of students and general readers theological essays on both the Old and New Testaments. Theology is seen to derive from a number of sources: the biblical language, biblical rhetoric and composition, academic disciplines other than philosophy, and above all a careful exegesis of the biblical text. The essay on Psalm 23 makes use of anthropology and human-development theory; the essay on Deuteronomy incorporates Wisdom themes; the essay called "Jeremiah and the Created Order" looks at ideas not only about God and creation but also about the seldom-considered idea of God and a return to chaos; and the essay on the "Confessions of Jeremiah" examines, not the words that this extraordinary prophet was given by God to preach, but what he himself felt and experienced in the office to which he was called. One essay on "Biblical and theological themes" includes a translation into the African language of Lingala, which weaves together the story of early Christianity with the more recent founding of churches in Africa and Asia. Jack R. Lundbom argues eloquently through these essays that theology is rooted in biblical words, in themselves, in rhetoric and their different contexts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="218"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Permissions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lundbom</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Grace and Favor in the Old Testament:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hebrew ḥnn</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic meaning of the root<italic>ḥnn</italic>is “grace,” which is one of two primary translations for its cognate noun<italic>ḥēn</italic>. The noun is first a term of beauty. It denotes an aesthetically pleasing presentation or aspect of someone or something, and is properly the quality someone or something possesses. The response to this projection of beauty is also<italic>ḥēn</italic>, “favor.” The derived sense is used in Hebrew primarily for the pleasing impression made upon one individual by another. It is possible to show<italic>ḥēn</italic>to the beloved ruins of Jerusalem (Ps 102: 14–15[Eng 13– 14]), but this usage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Burning Anger in the Old Testament:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hebrew ⁴rh, yṣt, and yqd</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The verbs<italic>ḥarâ</italic>and<italic>ḥrr</italic>have the basic meaning “burn.”² Both most probably derive from a biliteral<italic>ḥr</italic>in Old Hebrew. Ugaritic<italic>ḥrr</italic>means “burn,” “scorch,” or “roast.”³ Akkadian erēru and arabic<italic>ḥarra</italic>also mean “burn” (although Rabin⁴ takes<italic>waḥara</italic>to be the real arabic cognate). The aramaic<italic>ḥrr</italic>of the Targumim (Pss 2: 12; 102: 4[3]; ezek 15: 4–5) has the meaning “ burn” or “be blackened, charred.” at Boghazköy,<italic>re-e-ú</italic>is attested as a canaanite loanword = *<italic>ḥre</italic>, “angry.”⁵</p>
                     <p>The verb<italic>ḥarâ</italic>occurs mainly in the qal with ’<italic>ap</italic>as the expressed or implied subject:<italic>ḥarâ</italic>’<italic>ap</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>God in Your Grace Transform the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme for the ninth Assembly of the World Council of Churches (WCC) at Porto Alegre, Brazil, “God in Your Grace Transform the World,” consisted of a prayer by the church that God in his infinite grace transform his world and ours.</p>
                     <p>The New Testament witness that God graciously sent Jesus Christ into the world has to be the preeminent transforming act overshadowing every other transformation, past or future. The gospel writer John says: “And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, full of grace and truth” (John 1:14). Paul too tells the church at Rome that “all have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Biblical and Theological Themes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Grace in the Old Testament is, first of all, a beauty or perceived beauty that is possessed. Genuine beauty is seen in the gracious woman (Prov 11:16), but charm can be deceitful (Prov 31: 30), as, for example, in harlots (Nah 3:4). A doe bounding through the forest is graceful (Prov 5:19). Even a stone can possess graceful beauty, but one must be on guard against bribes that are likened to it (Prov 17:8). The one having gracious speech will have the king as his friend (Prov 22:11), but gracious speech can also be a cover for deceit in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Deuteronomy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deuteronomy, the fifth book of the Pentateuch, is the Preeminent document on law and ethics in the Hebrew Scriptures / Old Testament (OT). Emanating from the late eighth or early seventh century BC, the major portion of the book (Deuteronomy 1–28) updates, supplements, and sermonizes on the Decalogue and Covenant Code of Exodus 20–23. Deuteronomy also differs in content from the so-called Priestly laws in Exodus, Numbers, and Leviticus, as well as the Holiness Code of Leviticus 17–26. The book has recognized parallels to preaching of the eighth-century prophets, particularly Amos and Hosea, stating climactically in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Yahweh Comes to Be King on Earth (Deut 33:2–5)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deuteronomy, before reporting the death of Moses in a final chapter (34), has included a Blessing of Moses (33), one of two old poems in a second supplement to the book (31–34), the other being the Song of Moses (32: 1– 43). The Song of Moses is a strident rebuke of Israel for chasing after other gods. With a concluding blessing on the twelve tribes (excluding Simeon), the book of Deuteronomy can now end on a calming note before Moses dies and Joshua replaces him as israel’s leader. The book of Genesis similarly ends with a Blessing of Jacob</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>And the Word of the Lord Came to Huldah</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My maternal grandmother’s name was Hulda: Hulda Ohlson. During my early years she stood before me as a towering figure. Forceful in word and deed, she had no identity crisis so far as I can tell. She knew who she was. Hulda also had what you would call presence—that is, you knew when she was in the room, just as you always knew when she was merely around the corner.</p>
                     <p>Hulda was a strong but not overpowering wife to my grandfather. Their marriage was dynamic—plenty of give and take, plenty of mutual help, plenty of love. There was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Jeremiah and the Created Order</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One may well pose the question whether Jeremiah had any thoughts at all on creation, living as he did on the eve of a calamitous destruction—people dying from sword, famine, and disease; the land he loved becoming an uninhabitable ruin; and the nation he loved tumbling headlong into inglorious demise. How much more we might learn from Second Isaiah, whose eloquence on creation compares with writers of Gen 1, Ps 104, and a handful of other biblical texts on the subject (Isa 40:21–31; 42:5–9; 43:1–7; 44: 1–5, 21–28; 45:12–18; 51:12–16). it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Confessions of Jeremiah</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Jeremiah we are accustomed to speak of the prophet’s confessions, so named because of their likeness to the<italic>Confessions</italic>of Saint Augustine. These are a singular legacy of Jeremiah, for in them the prophet is not so much speaking Yahweh’s word with power and passion, although some of this is definitely to be found in them, but rather telling us how he feels about what is going on, and what impact his preaching is having on him personally. We see in these confessions the other side of Jeremiah’s role as mediator and divine messenger, which is to bring concerns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Psalm 23: Song of Passage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One September evening after the nurse had gone out on an errand, I stood at George’s bedside alone. His face against the pillow had a strange pallor, and all the color was drained from his lips. I knew that the end was near. I felt his hands. They were cold, icy cold, and I held them to my breast, trying to warm them. “George, can you hear me, darling?” I whispered, my lips close to his ear. His eyelids fluttered, and I knew he had heard me. “Shall I read to you, darling?” I asked. I reached for the Bible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Mary Magdalene and Song of Songs 3: 1–4</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early on the first day of the week, while it was still dark, Mary Magdalene came to the tomb and saw that the stone had been removed from the tomb . . . Mary stood weeping outside the tomb. As she wept, she bent over to look into the tomb; and she saw two angels in white, sitting where the body of Jesus had been lying, one at the head and the other at the feet. They said to her, “Woman, why are you weeping?” She said to them, “They have taken away my Lord, and I do not know</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>All Great Works of God Begin in Secret</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The great New Testament scholar Johannes Weiss, in commenting on the dearth of information we possess about the beginnings of the Christian church, said, “it lies in the nature of things that the first beginnings of a religious movement are obscure, and hid from the eyes of contemporaries.”² Put into theological terms, I would say that it lies in the very nature of God to begin all great works in secret. That is what I want to speak to you about this evening. Throughout the Bible, and also in our own day, we see that great works of God begin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Theology in Language, Rhetoric, and Beyond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christian theology, which is discourse about God and things related to God, and divine revelation, which is discourse about God’s self-disclosures from individuals and communities that have come to believe them, possess two distinguishing characteristics: 1) both discourses, almost without exception, are proclamatory and certain, made in the assertive mode;² and 2) both discourses tend to become systematic in nature, due to a joining of faith assertions with philosophic inquiry.</p>
                     <p>That Christian theology be assertive—strongly and aggressively assertive—should occasion no surprise, since Christian preaching from earliest times has 1) centered on gospel proclamation (<italic>kerygma</italic>in acts 2: 14–</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf54j.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
