<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7pcf9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Medieval Hispanic Studies in Memory of Alan Deyermond</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Beresford</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Haywood</surname>
               <given-names>Louise M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Weiss</surname>
               <given-names>Julian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781855662506</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782040750</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk; Rochester, NY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Contributors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt284t3h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Professor Alan Deyermond was one of the leading British Hispanists of the last fifty years, whose work had a formative influence on medieval Hispanic studies around the world. There were several tributes to his work published during his lifetime, and it is fitting that this one, in his memory, should be produced by Tamesis, the publishing house that he helped establish and to which he contributed so much as author and editor right up to his death. The contributors to this volume are some of Professor Deyermond's former colleagues, doctoral students, and members of the Medieval Hispanic Research Seminar. Given Professor Deyermond's breadth of expertise, the span of the essays is appropriately wide, ranging chronologically from the thirteenth to the sixteenth century, and covering lyric, hagiography, clerical verse narrative, frontier balladry, historical and codicological studies. The volume opens with a personal memoir of her father by Ruth Deyermond, and closes with the draft of an unpublished essay found amongst Professor Deyermond's papers, and edited by his literary executor, Professor David Hook. Andrew M. Beresford is Reader and Head of Hispanic Studies at the University of Durham. Louise M. Haywood is Reader in Medieval Iberian Literary and Cultural Studies, and Head of the Department of Spanish and Portuguese at the University of Cambridge. Julian Weiss is Professor of Medieval &amp; Early Modern Hispanic Studies at King's College London.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="334"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alan Deyermond: A Memoir</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deyermond</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of my earliest memories of my father is of us both in his office in Westfield College. He is standing at the door, answering a knock from what sounds like a student, and I, aged probably about three and sitting in his chair, am taking advantage of his distraction to eat the bar of chocolate he keeps in his desk drawer.</p>
                     <p>I am struck by this memory, thinking back about my father, because of what it suggests about him. This was in the mid-1970s, two decades before the emergence of ‘Take Your Daughter to Work Day’, but it seemed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alan Deyermond, 1932–2009</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERESFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREW M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAYWOOD</surname>
                           <given-names>LOUISE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEISS</surname>
                           <given-names>JULIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alan Deyermond was one of the most prolific and influential hispanists of his generation, whose professional career spanned over five decades of teaching, research, and administration at the University of London, first at Westfield College then, following a college merger, at Queen Mary. It was at Westfield that he founded the renowned Medieval Hispanic Research Seminar (1967), and at Queen Mary that he started the Publications of the Medieval Hispanic Research Seminar (1995) and where, following his retirement, he became research professor and honorary fellow (1999). As a committed feminist and champion of women’s rights and equality, Alan was a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Sanctity and Prejudice in Medieval Castilian Hagiography:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Legend of St Moses the Ethiopian</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERESFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREW M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The legend of the black saint, Moses the Ethiopian (<italic>c</italic>. 330–405), offers a unique insight into the complexity not just of fourth-century asceticism, but of the evolution of popular attitudes towards questions of ethnic origin and somatic type in Christian tradition as a whole. Characterized by an overarching impression of duality, Moses stands partly as one of the many who followed in the footsteps of St Antony of Egypt, forsaking the corruption of society to lead a life of ascetic isolation in the desert, but partly also as an exception, remarkable not for his achievements in piety, but for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Image of the Phoenix in Catalan and Castilian Poetry from Ausiàs March to Crespí de Valldaura</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOASE</surname>
                           <given-names>ROGER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alan Deyermond discussed the phoenix in two important articles: one in Galician (2002), concerning four bestiary birds in Spanish medieval literature; and the other, in Castilian, on bestiary images in the Catalan poetry of Roís de Corella (2007: 119–31). My purpose is to expand upon this research within the confines of fifteenth-century Castilian and Catalan poetry, exploring the spectrum of symbolic meanings that the phoenix had, beginning with poems addressed to Lucrezia d’Alagno at the Neapolitan court of Alfonso the Magnanimous, surveying the Petrarchan image of the phoenix in Castilian poetry from Santillana to Boscán, examining this symbol in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>On the Frontiers of Juan Rodríguez del Padrón’s Siervo libre de amor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAYWOOD</surname>
                           <given-names>LOUISE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of Alan Deyermond’s work on sentimental romance concerned the various frontiers of the genre, be they generic or linguistic.¹ In this article, I wish to foreground the material frontiers of Juan Rodríguez del Padrón’s<italic>Siervo libre de amor</italic>(<italic>c</italic>. 1440) within its manuscript context as a participant text in a particular<italic>scriptum</italic>, ‘the unique presence that is the individual, concrete manuscript’ (Dagenais 1994: 129). The focus on the physical context of<italic>Siervo</italic>will permit me some reflections on generic relations and linguistic analogues. My approach is particularly informed by the lines pursued by Pedro M. Cátedra (1995), Emily Francomano</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Memory as Mester in the Libro de Alexandre and Libro de Apolonio</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAZBUN</surname>
                           <given-names>GERALDINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After more than a century of scholarship on the<italic>mester de clerecía</italic>, the second stanza of the<italic>Libro de Alexandre</italic>remains at the foundations of discussions about the literary and cultural significance of this poetic mode:¹</p>
                     <p>Mester traigo fermoso, non es de joglaría,</p>
                     <p>mester es sin pecado, ca es de clerezía</p>
                     <p>fablar curso rimado por la quaderna vía,</p>
                     <p>a sílabas contadas, ca es grant maestría. (2)</p>
                     <p>Manuel Milá y Fontanals (1874) and Marcelino Menéndez Pelayo (1913) first regarded the<italic>mester de clerecía</italic>as a learned poetic school, diametrically distinct from a<italic>mester de juglaría</italic>.² Scholars subsequently challenged this division, none</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Advancing on ‘Álora’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOOK</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alan Deyermond and I took different views over some points in the interpretation of the ballad of ‘Álora la bien cercada’, which occupied us on a number of train journeys into London in the early 1990s, although naturally we found common ground on some other aspects of it. The relevant paragraphs in his 1996 Kate Elder lecture at Queen Mary and Westfield College, as it then was, now constitute, alas, his final major contribution to the extensive commentary which this intriguing text has attracted, although brief observations also occur in later contexts (Deyermond 2001: 68).¹ In returning to ‘Álora’ (Smith</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Time is of the Essence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Essence, Existence and Reminiscence in Two Portuguese Poets</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RECKERT</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Time, like an ever-rolling stream (so E. M. Forster maintained), bears all her sons away unless they are very careful. Here I shall be looking at some ways of being careful that have commended themselves to two of the few Portuguese poets who have yet succeeded in breaking through the glass ceiling of their still rather unfashionable language and been admitted to the Western canon: Francisco Sá de Miranda (1481?–1558) and Luís de Camões (<italic>c</italic>. 1524–80).</p>
                     <p>For Antonio Machado, ‘toda la imaginería/ que no ha brotado del río’ was nothing but ‘barata bisutería’ (‘De mi cartera’, st. 4).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Gómez Manrique’s Exclamación e querella de la governación:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poem and Commentary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROUND</surname>
                           <given-names>NICHOLAS G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The collapse of Castilian royal authority in the 1460s challenged the wielders of power there to redefine in practice where, in relation to Enrique iv’s much-weakened monarchy, their interests and allegiances now lay. It also called in question the ethically and juridically grounded models of royal rule as sanctioned by providence, promoted among them by the secular court culture of Enrique’s father Juan ii. For most individuals, no doubt, this meant adjusting the theory to validate their newly identified interests – which was what happened collectively in the settlement eventually established by the Reyes Católicos. At the time, even so,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Misa de amor in the Spanish Cancioneros and the Sentimental Romance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SEVERIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHY SHERMAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alan Deyermond’s contribution to the study of the sentimental romance is so essential that, before he wrote his seminal essay on the genre in the medieval volume of his<italic>Literary History of Spain</italic>(1971), we used to call it the sentimental novel. To him I owe the inspiration for my book on the genre (2005), and this additional footnote to that book. When I categorized religious parody in the sentimental romance in that book, I did not include the category of the<italic>Misa de amor</italic>, although I made a passing reference to it. A rereading of the key texts of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>‘Manus mee distillaverunt mirram’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Essence of the Virgin and an Interpretation of Myrrh in the Vita Christi of Isabel de Villena</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TWOMEY</surname>
                           <given-names>LESLEY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alan Deyermond’s pioneering work on medieval Hispanic women writers began in the 1970s with the medieval volume of his<italic>A Literary History of Spain</italic>:</p>
                     <p>Writing in 1970, I gave half a page to (Leonor) López de Córdoba, seven lines to Florencia Pinar, and three lines of a footnote to Teresa of Cartagena. Yet this inadequate coverage is a good deal more than these authors receive in any other recent history of literature (most do not mention them at all), and it was indeed condemned as excessive by a Spanish reviewer.²</p>
                     <p>This article combines the study of one woman writer with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>‘Nos soli sumus christiani’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conversos in the Texts of the Toledo Rebellion of 1449</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOVAL</surname>
                           <given-names>ROSA VIDAL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late medieval Spain witnessed a series of religious, social, and political controversies following the mass conversion of Jews in the late fourteenth and early fifteenth centuries. While at first these conversions had been regarded as eminently desirable, even miraculous, by the 1450s there was a growing sense in some Christian circles that their effects had been deleterious, and they were the source of many grave problems (Nirenberg 2003: 137). The attempts to eradicate these perceived difficulties led to the establishment of the Inquisition, the expulsion of the Jews, and a division of the Christian community on the basis of blood,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Vernacular Commentaries and Glosses in Late Medieval Castile, ii:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Checklist of Classical Texts in Translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEISS</surname>
                           <given-names>JULIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present checklist is the second in a series devoted to documenting the scope of vernacular commentaries and glosses on Castilian literary and religious texts during the later Middle Ages, a transformative period in the history of vernacular literary culture. Although the vast majority of the works included derive from the fifteenth century, the chronological span of these lists runs from the mid-fourteenth (with Juan García de Castrojeriz’s commentary on Aegidius Romanus’<italic>De regimine principum</italic>) to the end of the post-incunable period (with works such as the parodic commentary on the<italic>Carajicomedia</italic>, composed 1506–19). The series starts with a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Games of Love and War in the Castilian Frontier Ballads:</title>
                     <subtitle>El romance del juego de ajedrez and El romance de la conquista de Antequera</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>YIACOUP</surname>
                           <given-names>ŞIZEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her overview of the symbolism of games in the<italic>romancero</italic>, Edith Rogers observes that the use of the game as a central motif ‘creates an atmosphere of tension and imminence of change’ relating to a shift of fortune or a reversal of the relative position of two adversaries, while at the same time serving as ‘a visible, condensed, localized expression of the emotional conquest’ involved in courtship (1972: 424). The following analysis seeks to develop Rogers’ theory by focusing on two frontier ballads,<italic>El romance del juego de ajedrez</italic>and<italic>El romance de la conquista de Antequera</italic>, and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>‘Esta tan triste partida’ (Conde Dirlos, v. 28a):</title>
                     <subtitle>maridos y padres ausentes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deyermond</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Edited by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hook</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is the text rescued from a group of thirteen battered sheets of A4 paper, consisting of page proofs from three separate works, reused by Alan Deyermond on their blank versos as was his laudable habit. It represents the surviving typescript of a lecture delivered by him in Oviedo in 2003, as the opening session of the<italic>Jornadas de Homenaje Universitario a Isabel Uria Maqua</italic>(15–16 October). This torn, dog-eared typescript (the pages were not contained in a folder or document wallet) is a typical specimen of what seems to have been his late<italic>modus operandi</italic>in preparing a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt284t3h.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TABULA IN MEMORIAM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
