<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DR83.2.L4T63 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Levski, Vasil Ivanov, 1837–1873</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Tomb</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Levski, Vasil Ivanov, 1837–1873</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Death and burial</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Revolutionaries</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Bulgaria</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bulgaria</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Bones of Contention</book-title>
         <subtitle>The living archive of Vasil Levski and the making of Bulgaria's national hero</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Todorova</surname>
               <given-names>Maria</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789639776241</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9786155211638</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Maria Todorova</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt128245"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is about documenting and analyzing the living archive around the figure of Vasil Levski (1837–1873), arguably the major and only uncontested hero of the Bulgarian national pantheon. The processes described, although with a chronological depth of almost two centuries, are still very much in the making, and the living archive expands not only in size but constantly adding surprising new forms. The monograph is a historical study, taking as its narrative focus the life, death and posthumous fate of Levski. By exploring the vicissitudes of his heroicization, glorification, appropriations, reinterpretation, commemoration and, finally, canonization, it seeks to engage in several broad theoretical debates, and provide the basis for subsequent regional comparative research. The analysis of Levski's consecutive and simultaneous appropriations by different social platforms, political parties, secular and religious institutions, ideologies, professional groups, and individuals, demonstrates how boundaries within the framework of the nation are negotiated around accepted national symbols.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="639"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about documenting and analyzing the living archive around the figure of Vasil Levski, arguably the major and only uncontested hero of the Bulgarian national pantheon. In the course of working on the problem, it became clear that this cannot be a finite task. The processes described, although with a chronological depth of almost two centuries, are still very much in the making, and the living archive expands not only in size but constantly adds surprising new forms. While archives continue to occupy an almost sacral place both in the public imagination (as the repositories of truth) as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was in late December 1985 when my old friend Diana Gergova called me over the phone, and asked to meet her urgently. We had been inseparable since the 1960s in high school, and later as history students at the University of Sofia. At the time of the call, I was associate professor of Balkan history at the University of Sofia, and Diana was a research fellow at the Archeological Institute at the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences. She acted also as party secretary of the institute.¹ She immediately came to the point: my father, at that moment acting as vice</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>A “Social Drama” at the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social dramas, as Victor Turner describes them, are “in large measure political processes, that is, they involve competition for scarce ends—power, dignity, prestige, honor, purity—by particular means and by the utilization of resources that are also scarce—goods, territory, money, men and women. Ends, means, and resources are caught up in an interdependent feedback process.”<sup>12</sup>What is significant is Turner’s insistence that social dramas are not merely a representation (oral or written) of discord or conflict in society, and as such only a story with its “discernible inaugural, transitional, and terminal motifs” to use Hayden White’s terminology.<sup>13</sup>For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>From Breach to Crisis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was only 23 years after the excavations, in 1979, that a journal article appeared which revived Giaurov’s thesis.<sup>78</sup>What was remarkable was that one of the authors was a direct participant and witness of the excavations—Sava Bobchev. Bobchev, an architect and research associate of the Archeological Institute, had been commissioned in 1956 to be the deputy of Mikhailov, and specifically charged with completing the architectural sketches of the excavations. Immediately following this publication, and in the same vein of reasoning, was a newspaper article in<italic>Puls</italic>authored by a legal historian, a historian of the Revival Period, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>No Redress, or Where Are Levski’s Bones?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When all was said and done, there were two lingering problems that at times were posed directly, at other times were present only obliquely. One was the archeologists’ question why all the noise when nothing could be proven categorically. For them, once it was clear that a definitive conclusion could not be accepted or imposed about the remains of Skeleton No. 95, this made the whole discussion immaterial and a waste of time. After all, science deals only with proven theses. In a charitable version, this question can explain part of the implicit passivity of some among the archeologists. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>A Socialist Public Sphere?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At first glance, Khaitov’s geopolitical confabulations might serve to delegitimize his general credibility. But one shouldn’t apportion too much guilt by association. Khaitov’s general motivations and his onslaught on the archeologists should be taken apart. His whole worldview, his<italic>de facto</italic>religion and deepest personal attachments were centered around nationalism, and he had devoted himself to rectifying what he thought of as the assimilationist and de-nationalizing tendencies of communism, and after 1989, of globalization. The discussion with the archeologists was not his invention. He picked up an existing debate and turned it into a public event. That he succeeded in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>“Professionals” and “Dilettantes”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When speaking of the BAN debates as Turner’s redressive phase, what is peculiar about the Bulgarian case is that the whole framework upon which the redressive mechanism was based was itself in a legitimacy crisis from the mid-1980s on. By the 1990s it had completely collapsed and this is probably the most salient explanation why the redressive machinery did not “fix” the problem. What the BAN debates did demonstrate, however, is that “it is in the redressive phase that both pragmatic techniques and symbolic action reach their fullest expression.”<sup>218</sup>
                     </p>
                     <p>The value of the BAN debates, and to some extent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Recognizing the Schism, or What Is Worse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bad Professionals or Good Nationalists?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Already at the end of the BAN debates it was clear that a compromise, let alone a consensus, could not be reached between the two sides. While Khaitov’s framing imagination may have taken him too far—both in the deployment of political conspiracies and in his patriotic claim that the church “Sv. Petka” may have served as a burial pantheon for freedom fighters<sup>280</sup>—his concrete analytical assault on the opposing version was devastating. It irrefutably demonstrated that the “professionals” had been anything but professional. The archeologists, on the other hand, although privately acknowledging mistakes, decided that even a partial concession</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1998, I visited the artist Todor Tsonev, who had become famous after 1989 with his exhibition of cartoons of Todor Zhivkov that he had painted during communism, one of the very few cases where the expectation of a “closet full of masterpieces” that were cached away from the forbidding eyes of censorship actually was vindicated. Maria Ovcharova, his close friend and collaborator and a scholar in her own right, had organized this exhibit after 1989, and it triggered enormous interest. For a brief period of time Tsonev became the hero of democracy, the notion which in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>What Is a Hero and Are Heroes Born?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It should be no coincidence that the great interest in heroes as well as the beginning of the study of heroic myth falls on the high age of nationalism. It was also the high age of revolutions, of the advent of mass politics, of science, and the passionate struggle between a numbers of -isms: conservatism, liberalism, socialism, republicanism, romanticism, anarchism, and so on. No wonder that the great debate in an era that saw the shaping of several social science disciplines was about the role of individuals in history, notably heroes, versus the blind operation of structural forces and social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The “Making” of Vasil Levski</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first post-Liberation decade—the 1880s—saw the publication of the first biography of Levski by Zakhari Stoianov (1883) that immediately engaged contemporaries in a heated debate about the assessment of Levski’s role.<sup>54</sup>Now that the outcome of the Russo—Turkish war had vindicated the effort of the revolutionaries, there were no doubts about the general assessment of Levski, similar to the ones voiced in the pre-1878 period by individuals or groups suspicious of revolutionary radicalism.<sup>55</sup>There was also no question about recognizing his important presence in the revolutionary movement; the debate was around his place relative to the contribution</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>A Banner for All Causes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Appropriating the Hero</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The voluminous body of scholarly work on Vasil Levski, among which some genuine and masterly contributions stand out, is focused entirely on the historical figure and its activities. The first and only analysis of Levski’s posthumous fate is Genchev’s chapter on “Vasil Levski in the Bulgarian historical memory,” which he published in his 1987 book on Levski. In it, Genchev makes an attempt to explain the abrupt turn in the Levski discourse after the Balkan Wars and the First World War. He contends that history itself vindicated Levski’s ideas. The reason for this, according to Genchev, is the critical reassessment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Contesting the Hero</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1898 when Blagoev mentioned that Levski had his enemies, and was lamenting the insufficient attention to his person and ideas, he was not far off the mark. Despite the icon-like and, as we shall see in Part III, literal iconic status of Levski, as well as the correct impression of his universal acceptance, there were questions raised about his personality or his interpretation both by his contemporaries, as well as today. The story of the hero’s contestation, while muted as a whole and without much real effect, deserves to be told, because it allows for a more complex glimpse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>The Literary and Visual Hypostases of the Hero</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a long time the “novelization” of Levski was resisted. Vazov’s<italic>oeuvre</italic>introduced the fictional genre in the treatment of Levski (both in his poetic ode as well as the short stories), but the latter somehow acquired the status of documentary evidence in public perception, although Vazov had never (and did not pretend) to have met and known Levski. Levski’s biographer Stoianov also had never met Levski and suffered profoundly from this “deficiency.” His first attempt at biography (moving away from the memoirist genre) was Levski, and he was adamant that it was true to facticity and resisted the temptations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>From Hero for All to Dissident and Back</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The review of Levski’s reception and appropriation in the interwar period, especially in comparison to the respective reception of Botev, shows that both figures, despite certain idiosyncratic trends in their legacy highlighted by different political groups, had been explicitly accepted as common national figures. Both were truly heroes for all. The assertion that Botev and Levski were pitched against each other already in this period, and that after 1944 the communists had elevated Botev as their exclusive symbol at the expense of Levski who was allegedly largely forgotten, was a later hyperbolic interpolation, dating from the 1970s and especially the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On July 14, 2000 in the tiny and, as yet, empty interior of the newly-built chapel of “All Bulgarian Saints,” a part of the Vasil Levski Museum ensemble in Karlovo, a couple of men were leveling a marble and glass container. This was the only other object supposed to be installed in the chapel aside from the iconostasis with the icons. It is a pretty<italic>objet d’art</italic>made out of a green marble base, carrying a glass case flanked at the corners with four gilded lion heads, and crowned with a gilded cross. The glass case was supposed to house</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Split, or How a Bicephalous Organism Functions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The birthday of the split was May 25, 1992 when Metodi Spasov—the then director of the Office of Religious Affairs (ORA), an agency directly under the cabinet of ministers—issued decree No. 92 declaring Patriarch Maxim and his Holy Synod illegitimate, and appointing in its place a new Holy Synod under Metropolitan Pimen as its<italic>pro tempore</italic>president. This act legitimized the internal secession of five metropolitans a week earlier, who had announced the formation of a new Synod headed by Metropolitan Pimen of Nevrokop. Spasov’s decision rested on the argument that Maxim’s election in 1971, in the climate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The Canonization and Its Implications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This, then, is the background against which the elevation of Levski to a sanctified status has to be understood. To reverse the popular definition of historical background as the limbo inhabited by people who do not really interest us, it is precisely the inhabitants of this limbo who capture the attention in this story. For the clergy of the alternative Synod, the canonization was a move that, for the first time, propelled their activities out of the heretofore exclusively political field, and into the cultural field. Was this a deliberately calculated and carefully staged act intended to exploit a powerful</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Levski and the Bulgarian Church:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory and Narration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A few comments about Levski’s standing in the church while he was alive are in order. While there exists consensus between most biographers on the main stages of his career, there are differences in interpretation, and nuances of articulation that are important for the overall assessment of his relationship to the church. Vasil Kunchev entered in the service of the church at age 15, in 1852, as a novice of his uncle, a hieromonk of the Khilendar Monastery of Mt. Athos. This was an arrangement between his recently widowed mother and her brother, the monk Khadzhi Vasilii, who employed the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>The Orchestration of a Grassroots Cultus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The church “Sveta Bogoroditsa” (“Holy Virgin”) in Karlovo cuts a handsome profile with its blue and white bell tower. The bell tower is relatively new, from 1897, but the church building, as the inscription above the western entrance tells us, dates from 1851. Before they began constructing this new building in 1847, there had been a rather insignificant structure erected in 1839 in the place of the older church of the Holy Virgin that had burnt down in 1813. This latter church, about which little is known, is believed by some to have been built already at the end of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Commemoration, Ritual, and the Sacred</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>447</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do we begin to think about all of this? What is the proper framework of interpretation? One may be tempted to see the phenomenon of Levski’s present veneration and canonization fall under the rubric of what Katherine Verdery calls “the political lives of dead bodies” in post–socialist Eastern Europe or, more aptly and wittily, in the first version of her manuscript, as “post-socialist necrophilia.” Verdery tried to make sense of the hectic activity around dead bodies (reburials of famous persons returned from abroad, or of famous and anonymous ones at home, as well as the erection and tearing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Heroes and Saints:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dialectics of Reincarnation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the different theorists of heroic myth, it is Lord Raglan who insisted most adamantly on the link between myth and ritual and became, as it were, the father and chief exponent of myth-ritualism.<sup>290</sup>While one does not have to adopt his rejection of the historicity of heroes (particularly his insistence that historical heroes are fundamentally different from mythical heroes), and not even accept the particular way in which he established the connection between myth and ritual, it has been clearly demonstrated that, in the case of Levski, the link is there. What characterized all hero myth theorists in general,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has been an argument for the relevance of microhistory, an attempt to demonstrate the significance of local knowledge in approaching the big issues of the profession and of life in general. It is taken for granted that a narrative, written in a few big languages and using examples of a few big countries, has universal connotations. Other examples in other languages (even large languages as Mandarin, Arabic or Hindi) are, at most, allowed to be footnotes in this universal sweep. It is this book’s attempt to demonstrate the general meaning and worth of examples from very small places,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix I</title>
                     <subtitle>The Scholarly Consensus on the 1956 Excavations until the 1980s, Exemplified by the Writings of Stamen Mikhailov: A Critical Analysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>517</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix II</title>
                     <subtitle>The Discussion at the Academy of Sciences on 10, 12, and 27 February 1986</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>528</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix III</title>
                     <subtitle>Letter of 20 Bulgarian Historians to Todor Zhivkov</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>562</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix IV</title>
                     <subtitle>Poems Written by Citizens on the Topic of Levski’s Grave</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>567</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix V</title>
                     <subtitle>Letter of Radka Poptomova, April 1987</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>571</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VI</title>
                     <subtitle>Letter of the Mediavel Archeology Section at Al, June 2001</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>576</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VII</title>
                     <subtitle>The Double-headed Hierarchy of the Bulgarian Orthodox Church (1996–2004)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VIII</title>
                     <subtitle>School Questionnaires on Levski</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>579</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>587</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt128245.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>601</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
