<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In the Eyes of God</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Metaphorical Approach to Biblical Anthropomorphic Language</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Howell</surname>
               <given-names>Brian C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174333</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902257</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Brian C. Howell</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0wh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Anthropomorphic language has provided a conundrum for exegetes and theologians for millennia. Attempting to use human language to describe the divine presents ontological and epistemological problems that push our speech to the breaking point. In this new work, Howell shows that instances of divine action should not automatically be reduced simply to theological categories such as omnipotence, omniscience, omnipresence, immutability, etc., nor to criteria such as personhood, life, and approachability. Rather, he introduced readers to two unique approaches to “anthropomorphic expressions".</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Approaching Biblical Anthropomorphic Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to Brevard Childs, “no modern theological issue which presently challenges the church is in more need of serious theological reflection from both biblical, historical, and dogmatic theology than the identity of God whom we worship.”¹ This issue is also an ancient one, as we find in the Old Testament. For example, Daniel rebukes the king for honoring false, inanimate “gods,” over the God of life. He says, “You have praised the gods of silver and gold, of bronze, iron, wood and stone, which do not see, hear or understand. But the God in whose hand are your life-breath and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Approaching Divine Metaphors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we said that metaphors provide us with a manner of speaking of God that is neither too human in its univocity, too nebulous in equivocity, too ungrounded as with analogy, while being both functional and context-sensitive. We now take a closer look at how metaphors convey information, the type of information they bear, and their ability to make truth-conditional propositions. As we shall see, these factors directly impact subsequent interpretations of the Bible, including its descriptions of God.</p>
                     <p>Initially, we consider the manner in which metaphors convey meaning. For this we find the conceptual framing in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Theomorphism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At this point, it is important to note how the problem of direction of transference within a metaphor impacts anthropomorphic language. Whilst the theories of Lakoff and Grady propose a transference from the source to the target domain, in biblical anthropomorphic language it becomes difficult to discern which is which. The traditional approach involved a transfer of human concepts to the divine, often resulting in either a mundane univocity, or a need for accommodating the language to the point of rendering it equivocal with respect to the divine. But, as we have seen, this need not be the case. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Seeing Good and Evil—Genesis 1–3</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we found that according to the biblical text, mankind is actually in a theomorphic relationship with God. This effectively casts the human sense of terms as the derivative one, with the divine sense being primary. Hence, the divine sense cannot be determined from the human, as the human is dependent upon the divine. Rather, this must be gleaned from its context of usage—something Josef Stern’s approach is uniquely suited to do. In his conception, metaphors (<italic>de re</italic>) can point to objects without fully defining them. Rather, their content is determined, like that of the indexical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>God, the Sons of God, and the Man of God</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 6:2, 5, 12; 7:1; 9:16</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A similar theme of divine sight runs through the Flood narrative.¹ Both prominent and key to the story’s structure, it provides us yet another contrast—that of the “sons of God.” This particular usage holds special interest due to the non-corporeal nature of these beings. Additionally, the many echoes throughout this pericope drawn from earlier texts give us further insight into the nature of divine sight. In the following, we shall examine the nature of the vision of the “sons of God” (6:2), contrasting it with that of God Himself (6:5, 7:1). Then we shall look at a different instances</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>A View to Judgment</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 11:5</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen that God’s sight can incur many different connotations, from receiving aesthetic pleasure, transferring authority, judgment of sin, acknowledgment of righteousness, and active commitment to a covenant. In this narrative, we find sight expressing irony as well as discrediting the builders of the tower, again demonstrating the context-sensitivity of the metaphor.</p>
                     <p>In the middle of the Tower of Babel story, we find God going down “to see” the city and the tower that the sons of men had made. When we look at the structure of this short story, we find that this instance of God “seeing” is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Status and Blessing in the Sight of God</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 16</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen in our previous discussions that divine sight can involve aesthetic and moral appreciation, a transfer of authority, an acknowledgement of moral uprightness, and a judgment fitting the crime. In our next context, we find yet another function and meaning for divine sight—establishing worth. A disconcerting and yet pivotal chapter in the story of Abraham, Gen 16 has traditionally been assumed to recount a failed human attempt to build a legacy. Many clues, however, indicate that more is happening than meets the eye. Not only are the patriarch and matriarch of the people of God, the models</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A Second Look at Sodom</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 18:1—19:29</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our previous chapter, we found divine sight to be informed by the primary themes of status and blessing. It thus functioned as both an affirmation of Hagar’s worth as well as motivation for her to return to the conduits of God’s covenantal blessing, Abram and Sarai. The story of Babel laid emphasis on God’s vantage point in looking at the city and the tower, and thus commented on the project as well as its future ramifications. In our next text, Gen 18 and 19, we find a narrative in which the act of “seeing” plays both a structural and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Mountain with a View</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 22</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our last chapter, we found God’s sight acting in both a performative manner and by proxy. It performed actions through the use of sight, such as witnessing, confronting, and extending mercy. This accords with Stern’s context-based approach to metaphor, which expects to find differing meanings within each individual instantiation of a particular metaphor like divine “sight.” Furthermore, it demonstrates a distinct overlap in divine and human abilities. Although the<italic>modus operandi</italic>might be different, God is still using sight in a manner that humans use it.</p>
                     <p>In this next pericope, we find just such an instance of metaphorical sight.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>236</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropomorphic language has provided a conundrum for exegetes and theologians for millennia. Attempting to use human language to describe the divine presents ontological and epistemological problems that push our speech to the breaking point. Initially, we looked at several different modes of speech, the univocal, equivocal, analogical, and metaphorical, looking at their approach to speaking of a transcendent being. The univocal approach treated language for God and for humans as having the same sense. This immediately runs into problems, however, as God is a non-created Being and His attributes are neither contingent nor finite in nature. Process theologians attempt to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix A:</title>
                     <subtitle>Exegesis of Genesis 16:13–14</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix B:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Righteousness of Lot</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix C:</title>
                     <subtitle>Testing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0wh.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
