<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Life in the Spirit</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Post-Constantinian and Trinitarian Account of the Christian Life</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>snavely</surname>
               <given-names>Andréa D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175521</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905210</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andréa D. Snavely</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0pd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Christians are united in saying that the Christian life is a life in the Spirit. But the unity breaks down when explaining how the Christian life is a life in the Spirit. Life in the Spirit is the first book to engage the post-Constantinian critique of the church with the field of Spirit Christology. Building upon the work of post-Constantinians John Howard Yoder and Stanley Hauerwas and upon the Trinitarian Spirit-Christology of Leopoldo Sánchez, this account provides a framework for seeing one’s Christian life as one transformed by the Spirit. Snavely rejects the characterisation of life in the Spirit as bringing sinners to faith, and instead proposes that as Jesus lived as the Son of the Father in the Spirit, the Spirit also makes other sons of the father in the image of Jesus. This Trinitarian interpretation shows the Christian life as being one of total trust in God with one’s own life, and after death living in Jesus’ resurrected life in the Spirit. Snavely’s account calls for a reimagining of the church and the Christian life in terms of ecclesial structure, Christian discipleship and the Christian view of marriage. Life in the Spirit will not only help Christians to have a better understanding of the place of vocation in the world as witnesses to the lordship of Jesus Christ, but it will also promote unity in the body of Christ based on the actual unity that all his adopted sons and daughters already have by belonging to Jesus Christ’s life in the Spirit.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="228"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Okamoto</surname>
                           <given-names>Joel P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christians are united when saying<italic>that</italic>the Christian life is a life in the Spirit. But the unity breaks down when explaining<italic>how</italic>the Christian life is a life in the Spirit. A stereotype of one extreme comes from my own Lutheran tradition. It can leave the impression that the Spirit’s work in the Christian life consists entirely in bringing sinners to faith, doing nothing to transform believers and bring them to new life. This can happen when Lutherans explain good works by quoting Isaiah—“as filthy rags”—and when they regard the righteousness God conveys in justification as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Snavely</surname>
                           <given-names>Andréa D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Christian Life as Life in the Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This work will give an account of the Christian life as life in the Spirit. This should be obvious enough from the new testament witness and especially Paul’s description of the Christian life as the Spirit’s work of making people into the image of Jesus Christ. However, we should not take it for granted that we have and in fact live by such an account for two reasons. The first reason is that the kind of life Jesus lived is not taken seriously for what it means for a Christian to live a life in the Spirit, or even for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Spirit-Christology That Works for the Christian Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I intend to lay the theological groundwork for an account of Spirit-Christology to be given in the following chapters that explains the Christian life as life in the Spirit based on the constitutive events in Jesus’ life and death, showing that the Christian life is not only life in the Spirit but that such life in the Spirit is also a cruciform life. to do so, I will examine other Spirit-Christologies and Pneumatologies to see whether they contribute to the kind of Spirit-Christology given here that begins with Jesus’ life and death as the basis for showing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Trinitarian Spirit-Christology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jesus, Son of God in the Spirit</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The criteria previously discussed will now be used to establish Jesus’ life, death, and resurrection as constitutive for not only what it meant for him to live in the Spirit as the unique Son of God but what his life in the Spirit means for Christians to live in the Spirit as adopted sons of God. These criteria will be used here in the following progression to arrive at a trinitarian Spirit-Christology: first, it must derive strictly from the narrative of Jesus’ life described in the gospel accounts; second, it must locate constitutive events in the narrative that speak directly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>God Gives His Spirit by Working Jesus Christ in Others</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic difficulty in giving the kind of account presented here is the fact that much theological reflection on the Christian life discounts the life of Christ as determinative for the Christian life. As I discussed earlier, yoder took up this problem especially in<italic>The Politics of Jesus</italic>, in which he argued that the Incarnation implied that Christ’s life must inform the life of the Christian. But yoder’s account does not adequately attend to the question of<italic>how one is made a disciple</italic>of Jesus, what Adolf Köberle called the “energy” question,¹ because he does not adequately account for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Shape and Direction of the Christian Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conformed to Christ’s Cruciform Life in the Spirit</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Now that we have seen how the Spirit transforms a person by the proclamation of the gospel of Jesus Christ into adopted sons of God, we are at a place where we can define the shape and direction of the Christian life. Since life in the Spirit is having been transformed by the Spirit into Christ’s life in the Spirit, whose own life was cruciform, Christ’s cruciform life is the shape and direction of the Christian life as well. This brings us to our final question asked here in chapter 5, “What does the Christian life look like today for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Concluding Summary and Implications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this discussion I have given an account of the Christian life as life in the Spirit. Given the new testament’s witness to the Christian life as one lived in the Spirit, this project will seem to some as highly unoriginal, but, given modern theology’s propensity to ignore Christ’s life in accounts of the Christian life, there turns out to be considerable room for various kinds of contemporary accounts of the Christian life, including life in the Spirit.</p>
                     <p>As I discussed in chapter 1, without Jesus’ life defining the Christian’s life, other accounts are given priority over Jesus’ life, not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0pd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
