<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DC397.H44 1993</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ecole nationale supérieure des cadres d’Uriage</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Uriage-les-Bains (France)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1940–1945</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Knight-Monks of Vichy France</book-title>
         <subtitle>Uriage, 1940-1945</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HELLMAN</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>1993</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773509733</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773563742</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Buffalo</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1993</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt80qmf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In The Knight-Monks of Vichy France John Hellman describes the founding, operation, transformation, and demise of the school, details the institution's ideological and political struggles with other segments of French society, and deals with the remarkable rise of Uriage ideas and alumni in postwar France. By focusing on the social, philosophical, and psychological concepts propounded by the staff of the school, Hellman has produced the first study that shows the École Nationale des Cadres d'Uriage to have been an original educational and group experience which inspired French youth from very different backgrounds to abandon the liberal democratic tradition for a new political and social vision. Drawing on a variety of sources, including interviews, newly available archival material, Vichy publications, correspondence, and diary entries, Hellman contributes to the current, lively debate concerning the phenomenon of collaboration and the response of the French population to fascism and to the occupation during the Second World War. This book will be of particular interest to readers concerned with the intellectual and political life of modern France, modern religious thought and experience, fascism and the Vichy regime, changes in France in the prewar and postwar periods, and the "third way" political option in contemporary Europe.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>French Catholic Intellectuals and the Ideological Origins of the Vichy Regime</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Was there a “French fascism”? Once this would have been a lunatic fringe question, but recent monographs have suggested not only that there was a distinctive French fascism but that fascism itself, far from being a somewhat ephemeral Italian or German import, actually originated in France.¹ Beyond that, contemporary historians have been suggesting that French support for<italic>Pétainisme</italic>, if not for outright fascism, though marginal according to the accepted view in France since the Liberation, was in fact widespread. Acceptance of the new view of France’s relationship with fascism/<italic>Pétainisme</italic>requires a rethinking of several aspects of the history of modern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Beginnings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Against the stirring spectacle of European young people leading movements for freedom and democracy in the late 1980s, it is doubly difficult to imagine how easily European regimes just a half-century earlier set about transforming their societies through a totalitarian remoulding of their young people. Yet after the terrible shocks of defeat and occupation in 1940, the newly created authoritarian government of unoccupied France undertook just such an indoctrination. Marshal Pétain declared the transformation of youth essential to France’s “National Revolution,” and earmarked revolutionized young people to be the key agents for the remaking of their peers.</p>
                     <p>A peculiarity of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Beuve-Méry, the Research Department, and the Knightly Order</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By early 1941 France’s national leadership school was much taken up with the new idea of a communitarian personalist revolution. It was, however, publicly cautious about this: the uniqueness of Uriage, its faculty said, was “the Uriage Spirit,” not any doctrine peculiar to it, and Dunoyer de Segonzac insisted that his school never had “a doctrine other than that contained in the speeches of the Marshal.”¹ Indeed, from its earliest days the Ecole Nationale des Cadres exhorted “an absolute loyalty” and a “total submission” to Marshal Pétain on the part of its instructors, and an official objective of the school</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Uriage Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the second half of 1941 the École Nationale des Cadres d’Uriage was, for its admirers, the flagship of the National Revolution, the first school in the land, the training centre of France’s new elites. But was Uriage during its heyday in fact the truly national institution its title implied? Who was studying and teaching there? What was their daily life, and their real relationship with the Vichy government? What was the actual agenda of Dunoyer de Segonzac and his staff — for example, with regard to Vichy’s youth movements, or toward modern women? How should history judge the Uriage experience?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Uriage Influence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jeunesse ... France, Marche, and the Regional Schools</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the École Nationale des Cadres d’Uriage prospered, some of the more senior military officers involved with Vichy’s youth training began to bristle at young Captain Pierre Dunoyer de Segonzac’s pretentions, his independence, and the centrality of his personality in the school. The Study Bureau had attracted other high-profile personalities to Uriage — lively, sometimes controversial, young Catholic intellectuals such as Mounier, Lacroix, Beuve-Méry, de Lubac, and Maydieu. It was becoming clearer that Uriage was the focal point of a collective effort to orient the National Revolution in a certain direction as the school tried to reach the country with publications</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Uriage Network, 1941:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Équipe nationale, Économic et Humanisme, the Scouts and Compagnons</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An organized association of Uriage graduates, an “Équipe nationale d’Uriage,” was already envisaged by early 1941. It was thought that for the good of the alumni,</p>
                     <p>The school would remain the fixed point to which they could return to recharge their spiritual batteries when they were badly treated by life’s realities. They would think healthily again, and see things simply; once again they would shed the egotism and cupidity of modern life and experience that same state of spirit in which, at the end of their course, they had taken their oath at the foot of the flag.¹</p>
                     <p>Thus in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>The Struggle for Youth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the second half of 1941, the Vichy government was beginning to split over the direction its “youth revolution” should take, as the tensions that followed Uriage’s upgrading into an institution began to come into the open. The École Nationale des Cadres d’Uriage was dominated by devout and idealistic Catholics whom the “realists” around Admiral Darlan considered naive (patronizingly referring to them as “sacristy fleas”), while the hard-line proto-fascists at Vichy like Gaston Bergery or Pierre Pucheu made more and more disparaging remarks about “scoutish and churchy (<italic>calotin</italic>)” youth leaders. But no one could ignore the fact that these Catholics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Uriage under Attack (March 1942—January 1943)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The grandiose triumphalism of the Grande Fête at Uriage in the summer of 1942 masked the fact that the school, by that time, had serious difficulties with the government, fuelled by powerful rivals and critics. One sign of trouble had been the successful pressure exerted on the school the previous summer, apparently by Henri Massis, to do without the Abbé de Naurois and Emmanuel Mounier; another was the fact that Mounier was abruptly incarcerated in early 1942 on suspicion of Resistance activities. The government’s concern over the youth movements led to a summons to Vichy of their leaders, including Segonzac,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Exile from the Castle, the Order, and the Flying Squads</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The closing of the École Nationale des Cadres d’Uriage at the end of 1942 marked the end of the golden age of a community that had brought together some of the best and the brightest people to create a new kind of France. It was succeeded by a period that many of the alumni, in retrospect, saw as the best, the most heroic, even the most important, period in their lives. The activities of the Uriage group during the disintegration of the Vichy regime and the liberation of France are interesting and instructive, if not the most important from our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>De Gaulle, the Network, and the Liberation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the Free French in London knew very little about Pierre Dimoyer de Segonzac, the Uriage community, or the Order,¹ their informers in France sent strong warnings about the youth organizations that promoted the fascistic regimentation of French young people. An anonymous young intellectual of the Gaullist resistance, describing the state of the leading legal youth organizations in spring 1942, saw the French Scouts as “the conscious or unconscious, admitted or unacknowledged inspiration for everything that the RN did in the area of youth.” He noted that Father Doncoeur’s<italic>Péguy, la revolution et le sacré</italic>had preached “a delirious and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The École Nationale des Cadres d’Uriage may have been the solitary inspiration of a visionary young cavalry officer but it brought to common fruition a host of important “underground” movements of the 1930s. The euphoria of the great days at the Château Bayard represented the culmination of a period during which the hope of a communitarian spiritual revolution led by the young generated great enthusiasm and hope. The Uriage school brought together some of the best and the brightest young representatives of anti-democratic and anti-liberal thinking that the country had produced since the revolution — philosophers, ethnologists, doctors, economists, legal scholars,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt80qmf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
