<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jcz56</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3552.A45 Z849 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Baldwin, James, 1924–1987</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political and social views</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Political Companion to James Baldwin</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McWilliams</surname>
               <given-names>Susan J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>Series Editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Deneen</surname>
               <given-names>Patrick J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813169927</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813169925</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The University Press of Kentucky</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lexington, Kentucky</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The University Press of Kentucky</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1vxm8w9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In seminal works such as<italic>Go Tell It on the Mountain</italic>,<italic>Notes of a Native Son</italic>, and<italic>The Fire Next Time</italic>, acclaimed author and social critic James Baldwin (1924--1987) expresses his profound belief that writers have the power to transform society, to engage the public, and to inspire and channel conversation to achieve lasting change. While Baldwin is best known for his writings on racial consciousness and injustice, he is also one of the country's most eloquent theorists of democratic life and the national psyche.</p>
         <p>In<italic>A Political Companion to James Baldwin</italic>, a group of prominent scholars assess the prolific author's relevance to present-day political challenges. Together, they address Baldwin as a democratic theorist, activist, and citizen, examining his writings on the civil rights movement, religion, homosexuality, and women's rights. They investigate the ways in which his work speaks to and galvanizes a collective American polity, and explore his views on the political implications of individual experience in relation to race and gender.</p>
         <p>This volume not only considers Baldwin's works within their own historical context, but also applies the author's insights to recent events such as the Obama presidency and the Black Lives Matter movement, emphasizing his faith in the connections between the past and present. These incisive essays will encourage a new reading of Baldwin that celebrates his significant contributions to political and democratic theory.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="396"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deneen</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <role>Series Editor</role>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Those who undertake a study of American political thought must attend to the great theorists, philosophers, and essayists. Such a study is incomplete, however, if it neglects American literature, one of the greatest repositories of the nation’s political thought and teachings.</p>
                     <p>America’s literature is distinctive because it is, above all, intended for a democratic citizenry. In contrast to eras when an author would aim to inform or influence a select aristocratic audience, in democratic times, public influence and education must resonate with a more expansive, less leisured, and diverse audience to be effective. The great works of America’s literary tradition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McWilliams</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“It is a Baldwinian moment,” a colleague says to me in the spring of 2016. He says this at the end of an academic year in which college students across the United States have—with a speed that seems to surprise even themselves—organized protests and occupied buildings and issued demands for greater racial diversity, equity, and sensitivity on their campuses. Those students are reading Baldwin, quoting Baldwin, rediscovering Baldwin. The measure of a certain kind of public conversation, my Facebook feed flashes regularly with snippets of<italic>The Fire Next Time</italic>, a book that seems so newly relevant to so</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“A Most Disagreeable Mirror”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Race Consciousness as Double Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Balfour</surname>
                           <given-names>Lawrie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“As is the inevitable result of things unsaid, we find ourselves until today oppressed with a dangerous and reverberating silence.”¹ The writer of these words is James Baldwin (1924–1987), and “the dangerous and reverberating silence” is the unspoken story of racial brutality that qualifies any claim for the achievements of American democracy. Although Baldwin issued his warning before the undoing of legal segregation, his assessment of the United States as a nation haunted by its racial heritage goes to the core of the post–civil rights predicament. For Baldwin foresees the limits of formal equality and pushes beyond them to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Race of a More Perfect Union:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Baldwin, Segregated Memory, and the Presidential Race</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brendese</surname>
                           <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Barack Obama gave his revealing speech on race in America, he juxtaposed what he called “the white immigrant story” with the memories aired in black barbershops and beauty salons. In what is now known as his “More Perfect Union” address, Obama also made a distinction between his own generation’s experiences of how race is lived in America and the memories of Reverend Jeremiah Wright’s generation. In each case, Obama recognized a segregation of memory along the lines of color, class, and generation. The speech magnified the connection between America’s segregated memories and its segregated polity.</p>
                     <p>Challenging the boundaries of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>James Baldwin and the Politics of Disconnection</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McWilliams</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Giovanni’s Room</italic>begins with its protagonist, a young, white American named David, staring out the window of a house in the south of France. There, brooding on the events that he is about to recount, David emphasizes that they “were acted out under a foreign sky.” He suggests that this fact undergirds all others in the narrative, that if you didn’t know he was an American abroad, you wouldn’t be able to understand the nature of what has transpired. To understand David, and David’s story, you must understand that he is an American who has traveled outside of America. “There</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>What William F. Buckley Jr. Did Not Understand about James Baldwin:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Baldwin’s Politics of Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buccola</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The American Dream is at the expense of the American Negro.” This was the motion up for debate when the Cambridge Union Society hosted James Baldwin and William F. Buckley Jr. in February 1965. Baldwin, who was by then an internationally acclaimed novelist, playwright, essayist, and activist, was invited to argue on behalf of the motion, and Buckley, who, as editor of the<italic>National Review</italic>magazine and author of the books<italic>God and Man at Yale</italic>and<italic>Up from Liberalism</italic>, was fast emerging as a leading voice of American conservatism, was invited to argue against the motion. The scene of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Baldwin, Prophecy, and Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shulman</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although James Baldwin’s essays depict the relationship of white supremacy to the formation of American society and the shaping of national identity, prevailing forms of liberal and Marxist political thought, as well as most versions of so-called democratic theory, do not recognize him as a political thinker or even contributing to the understanding of politics. Their resounding silence about race, and his exclusion from their canons, bespeak the very conditions he analyzes as a political and moral catastrophe. These conditions are, in short, ongoing racial domination as the foundation of American life, and its disavowal by those it enfranchises. On</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Negative Political Theology of James Baldwin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                           <given-names>Vincent</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Religious language, ideas, and images pervade the essays, plays, stories, and novels of James Baldwin. A product of Black Pentecostalism and a teenage preaching prodigy, Baldwin describes his writing style as influenced by the King James Bible and the storefront church.¹ Verses from the Bible and snippets of gospel music pervade Baldwin’s texts. Yet religion also appears in Baldwin’s work as something he has overcome, a distasteful encounter with authoritarianism that he passed through to reach his present secular, democratic enlightenment. If this is the case, the religious language that appears in Baldwin’s texts could be read as rhetorical flourish,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Go Tell It on the Mountain:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Baldwin and the Politics of Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McWilliams</surname>
                           <given-names>Wilson Carey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Baldwin was a constant American despite all his years of expatriation, a native son whose subjects and audiences were primarily American, even when (as in<italic>Giovanni’s Room</italic>) he set his story overseas. He was a fervent critic of the American regime precisely because he was an anguished lover, and nothing is clearer in Baldwin’s work than the depth of his concern for American political life and culture.</p>
                     <p>Baldwin’s direct involvement in political affairs, however, was relatively slight, skeptical, and infrequent, confined almost entirely to the edge of movements, parties, and events.¹ He practiced a version of what Neal Riemer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Socrates in a Different Key:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Baldwin and Race in America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schlosser</surname>
                           <given-names>Joel Alden</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his recent book<italic>Democracy Matters</italic>, Cornel West names James Baldwin as the “black American Socrates.” “A blues-inflected, jazz-saturated democrat,” Baldwin, in West’s words, exercises “a powerful and poignant selfexamination—always on the brink of despair, yet holding on to a tragicomic hope,” bespeaking “a rare intellectual integrity and personal anguish.” Like Socrates, Baldwin infects others with perplexity, forcing his readers to grapple with the difficulties of “trying to be a decent human being and thinking person in the face of the pervasive mendacity and hypocrisy of the American empire.”¹</p>
                     <p>Taking its cue from West, this essay explores how James</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Crossing Identitarian Lines:</title>
                     <subtitle>Women’s Liberation and James Baldwin’s Early Essays</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Norman</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1970, celebrated black writer and political spokesperson James Baldwin met with renowned anthropologist Margaret Mead for “A Rap on Race.” The following year, Baldwin sat down for “A Dialogue” with young activist poet Nikki Giovanni on the television show<italic>Soul!</italic>In each meeting, Baldwin doggedly maintained that the nation and all its divided groups must address their shared past of disenfranchisement and discrimination if the nation stood a chance at achieving its promises of full inclusion for all. The very public conversations evidence the tensions between white liberalism, integration projects, and a newly militant generation calling for self-determination and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“Where the People Can Sing, the Poet Can Live”:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Baldwin, Pragmatism, and Cosmopolitan Humanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schulenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulf</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>270</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the legacy of James Baldwin? From today’s perspective, there are numerous possibilities for answering this question. One could, for instance, consider his impact on black studies, cultural studies, gay and lesbian studies, diaspora studies, and American studies. Or one might feel inclined to contend that his version of a radical humanism is particularly useful for postidentity politics at the beginning of the twenty-first century. Another possibility for confronting the question of Baldwin’s legacy would be to call attention to his understanding of the function of the writer as a public intellectual. According to Baldwin, the poet’s responsibility “is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Baldwin’s Individualism and Critique of Property</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Turner</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Baldwin’s critique of white supremacy is largely existential. In addition to being a moral atrocity, white supremacy is a system of self-delusion, preventing its adherents from facing reality and taking responsibility for their freedom. In<italic>The Fire Next Time</italic>(1963), Baldwin speculated that fear of death was one of the wellsprings of not only white supremacy but all forms of racial, religious, and national chauvinism: “Perhaps the whole root of our trouble, the human trouble, is that we will sacrifice all the beauty of our lives, will imprison ourselves in totems, taboos, crosses, blood sacrifices, steeples, mosques, races, armies,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>James Baldwin on Violence and Disavowal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beard</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is fitting that in national discourse surrounding police killings and related Black Lives Matter protests, so many reporters and activists have turned to James Baldwin to interpret contemporary racial politics and summon people toward political action. Baldwin, so relentless at confronting “white innocence” in his time, offers a vocabulary about violence and disavowal that aligns with and enunciates Black Lives Matter interventions in important ways.</p>
                     <p>In Baldwin’s account, white violence is not only monstrous but also denied, hidden behind national stories of civic virtue and myths of black criminality. The contemporary moment in US racial politics—from protests in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>James Baldwin and Black Lives Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glaude</surname>
                           <given-names>Eddie S.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I found myself the other day—and upon reflection this was an astonishing thing to say, no less think—wishing my son were seven years old again. He was adorable at seven. The vexations of the teenage years were far off, and he still liked me. But I said this not because I find having an empty nest unbearable, although at times I do, or that I long to raise a teenager again—and eventually he would be a maddening teenager again. I just thought—felt, even—that he would be safer at home, with us.</p>
                     <p>Now my son attends</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>“Tell Him I’m Gone”:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Margins in High-Tech City</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brahinsky</surname>
                           <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Wandering through San Francisco with a public television crew in 1963, writer James Baldwin commented on the crumbling geographies of liberally inclined cities like this one. At the time, the politics of racism smoldered across the nation. Shuttled by the TV crew from one end of the city to the next, Baldwin listened as young Black teens expressed their frustrations and anger at a city that enjoyed a progressive reputation, even as these youth and their neighbors struggled to survive the premature deaths of unemployment and urban renewal, which were rippling through the city at the time.</p>
                     <p>A half century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>S. J. M.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>409</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm8w9.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
