<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Joshua Delusion?</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rethinking Genocide in the Bible</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Earl</surname>
               <given-names>Douglas S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a response by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wright</surname>
               <given-names>Christopher J.H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moberly</surname>
               <given-names>R.W.L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173763</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902141</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Douglas S. Earl</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0x1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Many Christians wrestle with biblical passages in which God commands the slaughter of the Canaanites - men, women, and children. The issue of the morality of the biblical God is one of the major challenges for faith today. How can such texts be Holy Scripture? In this bold and innovative book, Douglas Earl grasps the bull by the horns and guides readers to new and unexpected ways of looking at the book of Joshua. Drawing on insights from the early church and from modern scholarship, Earl argues that we have mistakenly read Joshua as a straightforward historical account and have ended up with a genocidal God. In contrast, Earl offers a theological interpretation in which the mass killing of Canaanites is a deliberate use of myth to make important theological points that are still valid today. Christopher J. H. Wright then offers a thoughtful response to Earl's provocative views. The book closes with Earl's reply to Wright and readers are encouraged to continue the debate.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moberly</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evangelical Christians are characterized by, among other things, high regard, indeed reverence, for Scripture. The Bible is the word of God. This means, among other things, that the Bible is understood to contain the self-revelation of the one true God, who is made known in many and various ways, and supremely in Jesus Christ. As such, the Bible is to be trusted and what it says is to be carried out – this is the way to live life most fully and faithfully.</p>
                     <p>Unfortunately, there are many difficulties within the Bible. Sometimes it is a problem of understanding what the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It would be interesting to conduct an opinion poll of Christians in order to discover what the biggest obstacle to delving into the Old Testament is today. For some it might be the detailed laws; for others it might be the repetitive histories and genealogies, or it might be the alien or perhaps seemingly irrelevant world that is presented there. But I suspect that for many the problem is often that of pictures of genocide and violence, especially now that we are all too familiar with harrowing scenes of violence and its aftermath on our TV screens. How is this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>If Jericho was Razed, is our Faith in Vain?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his 1982 book,<italic>The Quest for the Historical Israel: Reconstructing Israel’s Early History</italic>, G.W. Ramsey devotes a chapter to the question, ‘If Jericho was not Razed, is our Faith in Vain?’¹ The question is a witty allusion to 1 Corinthians 15:14 (if Christ has not been raised, then … your faith has been in vain). Ramsey asks the question in order to consider how the ‘historical truth’ of an Old Testament narrative affects its theological value. In other words, if Jericho was not utterly destroyed as described in Joshua 6, then does the story lack truth and theological value?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>On Wearing Good Glasses:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Importance of Interpretation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 1 we saw that concerns with historical and ethical difficulties might point us to a new (or renewed) way of reading Old Testament texts. The Church Fathers suggest to us that historical and ethical difficulties in a narrative might be indicators to us that we misread an Old Testament text if we read it primarily in terms of historical or ethical description via the ‘plain sense’ of the text. The Fathers mapped out a whole other way of reading the texts in a theologically faithful scheme, but a scheme that is perhaps unconvincing in a number of its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Clearing the Ground:</title>
                     <subtitle>Understanding Joshua as an Ancient Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We saw in chapter 2 that the significance of the book of Joshua is not restricted to what it might have ‘originally meant’. To read it as a ‘revelatory text’ – as Christian Scripture – means that the text is used in ways that go beyond what it ‘originally meant’, such as in the case of Rahab’s story. The ‘world of the text’ portrayed in Joshua has a ‘plenitude’ of meanings, meanings evoked as it is read in new situations and contexts. But this is<italic>not</italic>to say that we can use it as we please if we are to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Reading Joshua</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I would like to present something of an exploration of the story of Joshua as a text in the context of the Old Testament. I am concerned with tackling the question of what Joshua is about as a piece of discourse within the world of the Old Testament. I do not intend to address the question of Joshua’s Christian significance here – that will come in the next chapter where I shall consider how the plenitude of the text may be explored well in new Christian contexts as new questions are put to the text. Here, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Reading Joshua as Christian Scripture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 4 we sought to understand what the book of Joshua was about as discourse. We asked, ‘What are the concerns of this text and what was it composed to achieve in the kinds of context in which it would have been heard and used ‘originally’?’ But this is not the same as reading Joshua<italic>as Christian Scripture</italic>today, and I suggest that it is within the canonical as well as the contemporary context that Joshua ought to be read by the Christian if it is to be read well today. In very general terms, we saw in chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>So what?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sort of reading of Joshua that I am proposing is perhaps something of a double-edged sword for many Christians – something that I feel myself. On the one hand, in our contemporary context in which genocide and religiously motivated violence are, sadly, all too familiar, with the Old Testament being something of an embarrassing ‘no go area’ for many Christians owing to its apparent collusion with genocide, a reading like the one proposed here might provide a renewed way of engaging wholeheartedly with our more difficult yet nonetheless cherished texts. But on the other hand, a reading like the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response to Douglas Earl</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wright</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher J. H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book by Douglas Earl is a stimulating and challenging contribution to how we think about the book of Joshua and there is much in his argument that is welcome and illuminating, as well as some points on which I still find myself uncomfortable and questioning. I think Earl goes a long way in enabling a different and more fruitful reading of the book, but does not quite manage to remove it from the category of being a ‘troublesome text of conquest’ (p. 138). This is an issue that I have wrestled with for many years as a teacher and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response to Christopher J. H. Wright</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Earl</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would like to thank Dr Wright for his thoughtful and important comments on<italic>The Joshua Delusion?</italic>I am grateful for his appreciation in numerous areas, especially with reference to my reading of the text of the book of Joshua, and for opening up important debates on wider issues of history and morality.</p>
                     <p>My primary response to Wright is to note – a point surely of considerable significance – that he does not challenge my reading of the text of Joshua. Wright appears more concerned with the<italic>implications</italic>of my reading for how we understand Scripture. He seems primarily concerned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Endnotes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0x1.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
