<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1590.S6K73 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Performing arts</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Performing arts</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Staging Philosophy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Intersections of Theater, Performance, and Philosophy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Krasner</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Saltz</surname>
               <given-names>David Z.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472099504</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472025145</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.147168"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The fifteen original essays in<italic>Staging Philosophy</italic>make useful connections between the discipline of philosophy and the fields of theater and performance and use these insights to develop new theories about theater. Each of the contributors-leading scholars in the fields of performance and philosophy-breaks new ground, presents new arguments, and offers new theories that will pave the way for future scholarship.<italic>Staging Philosophy</italic>raises issues of critical importance by providing case studies of various philosophical movements and schools of thought, including aesthetics, analytic philosophy, phenomenology, deconstruction, critical realism, and cognitive science. The essays, which are organized into three sections-history and method, presence, and reception-take up fundamental issues such as spectatorship, empathy, ethics, theater as literature, and the essence of live performance. While some essays challenge assertions made by critics and historians of theater and performance, others analyze the assumptions of manifestos that prescribe how practitioners should go about creating texts and performances. The first book to bridge the disciplines of theater and philosophy,<italic>Staging Philosophy</italic>will provoke, stimulate, engage, and ultimately bring theater to the foreground of intellectual inquiry while it inspires further philosophical investigation into theater and performance.David Krasneris Associate Professor of Theater Studies, African American Studies, and English at Yale University. His books include<italic>A Beautiful Pageant: African American Theatre, Drama, and Performance in the Harlem Renaissance, 1910-1920</italic>and<italic>Renaissance, Parody, and Double Consciousness in African American Theatre, 1895-1910</italic>. He is co-editor of the series Theater: Theory/Text/Performance.David Z. Saltzis Associate Professor of Theatre Studies and Head of the Department of Theatre and Film Studies at the University of Georgia. He is coeditor of<italic>Theater Journal</italic>and is the principal investigator of the innovative Virtual Vaudeville project at the University of Georgia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Krasner</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Saltz</surname>
                           <given-names>David Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the past fifteen years have observed a veritable golden age of performance theory—a lively discourse that draws on anthropology, sociology, linguistics, psychoanalysis, political theory, cultural studies, feminism, and queer theory—performance theorists rarely draw on works emanating from American philosophy departments.¹ Similarly, very few professional philosophers have focused in depth on questions pertaining to the phenomena of theater or performance.² This situation is especially surprising given the attention recent philosophers have lavished on other art forms, such as painting, music, and film.</p>
                     <p>The guiding principle of this book is a sustained engagement with philosophy and performance theory. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Text/Performance Split across the Analytic/Continental Divide</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walker</surname>
                           <given-names>Julia A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No topic has dominated contemporary scholarship in theater and performance studies more than the text/performance split. From Susan Harris Smith’s critical assessment in 1989 of the “anti-dramatic bias” in both canonical and revisionist models of American literature, to W. B. Worthen’s critique in 1995 of the textual presuppositions inherent in performance studies in the pages of TDR, to a number of attempts to understand the relationship between textual and performative modes of signification,¹ scholars have begun seriously to explore the seeming incommensurability yet persistent interdependence of performances and texts. Although it is often traced back to the antitheatrical prejudice evident</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Kenneth Burke:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theater, Philosophy, and the Limits of Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Puchner</surname>
                           <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy, a discipline concerned with truth, being, and the foundations of knowledge, was predestined to abhor the theater, which is premised on lying, appearance, and the construction of false worlds. Philosophical attacks on the theater, as they accompany the history of philosophy from Plato onward, are thus not only frequent but also unsurprising. At the same time, self-declared defenders of the theater, including many playwrights, have fought back by creating mock philosophers who are exposed as fools and charlatans on the stage, a tradition that begins with Aristophanes’ unflattering portrayal of Socrates in<italic>The Clouds.</italic>Indeed, Plato and Aristophanes can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Critical Realism and Performance Strategies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nellhaus</surname>
                           <given-names>Tobin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the muddier topics in theater and drama studies is the concept of genre. Are comedy and tragedy each genres, or do they cover numerous genres? Is naturalism a genre, or a style (or is there even a difference between the two)? If it is a genre, is it the same genre when funny as when serious? Or should the term be reserved for narrower categories like gothic melodramas, mystery plays, modernist verse dramas, Jacobean revenge tragedies, and absurdism? Do Shakespeare parodies constitute a genre? When a term can be used in such disparate ways, chances are good that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Humanoid Boogie:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Robotic Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Auslander</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sergei Shutov’s<italic>Abacus</italic>(2001) in the Russian pavilion of the 49th Venice Biennial International Exposition of Art (June 10–November 4, 2001) was a frequent subject of discussion during the press opening for the exhibition, which I attended in my capacity as a critic of the visual arts. Abacus consists of over forty crouching figures draped in black, which face an open door and pray in numerous languages representing a multitude of faiths while making the reverential movements appropriate to prayer. Nearby video monitors display the texts of the prayers in their many alphabets. People at the opening talked of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Philosophy and Drama:</title>
                     <subtitle>Performance, Interpretation, and Intentionality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carroll</surname>
                           <given-names>Noël</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this article is to probe one of the central questions of the philosophy of theater, namely, “What is drama?” However, before broaching the issue of the nature of drama, there is a more basic question: how are we to understand the very notion of a philosophy of theater? For surely one’s conception of the philosophy of theater will influence one’s approach to answering the query, “What is drama?” So let me begin by saying brie› y where I am coming from philosophically before we plunge into the more substantive topic of the nature of drama.</p>
                     <p>The brand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Embodiment and Presence:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ontology of Presence Reconsidered</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jaeger</surname>
                           <given-names>Suzanne M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following discussion addresses recent contentions in performance theory about the concept of presence. Two conflicting viewpoints are evident. First there are those for whom the lived phenomenon of presence still makes sense and is borne out in practical experience.¹ Presence is thought of as “the<italic>lingua franca</italic>” for many stage performers, acting teachers, critics, and audiences. Second are poststructuralist interpreters of performance art who reject the possibility of any singularly meaningful experience of self-presence. Experiences of presence are contested by solely linguistic explanations of the nature of meaning. The challenge, therefore, for a performance theory that aims to af‹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Presence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Erickson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>You are standing waiting at an airport gate for the beloved’s plane to arrive.¹ Air traffic has been heavy and the plane is late. Finally the plane arrives at the gate and passengers begin to emerge out of the tunnel. You search for her face among all the various faces of the people being greeted warmly by family and friends, or simply moving quickly to some connecting flight. You keep scanning but see no sign of her as more and more people get off. You are annoyed that none of these faces, which you glance at and then ignore, are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Technique</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crease</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lutterbie</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When techniques are broadly defined—as process-oriented and involving any systematic and goal-directed human action—one finds them in every creative human activity: in sports, painting, dancing, playing musical instruments, and acting; in physics, chemistry, medicine, and astronomy; in education, administration, and sex. Joseph Agassi argues that magic consists of techniques, though unscientific ones.¹ The swing-era ballad “Oh, Look At Me Now” mentions “technique of kisses.” But techniques can also be much more narrowly defined to include only fully articulated and independently recognized practices that are specifically identified and studied as techniques (the “Alexander technique”).</p>
                     <p>Whether broadly or narrowly conceived,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Presenting Objects, Presenting Things</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rayner</surname>
                           <given-names>Alice</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theater habitually situates abstractions in material realities. If the philosophical debates over the meanings and functions of presence initially draw from theater, practice returns them there, materializes and frames not only the qualitative sense of heightened being or charisma and the temporality of disappearance but the occasion of perception and the paradoxes of its partiality. All these elements have been carefully and well discussed in the essays in this anthology by Philip Auslander, Noël Carroll, Jon Erickson, and Suzanne Jaeger. Instead of duplicating their efforts, I want to consider one way in which theater presents—not so much to examine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Infiction and Outfiction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Role of Fiction in Theatrical Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Saltz</surname>
                           <given-names>David Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the online art lexicon ArtLex, what distinguishes “performance art” from “theater” is that “ theatrical performances present illusions of events, while performance art presents actual events as art.”¹ This conception of theater has a long history, one that we can trace back at least as far as Plato. In particular, the assumption that theatrical performance presents illusory, as opposed to real, events was an orthodoxy in twentiethcentury theory, from the Prague structuralists through existentialism and phenomenology and, most emphatically, semiotics and poststructuralist theory. The standard view is that a theatrical performance is a kind of text whose primary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Understanding Plays</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                           <given-names>James R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theatrical performances require time for their presentation.¹ Theatrical performances require time for their reception. The time in which theatrical performance is received by an audience is the same time as that of its presentation.</p>
                     <p>Theatrical performances consist of events arranged in a sequence. The sequence of events in which a given production of a play is performed need not always be the same from performance to performance. We can imagine a production in which the scenes are numbered and, upon arrival for each evening’s performance, the company settles on the ordering of the scenes by drawing from a hat numbers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Perception, Action, and Identification in the Theater</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nanay</surname>
                           <given-names>Bence</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My endeavor in this chapter is to examine the ways in which the general structure of perception is modified in the case of the reception of theater performances. First, perception in general is examined. I will then argue that a basic characteristic of perception is that it is sometimes interdependent with action. Next I turn to the special case of the perception of a theatrical performance—what I call<italic>theater perception</italic>—examining the role of perception for the possibility of action in the case of watching a performance. I contend that theater perception cannot be sufficiently analyzed without taking into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Empathy and Theater</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Krasner</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay I examine “empathy” insofar as it is a possible audience response in live theater. In particular I attend to empathy not merely as an emotional response but as something possessing cognitive function as well. My main concern will be with the idea of a theatrical experience that evokes empathy, that makes use of empathetic responses as part of the mechanism of artistic comprehension, and that emphasizes emotional responses as a unique, as well as a rational, activity. The subject of emotion in fiction and art has been the central focus in several recent studies, but less has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Voice of Blackness:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Black Arts Movement and Logocentrism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sell</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “And Shine Swam On,” his most incisive description of the cultural, political, and philosophical imperatives of the Black Arts Movement (BAM), Larry Neal asks us to “listen to James Brown scream. . . . Have you ever heard a Negro poet sing like that?” He answers, “Of course not, because we have been tied to the texts, like most white poets. The text could be destroyed and no one would be hurt in the least by it.”¹ At least, no one committed to the overthrow of political and economic powers reeling from the shocks of India, Ghana, Cuba, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>Theatricality, Convention, and the Principle of Charity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Quinn</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the crucial words that remains in the vocabularies of both the practical theater and theater theory, though in a fairly unexamined state, is<italic>convention</italic>. From the sociological standpoint of Elizabeth Burns the “theatrical metaphor” generated conventions that served as constitutive agreements for knowledge.¹ Yet this metaphor is also, for her, a “mode of perception,” a basic phenomenological category like those described by Ernst Cassirer or Susanne K. Langer, which produces the social concepts that make theater—and any other concomitant forms of analogical “theatricality” in other contexts—possible.² Theater for Burns, then, is not a kind of knowledge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.147168.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
