<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PA6664.P53S44 1986</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A. D. Phaedra</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phaedra (Greek mythology) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychoanalysis and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Language and Desire in Seneca's "Phaedra"</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Segal</surname>
               <given-names>Charles</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400885763</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400885760</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1986</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1m3nxp7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This close reading of Seneca's most influential tragedy explores the question of how poetic language produces the impression of an individual self, a full personality with a conscious and unconscious emotional life.</p>
         <p>Originally published in .</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback and hardcover editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="257"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations Used in the Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Senecan Tragedy and the Drama of the Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From August Wilhelm von Schlegel down to comparatively recent times Senecan tragedy has suffered from comparison with its Greek models.¹ To view Seneca in the shadow of the Greeks, however inevitable, is also to miss the unique qualities of these plays. Instead of the theological concerns and intellectual questioning of Greek drama, Seneca develops the moral conflicts which he took over from the Greek dramatists in ways that owe at least as much to Virgil and Ovid as to Sophocles and Euripides. From his Roman predecessors he inherited a rich vocabulary for exploring morbid states of mind, the dark world</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Language and the Unconscious:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards a Rhetorical View of Character</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consciousness does not cover the entire field of our mental life. There is another area of mental activity that we glimpse in what we recall of dreams, in slips of the tongue, and more dramatically in behavior under hypnosis. This area, the unconscious, resists being known or spoken; and to bring it to consciousness we encounter resistance or repugnance and feel a sense of exertion.¹ Because of its resistance to becoming conscious knowledge, the unconscious has a paradoxical nature. It is both there and not there, both known and not known. “The unconscious, Lacan says, is knowledge; but it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Imagery and the Landscape of Desire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all of Seneca’s plays the psychological atmosphere depends heavily on imagery. In the Phaedra images of fire, enclosure, and heaviness and the contrasting imagery of interior and exterior space depict the stifling emotional world in which the characters seem entrapped. Against this mood of constriction, however, Seneca sets elaborate rhetorical descriptions of sky, forest, or sea. The concentrated energy of such descriptions sets into sharp relief the protagonists’ ineffectiveness or helplessness in the face of the emotional violence within and around them.</p>
                     <p>Hippolytus ends his opening song with a call from the nearby forests and the expectation of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Forest World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The emotional violence that Phaedra releases from Hippolytus’ ostensibly peaceful landscape reveals the contradictions in his character and the precariousness of a personality that uses violence as a defense against sexuality. Seneca owes the basic structure of the situation to Euripides, but he develops it with a density and consistency of imagery that produce an entirely new way of presenting character.¹</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Phaedra</italic>is the only Senecan tragedy to begin with a lyrical solo part.² Although formally detached from the action of the play, this passage, Hippolytus’ hunting song, has an important function. It is not merely a pretext for an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Golden Age and Nature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When confronted by Phaedra’s desire, Euripides’ Hippolytus retreats to a Utopian vision of sexless, or rather womanless, reproduction. As an alternative to procreation from women, he desiderates the acquisition of offspring by leaving gold, silver, or bronze in the temples of Zeus (<italic>Hipp.</italic>616-24).¹ Seneca’s hero, confronted with Phaedra, takes refuge not in an imaginary social order outside of time or in a timeless present, but in a historical construction, an idealized image of the Golden Age (483-564).</p>
                     <p>In one respect at least the interiorizing mood of Senecan tragedy is heir to the subjectivizing of experience that runs from Hellenistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Rivalry with the Father:</title>
                     <subtitle>Initiation and Failure</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Greek myth the youthful hero’s initiatory passage from adolescence to adulthood often has a double component: martial deeds (rivalry with or imitation of the father) and a sexual adventure, trial, or temptation. Familiar examples, with success (overt or implicit) in both areas, are the stories of Bellerophon, Peleus, Meleager, Telemachus, Theseus (in Bacchylides 17) and in displaced form the tales of Orestes and Perseus. Failures include Actaeon, Adonis, Hylas, Pentheus, and the “flower children,” Narcissus, Hyacinthus, and Cyparissus. The myth of Theseus (along with that of Perseus) is the success story par excellence.¹ This pattern is still present in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Parental Models:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ideal and Nightmare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dramatist has to convince us that there is an iceberg of coherent human reality beneath the tip of character that we see on the stage.<italic>Nihil ex nihilo fit</italic>applies to effective drama as well as to physics. If a character is to interest us, the events for which he is responsible have to appear as more than arbitrary, detached, isolated gestures. They must in some way express what the novelist George Eliot called “that inexorable law of human souls, that we prepare ourselves for sudden deeds by the reiterated choice of good and evil which gradually determines character.”¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Character Structure and Symbols of Power:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sword and Scepter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Euripides’<italic>Hippolytus</italic>the protagonist’s cultural and psychological marginality is expressed in his occupation as a hunter in the wild; his social marginality in his status as a bastard; and his religious marginality in his association with a mode of mystical worship which is at one point identified with Orphism (<italic>Hipp.</italic>952).¹ As a virgin youth, he relinquishes his potential status as the founder of a family and a citizen. Remaining a hunter and athlete, he fixes himself in the role of the perpetual adolescent sportsman, avoiding the civic responsibilities that would follow from the position that his father now</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Desire, Silence, and the Speech of the Sword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Seneca’s Phaedra, as for Euripides’ and Racine’s, the crossing of the barrier between silence and speech is the critical event. Once these words of desire are spoken, the relation between the speakers is irrevocably changed. Neither the lover who confesses the love nor the beloved who receives the message can ever be quite the same toward one another again. This climactic point of decisive speaking lies at the heart of dramatic representation: the art of converting the exchange of words and feelings into theatrical situation. Communication becomes surrounded with a suspenseful direction that draws us inevitably toward an overwhelming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Father, Underworld, and Retribution:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phaedra and Theseus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Frequently in ancient literature the father’s descent to the Underworld is the occasion for the release of repressed desires.¹ A fit of homicidal madness follows upon Hercules’ return from Hades in Seneca’s<italic>Hercules Furens</italic>and in its Euripidean original. Complementary to this motif is the chaos that results when the father-figure is absent. The absence of Father Zeus during the sleep that follows his seduction by Hera in<italic>Iliad</italic>14 contributes to the disorder that culminates in the death of Patroclus and so, indirectly, causes the death of the chief hero, Achilles. In the<italic>Aeneid,</italic>although Jupiter is not in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Seneca’s Patricide and the Trace of Writing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the secondary elaboration of a celebrated classic, Seneca’s<italic>Phaedra</italic>is at nearly every point conscious of its literary ancestry and therefore of its literariness. The ghost of Euripides haunts every line. Seneca has his own message to convey; but, because that message is inextricable from his implicit commentary on the Euripidean play, his work calls attention to its textuality, that is, to its status as a work<italic>written</italic>in response to a pre-existent text that the author knows, presumably, through reading. It thus stands in a context of verbal artifice and artificiality; and its very existence implies and demands</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Closure, Form, and the Father</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last scene of the<italic>Phaedra</italic>has a peculiarly complex form of literariness and textuality, for Seneca here “contaminates” Euripides’<italic>Hippolytus</italic>with the<italic>Bacchae.</italic>He suppresses the reconciliation between father and son that closes the extant<italic>Hippolytus</italic>and instead develops his own version of the aged, enfeebled father-figure, Cadmus, who pathetically recomposes the mutilated corpse of Pentheus.¹</p>
                     <p>Just below the surface of Seneca’s text, with the attempt to recompose mutilated fragments of a once beautiful form, lies Seneca’s own authorial problem: recomposing into a beautiful unity the now scattered pieces of a past tradition: the two Hippolytus plays of Euripides,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rhetoric and Reality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following Freud, Lacan questions the Cartesian identification of our conscious mental processes with our identity as a “self” (<italic>cogito ergo sum</italic>). Going somewhat beyond Freud, he suggests too that the language in which we can express the existence of self is also the condition of our alienation from self. The processes of substitution implied in language make civilized life possible, but at the cost of our alienation from the primary “knowledge” of ourselves hidden in the unconscious.¹ Language is itself part of a series of absences through which the unconscious leaves its mark. For Lacan, as for Plato, the realm</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3nxp7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
