<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PG3501.U4 Z34 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Russian fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ukraine</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Authors, Russian</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ukraine</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Where Currents Meet</book-title>
         <subtitle>Frontiers of Memory in Post-Soviet Fiction of Kharkiv, Ukraine</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Zaharchenko</surname>
               <given-names>Tanya</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789633861196</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789633861219</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Tanya Zaharchenko</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt1d4txtp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Where Currents Meet treats the Ukrainian and Russian components of cultural experience in Ukraine’s East as elements of a complex continuum. This study of cultural memory in post-Soviet space shows how its inhabitants negotiate the historical legacy they have inherited. Tanya Zaharchenko approaches contemporary Ukrainian literature at the intersection of memory studies and border studies, and her analysis adds a new voice to an ongoing exploration of cultural and historical discourses in Ukraine. This scholarly journey through storylines explores the ways in which younger writers in Kharkiv (Kharkov in Russian), a diverse, dynamic, but understudied border city in east Ukraine today come to grips with a traumatized post-Soviet cultural landscape. Zaharchenko’s book examines the works of Serhiy Zhadan, Andrei Krasniashchikh, Yuri Tsaplin, Oleh Kotsarev and others, introducing them as a “doubletake" generation who came of age during the Soviet Union’s collapse and as adults revisited this experience in their novels. Filling the space between society and the state, local literary texts have turned into forms of historical memory and agents of political life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="226"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON FORMAT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As happens at times, this book grew out of my PhD dissertation, “Where the Currents Meet: Frontiers of Memory in the Post-Soviet Fiction of East Ukraine,” which was completed at the University of Cambridge in 2014. The last day of February was my chosen deadline for unloading its softbound copies at the Board of Graduate Studies in a partly triumphant and partly anticlimactic local ritual known as submission. The week before, Ukraine’s Maidan uprising claimed its largest number of victims yet. The bloodshed continued for several days. February 2014 saw the Maidan movement’s most fatal time.</p>
                     <p>Shortly afterwards, Twitter released</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>DOUBLETAKE GENERATION AND THE SHIMMER OF FRONTIERS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lot’s wife may have faced a different fate today: these are exciting times for backward glances. As cultural, political, and social changes swept across the postsocialist regions of the world in recent decades, the study of how the past is remembered and forgotten acquired a particular relevance for those nations undergoing rapid transformation. In Ukraine, a new virtuoso generation of writers has been picking up the theme of their country’s complex twentieth-century legacy and transforming it into captivating—and often surreal—narratives. The city of Kharkiv,¹ Ukraine’s second-largest, is a major hub of this creative activity.</p>
                     <p>A significant portion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>FRONTIERS OF IDENTITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Ukrainian studies of recent years, the formula of Two Ukraines—a conceptualization of the country as a synthetic and flammable combination of two predetermined conflicting entities—has arguably become a universal explanatory mechanism with “a near-absolute discursive power.”¹ This proclaimed battle between the “pro-European West” and the “pro-Russian East” has provided a convenient binary interpretative framework, rendering a complex country temptingly simple: its internal dynamics could now be attributed to a skirmish between its good and bad halves.² And despite pleas for mutual understanding, this alienating approach continues to seduce minds and secure loyalties on both sides of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>FRONTIERS OF EMPTINESS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In December 2010, the BBC Ukrainian Book of the Year prize was awarded to writer Serhiy Zhadan for his novel<italic>Voroshylovhrad</italic>. Four years later, in December 2014,<italic>Voroshylovhrad</italic>was named the BBC Book of the Decade. This literary work interlaces black humor and uncensored language (peoplespeak) with the harsh realities of post-Soviet life. The result is a collection of adroitly forthright reflections on today’s Ukraine, in all its complexities and contradictions. Among these complexities, the country’s past plays a key role.</p>
                     <p>The author has referred to his novel as “a metaphor of memory.”¹ Indeed,<italic>Voroshylovhrad</italic>deals with remembering and recollection</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>FRONTIERS OF LIFE AND DEATH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Park kul’tury i otdykha</italic>(Park of culture and leisure, 2008), a collection of short stories by Kharkiv writer Andrei Krasniashchikh (b. 1970), most events take place in the gap between life and death. This deep, inhabitable abyss is far from being a mere border between two separate worlds. As the book’s description explains, “this rift (<italic>prosvet</italic>) is not always clearly tangible on a daily basis, but it is quite noticeable when ghosts and corpses emerge from it. Or when our dreams and fantasies leak into it.”¹ In an interesting parallel, Zhadan observes in a separate piece of writing: “Literature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>FRONTIERS OF TRAUMA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One wintry night, walking home from a knight-themed party, three merry young men with swords come across a white statue in a cold dark park. They dare each other to behead it, and after much effort, on the fifth blow, one succeeds. As his drunken friends celebrate the statue’s demise, the decapitator suddenly falls to his knees, vomiting violently. The dotingly picturesque description of this abrupt physical reaction, along with its sound effects (“He gagged, then rattled, and snowflakes melted in his hoarse breath”), constitutes the most vivid part of a tiny, 150-word story “Briug” (1996) by Kharkiv writer Yuri</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>FRONTIERS OF (IN)SANITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The stories examined in this chapter consist of a peculiar kind of monologues. Their halting, fragmented narratives are shaped into a vortex—rather than a stream—of consciousness. Semicoherent storytelling, rife with nonchronological associative leaps of thought, reflects the nonlinear nature of traumatic memory involved in creating such vortices.</p>
                     <p>The themes of these monologues can be divided into two broad groups. In one, protagonists engage in confessional recollections of traumatic events. But unlike the narrators introduced in chapter 4, these characters are relatively clear about what happened to them, ranging from a childhood blunder to a violent murder. To process</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study has examined how, in “a culture increasingly dominated by space and spatial logic,”¹ contemporary Ukrainian writers of the younger generation—doubletake writers—work their characters into a traumatized cultural landscape. In such a landscape, the language of categories and coordinates is subverted in favor of blurriness, uncertainty, and the supernatural. I call this cohort the doubletake generation, in reference to their coming of age at the time of the Soviet Union’s collapse. Upon reaching adulthood, they revisit the intense historical experience that coincided with their childhood or adolescence—a time when external changes fuse with internal ones, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PRIMARY SOURCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txtp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
