<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">760882</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">F1219.76.R45B375 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aztecs</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Relgion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aztec gods</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aztecs</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Rites and ceremonies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Archaeology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Fate of Earthly Things</book-title>
         <subtitle>Aztec Gods and God-Bodies</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bassett</surname>
               <given-names>Molly H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780292760882</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780292762985</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>AUSTIN</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Texas Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7560/760882"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Following their first contact in 1519, accounts of Aztecs identifying Spaniards as gods proliferated. But what exactly did the Aztecs mean by a "god" (teotl), and how could human beings become gods or take on godlike properties? This sophisticated, interdisciplinary study analyzes three concepts that are foundational to Aztec religion—teotl (god), teixiptla (localized embodiment of a god), and tlaquimilolli (sacred bundles containing precious objects)—to shed new light on the Aztec understanding of how spiritual beings take on form and agency in the material world. In The Fate of Earthly Things, Molly Bassett draws on ethnographic fieldwork, linguistic analyses, visual culture, and ritual studies to explore what ritual practices such as human sacrifice and the manufacture of deity embodiments (including humans who became gods), material effigies, and sacred bundles meant to the Aztecs. She analyzes the Aztec belief that wearing the flayed skin of a sacrificial victim during a sacred rite could transform a priest into an embodiment of a god or goddess, as well as how figurines and sacred bundles could become localized embodiments of gods. Without arguing for unbroken continuity between the Aztecs and modern speakers of Nahuatl, Bassett also describes contemporary rituals in which indigenous Mexicans who preserve costumbres (traditions) incorporate totiotzin (gods) made from paper into their daily lives. This research allows us to understand a religious imagination that found life in death and believed that deity embodiments became animate through the ritual binding of blood, skin, and bone.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>God-Bodies, Talk-Makers: Deity Embodiments in Nahua Religions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Mexicas walked out of their place of origin many years before they finally stepped into the Central Valley.¹ During their long and winding peregrination, the people frequently begged their patron god Huitzilopochtli to settle, but he forced them to press on again and again. When the Mexicas finally arrived in the Central Valley, the Colhuas, an established polity, allowed them to live at Tizaapan, an area believed to be uninhabitable because of an epic scorpion and snake infestation. Against these odds, the Mexicas thrived in Tizaapan, a feat that launched their reputation as fierce and fearless. Seeing that his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Meeting the Gods</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These four episodes of apotheosis from the Encounter underscore the roles of religion, material culture, and embodiment in early exchanges between Mesoamericans and Europeans. According to these accounts (all redacted by Europeans), the Aztecs identified Hernán Cortés and his companions as<italic>teteo</italic>(deities) and<italic>teixiptlahuan</italic>, their localized embodiments: first, in Francisco López de Gómara’s account, “the Mexicans”—a gathering of Amecamecan locals—associate the Spaniards with gods; second, the Tlaxcalans describe Cortés’s translator Marina/Malintzin as a goddess; third, the<italic>tlahtoani</italic>(speaker;ruler) Moteuczoma Xocoyotl (Lord Angry, Younger) identifies Cortés with Quetzalcoatl (Quetzal Feather Serpent); and fourth, Chimalpahin’s annotation reiterates and elaborates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Ethnolinguistic Encounters:</title>
                     <subtitle>Teotl and Teixiptla in Nahuatl Scholarship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understanding “the gods” concerned both the Aztecs and the Spaniards from the earliest moments of Contact. As the Aztecs observed the Spaniards, apprehension about the gods’ presence and absence plagued Moteuczoma and his priests. Accounts of the Encounter leave us with a mythohistorical mix of (re) actions ascribed to the<italic>tlahtoani</italic>(speaker; leader): in the days leading up to the Spaniards’ arrival, Moteuczoma desperately attempted to read a series of eight omens; he sent messengers disguised as merchants to spy on the strangers; he gave Cortés deity costumes as an enticement to leave; he stopped eating and suffered from insomnia;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Divining the Meaning of Teotl</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aztec<italic>teteo</italic>(gods) acted in the world: they spoke to devotees, they inhabited and oversaw elements of the landscape, and they appeared in localized embodiments constructed by priests and practitioners. Hearing Aztecs call mountain-shaped dough figurines, human god-bodies, and bodies of water—let alone Cortés and company—<italic>“teteo”</italic>must have perplexed the conquistadors, friars, and chroniclers who encountered them and their stories. We know this in part from the awe they expressed regarding the Aztec gods and their embodiment. Bernal Díaz del Castillo wrote of the dazzling impression deity statues covered in precious stones made upon him, and Bernardino de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Gods in the Flesh:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Animation of Aztec Teixiptlahuan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Teteo</italic>(gods) and their<italic>teixiptlahuan</italic>(localized embodiments) frequently appear together in Nahuatl accounts of ritual activity, especially in those that describe devotees constructing and venerating a deity embodiment—whether human, dough, wood, or stone. Aztec rituals and devotional practices often involved multiple<italic>teixiptlahuan</italic>representing several<italic>teteo</italic>. This multiplicity has contributed to scholars’ tendency to fuse the two concepts—<italic>teotl</italic>and<italic>teixiptla</italic>(localized embodiment)—into a single more manageable one. A description of Painal’s appearance at the temple of Huitzilopochtli from the<italic>Florentine Codex</italic>exemplifies ritual contexts in which devotees interacted with multiple<italic>teixiptlahuan</italic>:</p>
                     <p>Auh in otlathuic, niman ye ic hualquiza,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Wrapped in Cloth, Clothed in Skins:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aztec Tlaquimilolli (Sacred Bundles) and Deity Embodiment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the reign of Moteuczoma Ilhuicamina (ca. 1440–1469), the Aztecs waged war on the Cuitlahuacas under the pretext of returning a third group, the Atenchicalque, to their homeland. During the battle, Yaocuixtli of Mexicatzinco ran into the burning temple of the deity Mixcoatl to rescue the goddess Itzpapalotl’s tlaquimilolli (something wrapped or bundled; sacred bundle). As the temple burned, Moteuczoma’s representatives initiated an exchange with Texoxomoctzin in which they demanded that the ruler hand over the teixiptla (localized embodiment) of Mixcoatl. Texoxomoctzin directed his reply toward the story’s audience as much as to the Aztecs standing before him. He explained</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Fates and Futures: Conclusions and New Directions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 2007, the year aft er I first witnessed Chicomexochitl, the community and several of my colleagues performed the ceremony again. The<italic>tepahtihquetl</italic>(ritual specialist) brought a new apprentice, and they changed the order of the ritual activities. He began the ritual at the pozo (well) where it usually concludes and arranged the<italic>altepetl</italic>(mountain) altars differently than before. After the ceremony ended, the participants returned to their respective homes and most of the visitors left the community. Everyone who remained agreed that the new ritual sequence seemed askew.</p>
                     <p>As my colleague Kelly McDonough was preparing to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX A.</title>
                     <subtitle>Ixiptla Variants in Early Lexicons</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX B.</title>
                     <subtitle>A List of Terms Modified by Teo- in the Florentine Codex (English translations from Anderson and Dibble)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX C.</title>
                     <subtitle>Turquoise, Jet, and Gold</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">760882.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
