<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13xv58b</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rancière and Film</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bowman</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748647361</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748647378</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748647376</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul Bowman</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b27n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first collection of critical essays on the film work of the philosopher Jacques Rancière</p>
         <p>Jacques Rancière rose to prominence as a radical egalitarian philosopher, political theorist and historian. Recently he has intervened into the discourses of film theory and film studies, publishing controversial and challenging works on these topics. This book offers an exciting range of responses to and assessments of his contributions to film studies and includes an afterword response to the essays by Rancière himself.</p>
         <p>Contributors includeNico Baumbach, Columbia UniversityRey Chow, Duke UniversityBram Ieven, Utrecht UniversityMónica Lopez Lerma, Helsinki UniversityPatricia MacCormack, University of East AngliaRichard Stamp, Bath Spa UniversityJames Steintrager, University of California, Irvine</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Rancière and the Disciplines:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction to Rancière before Film Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bowman</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the relation ‘Rancière and<italic>film’</italic>quietly presupposes another relation: ‘Rancière and film<italic>studies’</italic>. This leads to a bifurcation: what is the character, status and significance of Rancière’s work on<italic>film</italic>, and – quietly – therefore also, the character, status and significance of Rancière’s work in relation to the discipline or disciplines of film<italic>studies</italic>? I say ‘disciplines’ because film studies both is and is not<italic>one</italic>discipline. No discipline is univocal. No discipline is singular – other than in the eyes, or the fantasy, of the most reductive, taxonomical and exterior gaze – a gaze from outside of the field in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>What Does It Mean to Call Film an Art?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baumbach</surname>
                           <given-names>Nico</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The origins of this essay derive from the attempt to make sense of a certain resistance to Jacques Rancière’s work that I have encountered at film studies conferences in the United States. As I see it, this resistance can be traced to what is seen as a tension or contradiction between Rancière as the self-proclaimed amateur advocating for universal equality on the one hand, and what are perceived as the trappings of cultural distinction that mark his writings on cinema on the other – specifically the familiar auteurist pantheon that makes up the films he focuses on and, perhaps more significantly,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>After the Passage of the Beast:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘False Documentary’ Aspirations, Acousmatic Complications</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chow</surname>
                           <given-names>Rey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his classic<italic>Introduction to Documentary</italic>, Bill Nichols writes that a great deal of the persuasiveness of documentary films stems from the soundtrack, which he equates more or less with the spoken word (Nichols 2010: 26). Of what does the audience need to be persuaded? – the truthfulness, authenticity and plausibility of what is presented. This association of sound with a rhetorical function (persuasion) underscores sound’s relation to the image in documentary film as one of support. Working in a subordinate role, sound, it is thought, enhances and consolidates the tasks set by the image; the soundtrack is simply part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Spectator without Qualities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geil</surname>
                           <given-names>Abraham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jacques Rancière’s book<italic>The Emancipated Spectator</italic>marks his first sustained discussion of spectatorship (Rancière 2008b; 2009a).¹ This might seem a surprisingly late addition to Rancière’s project of rethinking the conjunction of art and politics. From the disciplinary perspective of Anglo-American film studies, it is a belated intervention indeed. For the question of the spectator is the terrain upon which many of the most significant disciplinary battles over the politics of film theory have been waged over the past three decades. In that time, critical approaches to spectators have proliferated: feminist revisions of psychoanalysis; cultural studies models of differentially ‘decoding’ viewers;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Memories of Modernism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jacques Rancière, Chris Marker and the Image of Modernism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ieven</surname>
                           <given-names>Bram</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the recurring tropes within modernist theories of images, and filmic images in particular, is their tendency to play out the tensions between the seeming immediacy of the visual, its epiphany-like and revelatory force that suggests a truth beyond arguing on the one hand, and a focus on the technological conditions of the image on the other. Within modernist theory these two aspects of the image can be arranged in different ways. Some modernist critics, such as André Bazin, have argued that the technological underpinnings of photographic and filmic images ascertain their historical accuracy, or at the very least</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Aesthetic Irruptions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Politics of Perception in Alex de la Iglesia’s La Comunidad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lerma</surname>
                           <given-names>Mónica López</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Combining black humour, thriller and horror film, Alex de la Iglesia’s<italic>La Comunidad (Common Wealth</italic>2000) tells the story of a gruesome community of neighbours who have signed a contract to share the money that another of their neighbours has won in the<italic>quiniela</italic>(football pools) after his death. However, their plans are frustrated when a new arrival, the estate agent Julia, finds the dead man’s money and decides to keep it for herself. From then on, the community will do anything (including murder) to retrieve the money, resulting in its own destruction. When asked about this bleak portrayal of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Inhuman Spectatorship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacCormack</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>On the Shores of Politics</italic>Rancière describes the task of politics as giving substance to the evanescent moment which regulates the multiplicity of ecstatic pleasures found in<italic>demos</italic>, what he calls a ‘jubilant’ ethics. Evanescence is found in the ‘in-between’. The evanescent moment is defined as the event of ‘the philosophical realisation of the art of politics’ (Rancière 1995: 19). As these three trajectories of art, politics and philosophy coalesce to transform themselves as in-between discourse, they emancipate the evanescent moment from being an ideational or mythic impossible utopia, opening out the possibility of a realizable utopia. The future</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Cinemarxis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rancière and Godard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A grey corrugated iron fence on the corner of a street, probably London, shot from across the junction as cars pass in front of the camera. People stroll by. A young man walks up to the fence and begins to spray in large letters, one letter at a time:</p>
                     <p>and then a bright red bus passes between the camera and the corner, and the scene is cut. Jacques Rancière writes substantially on Jean-Luc Godard in<italic>La Fable cinématographique (Film Fables</italic>) (2001),<italic>Le Destin des images</italic>(<italic>The Future of the Image</italic>) (2003) and<italic>Les Écarts du cinéma</italic>(2011), in the essays</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Jacques Rancière’s Animated Vertigo; or, How to be Specific about Medium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stamp</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 1971 article for<italic>American Cinematographer</italic>, the monthly publication of the American Society of Cinematographers, an experimental filmmaker explains how he started developing ‘animation mechanisms’ over a decade earlier. These machines are conceived as tools capable of ‘drawing’ with precisely controlled incremental variations that might match the ‘precise incremental stepping process’ that underpins the cinematographic apparatus of celluloid film and its machines (the camera, the editing table and the projector). Although he claims that he began his work with the aim of making something ‘useful’, he then confesses, with wry self-deprecation, to a feeling of disappointment when his first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Medium Is Not the Message:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rancière, Eschatology and the End of Cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steintrager</surname>
                           <given-names>James A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me begin with a provocation: Jacques Rancière is not a media theorist. This provocation is<italic>not</italic>mine but his, and he makes it in order insist that we account for the complex genealogy of aesthetics rather than giving in to the temptations of reduction and simplification inherent in much media theory. Thus, in the prologue to<italic>Film Fables</italic>, Rancière remarks: ‘There is no shortage of theoreticians who have attempted to ground the art of moving images on the solid base of the means specific to it. But the means specific to yesterday’s analogical machine and today’s digital machine have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Remarks by Way of a Postface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rancière</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The editor of this volume insists that I make my contribution. The problem is that several contributors have already shown perfectly the principles that guide my approach to cinema and what consequences follow from them. Since I have no reason to contradict them and no wish to repeat them, the only path remaining to me is one of transposition. They have gone about things in an orderly way and argued with a subtlety that leaves nothing to be desired. It remains to me to punctuate in a crude and disorderly way the points that they have brought to light.</p>
                     <p>I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b27n.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
