<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vk8d</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML421.G72 O47 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Grateful Dead (Musical group)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Improvisation (Music)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rock music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Listening for the Secret</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Grateful Dead and the Politics of Improvisation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>OLSSON</surname>
               <given-names>ULF</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520961760</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520961765</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oakland, California</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1p0vkcz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Listening for the Secret</italic>is a critical assessment of the Grateful Dead and the distinct culture that grew out of the group's music, politics, and performance. With roots in popular music traditions, improvisation, and the avant-garde, the Grateful Dead provides a unique lens through which we can better understand the meaning and creation of the counterculture community. Marshaling the critical and aesthetic theories of Adorno, Benjamin, Foucault and others, Ulf Olsson places the music group within discourses of the political, specifically the band's capacity to create a unique social environment. Analyzing the Grateful Dead's music as well as the forms of subjectivity and practices that the band generated, Olsson examines the wider significance and impact of its politics of improvisation. Ultimately,<italic>Listening for the Secret</italic>is about how the Grateful Dead Phenomenon was possible in the first place, what its social and aesthetic conditions of possibility were, and its results.This is the first book in a new series,<italic>Studies and Texts of the Grateful Dead Phenomenon</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="200"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meriwether</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicholas G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the bandʹs inception, the Grateful Dead attracted critical attention ranging from insightful to sensationalistic. Often obscured by the media fanfare was the seriousness of the groupʹs project, although some of that early attention was thoughtful, appreciative, and even scholarly. As early as 1966, academics gravitated toward the band, attracted by the intelligence and accomplishment they heard. What was also clear was the depth of the bandʹs commitment, which became one of the hallmarks of the Dead, especially noteworthy in an industry substantially defined by brevity, novelty, and shallowness. Over the course of their thirty-year career, the Dead managed to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On February 24, 1974, the Grateful Dead played at Winterland in San Francisco, California. The show, presented by Bill Graham, also was introduced by the promoter, who said ʺWhatever is going on in the rest of the world, if itʹs war or kidnappings or crimes, this is a peaceful Sunday night with the Grateful Dead.ʺ Indeed; this was just one of the fifty-nine shows that the Grateful Dead played at Winterland; one more night, then, in the life of a hardworking rock and roll band.</p>
                     <p>And, could we add, perhaps one more night protected from the evils of society? Maybe.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Popular Avant-Garde?</title>
                     <subtitle>Renegotiating Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When studying the Grateful Dead—both the band and the wider cultural phenomenon—one should not be surprised if the image discovered is mixed or even contradictory: Was the Grateful Dead a rock band at all? If not, what was it? Jerry Garcia early on could claim that the band was not for ʺcranking out rock and rollʺ but ʺto get high.ʺ¹ Bob Weir stated that ʺweʹre a jazz band. I wonʹt say weʹre nothing but a jazz band, because our basic premise is rock ʹnʹ roll. We just approach it from a jazz point of view.ʺ² Phil Lesh talked</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Wave That Flag:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Apolitical Band</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On January 20, 1994, Vuong Thinh, director of International Relations for the Ministry of Culture and Information, sent the Grateful Dead an ʺOfficial invitation to perform in Vietnamʺ at what was called ʺThe U.S.A./Vietnam Peace, Healing and Friendship Festival.ʺ¹ The band never did perform in Vietnam, but why would a self-declared ʺapoliticalʺ band be invited to the Socialist Republic of Vietnam? Whatever the Vietnamese authorities might have thought, the Grateful Dead never really actively protested the war. The band stubbornly called itself ʺapolitical,ʺ defending itself against appropriation from conventional ʺestablishmentʺ politics, as well as from antiestablishment, left-wing politics. This probably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Crashes in Space:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aspects of Improvisation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Grateful Dead improvised—this is a given. Improvisation was a decisive aspect of what made the band special and set it apart from other bands. The band, of course, acknowledged the fundamental role of improvisation in its music—one could say it was part of the bandʹs DNA. Jerry Garcia said, ʺWe don’t improvise out of choice! We improvise because we donʹt have any choice! Itʹs not as though we could play anything exactly the same as we played it last night because weʹre incapable. So, improvisation, for us, is not an option, itʹs our coloration, itʹs our personality.ʺ²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>Listening for the Secret</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Was it all just a ʺsunshine daydreamʺ? The world at large kept on with its usual business of ʺwar, kidnappings, crimes,ʺ as Bill Graham had said when introducing the band (above, Introduction), while the Grateful Dead played on, listening for secrets and searching for sounds as Robert M. Petersenʹs lyrics for ʺUnbroken Chainʺ describe, or Bob Weir proclaiming the ʺsunshine daydreamʺ of ʺSugar Magnolia.ʺ Maybe it was just a daydream—but if so, then it was one that lasted for an unusually long stretch of time. And apparently that daydream was real enough to create believers in that promise of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Discography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p0vkcz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
