<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt234xxj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR9340.5.M87 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">West African literature (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Slave trade in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Metaphor and the Slave Trade in West African Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MURPHY</surname>
               <given-names>LAURA T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780821444122</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0821444123</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ohio University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j7x98t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Metaphor and the Slave Trade</italic>provides compelling evidence of the hidden but unmistakable traces of the transatlantic slave trade that persist in West African discourse. Through an examination of metaphors that describe the trauma, loss, and suffering associated with the commerce in human lives, this book shows how the horrors of slavery are communicated from generation to generation.Laura T. Murphy's insightful new readings of canonical West African fiction, autobiography, drama, and poetry explore the relationship between memory and metaphor and emphasize how repressed or otherwise marginalized memories can be transmitted through images, tropes, rumors, and fears. By analyzing the unique codes through which West Africans have represented the slave trade, this work foregrounds African literary contributions to Black Atlantic discourse and draws attention to the archive that metaphor unlocks for scholars of all disciplines and fields of study.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Metaphor and the Slave Trade</italic>examines the hidden though significant role the transatlantic slave trade has played in the Anglophone West African imagination and the means by which it has been metaphorized in the literary production of the region. It explores how four canonical authors in particular—Amos Tutuola, Ben Okri, Ayi Kwei Armah, and Ama Ata Aidoo—integrated metaphors of the slave trade into their fictional worlds, metaphors that were inherited from or invented as a reflection of the coded discourse surrounding the slave trade in their cultures. In much of West African fiction—even in works that employ</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Against Amnesia:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metaphor and Memory in West Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Metaphor and the Slave Trade</italic>explores the way the transatlantic slave trade has endured in the cultural memory of West Africa because people continue to generate discourse about the trade and, not insignificantly, because they continue to survive a legacy of suffering associated with it. Within the West African literary tradition, creative writers of all stripes, including many of the most canonical fiction authors as well as other dramatists, poets, popular novelists, and children’s authors, have similarly attempted to come to terms with the memory and legacy of the slave trade. The central focus of this study is an analysis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Magical Capture in a Landscape of Terror:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Trope of the Body in the Bag in Amos Tutuola’s My Life in the Bush of Ghosts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One afternoon while young Olaudah Equiano’s parents worked in the fields, he spied an intruder kidnap the “stout” children of his neighbors two yards over. He shouted out to his friends, who caught the assailants and bound them, and together they waited for their parents to return home and punish the crime. This was no uncommon occurrence: attackers from other regions frequently raided Equiano’s village to “carry off as many [children] as they could seize,”¹ a practice that was especially acute in times of famine. So common were these raids and other attacks on his village that Equiano’s family and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Geographies of Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mapping Slavery’s Recurrence in Ben Okri’s The Famished Road</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mahommah Gardo Baquaqua lived as a free man and a trusted servant in the court of the local king of Djougou,¹ in what is today called Benin.² As the king’s most treasured servant, he sat at the foot of the royal throne and drew the envy of his avaricious colleagues. In his self-published narrative of 1854, Baquaqua informs us that a great “wickedness” was growing inside the king and among his counsel. Baquaqua, with other guards and soldiers “bent on mischief ” (32), would lie in wait along the market road to steal the wine that women carried through the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Curse of Constant Remembrance:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Belated Trauma of the Slave Trade in Ayi Kwei Armah’s Fragments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When European slave ships sailed into the port of Old Calabar in the late eighteenth century, Antera Duke, a wealthy local trader, welcomed them with a lengthy protocol that he and his merchant neighbors and family members had developed over generations of trading with Europeans. In a diary he kept of his daily life and labor, Duke depicts the elaborate ritual that took place as the ships pulled to shore and Duke and his people prepared a welcome. “I see Coffee Duke send his son to till mee news about new ship after Little time I hear 5 great guns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Childless Mothers and Dead Husbands:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Enslavement of Intimacy and Ama Ata Aidoo’s Secret Language of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the transatlantic slave trade was outlawed in Denmark in 1802, in England in 1807 , in the United States in 1808, in Sweden and Norway in 1813, in the Netherlands in 1814, and in France both in 1794 and again in 1817 (after Napoleon reinstated the trade in 1802 ), the illicit trade in human lives was still a lucrative enterprise on the west coast of Africa by the 1830 s and ’40s. Historians of West Africa disagree on the degree of impact that abolition had on the sale of slaves, both domestic and transatlantic, but all agree that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>The Suffering of Survival</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When African-born Phillis Wheatley was less than twenty years old, she wrote what came to be one of the most famous poems in the American literary canon, a reflection on her experience of the transatlantic slave trade. In this poem, “On Being Brought from Africa to America,” she expresses her gratitude that the slave trade provided her with access to the Christian salvation and faith that she would not have had, nor indeed desired, had she remained in Africa. By utilizing the word “brought,” she exposes a positive teleology for her experience of the slave trade. It simultaneously reveals her</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE</title>
                     <subtitle>The Future of the Past: The New Historical Fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the rise of African American cultural tourism, the launching of the UNESCO International Slave Routes project, the immigration of more African writers to the United States and Britain, as well as the growth of academic interest in the legacy of the slave trade, writers in the last decade (loosely the first ten years of the twenty-first century) have been even more attuned to the historical effects of the slave trade and its centrality to contemporary concerns and cultures. Wole Ogundele has correctly assessed postcolonial African literature as largely lacking a<italic>historical novel</italic>that explicitly depicts the era of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x98t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
