<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p7tm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Philosophical criminology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Millie</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781447323730</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1447323734</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bristol</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Policy Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1t890xp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This accessible book is structured around six philosophical ideas concerning our relations with others: values, morality, aesthetics, order, rules and respect. Using examples from a range of countries, it provides a platform for engaging with important topical issues.Philosophical criminology asks big questions about how we get on with one another and what happens when we do not. This accessible book in the New Horizons in Criminology series is the first to foreground this growing area. The book is structured around six philosophical ideas concerning our relations with others: values, morality, aesthetics, order, rules and respect. Building on the author’s theoretical and empirical research, the book considers the boundaries of criminology and the scope for greater exchange between criminology and philosophy. The book is illustrated using examples from a range of countries, and provides a platform for engaging with important topical issues using philosophical and theoretical insights.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="168"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the author</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Millie</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>A philosophical criminology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book about philosophy and criminology. There will be criminologists who question the need for closer engagement with philosophy and, likewise, philosophers who do not see a great deal of benefit from associating with criminology. My argument here is that philosophy is essential to criminology as philosophers have for centuries been asking questions concerning how we get on with one another – and what happens when we do not – that have direct bearing on criminological concerns. Philosophers might also gain from engagement with criminology and greater exposure to the messy and dirty ‘real world’. For some the subject of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Value judgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sociologist Howard Becker once claimed that value-neutral sociology is not possible, that a person’s research cannot be divorced from their personal beliefs and values. The same is true for philosophy, criminology and, arguably, all other academic disciplines – despite some academics’ claims that their research is value free. According to Becker:</p>
                     <p>... one would have to assume, as some apparently do, that it is indeed possible to do research that is uncontaminated by personal and political sympathies. I propose to argue that it is not possible and, therefore, that the question is not whether we should take sides, since we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the British criminologist Anthony Bottoms (2002: 24), ‘if they are true to their calling, all criminologists have to be interested in morality’. Moral philosophy, or ethics, is concerned with how we live and how we ought to live with one another. It considers what is good or bad, as well as deontic judgements of rightness, wrongness, obligation, requirement, reason for doing and what<italic>ought</italic>to be. Such concerns should be central criminological concerns. Criminologists assert that crime – or harm or deviancy – is a social construction and ask what it is about such actions (or inactions) that makes them</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Aesthetics and crime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a picnic bench on the shore of Loch Morlich in Scotland with a panoramic view of the wild Cairngorm mountains, one of the most beautiful views that I know. I may even go so far as to say that the landscape is sublime. But when I say the view is beautiful or sublime, what do I mean? Similarly, what makes something stand out as good art, or what characteristics make an everyday object or encounter a beautiful contribution to contemporary life? These are the concerns of aesthetics. In this chapter the relevance of aesthetics to criminology is explored.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Order and disorder</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2002 an episode of<italic>The Simpsons</italic>was broadcast in which Bart Simpson had an infectious illness forcing him to live in a clear plastic bubble. In one scene Bart was told off for slurping his soup. Bart’s reply was a simple, “My bubble, my rules”. His response neatly encapsulated the ethical egoism of late modern individualism, where the self is supreme and often blind to its impact on others. According to Michael Hechter and Christine Horne (2009) the basic problem of social order is how this individualism can be reconciled with the necessities of living a social existence: The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Rules</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In political and policy rhetoric there is much talk of ‘playing by the rules’. For instance, in the US Barak Obama declared in his 2010 State of the Union address that, ‘we should … enforce our laws, and ensure that everyone who plays by the rules can contribute to our economy and enrich our nation’. Similarly, in the UK during his successful 2010 election campaign David Cameron claimed, ‘We’re fighting the fact that people who do the right thing, who work hard, who save, who play by the rules get hit by the system’. Six years earlier Tony Blair (2004)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Respect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far this book has considered philosophical ideas of values, morality, aesthetics, order and rules and how they relate to criminological concern. This chapter explores a positive way forward centred on the concept of respect. The meaning of ‘respect’ has been a concern for moral philosophy for some time (for example Darwall, 1977; Dworkin, 1977; Hill, 2000; Bagnoli, 2007; Carter, 2011). Much of this work draws, at least in part, on the writings of Immanuel Kant centred on the categorical imperative (see Chapter Three) and the notion of human dignity, that ‘respect for the moral law entails treating persons (oneself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Conclusions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both criminology and philosophy share concerns about how we might get on with one another and what we could, or perhaps ought to do when we do not. In this concluding chapter the place of a philosophical criminology is considered. According to Christopher Williams and Bruce Arrigo:</p>
                     <p>Historically, philosophers have written very little about the subject of crime. Similarly, criminologists have written very little about the subject of philosophy. In both cases, the linkages between philosophy and crime have been left implicit … However, to be sure, law and justice have been particularly significant concerns throughout the history of philosophy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t890xp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
