<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8bs7</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS135.R7 H645 2018</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939–1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Romania</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romania</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnic relations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Holocaust Public Memory in Postcommunist Romania</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Florian</surname>
               <given-names>Alexandru</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253032744</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253032741</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2050vp3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How is the Holocaust remembered in Romania since the fall of communism? Alexandru Florian and an international group of contributors unveil how and why Romania, a place where large segments of the Jewish and Roma populations perished, still fails to address its recent past. These essays focus on the roles of government and public actors that choose to promote, construct, defend, or contest the memory of the Holocaust, as well as the tools-the press, the media, monuments, and commemorations-that create public memory. Coming from a variety of perspectives, these essays provide a compelling view of what memories exist, how they are sustained, how they can be distorted, and how public remembrance of the Holocaust can be encouraged in Romanian society today.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Memory under Construction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Introductory Remarks</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Florian</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandru</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume concludes a research project on Holocaust memory in post-communist Romania, supported by the Romanian Ministry of National Education, CNCS–UEFISCDI, under grant number PN-II-ID-PCE-2012-2-4-0620.</p>
                     <p>The project was prompted by what seemed to be a very simple question: how do we explain that seventy years after the end of the Second World War, in Romania the public memory of the Holocaust is still disputed, and approaches that minimize or even deny it have become more dominant in the public sphere?</p>
                     <p>To answer this question we should first examine the clear differences between the prevailing practices in public memory in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>ETHNOCENTRIC MINDSCAPES AND MNEMONIC MYOPIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bărbulescu</surname>
                           <given-names>Ana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 1940 and 1944 the Romanian authorities imposed broad antisemitic legislation that led to the exclusion of the Jewish minority from all levels of society. The Jews from the Old Kingdom of Romania were subjected to two major outbreaks of violence: the pogroms in Bucharest (January 1941) and Iaşi (June 1941). The pogrom in Bucharest led to the killings of 125 Jews, while the one in Iaşi resulted in as many as 14,850 Jewish deaths.</p>
                     <p>In late summer 1941 Transnistria was transferred under Romanian authority and Ion Antonescu ordered the deportation of the Jews from Bessarabia and Bukovina to these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>POSTCOMMUNIST ROMANIA’S LEADING PUBLIC INTELLECTUALS AND THE HOLOCAUST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Voicu</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Voicu</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandru</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do Romania’s most influential intellectuals after 1989 relate to the Holocaust in general and to its Romanian chapter in particular? Given the powerful impact of their views on the public opinion in the country, one could say that the answer to such a question unveils to a great extent the very foundation of the social perception of the catastrophe experienced by the European Jews during the Second World War. Undeniably, this preliminary assumption does not simply imply a cause-effect relationship between those who articulate the mainstream public discourse and the larger society to which they belong; in many respects,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>LAW, JUSTICE, AND HOLOCAUST MEMORY IN ROMANIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Climescu</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandru</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fall of communism in 1989 created favorable conditions for various versions of the past to be promoted by public actors. Holocaust denial and the public worship of Marshal Ion Antonescu, Romania’s dictator during the Second World War, whose rehabilitation began during the period of national communism,¹ became common discourses among politicians, historians, military officials, and representatives of civil society. The rehabilitation of the Legionary Movement, Romania’s main interwar fascist organization, was also supported by some historians, Orthodox priests, and various nongovernmental organizations.</p>
                     <p>After 1989, historiographical works, political discourses, and commemoration activities meant to rehabilitate the Antonescu regime were complemented</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>ROMANIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>Neither “Fleishig” nor “Milchig”: A Comparative Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shafir</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Right after the change of regime in December 1989, Romania displayed some features that were common to most postcommunist East-Central European countries in regard to antisemitism, as well as some specific features of its own. Freed from ideological and censorship constraints, latent antisemitism erupted in the public space, and after a while it became a cross-party phenomenon. This does not mean that political parties had all put antisemitism on their banners; it rather means that regardless of ideology, both antisemitic prejudice and, above all, the perception of Romania’s “dark past”¹ of the interwar period and the Second World War, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>“WANTING-NOT-TO-KNOW” ABOUT THE HOLOCAUST IN ROMANIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Wind of Change?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geissbühler</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The exposure of the general public in Romania and in many other countries of Central and Eastern Europe to the Holocaust and knowledge about the history of it has been and continues to be marginal.¹ Under the communist regimes, acknowledgement of the Holocaust was all but impossible. Jews, Jewish identity and history, and especially the Shoah were taboo topics for almost fifty years.² Romania was no exception to that rule.³ Having been a close ally of Nazi Germany and having implemented the mass murder of Jews and of Roma autonomously, Romania under communist rule felt an even more acute urge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>MIRCEA VULCĂNESCU, A CONTROVERSIAL CASE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Outstanding Intellectual or War Criminal?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Florian</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandru</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1989, at the time of the December Revolution, Romania had only one highway, 120 kilometers long. In 2017, despite all the strategies to modernize the infrastructure, there are only two highways and parts of a third; there is no highway from north to south, or from east to west. When we think of places of memory,<italic>lieux de mémoire</italic>in public spaces, the situation is no better—the postcommunist public space includes very diverse and very contradictory memorials to the recent past. For example, a bust of Adrian Păunescu, a poet and ideologue during the Ceaușescu regime, was erected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>ION ANTONESCU’S IMAGE IN POSTCOMMUNIST HISTORIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cazan</surname>
                           <given-names>Marius</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ion Antonescu was the leader of the Romanian state from September 1940 to August 1944. From September 1940 to January 1941 he shared power with the far-right Legionary Movement in what was called the National Legionary State. The collaboration between Antonescu and the legionaries did not last, and conflicts between the two sides became frequent as the abuses of the legionaries were increasingly apparent. In January 1941 Antonescu crushed the attempt of the former government partners to oust him, and, counting on his slightly unclear agreement with Hitler, managed to stay in power. As head of government, he developed a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>RETHINKING PERPETRATORS, BYSTANDERS, HELPERS/RESCUERS, AND VICTIMS:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study of Students’ Perceptions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Babeş</surname>
                           <given-names>Adina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Public memory may be defined as a relationship with the past expressed in the public space. It finds its expression in the institutionalized elements that connect it to the public space, such as memorials, prevailing discourses, books, courses, and so on. This research relates to the complex issues that the Holocaust, as well as other genocides, might be caused by situations still present in contemporary society, including the fragility of political and social institutions and society’s responsibility to its people, all in the context of post1989 Romania and its road toward democratization.</p>
                     <p>In discussions about the Holocaust, debate inevitably turns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vp3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
