<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmsm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL51 .R385 2002</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, European</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rethinking Philosophy of Religion</book-title>
         <subtitle>Approaches from Continental Philosophy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Goodchild</surname>
               <given-names>Philip</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2002</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823276974</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2002</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2kncw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>These original essays reconceive the place of religion for critical thought following the recent ‘turn to religion’ in Continental philosophy, framing new issues for exploration, including questions of justice, anxiety, and evil; the sublime, and of the soul haunting genetics; how reason may be reshaped by new religious movements and by ritual and experience.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="356"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Continental Philosophy of Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goodchild</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is a Continental philosophy of religion?¹ Philosophy of religion, in English-speaking countries, has a clear and distinct identity, and has been enjoying a resurgence: it focuses largely on the truth-claims, rationality, and coherence of religious propositions, and particularly those of “classical theism.”² Yet for those who work in the traditions of philosophy derived from Germany and France, the problems, tasks, concepts, reasoning, and cultural location are markedly different from this identity. When even the individual terms of the phrase “Continental philosophy of religion” are highly contestable, can this title designate any determinate field? In spite of its weaknesses, this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Poetics of the Impossible and the Kingdom of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caputo</surname>
                           <given-names>John D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Kingdom of God abides by a certain logic, but it is a divine logic. From the point of view of the world, which is its antagonist, what goes on in the Kingdom looks mad and even impossible. Still, it can be said in defense of the Kingdom that it is not simply impossible but rather, let us say,<italic>the</italic>impossible. We might even speak of the logic of the impossible, on the perfectly logical assumption that with God, all things are possible (Luke 1:37), including the maddest and most impossible. But beyond any possible logic, even a logic of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Toward a “Continental” Philosophy of Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida, Responsibility, and “Nondogmatic” Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Halteman</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthew C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From its inception in Kant’s striving to imagine a “religion within the limits of reason alone,” the Continental tradition has maintained a strict division of labor between theological and philosophical reflection on religion. Many of its most influential thinkers have argued, moreover, that theological inquiry is secondary to the more fundamental philosophical task of elucidating a conceptual logic of "the religious," the universal structure that underlies all particular faith traditions.</p>
                     <p>In what follows, I examine this Continental legacy in the context of Jacques Derrida’s recent work on the concept of responsibility. First I discuss three guiding themes (the limits of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Ethical Experience:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mauvaise Conscience and Necessary Sadness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jowett</surname>
                           <given-names>Donna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is conscience the “voice of God within,” or is it, as both Nietzsche and Freud would see it, the internalized authority of our culture and family? I have put this question baldly and naively; my intention is only to gesture toward the different camps or traditions that have framed themselves on either side of the question. And today such a question has a slightly old-fashioned appearance; it is built on a series of binary oppositions and it further fortifies and extends them in anticipating, if not forcing, the terms of mutual exclusion it presumes. My aim in this paper is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Anxious Responsibility and Responsible Anxiety:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard and Levinas on Ethics and Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bergo</surname>
                           <given-names>Bettina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years two thinkers, Derrida and Levinas, have contributed decisively to shaping the concept of radical responsibility, both before the human other and what has been called the divine. Within the parameters of philosophy of religion, if we would understand the way in which the concept of responsibility opens new avenues of thinking about the meaning of human justice, then we must come to terms with what Derrida and Levinas have recently argued. Furthermore, both men’s thought—preeminently and explicitly that of Derrida—is as if haunted by the work of Kierkegaard.</p>
                     <p>One caveat is in order. The notion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Derrida, the Messianic, and Eschatology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Banham</surname>
                           <given-names>Gary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The predominant reception of<italic>Specters of Marx</italic>has been to view it as a work in which Derrida reveals an unexpected receptivity to the notion of the messianic. That this understanding of the work is at best partial is what I wish to make clear, through setting out the kind of use Derrida is making of the notion of the messianic. In one of the most frequently cited passages from the work, Derrida refers to an “ascesis” that strips the messianic hope of all Biblical forms, and he adds that this “denuding” is done in view of:</p>
                     <p>responding to that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Birth and the Powers of Horror:</title>
                     <subtitle>Julia Kristeva on Gender, Religion, and Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jantzen</surname>
                           <given-names>Grace M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In these words, Julia Kristeva explores the religious sensibility of the seventeenth-century mystic Jeanne Guyon, setting her against Descartes, who completed the foundation of secular modernity by the “subordination of passions to thought.”¹ In Kristeva’s work, the transformation of the West into a secular symbolic is crucial for understanding the modern subject, who, with the loss of religion, no longer has available the “cathartic power" that was part of the central drama of Christianity.² Human subjects, she holds (following Freud and Lacan), are constituted by “a series of splittings . . . birth, weaning, separation, frustration, castration.” Such splittings are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Ineffable Knowledge and Gender</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Pamela Sue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who does<italic>Continental</italic>philosophy of religion? The received view is that Anglo-American philosophers do<italic>philosophy of religion.</italic>Yet increasingly, contemporary philosophers and some theologians would reply “Jacques Derrida” to this opening question. What makes Derrida’s philosophy Continental? What topic in philosophy of religion does Derrida consider? I hope to give some indirect answers to these questions. Instead of looking di rectly at Derrida, I choose to focus my attention on the nature of an exchange at the interface of what have been labeled “Continental” and “analytic” philosophies. I will focus on an example that makes a similar distinction, but uses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Speaking Otherwise:</title>
                     <subtitle>Postmodern Analogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ward</surname>
                           <given-names>Graham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to argue for the significance of theology to philosophy and the importance today of philosophical theology rather than philosophy of religion. I want to demonstrate how a new space for analogical thinking has been opened up by certain poststructuralist discourses; how this is a space in which we can think again of an analogical world and a cosmological project; but how, left to poststructural critical thinking alone, this worldview can all too easily endorse a culture of sadomasochism, by enjoying and enjoining its own endless victimage. Only a theological account (not, note, foundation), as the necessary supplement to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Apophasis and Askêsis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Philosophy and Mystical Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ellsworth</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This much, at least, is clear: we continue to speak of<italic>apophasis.</italic>Studies on the logic and language of apophatic discourse abound,¹ and more are on the way. But why this concern, today, with apophaticism? More specifically, why is it that apophatic theologies are (still? again?) being studied and discussed in certain segments of contemporary philosophy? And to what end? This essay will first hazard a few answers and offer some remarks on contemporary philosophy’s ongoing interests in-and appropriations of—apophatic theological language. Attention will then be called to an essential feature of these apophatic texts that many studies neglect,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Continental Philosophy, Catholicism, and the Exigencies of Responsibility:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Resources of Maurice Blondel’s Works</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sadler</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A question that confronts practicing Roman Catholics engaged in Continental philosophy is the relationship between the practices, tradition, and intellectual resources of the Catholic Church and the boundaries of what is called Continental philosophy. Often the discourses that allow a renewed philosophical boldness in speaking about Christianity are marked by an equally liberating and corrosive temerity that, claiming to speak for none, or perhaps only for the other or the guest, seems to easily to aim to speak for all, to judge for all, to legislate for all. We must ask whether it is true that orthodoxy, one’s self-location within</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>From Neo-Platonism to Souls in Silico:</title>
                     <subtitle>Quests for Immortality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wyschogrod</surname>
                           <given-names>Edith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Sie haben alle mde Münde/Und helle Seelen ohne Saum [they all have weary mouths/pure souls without a seam],” wrote Rilke longingly.¹ Awe-inspiring and mysterious, humans in their mortality could not hope to attain the enviable purity of the angelic soul. The yearning for soul has become far more complex in postmodernity, in that soul has been rendered moot in modernity’s various accounts of mind-body dualism. In its Cartesian version, mind as the ground of certainty came to occupy the void left by the evacuation of soul. With the demise of the modern subject famously described as the ghost in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Gilles Deleuze and the Sublime Fold of Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crockett</surname>
                           <given-names>Clayton</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In many ways, the possibilities for contemporary philosophical and theological thinking have been determined by Kant. Whether explicitly or implicitly, religion has been thought consistently either within, along, or beyond the limits legislated by classical modern reason. At the same time, its status has remained problematic, because it was left out of the fundamental sources of human knowledge according to Kant’s critique. Although he essentially appended religion onto morality, since that time, religion has flirted with and been skirted by scientific theoretical knowledge, ethics, and aesthetics. In his<italic>Theology of Culture,</italic>Paul Tillich has eloquently described this dilemma, and his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Schelling, Bloch, and the Continental Philosophy of Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hudson</surname>
                           <given-names>Wayne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay I discuss in part I some aspects of the approach to religion that Schelling developed in his late “positive philosophy.” In part II, I explain how these ideas were taken up and reworked by Ernst Bloch. In part III, I interpret the implications of these developments for the contemporary Continental philosophy of religion. The first two parts of the essay are fairly conventional; the third part is not. Since at least the seventeenth century, there have been attempts to challenge “stasis thinking” in the West. The most important challenge to stasis thought, however, occurred in the work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Politics and Experience:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bergsonism beyond Transcendence and Immanence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goodchild</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper assumes a political vision that, not being widely shared, requires explicit statement. The fundamental human relations that determine the shape of ecological, social, and personal worlds are not governed by legal, contractual, or institutional principles, but by constitutive practices. At present, the dominant constitutive practice of contemporary social relations is the global market. Production, distribution, and consumption are constituted for the purposes either of making money or of providing “value for money”—that is, a value subject to public measurement. These economic principles, by giving a public and social representation of diverse needs and impulses, usurp the place</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kncw.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>344</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
