<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Biographical methods and professional practice</book-title>
         <subtitle>An international perspective</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Chamberlayne</surname>
               <given-names>Prue</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bornat</surname>
               <given-names>Joanna</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Apitzsch</surname>
               <given-names>Ursula</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781847425874</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1847425879</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bristol, UK; Chicago, IL, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Prue Chamberlayne</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Joanna Bornat</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Ursula Apitzsch</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1t89d2j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The turn to biographical methods in social science is invigorating the relationship between policy and practice. This book shows how biographical methods can improve theoretical understanding of professional practice, as well as enrich the development of professionals, and promote more meaningful practitioner - service user relationships.This book uses a range of interpretive approaches to reveal the dynamics of service users' and professionals' individual experiences and life-worlds. From their research the contributors show how biographical methods can improve theoretical understanding of professional practice, as well as enrich the learning and development of professionals, and promote more meaningful and creative practitioner - service user relationships. The book: · reviews applications of biographical methods in both policy and practice in a range of professional contexts, from health and social care to education and employment; · explores the impact of social change in three main arenas - transformation from Eastern to Western types of society in Europe, major shifts in social and welfare principles, experiences of immigration and of new cultural diversities - on professional practice; · critically evaluates subjective and reflexive processes in interactions between researchers, practitioners and users of services; · considers the institutional arrangements and cultural contexts which support effective and sensitive interventions; · draws on actual projects and tracks reflection, progress and outcomes. With contributions from leading international experts, it provides a valuable comparative perspective. Researchers, policy analysts and practitioners, postgraduate students, teachers and trainers will find this book a stimulating read.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apitzsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Ursula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bornat</surname>
                           <given-names>Joanna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chamberlayne</surname>
                           <given-names>Prue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume is concerned with the relevance of biographical methods and the contextualised understanding of human agency, as keys in professional interventions. Its interest lies in the usefulness of biographical methods in investigating and generating new forms of social practice and in gaining fresh insights into institutional processes. The contributions to this volume portray ways in which biographical methods have been (or are starting to be) applied in various aspects of professional training as well as in partnership with users of services. The volume evaluates biographical practice against a mapping of practitioner and user positioning and experience. It also does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Biographical methods and social policy in European perspective</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chamberlayne</surname>
                           <given-names>Prue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rapid expansion of biographical methods comes at a time of frustration with a number of aspects of social policy, such as positivistic, top–down approaches, the failure to solve issues of expense, efficiency and dependency, and the cultural lag between welfare systems and social change¹. European welfare systems, already under pressure from neoliberal forces, must reorient to new social realities in the labour market, in relations between public and private spheres, in gender relations, and in notions of citizenship and democratic agency. Biographical methods provide a tool for reconnecting welfare systems with lived experience and processes of social change,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Balancing precarious work, entrepreneurship and a new gendered professionalism in migrant self-employment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apitzsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Ursula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The structural crisis experienced generally in post-industrial society since the last third of the 20th century has been characterised by the continuous dismantling of jobs and workplaces, with no compensation in sight. This has prompted some intellectuals and policy makers to speak in terms of the ‘economically redundant’, in much the same way that industrialisation discourse of the 19th century spoke of a ‘surplus population’¹.</p>
                     <p>Also, however, in the eyes of neoliberal economists, a sector of the migrant population in industrial societies seems to have shown itself to be crisis-resistant: entrepreneurial migrants who subsist in an ‘ethnic’ economy. On the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Considerations on the biographical embeddedness of ethnic entrepreneurship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kontos</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over recent decades in most European countries, the long-term decline in self-employment rates has significantly reversed (Apitzsch, 2000; Bögenhold, 2000). These ‘new self-employed’ differ from the classical type of self-employed in their motives for entrepreneurship. Whether it is the desire for self-realisation, to achieve an autonomous life plan (Hakim, 1999) or, in the case of collective entrepreneurship, a wish for solidarity in the workplace through self-employment (Vonderach, 1980; Heider, 1996), or the goal of gaining access to income (Bögenhold, 1987), the ‘new self-employment’ seems to have little to do with the classical entrepreneur. Self-employment seems to have become an individual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Ethnic entrepreneurship as innovation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kupferberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Feiwel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is a result of long-standing interest in three different research areas that rarely intersect or are even seen as of mutual interest: biography, entrepreneurship and innovation. The reasons why biographical research and entrepreneurial research have rarely engaged in an effort of interdisciplinary communication are easy to identify. Entrepreneurial research is a branch of business economics that specialises in the founding of new ventures, mainly small businesses (Gartner, 1985), and in particular the problems of legitimisation that such new ventures encounter as they seek to gain trust among potential stakeholders and business partners (Gartner, 1990; Gartner et al, 1992;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The social subject in biographical interpretive methods:</title>
                     <subtitle>emotional, mute, creative, divided</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cooper</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter asks questions about the conceptualisation of the ontology of the social subject that informs biographical methods of research. Arguing from a psychoanalytically informed view of the subject, I suggest that emotionality and creativity as it derives from our capacity to dream (or what Freud referred to as primary process thinking), and our hesitant and uncertain development as subjects out of infantile states of near complete inarticulacy, are all necessary dimensions of a fully developed concept of what it is to be a subject.</p>
                     <p>The chapter was first conceived immediately following an experience of listening to the accounts of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>A socially and historically contextualised psychoanalytic perspective:</title>
                     <subtitle>Holocaust survival and suffering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bar-On</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Holocaust did not only divide humanity into survivors, bystanders, perpetrators and rescuers and define generations as first, second and third generations of each category. The Holocaust also reinforced perspectives that became associated with the construction of collective memory, especially in countries where society identified itself, or was identified by, these categories, specifically Israel and Germany. ‘Who was a Holocaust survivor?’ was determined first legally and then historically (Gutman, 1990). In Israel, this identity became an important issue in terms of social labelling in the 1950s, and later became salient in terms of self-chosen categorisation in the 1980s and 1990s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Professional choices between private and state positions in Russia’s transformation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Semenova</surname>
                           <given-names>Victoria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The impact of organisational structures is a much-discussed issue in Russia and elsewhere today; for example, state-run organisations, international companies, or small private firms on professional hierarchies¹. Positions are often ranked in relation to salary levels, social functions (such as service orientation and responsibility), issues of autonomy and control, type of management (such as degrees of hierarchy), and systems of social security (such as sickness and pension benefits) (Parsons, 1964; Balzer, 1996).</p>
                     <p>The subjective meaning of a professional career choice between ‘private’ and ‘state’ employment is usually considered in terms of a dilemma between more social security (in a state</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Maintaining a sense of individual autonomy under conditions of constraint:</title>
                     <subtitle>a study of East German managers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nagel</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulrike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter deals with the biographical situation and coping strategies of highly educated cadres under the authoritarian regime of the former German Democratic Republic (GDR). It draws from a study of work biographies of contemporary East German managers who had previously been economic cadres in the GDR. The second part of the chapter considers methodological difficulties of cross-cultural research, particularly in the arenas of post-socialist transformation research and migration research. The problem of providing an adequate framework of interpretation for the social phenomena of a culture unfamiliar to the researcher will be captured by the notion of lacking the ‘common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Biographical reflections on the problem of changing violent men</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gadd</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After a lengthy period of neglect within criminology, the study of men’s violence towards female partners gained a high profile during the 1980s as a consequence of feminist activism and feminist research with victims and survivors. Attention was drawn to the pervasive and extensive nature of violence against women, the greater danger posed by men that women know (as opposed to male strangers), the continuous relationship between physical and sexual assaults and emotional abuse, and the criminal, sometimes fatal, consequences of this abuse (Dobash and Dobash, 1980; Kelly, 1988; Hester et al, 1995). Yet, it was not until the mid-</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>The biographical turn in health studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rickard</surname>
                           <given-names>Wendy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter offers an overview of existing biographical methods in health studies. The focus comes from my own efforts over the past few years to draw together a picture of some potentialities, possibilities and challenges of using biographical methods in health studies, both in research with marginalised groups and individuals, and in university teaching. I came to the topic initially from British oral history work in the two different – but both highly politicised – areas of HIV and AIDS (for example, Rickard, 1998, 2000) and prostitution (for example, Rickard, 2001; Rickard and Growney, 2001), work that I undertook in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Ethical aspects of biographical interviewing and analysis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kaźmierska</surname>
                           <given-names>Kaja</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may seem obvious to say that biographical research differs from all other sociological research. The differences apply to research techniques, procedures of analysing biographical material and something that can be called a ‘style of work’, which covers the very time-consuming research stages of material collection and analysis. These and many other specific features of biographical research are grounded in theoretical and methodological assumptions which vary for particular types of biographical work. However, the outstanding characteristic of this kind of work is that the research material is biography.</p>
                     <p>Each biographical story is unique. The situation of its creation is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Ghost writers:</title>
                     <subtitle>using biographical methods across languages</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Temple</surname>
                           <given-names>Bogusia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What this volume demonstrates, as did<italic>The turn to biographical methods in social science</italic>(Chamberlayne et al, 2000), is that there are undoubted benefits in research with people who are different to you in terms of widening perspectives and horizons. When language is a barrier to communication, many researchers and service providers employ translators and interpreters to try to harvest these benefits. However, ensuring that perspectives other than that of the researcher can be heard is not a straightforward task. In this chapter, I am interested in the implications, when translating, of Spivak’s (1993, p 189) call to “discriminate on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>‘Bucking and kicking’:</title>
                     <subtitle>race, gender and embodied resistance in healthcare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gunaratnam</surname>
                           <given-names>Yasmin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Concerns about how to work with and across differences of ethnicity, culture, language and religion are central to discussions on policy and practice development in the health and social care services in Britain (Alexander, 1999), where references to the need for cultural ‘awareness’, ‘sensitivity’ and ‘competence’ are commonplace. These concerns have taken on further meaning with the renewed attention to ‘institutional racism’ (Macpherson, 1999) in public sector services, and with the extension of race relations legislation (2000 Race Relations [Amendment] Act) to these services. However, despite the increasing attention being given to the need for culturally sensitive and anti-discriminatory professional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>Biography as empowering practice:</title>
                     <subtitle>lessons from research</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bornat</surname>
                           <given-names>Joanna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walmsley</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The use of biography and autobiography today, compared with only 20 years ago in the UK, is now ubiquitous in work with vulnerable people in care settings. Biographical materials exist implicitly and explicitly in a variety of forms, from documents (such as case notes, patient histories, and care plans) to more journalistic public accounts in the media following instances of abuse or fatal accident, as well as in service users’ own accounts often presented in the form of life storybooks, or audiovisual recordings. The use of autobiography and biography has also become a common research tool in health and social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>‘It’s in the way that you use it’:</title>
                     <subtitle>biography as a tool in professional social work</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kyllönen</surname>
                           <given-names>Riitta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do social workers use biographies in designing social welfare intervention? How can biographies be useful in analyses of the ideological dimensions of welfare practices? These are questions that I will elucidate in this chapter. My discussion is based on a study that I conducted of how Venetian social welfare services interpret their lone mother recipients’ needs and respond to them¹. First, I locate social welfare services in the feminine subsystem of welfare programmes and discuss how the feminine subtext defines the status of its beneficiaries. I then go on to delineate the analytical framework adopted to examine discursive and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>Interpreting the needs of homeless men:</title>
                     <subtitle>interviewing in context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schlücker</surname>
                           <given-names>Karin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Staff members of an advice centre for homeless men were seeking to improve the effectiveness of their service by investigating the ‘needs’ of service users, actual or potential¹. I was approached by one of my students to see if I could help set up and conduct a project without incurring high financial cost, and so the study was initiated within the framework of a university training programme in qualitative research². Exceptionally, the research was set up as a supervised students’ project. In weekly meetings, students planned each step of their research design with their two lecturers and reflected on their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHTEEN</label>
                     <title>In quest of teachers’ professional identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>the life story as a methodological tool</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chanfrault-Duchet</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-Françoise</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Applying the methodological tool of the life story, this chapter addresses the issue of the professional identity of teachers of French in secondary schools in France. I will explain this specific choice of issue and method by answering the reader’s usual question, ‘What position does the author speak from?’. This requires some background information on my own professional and intellectual development both as a researcher and academic.</p>
                     <p>As a researcher in scientific linguistics, I have worked for 20 years on the life story as a tool for collecting data within the framework of the social sciences. As an academic, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINETEEN</label>
                     <title>Narratives, community organisations and pedagogy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Du Plessis</surname>
                           <given-names>Rosemary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Higgins</surname>
                           <given-names>Jane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mortlock</surname>
                           <given-names>Belinda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter engages with three categories of narrative: stories about teaching a social research course; students’ stories about their practice as researchers; and the stories of 42 women and men working for community organisations in a city in New Zealand. These stories emerge from a teaching programme in which final-year sociology students are involved in biographical research. Students write a life-story narrative drawn from multiple interviews with a single narrator, as well as a research journal, in which they offer an autobiographical account of their research process. They also submit an analytical essay; that is, a sociological commentary that locates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWENTY</label>
                     <title>Doctors on an edge:</title>
                     <subtitle>a cultural psychology of learning and health</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>West</surname>
                           <given-names>Linden</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter derives from in-depth, longitudinal, collaborative and what is termed auto/biographical research among 25 general practitioners (GPs), or family physicians, working in demanding inner-city contexts, including inner London (West, 2001). The research focuses on the learning, role and wellbeing of such GPs during a time of changing roles and expectations, including within the management of healthcare in Britain, and a period of growing criticism over performance and levels of accountability. The serial killer Dr Harold Shipman has replaced, at least in part, the heroic Dr Kildare in the popular mind, and stories of doctors’ mistakes far outweigh the triumphs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWENTY ONE</label>
                     <title>Intercultural perspectives and professional practice in the university:</title>
                     <subtitle>what’s new in Germany</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Inowlocki</surname>
                           <given-names>Lena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vivar</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria Teresa Herrera</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herrschaft</surname>
                           <given-names>Felicia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Attracting students from other countries and world regions has been an objective for German universities for some time, and more recent policies have facilitated the admission of foreign students. Their attendance is understood as contributing towards internationally recognised standards of education. It was always expected that graduates would act as multipliers upon their return to their countries of origin, although currently there is also a perceived need that for a competitive economy, highly qualified graduates should stay on in Germany to work. At the universities, new study courses and credit point systems have been established towards internationally comparable academic degrees.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89d2j.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
