<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9m0s24</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Recognizing the Gift</book-title>
         <subtitle>Toward a Renewed Theology of Nature and Grace</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rober</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506410548</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506410545</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506409085</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506409083</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortres</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19qgfxw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Recognizing the Gift puts twentieth-century Catholic theological conversations on nature and grace, particularly those of Henri de Lubac and Karl Rahner, into dialogue with Continental philosophy, notably the thought of Jean-Luc Marion and Paul Ricoeur. It argues that a renewed theology of nature and grace must build on the accomplishments of the recent past while acknowledging that an engagement with the political is unavoidable for theology. Ultimately, the aim is to revive and broaden discussion of nature and grace by drawing together the insights of contemporary theologians and Continental philosophers. Too often these areas of inquiry remain quite separate, in part due to differing priorities. This work tries to open that conversation, in part by critically pointing out, in dialogue with Ricoeur, the need in Marion’s work for an acknowledgment of recognition, reciprocity, and the political. It thus argues for a theology of nature and grace in terms of recognition of the gift, drawing out the reciprocal and political nature of gift and givenness in opposition to those, including Marion, who would seek to avoid politics and reciprocity as a proper avenue of inquiry for theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nature and Grace as a Contemporary Theological Problem</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the relationship between nature³ and grace⁴ has been a classic Christian theological problem dating back to the letters of Paul, and has resurfaced throughout the history of Christianity. Of abiding significance has been the response of Augustine to the Pelagians.⁵ It was a major area of interest to Thomas Aquinas⁶ and became one of the key issues in the Protestant Reformation. Controversies about nature and grace continued in post-Reformation Catholic theology and culture, manifested particularly in the conflicts surrounding Molinism and Jansenism.⁷ The debate about nature and grace has thus served as a catalyst or focal point</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Mid-Twentieth-Century Debates about Nature and Grace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relationship between nature and grace was arguably the most-debated topic in Catholic theology in the early to middle twentieth century, a period that is now largely seen as culminating in the change in ecclesial and theological atmosphere surrounding the Second Vatican Council (1962–1965). These midcentury debates are the inevitable historical and theological backdrop for any contemporary study of nature and grace. This chapter thus explores the development of Catholic thought on nature and grace beginning with the work of Maurice Blondel against the backdrop of the Modernist controversy, continuing with the contributions of Pierre Rousselot, and concluding with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Nature and Grace after Vatican II:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hans Urs von Balthasar and Liberation Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first chapter analyzed the transformation in Catholic theology of nature and grace through the work of Maurice Blondel, Pierre Rousselot, Henri de Lubac, and Karl Rahner. All worked against the backdrop of secular and ecclesial politics, yet none can be called a political theologian in the sense that this term would develop. Their achievements in developing theology thus had political implications, but they remained precisely implied rather than explicit. By the later 1960s and 1970s, however, the question of politics (and thus, in a sense, of recognition) became impossible to avoid, whichever side one took. It is within this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Jean-Luc Marion’s Phenomenology of the Gift:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Resource for the Theology of Nature and Grace?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explores the work of French philosopher Jean-Luc Marion. Christina Gschwandtner has argued that at first glance, Marion’s work has “been engaged in three very different projects that apparently have very little to do with each other, namely (1) primarily historical and exegetical work on Descartes (2) theology and (3) phenomenology.”¹ As she goes on to point out, these “extremely divergent interests are, however, much less incompatible than they might seem.”² In particular, Marion in the 1980s and 1990s began developing a phenomenology of the gift that seemed to invite application to the theology of grace. This project, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Paul Ricoeur and the Possibility of Recognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter continues the exploration of the problem of the gift in continental philosophy. In particular, it turns to the work of the philosopher Paul Ricoeur as a resource for reformulating Marion’s concept of a gift in such a way as to answer the criticisms posed by Milbank and Tanner while retaining important parts of the overall project. Ricoeur notably brings forward a conception of<italic>recognition</italic>that is underdeveloped in Marion’s work and that serves as a key corrective. Though Ricoeur was an older contemporary of Marion’s and the two had common interlocutors, such as Emmanuel Levinas and David Tracy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Recognizing the Gift of Grace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous two chapters have raised the question of gift and recognition as a resource for the theology of nature and grace. Jean-Luc Marion’s careful analysis of the gift and the saturated phenomenon offers valuable insights while also making overtures to theology, but it falls short on some key points, particularly its denial of reciprocity and underdeveloped notion of recognition. Paul Ricoeur’s work, as I have explained, offers correctives to Marion’s by pairing a less-developed notion of gift with a stronger account of recognition and reciprocity. In the conclusion of the last chapter, I began to draw out how these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgfxw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>250</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
