<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">CC83.A69 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Archaeology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Archaeology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Archaeology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Methodology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mnemonics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social archaeology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Eurasia</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Case studies</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Prehistoric peoples</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Eurasia</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Eurasia</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Antiquities</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Eurasia</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Archaeology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Archaeology and Memory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Borić</surname>
               <given-names>Dušan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781842173633</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781842178126</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Oxbow Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oxford; Oakville</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Oxbow Books</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cd0pmc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Memory can be both a horrifying trauma and an empowering resource. From the Ancient Greeks to Nietzsche and Derrida, the dilemma about the relationship between history and memory has filled many pages, with one important question singled out: is the writing of history to memory a remedy or a poison? Recently, a growing interest in and preoccupation with the issue of memory, remembering and forgetting has resulted in a proliferation of published works, in various disciplines, that have memory as their focus. This trend, to which the present volume contributes, has started to occupy the dominant discourses of disciplines such as sociology, philosophy, history, anthropology and archaeology, and has also disseminated into the wider public discourse of society and culture today. Such a condition may perhaps echo the phenomenon of a melancholic experience at the turn of the millennium. Archaeology and Memory seeks to examine the diversity of mnemonic systems and their significance in different past contexts as well as the epistemological and ontological importance of archaeological practice and narratives in constituting the human historical condition. The twelve substantial contributions in this volume cover a diverse set of regional examples and focus on a range of prehistoric and classical case studies in Eurasian regional contexts as well as on the predicaments of memory in examples of the archaeologies of 'contemporary past'. From the Mesolithic and Neolithic burial chambers to the trenches of World War I and the role of materiality in international criminal courts, a number of contributors examine how people in the past have thought about their own pasts, while others reflect on our own present-day sensibilities in dealing with the material testimonies of recent history. Both kinds of papers offer wider theoretical reflections on materiality, archaeological methodologies and the ethical responsibilities of archaeological narration about the past.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory, archaeology and the historical condition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Borić</surname>
                           <given-names>Dušan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Next to my bedside, there is a black and white sepia-toned family photo (Fig. 1.1). The photo shows my grandmother holding my great uncle’s son, my other great uncle feeding a horse, the boy sitting on the horse in his impeccable formal navy-like school-boy uniform, this anonymous horse standing still and an equally anonymous kitten in the arms of the boy. The year is 1936. It is the summer on the family farm in the region of Srem, Vojvodina, the northern province of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia. The tranquillity of the atmosphere on the photo may indicate a<italic>belle</italic>of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The diversity and duration of memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whittle</surname>
                           <given-names>Alasdair</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does it matter where archaeologists get their theories from? We are often told that our own world and culture are bad guides to what went on in the past, and the desire to avoid ethnocentrism is obvious and understandable. This has, however, regrettable consequences, since it can lead to the creation of very general, if not rather abstract theory. Current interest in agency is a good case in point. John Barrett has presented some of the most important discussions of this central topic. An earlier study was centred on the case study of developments in the area around Avebury during</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Happy forgetting?</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering and dismembering dead bodies at Vlasac</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Borić</surname>
                           <given-names>Dušan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper is a reflection on one of my previous accounts about social memory in the prehistoric past. The paper was forced into existence by the evidence that had come to light through a recent excavation of a site that previously I had been able to study only from archival data. New evidence triggered not only the question of remembering in relation to accounts of social memory but also the question of forgetting. While remembering may be crucial for the continuation of social institutions and identity construction as much for an individual as for a social group, how important or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Forgetting and remembering the digital experience and digital data</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tringham</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper grew out of a conversation about memories; about remembering my first Mac; what a sharp memory and a powerful event it was; and how all the memories of using computers and their peripherals in the field since then explode in its wake with ever increasing complexity and speed until the digital media engulf and revolutionise our field experience and we can hardly remember a time when experience in the field was entirely non-digital.</p>
                     <p>There are three threads of remembering and forgetting running in non-linear fashion through this paper:</p>
                     <p>Firstly, my starting point from Susan Sontag’s (1977) and especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Layers of meaning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Concealment, memory and secrecy in the British Early Bronze Age</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A number of features characterise mortuary rituals at the end of the Neolithic and the beginning of the Bronze Age in Britain (the period covering approximately 2200–1500 BC). These include the construction of barrows of layered earth and stone cairns of mounded rubble covering the dead; the burial of individuals as inhumations or cremations enclosed in grave cuts, stone cists, or coffins; and the deposition of artefacts in close association with the dead. Outside the mortuary sphere, but necessarily connected with it, this period of prehistory also witnesses the emergence of large scale hoards of artefacts, typically metalwork, typically</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Constructing the warrior:</title>
                     <subtitle>Death, memory, and the art of warfare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanks</surname>
                           <given-names>Bryan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There has been an increasing interest in exploring the social aspects of late prehistoric warriors in Eurasia. While some scholars have focused more on the ranking and prestige connected with political authority (<italic>e.g</italic>. Earle 1987; Kristiansen 1998; Kristiansen and Larsson 2005; Shennan 1986) others have emphasised the fluid nature of identity and ethnicity and the wide range of variability in their material expressions. Such approaches have shifted towards theoretical archaeologies, which explore the nuances of the socially constructed body, object materiality, and the significance of funerary rites and monuments as loci for the construction and negotiation of individual and community</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Memory and microhistory of an empire:</title>
                     <subtitle>Domestic contexts in Roman Amheida, Egypt</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boozer</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within an imperial framework, individuals and groups invoke memories of the past to denote both their social identity and their placement within the empire. An examination of quotidian mnemonic processes offers an opportunity for us to explore the ways in which local peoples negotiated, influenced, and responded to imperial social climates. The Roman Empire provides a salient framework for exploring memory because it was the iconic ancient empire, inscribing its control over a vast range of territories and peoples, each with its own distinct history and identity. The present work explores two Roman Egyptian houses as touchstones for the complex</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>The depiction of time on the Arch of Constantine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gutteridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Arch of Constantine was dedicated by the Senate of Rome, in celebration of the tenth year of the Emperor Constantine’s rule. Constantine had been acclaimed Emperor on the occasion of the death of his father, Constantius I, in AD 306 at York. At that time the Roman Empire was ruled by a collegiate system of Imperial government, with four emperors holding power together. The system of succession in this tetrarchy was non-hereditary, and Constantine’s attempt to become a member of the ruling Imperial college following the sudden death of his father amounted to a usurpation of legitimate authority, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Archaeology and memory on the Western Front</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Filippucci</surname>
                           <given-names>Paola</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The debris and devastation of the First World War in Belgium and France were quite rapidly removed and repaired during the early 1920s (see Clout 1996). Th e remains of trenches, shell-holes, dugouts and other installations were filled up with other debris and covered with a shallow layer of topsoil so that where possible cultivation and habitation could be restored. Only in the vicinity of memorials or monuments sometimes remains of the battlefield were preserved and conserved (see Gough 2004). Elsewhere, hasty burial and removal has helped to preserve wartime remains and war-shaped landscapes (see Saunders 2002). Excavations to retrieve</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Terra incognita:</title>
                     <subtitle>The material world in international criminal courts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weiss</surname>
                           <given-names>Lindsay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At this very moment, the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia, or ICTY, sits in a kind of global nowhere – a place of no state sovereignty – though it is located in a building formerly occupied by a bank in a quiet neighbourhood in The Hague. Slobodan Milošević and others have been tried here on a set of charges with which the world is now well familiar, but what is not familiar to the global audience is the context of this trial and the specifics of its day to day organisation. At its most obvious, this process is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>YugoMuseum:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory, nostalgia, irony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bajić</surname>
                           <given-names>Mrdjan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Have you ever wished that you could make an enormously voluminous collection of objects that together had absorbed the meaning of the epoch in which you lived? And then, to group these objects according to your decision, to your will or whim, with the conviction that, grouped in just this way, they render with more truth and blatancy their meaning and significance into the field of obviousness; creating a profile of the ‘fabric’ of historical facts and layers – of which they give evidence – thereby revealing the malignancy of the era. Yugomuseum is the result of such a wish.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0pmc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Memory, melancholy and materiality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buchli</surname>
                           <given-names>Victor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Memory requires a certain degree of iterability both material and discursive in order to sustain it. It is this iterability that presences the absence of a loved one, the nation, home, or ones subjectivity or sexuality. From Foucault we know the importance of the iterative structures both materially and discursively that sustains subjectivities through various disciplines, such as the trained sinews of the soldiers body that remind him that he is no longer a peasant but a well trained disciplined soldier. However, when this iterability fails, both materially and discursively then there is a crisis of being.</p>
                     <p>The recent significance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
