<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16d6823</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Cannibal Metaphysics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DE CASTRO</surname>
               <given-names>EDUARDO VIVEIROS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>edited and translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Skafish</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781937561215</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781937561970</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1937561976</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Univocal Publishing</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt17xr4vt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The iconoclastic Brazilian anthropologist and theoretician Eduardo Viveiros de Castro, well known in his discipline for helping initiate its "ontological turn," offers a vision of anthropology as "the practice of the permanent decolonization of thought." After showing that Amazonian and other Amerindian groups inhabit a radically different conceptual universe than ours-in which nature and culture, human and nonhuman, subject and object are conceived in terms that reverse our own-he presents the case for anthropology as the study of such "other" metaphysical schemes, and as the corresponding critique of the concepts imposed on them by the human sciences. Along the way, he spells out the consequences of this anthropology for thinking in general via a major reassessment of the work of Claude Lévi-Strauss, arguments for the continued relevance of Deleuze and Guattari, dialogues with the work of Philippe Descola, Bruno Latour, and Marilyn Strathern, and inventive treatments of problems of ontology, translation, and transformation. Bold, unexpected, and profound,<italic>Cannibal Metaphysics</italic>is one of the chief works marking anthropology's current return to the theoretical center stage.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="229"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Skafish</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can anthropology be philosophy? Can it not just contribute to but do, and even aid in reinventing philosophy, in the sense of constructive, speculative metaphysics? And what, in that event, would philosophy be, since most of its best instances begin, end with, and never abandon Western categories? Such questions might be lamely disciplinary were it not for the symmetrically unimaginative, joint response they still receive. For the philosophers, things are often quite simple: anthropology is a source of empirical specifications or exemplifications of matters conceived more universally by themselves, but only rarely does it accede to such a broad level</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>A Remarkable Reversal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I once had the intention of writing a book that would have been something of a homage to Deleuze and Guattari from the point of view of my discipline; it would have been called<italic>Anti-Narcissus: Anthropology as Minor Science</italic>. The idea was to characterize the conceptual tensions animating contemporary anthropology. From the moment I had the title, however, the problems began. I quickly realized that the project verged on complete contradiction, and the least misstep on my part could have resulted in a mess of not so anti-narcissistic provocations about the excellence of the positions to be professed.</p>
                     <p>It was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Perspectivism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Such a requalification of the anthropological agenda was what Tânia Stolze Lima and I wanted to contribute to when we proposed the concept of Amerindian<italic>perspectivism</italic>as the reconfiguration of a complex of ideas and practices whose power of intellectual disturbance has never been sufficiently appreciated (even if they found the word relevant) by Americanists, despite its vast diffusion in the New World.⁹ To this we added the synoptic concept of<italic>multinaturalism</italic>, which presented Amerindian thought as an unsuspected partner, a dark precursor if you will, of certain contemporary philosophical programs, like those developing around theories of possible worlds, others</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Multinaturalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“We moderns possess the concept but have lost sight of the plane of immanence….” (D. G. 1994: 104). All the foregoing is merely the development of the founding intuition, deductively effectuated by indigenous theoretical practice, of the mythology of the continent, which concerns a milieu that can rightly be called prehistorical (in the sense of the celebrated absolute past: the past that has never been present and which therefore is never past, while the present never ceases to pass), and that is defined by the ontological impenetrability of all the “insistents” populating and constituting this milieu—the templates and standards</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Images of Savage Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In calling perspectivism and multinaturalism an indigenous cosmopolitical theory, I am using the word “theory” by design.<sup>36</sup>A widespread tendency in the anthropology of the past several decades has consisted in refusing savage thought [<italic>la pensée sauvage</italic>] the status of a veritable theoretical imagination. What this denial primarily enlightens us about is a certain lack of theoretical imagination on the part of anthropologists. Amerindian perspectivism, before being a possible object of a theory extrinsic to it—a theory, for example, conceived as the derived epistemological reflex of a more primary animist ontology (Descola 2013) or an emergent phenomenological pragmatics peculiar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>A Curious Chiasm</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For my generation, the name of Gilles Deleuze immediately evokes the change in thought that marked the period circa 1968, when some key elements of our contemporary cultural apperception were invented. The meaning, consequences and very reality of this change have given rise to a still-raging controversy.</p>
                     <p>For the spiritual servants of order, “the yes-men that labor for the majority,”<sup>50</sup>this change foremost represents something from which future generations ought to have been and still must be protected—the guardians of today having been the protégés of yesterday and<italic>vice versa</italic>(and so on)—so as to reinforce the conviction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>An Anti-Sociology of Multiplicities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Anti-Oedipus</italic>, as is well known, Deleuze and Guattari overthrow the temple of psychoanalysis by knocking out its central pillar—the reactionary conception of desire as lack—and then replace it with the theory of desiring machines, sheer positive productivity that must be coded by the socius, the social production machine. This theory runs through a vast panorama of universal history, which is painted in the book’s central chapter in a quaintly archaic style that could make the anthropological reader wince. Not only does it employ the venerable savagery-barbarism-civilization triad, but the proliferating ethnographic references are treated in a seemingly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>Everything is Production:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intensive Filiation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If there is indeed an implicative asymmetry that could be taken as being primary in the Deleuzian conceptual system, it resides in the distinction between the intensive (or virtual) and the extensive (or actual). What interests me here is the bearing this distinction played in<italic>Capitalism and Schizophrenia</italic>’s rereading of the two chief categories of classical kinship theory, alliance and filiation. The choice is justifiable in the first place because Deleuze and Guattari’s treatment of these two notions expresses with particular clarity an important displacement that takes place between<italic>Anti-Oedipus</italic>and<italic>A Thousand Plateaus</italic>. Second, the choice also suggests the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>The Metaphysics of Predation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contrariwise reading of structuralism proposed below will first require some digression into intellectual autobiography. I beg the reader’s indulgence, as the story concerns my experience as an Americanist ethnologist in its bearing on the issues.</p>
                     <p>In<italic>Totemism Today</italic>and<italic>The Savage Mind</italic>, the two transitional works where the prestructuralism of<italic>The Elementary Structures of Kinship</italic>gives way to the post-structuralism of the<italic>Mythologiques</italic>,<sup>86</sup>Lévi-Strauss establishes a paradigmatic contrast between totemism and sacrifice that for me had a status that could be described as properly mythic, allowing me to more distinctly formulate what I had previously only confusedly perceived as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Nine</label>
                     <title>Transversal Shamanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have circled back to shamanism, which was dealt with above in our summary of perspectivist theory. On account of their capacity to see other species as the humans that these species see themselves as, Amazonian shamans play the role of cosmopolitical diplomats in an arena where diverse socionatural interests are forced to confront each other. In this sense, the function of the shaman is not entirely different from that of a warrior. Both are “commuters” or conductors of perspective, the first operating in a zone of interspecificity and the second in an interhuman or intersocietal one.<sup>95</sup>These zones are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Ten</label>
                     <title>Production Is Not Everything:</title>
                     <subtitle>Becomings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was emphasized above that the double author of<italic>Anti-Oedipus</italic>argued that “nothing is changed” by the fact that the primordial energy is one of affiliation—in other words, it would just be a contingent fact. We then asked whether it would not be legitimate to conceive of another intensive order where the primary energy would be an “energy of alliance.” The problem, we concluded, was to determine the conditions for the construction of a concept of alliance qua disjunctive synthesis.</p>
                     <p>The possibility of an intensive interpretation of alliance only becomes intelligible with<italic>A Thousand Plateaus</italic>, in the long chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eleven</label>
                     <title>The System’s Intensive Conditions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We will return once more to the passage from Lévi-Strauss already cited several times in these pages, the one where the dean of the Americanists connects “critical analyses” of the notion of affinity (which Brazilian ethnologists led the way in<sup>113</sup>) to the uncovering of an indigenous philosophical problematic. All of this derives, at the end of the day, from Lévi-Strauss himself, and I think that he knew it perfectly well. That South American affinity is indeed not a sociological category but a philosophical idea was something Lévi-Strauss had observed in a premonitory way in one of his very first works,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Twelve</label>
                     <title>The Enemy in the Concept</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Anti-Narcissus</italic>—the book that I would have liked to write but that I only managed to outline in the previous chapters—would have been a thought experiment [<italic>une expérience de pensée</italic>], an exercise in anthropological fiction. A “thought experiment” not in the usual sense of thought (imaginarily) entering experience but, rather, of the entry into thought of (real) experience. Not the imagining of an experiment, but an experimentation with the imagination or an “experimentation with thought itself.”<sup>122</sup>In the present case, the accumulated experience is that of a generation of ethnographers of indigenous Amazonia, and the experiment is a fiction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Thirteen</label>
                     <title>Becomings of Structuralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book’s question has often been the status of structuralism, and for good reason. Lévi-Strauss’ structuralism ought to be understood as a structural transformation of Amerindian thought—the result of an inflection sustained by the latter inasmuch as it was amenable to being filtered through problems and concepts characteristic of Occidental<italic>logopoiesis</italic>(the same and the other, the continuous and the discrete, the sensible and the intelligible, nature and culture…), according to a movement of controlled equivocation and unstable equilibrium incessantly fertilized by corrupting translations. I will thus reprise my thesis from the first chapter concerning the intrinsically translational condition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17xr4vt.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
