<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Leaving the North</book-title>
         <subtitle>Migration and Memory, Northern Ireland 1921–2011</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Trew</surname>
               <given-names>Johanne Devlin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846319402</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781385661</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Johanne Devlin Trew</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18mbcf8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Leaving the North is the first book that provides a comprehensive survey of Northern Ireland migration since 1921. Based largely on the personal memories of emigrants who left Northern Ireland from the 1920s to the 2000s, approximately half of whom eventually returned, the book traces their multigenerational experiences of leaving Northern Ireland and adapting to life abroad, with some later returning to a society still mired in conflict. Contextualised by a review of the statistical and policy record, the emigrants’ stories reveal that contrary to its well-worn image as an inward-looking place – 'such narrow ground' – Northern Ireland has a rather dynamic migration history, demonstrating that its people have long been looking outward as well as inward, well connected with the wider world. But how many departed and where did they go? And what of the Northern Ireland Diaspora? How has the view of the ‘troubled’ homeland from abroad, especially among expatriates, contributed to progress along the road to peace? In addressing these questions, the book treats the relationship between migration, sectarianism and conflict, immigration and racism, repatriation and the Peace Process, with particular attention to the experience of Northern Ireland migrants in the two principal receiving societies – Britain and Canada. With the emigration of young people once again on the increase due to the economic downturn, it is perhaps timely to learn from the experiences of the people who have been ‘leaving the North’ over many decades; not only to acknowledge their departure but in the hope that we might better understand the challenges and opportunities that migration and Diaspora can present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="348"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘The truth about stories’: Personal Perspectives on Ulster Migration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘The truth about stories,’ writes Native American author Thomas King, ‘is that’s all we are’ (2003: 2). From family stories, origin myths, fantastic fables or historical tales; the human being is a ‘story-telling animal … a teller of stories that aspire to truth’ (MacIntyre, 1981: 201). It is in narrative form that we store and retrieve our memories and transmit our histories, cultures and identities. As individuals, we live by storying; repeatedly telling ourselves and others who we are, what we do and where we belong. We think in story form, we remember in story, we imagine the past and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>History, Memory, Migration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Whose diaspora, whose migration, whose identity?’ (Mac Einrí and Lambkin, 2002) remain uncomfortable questions in post-partition Ireland. For although the concept of diaspora has proliferated in academic discourses of migration and identity since the 1990s, most often its application in the Irish context as a ‘victim’ diaspora (Cohen, 1997) has referred principally to the large number of famine emigrants, mostly Catholics and successive chain migrations of that group, primarily to the United States from 1845 to 1870.² The migration of Protestants from Ireland has tended to be set apart in an often partisan and somewhat marginalised literature on the Scotch-Irish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Northern Ireland:</title>
                     <subtitle>Migration History and Demography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Significantly, on 21 July 1920, only six days following the publication of the letter above, the outbreak of sectarian violence, known as the Belfast pogroms, began which by 1922 resulted in a quarter of the city’s Catholic population (some 23,000) having to flee their homes (Elliott, 2000: 374–5).² A few years later during the Boundary Commission hearings (1924–1925), it is evident how, in the absence of a plebiscite, outdated body counts based on 1911 census figures were bitterly disputed in border areas and used to argue for, or to contest, the redrawing of the boundary between the new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>‘They were always missed, they were always mentioned’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Migration, Generation and Family History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Montreal, Quebec. It is a sunny, warm July morning. I am a dark-haired, skinny child considered small for my six years, standing with my grandmother Roseena on the sidewalk of the Rue Sainte-Catherine – Montreal’s busy main shopping artery. We are alone she and I, my tiny left-hand firmly in her grasp, unnoticed by the many people walking by. Roseena, a small plump woman then in her seventies, gazes dreamily up at the Hudson’s Bay Company storefront across the street. Something in her mood causes me to look up at her. She sighs then and without altering her gaze, half whispers,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>‘Are you Catholic or Protestant?’</title>
                     <subtitle>Religion, Migration and Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>David was born in Belfast in 1940 to a father from County Cork and a mother from Dublin. His father, an elderly man when David was born, had in a previous marriage already reared a family; working in the insurance business for many years in Dublin, Liverpool and Twickenham, London before settling in Belfast during the 1930s. He was also a Baptist lay preacher, a Freemason and held strong Unionist beliefs. David’s mother was raised in the Church of Ireland in which he himself was confirmed. In his childhood home, David remembered the photograph of King George VI on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>‘Doubly invisible’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Being Northern Irish in Britain</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>February 2010. I receive a lovely card from Aimie, an elderly informant from Belfast who has lived in England since 1946. She writes, ‘I am losing my sight. No more lovely books and poetry … I will never be able to go home again but have happy memories … these memories help to sustain us at sad times.’ My own vision blurs with tears for Aimie is a woman who loves literature, poetry especially, and reading has been the only way over the past few years that she has been able to ‘travel’ home. Her words bring me back to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>‘A very tolerant country’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Immigration to Canada</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>June 2007. I am in a taxi hurtling through the streets of Toronto en route to Pearson International Airport to catch a flight to London. My driver, an Iranian immigrant who has lived in Toronto since 1988 appears delighted to discover that I am genuinely interested in his country when I mention having recently read two books about Iran.¹ We stop at a red light and from under the journey log sheet on his clipboard he pulls out a folded Iranian newspaper, holds it over the steering wheel and begins reading aloud, translating from Farsi, moving his finger under the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>‘I’m back where I belong’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Return Migration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marie, a woman in her late sixties, grew up in the prosperous south Dublin suburb of Blackrock. Her mother, Catherine, born into a Fermanagh farming family that worshiped in a Plymouth Brethren congregation, had decided at the age of eighteen after a life-threatening experience to convert to Catholicism. As a result, Catherine was expelled from the family home in Fermanagh forbidden ever to return, so she travelled to Dublin where she made her conversion official and subsequently married a man from a middle-class Catholic family. Marie was born the following year but when only two years old, her mother Catherine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>October 2012. Just as I am making final revisions to this book, my uncle informs me that he has unexpectedly found a few things belonging to my grandmother Roseena (whose story opens Chapter 3). In a brown envelope along with a few letters and some photographs of my mother, my brothers and me taken in Canada the summer before Roseena’s death, is her treasured watch, long assumed lost, a gift from her brother James sent from America. The fine inscription engraved on the back, ‘From James to Roseena Aug 20th 27’ provides another intriguing clue to her migration story. Though</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes and references</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Interviews</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcf8.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
