<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sodomscapes</book-title>
         <subtitle>Hospitality in the Flesh</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gallagher</surname>
               <given-names>Lowell</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275236</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">082327523X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1mtz73h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Sodomscapes presents a fresh approach to the story of Lot’s wife, as it’s been read across cultures and generations. In the process, it reinterprets foundational concepts of ethics, representation, and the body. While the sudden mutation of Lot’s wife in the flight from Sodom is often read to confirm our antiscopic bias, a rival tradition emphasizes the counterintuitive optics required to nurture sustainable habitations for life in view of its unforeseeable contingency. Whether in medieval exegesis, Russian avant-garde art, Renaissance painting, or today’s Dead Sea health care tourism industry, the repeated desire to reclaim Lot’s wife turns the cautionary emblem of the mutating woman into a figural laboratory for testing the ethical bounds of hospitality. Sodomscape—the book’s name for this gesture—revisits touchstone moments in the history of figural thinking and places them in conversation with key thinkers of hospitality. The book’s cumulative perspective identifies Lot’s wife as the resilient figure of vigilant dwelling, whose in-betweenness discloses counterintuitive ways of understanding what counts as a life amid divergent claims of being-with and being-for.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>ENTERING SODOMSCAPE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Figural Moorings of Hospitality in Sodomscape</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Cleveland Museum of Art houses one of the most challenging treatments of the Sodom story in twentieth-century visual culture, Anselm Kiefer’s multimedia work<italic>Lots Frau</italic>(plate 1). It is easy to miss the pale script spelling out “Lots Frau” in the painting’s lower right-hand corner; yet, without it, the work hardly bears relation to either Sodom’s biblical account or the art-historical archive. The inscription supplies only minimal clues, just enough so that the railway tracks and the postapocalyptic landscape eventually prompt recognition of the Sodom story’s generic narrative elements—the drama of exile, the specter of annihilation. For viewers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Exodus, Interrupted:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lot’s Wife and the Allegorical Interval</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Delicately limned veils of crimson flame, descending from the sky, are just beginning to cast a shadow over shimmering pink and ochre buildings, and a verdant, bosky landscape (plate 2). Signs of distress punctuate the cityscapes. Prostrate bodies, as though already struck dead, fill the streets, while other figures look heavenward with hands raised in supplication or alarm. Annihilation is imminent, but not for all. To the left of the condemned cities, angelic emissaries guide Lot and his daughters to safety, following the road’s vertical ascent. A ribbon of sacred text, the road’s lexical twin, silently proclaims the orthodox path,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Rise of Prophecy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Figural Neuter, Desert of Allegory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There’s no getting around it. The route connecting Maître François’s illuminated rendering of the flight from Sodom to Blanchot’s and Levinas’s guarded turns to the Sodom archive has no historical warranty. Blanchot and Levinas’s mutual interest in the question of art charted a wide-ranging interrogation of the enigmatic fact of the artwork’s existence and the unquiet character of art’s aesthetic and ethical open-endedness, conducted across several genres and historical environments.² Their expedition, however, did not pause at the late-medieval scene of manuscript illumination.</p>
                     <p>There are many mansions, of course, in the house of historical inquiry. The forensic model, with its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Remembering Lot’s Wife:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure of Testimony in the Painted Life of Mary Ward</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am looking at a capital “L” (fig. 7). It belongs to a series of ornamented letters, talking letters (<italic>iniziali parlante</italic>), produced in the studio of the sixteenth-century Florentine typographer Bartolomeo Sermartelli.² Sermartelli’s “L” stands for Lot. You can see Sodom in flames, on the horizon to the left of the letter’s spine. Filling the space bounded by the spine and foot is the cave near Zoar, where Lot’s two daughters, believing themselves and their father to be the sole survivors of the catastrophe, have hit upon the solution that will ensure the family’s survival. Given the incest scene’s visual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Avant-Garde Lot’s Wife:</title>
                     <subtitle>Natalia Goncharova’s Salt Pillars and the Rebirth of Hospitality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Out of the crush of sculptural masses and planar angles, bruised thunderheads enshroud the sky. Shards of flame plummet toward the bleached walls of the distant city and the arid expanse of desert, their diagonal chute jarring against the vertical thrust of pale, monumental figures (plate 8). The allusive title—<italic>Salt Pillars</italic>(<italic>Solianye stolpe</italic>)—gives the painting passport into the Sodom archive, even as it also introduces a counting error into the representational scheme with not one, but four pillars (and five subjects: observe the two conjoined figures in the first pillar). The aberration, far from violating an essential feature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Color plates</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Soundings in Sodomscape:</title>
                     <subtitle>Biblical Purity Codes, Spa Clinics, and the Ends of Immunity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>September 12, 2000, Ein Bokek, Israel. I stand defeated at the shores of the Dead Sea.</p>
                     <p>It is still possible to recapture something of François-René de Chateaubriand’s suavely austere reverie overlooking the Dead Sea in the early 1800s, but to do so you have to climb the heights of Masada at dawn (fig. 13).² There is a piece of irony in the detour. Not because the sublimity effect so readily encountered in the nineteenth-century archive of Dead Sea expeditions must be deliberately sought out, away from the sprawling industrial and consumerist complex that now dominates the profile of the region,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The Face of the Contemporary:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lost World Fantasies of Finding Lot’s Wife</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The digital photographs before you belong to Sodomscape in more ways than one (fig. 14, plate 10). Most obviously, they conform to the genre of tourist photography commonly found in the postcards and guidebooks designed to satisfy interest in well-known landmarks of the Dead Sea region. To this end, the photographs also display a characteristic negotiation of the documentary impulse and the taste for the picturesque’s “accidental beauty.”² No more than the illuminated image from Maître François’s studio do the photographs pretend to supply historically accurate information about the destroyed city of Sodom, though the reasons for the photographs’ agnosticism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Out of Africa:</title>
                     <subtitle>Albert Memmi’s Desert of Allegory in The Pillar of Salt</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1891, the French Jewish philanthropist Baron Maurice de Hirsch founded the Jewish Colonization Association, for facilitating the emigration of Ashkenazic Jews to agricultural colonies in the Americas. One of the initiative’s most prosperous outgrowths was the Jewish settlement in Argentina’s Entre Rios province, some 250 miles north of Buenos Aires. The founding residents designed Carmel colony to resemble a Russian village, reincarnating the image of a lost home. Today, only the cemetery and the synagogue survive (fig. 16). Following substantial migrations from the colony, the synagogue ceased to operate in the early 1950s. As a recent tourist publication notes,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mtz73h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
