<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3537 T4753Z6229 1988</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Stevens, Wallace, 1879–1955</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Play on words</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Poetry, Word-Play, and Word-War in Wallace Stevens</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>COOK</surname>
               <given-names>ELEANOR</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400859665</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400859662</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey; Guildford, Surrey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1988</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztwr5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the first full-length study of Wallace Stevens's word-play, Eleanor Cook focuses on Stevens's skillful play with grammar, etymology, allusion, and other elements of poetry, and suggests ways in which this play offers a method of approaching his work. At the same time, this book is a general study of Stevens's poetry, moving from his earliest to his latest work, and includes close readings of three of his remarkable long poems--Esthetique du Mal, Notes toward a Supreme Fiction, and An Ordinary Evening in New Haven. The chronological arrangement enables readers to follow Stevens's increasing skill and changing thought in three areas of his "poetry of the earth": the poetry of place, the poetry of eros, and the poetry of belief.</p>
         <p>Poetry, Word-Play, and Word-War in Wallace Stevens shows how, in setting words at play and in conflict, Stevens could upset the usual relations of rhetoric, grammar, and dialectic, and thus the book contributes to the current debate about logical and a-logical uses of language. Cook also places Stevens within the larger context of Western literature, hearing how he speaks to Milton, Keats, and Wordsworth; to such American forebears as Whitman, Emerson, and Dickinson; and to T. S. Eliot, his contemporary.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1988.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I need to say a number of things all at once, because readers come to word-play with such different assumptions. So I shall say them briefly, then speak in a general way about word-play, before proceeding to an outline of this book, and then to some specialized matters. First, the simple and important point that Stevens liked word-play because it is often wonderfully funny. We sometimes read him a shade solemnly. Second, Stevens ʺwords are almost always deflected from their common denotation,ʺ to quote Helen Vendler.¹ (ʺPersonally I like words to sound wrong,ʺ he once wrote apropos of a translation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Places, Common and Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Rhetoric of Beginning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stevensis such a master of openings that we expect the first poems of<italic>Harmonium</italic>to entice us, and we are a little baffled when they do not. Stevens selected these poems to open<italic>Harmonium</italic>, choosing from work written between 1916 and 1921; he saw no reason to alter the order in 1931 for a second edition or in 1954 for his<italic>Collected Poems</italic>. They are the entrance into his work and I propose to begin with the first six. Slight, pleasing poems, they lead into the powerful pair,<italic>Domination of Black</italic>and<italic>The Snow Man</italic>, but have themselves attracted little</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Play and War of Venus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love Poems and Florida Poems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The young Stevens was a love poet, who wrote verses of paralyzing dullness to his future wife He read erotic poetry when he ʺwas young and reading left and rightʺ (<italic>L</italic>381) Ovidʹs<italic>Ars Amatona</italic>(<italic>L</italic>65), Paulus Silentianus from Mackailʹs<italic>Greek Anthology</italic>(<italic>SP</italic>183–84), Campion, and so on When the miraculous year 1915 came, and Stevens inexplicably began to write major poetry, it was not surprising that one of his subjects was erotic love The poem itself is surprising It is<italic>Peter Quince at the Clavier</italic>, a variation on the Apocryphal story of Susannah and the Elders Stevens</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Limits of Word-Play:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Comedian as the Letter C</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Word-play has no limits, yet in practice it must be limited. Argument, on the other hand, tries to set its own limits. Word-play tends to raise a question of limits, argument tends to mask the question of limits.<italic>The Comedian as the Letter C</italic>is about limits and possible evasions of limits. It is about Stevensʹ younger poetic self, and it first took the form of a<italic>Bildungsroman</italic>, a form that itself provides a plot about overcoming limitations. Stevensʹ revisions changed this form and made the poem much more difficult, as he tried to evade expected plot lines, troping, closure,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Ludus of Allusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poems of Voice and Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Allusion is always a kind of play, if we go by the built-in<italic>ludus</italic>of its etymology, and one early meaning (OED2). Paul de Man calls it an ʺintertextual trope . . in which a complex play of substitutions and repetitions takes place between texts,ʺ¹ and Stevens becomes a master of such allusive play—ʺhe that of repetition is most master,ʺ to borrow a phrase from<italic>Notes toward a Supreme Fiction</italic>and use ʺrepetitionʺ in de Manʹs sense.² Only rarely does he use quotation and only sometimes allusion proper, that is, ʺpart of the portable library shared by the author</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Ways of Ending:</title>
                     <subtitle>Religious and Last Poems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Stevens of<italic>Sunday Morning</italic>is the Stevens with whom most students begin, and rightly so, for it is the first major poem he wrote, and he continued to rewrite it all his life To open his volume, Stevens chose something in the plain style that Perry Miller associates with New World writing.¹ But in 1915, he actually began differently His first major poem was an elegiac type of poem, in the Miltonic tradition that Josephine Miles distinguishes as one dominant American style ²<italic>Sunday Morning</italic>and Stevensʹ antipietistic poems are also poems of place, in their way Or rather,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>A Rhetoric of Beginning Again:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ideas of Order</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ideas of Order</italic>is a book of ending and beginning again, as we can see from the plots of the opening and closing poems. The opening poems tell us that beginning again is often a matter of returning, and the words ʺturnʺ and ʺreturnʺ echo through the volume like a refrain. The trade edition of 1936 opens with<italic>Farewell to Florida</italic>, a voyage from an old love, but not to a new one (the old love is Venus as Florida, the ʺreturnʺ is to a ʺviolent mindʺ). Next we have<italic>Ghosts as Cocoons</italic>: an address to a much-desired bride still</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Concerning the Nature of Things:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Man with the Blue Guitar</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Man with the Blue Guitar</italic>is pivotal in Stevensʹ work, at once a review and a new direction, a refinding of vocation and a preliminary to the major long poems of the forties. The series has a certain austerity, and Stevens himself conceded some boring patches, but rightly judged the poemʹs overall strength: ʺthe man with the blue guitar … while it bores me in spots, is a very much better book than ideas of orderʺ (<italic>L</italic>338, April 27, 1939). Stevensʹ effects are sometimes abrupt or compacted; there is occasional bitterness and disgust, and the poem approaches desperation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Against Synecdoche:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parts of a World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stevens enjoyed himself more in this volume than in<italic>Ideas of Order</italic>or<italic>The Man with the Blue Guitar</italic>, and he was disappointed when readers showed no corresponding enjoyment (<italic>L</italic>429–30, 433, 501) We can hear him indulging his old sense of fun from time to time, for example, in the casual, nudging asides on his own processes (ʺShucks,ʺ ʺPfttʺ) Or in a courtly bow to the reader after an unforgettable line and point ʺThe squirming facts exceed the squamous mind, / If one may say soʺ Or in the play with things that fall stones fall, night falls,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Transport and the Metaphor Poems</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title,<italic>Transport to Summer</italic>, plays in all its words. We should annotate, and we may allegorize or go even further. The annotation is from Stevens himself, who said flatly that by the word ʺsummerʺ he meant ʺrealityʺ (<italic>L</italic>719, June 19, 1951). ʺTransport to Summer,ʺ then, offers to convey us to where and what and how this summer-reality is. What usually transports us to summer is the turning earth itself, and the Stevens who wants to write a poetry of earth, and who has punned so long on turning as troping, must have smiled at this little allegory. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>War and the Normal Sublime:</title>
                     <subtitle>Esthétique du Mal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What kind of word-play is the title<italic>Esthétique du Mal?</italic>Weakly provocative might be one answer—a mixing of aesthetics and ethics, a calling-up of Baudelaire. The word ʺesthétiqueʺ suggests a question of translation, and not just French to English. Greek is also pertinent in the etymological sense of the word, and Stevens said he had this sense in mind. ʺI was thinking of aesthetics as the equivalent of aperçus, which seems to have been the original meaningʺ (<italic>L</italic>469, 1944; cf. OED, ʺaesthetics,ʺ ia, and the headnote, especially on Kant). John Crowe Ransom may have suggested one starting point,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Notes toward a Supreme Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stevens arranged the poems of<italic>Transport to Summer</italic>in approximate chronological order, except for the greatest,<italic>Notes toward a Supreme Fiction</italic>This poem, first printed privately in 1942, closes<italic>Transport to Summer</italic>, a collection written between 1942 and 1947</p>
                     <p>What is Stevens doing in this poem? To put it oversimply,<italic>Notes toward a Supreme Fiction</italic>is a poem that rewrites ʺsupremeʺ writing, that is, our sacred scriptures, or points toward ways of rewriting them It has its own kind of Genesis at the beginning, and its own kind of Revelation at the end Stevens foregoes the usual genres of beginning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Commonplace Apocalypse:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Ordinary Evening in New Haven</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the beginning of this book, I have been speaking of Stevensʹ sense of place. The challenge he sets himself in this poem is to see what remains of the vision that inspired the name and the place, New Haven, and what vision we can now have of such a place. This is a poem of place in the fullest sense of the word.</p>
                     <p>Readers of Stevens have no quarrel with the eucalyptic-apocalytpic word-play (to which I shall come), but may find themselves frustrated by what seems a lack of contact with the common corporeal world (Of course, ʺthe corporeal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Late Poems:</title>
                     <subtitle>Places, Common and Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have moved from the end of<italic>Transport to Summer</italic>to<italic>An Ordinary Evening in New Haven</italic>, the major long poem of Stevensʹ next volume. That poem, and the volumeʹs title poem,<italic>Auroras of Autumn</italic>explore ways of saying farewell. At the same time, Stevens increasingly writes short poems of peculiar force and intensity that do not give the effect of meditating on farewells, except by indirection. Randall Jarrell describes them as the work of a man ʺat once very old and beyond the dominion of age; such men seem to have entered into (or are able to create for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index to Works by Wallace Stevens</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztwr5.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>318</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
