<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6nwr76</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ6147.H5B84 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Historical fiction, Spanish</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spanish fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and history</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Spain</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spain</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Genre Fusion</book-title>
         <subtitle>A New Approach to History, Fiction, and Memory in Contemporary Spain</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brenneis</surname>
               <given-names>Sara J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781557536785</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781612493237</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Purdue University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>West Lafayette, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Purdue University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt6wq3rh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Genre Fusion opens with a straightforward overview of the relationships among history, fiction, and memory in contemporary culture. While providing an up-to-date context for scholarly debates about Spain’s historical memory, Genre Fusion also expands the contours of the discussion beyond the specialized territory of Hispanic studies. To demonstrate the theoretical necessity of genre fusion, Brenneis analyzes pairs of interconnected texts (one a work of literature, the other a work of historiography) written by a single author. She explores how fictional and nonfictional works by Montserrat Roig, Carmen Martín Gaite, Carlos Blanco Aguinaga, and Javier Marías unearth the collective memories of Spain’s past.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Origins of Genre Fusion in Spain</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aristotle theorized the relationship between history and fiction in the fourth century BC by writing that although the historian and the poet may use the same narrative tools, their “true difference is that one relates what has happened, the other what may happen” (68). By that token, the Greek philosopher wrote, “poetry tends to express the universal, history the particular” (68). Yet Aristotle foresaw the central issue that would stymie narratologists and historians in the coming centuries: What happens when the poet writes about history? According to Aristotle, he remains a poet, not a historian: “for there is no reason</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Montserrat Roig:</title>
                     <subtitle>Testimony of the Marginalized Catalan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Catalan photographer Francesc Boix’s filmed deposition at the Nuremberg Trials, in January 1946, illustrates the power of testimony. An unseen interlocutor asks Boix in French, “Does the witness recognize among the defendants anyone who visited the camp of Mauthausen?” Boix looks to his right, rises from the witness stand, and points across the room, responding to the question with one word: “Speer.” He proceeds to describe how at Mauthausen he developed photographs of Albert Speer, Hitler’s chief architect during World War II, and thus could vouch for Speer’s presence at the Austrian work camp in 1943 (“Trial Testimony against Albert</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Carmen Martín Gaite:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rewriting Spain’s Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After nearly three days lying in state at the Palacio de Oriente, during which hundreds of thousands of mourners filed past his open casket, Francisco Franco’s flag-draped coffin was transported some 60 kilometers outside Madrid to the Valle de los Caídos. There, it was ceremoniously lowered into a grave marked concisely with a cross and his name. Spaniards across the country were riveted to their television screens on November 23, 1975, watching the somber proceedings unfold. Franco’s family, military representatives, and the Chilean dictator Augusto Pinochet, among others, observed from inside the Valley’s cavernous mausoleum (Preston 779–80). On that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Carlos Blanco Aguinaga:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Spanish Other in Mexico</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Sinaia</italic>, sailing from Sète, France to Veracruz, Mexico in the summer of 1939, published its own newspaper, the<italic>Diario de la primera expedición de republicanos españoles a México</italic>. The May 30, 1939 edition included a summary of Professor Modesto Bargallo’s recently held mid-sea conference on Mexico’s geography: “Estados Unidos, al Norte; al Este, el Golfo de México; al Sur, la América Central y al Oeste, el Pácifico” (Ruiz Funes and Tuñón 73–74). This was necessary information for the refugees aboard, seeing as how many had almost no conception of their destination. “‘No tenía ni la menor idea de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Javier Marías:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genre Fusion in the New Millennium</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Spanish daily newspaper<italic>El País</italic>published an editorial by Javier Marías one day after the terrorist attacks at Madrid’s Atocha train station in 2004. Marías located this brutal act in the context of a well-worn routine:</p>
                     <p>Cada vez que ETA asesina —y casi siempre lo hace de buena mañana, los terroristas madrugan, o quizá es que no duerman la noche previa—, existe la costumbre de que, hacia el mediodía, los responsables de los ayuntamientos de las ciudades salgan a la puerta de sus edificios, con calor, frío o lluvia, y guarden uno o dos minutos de silencio. (“De</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his influential examination of the social and historical conditions that gave rise to the historical novel, Georg Lukács describes the power of a “real mass movement” to influence the way people view and lend importance to history. “The appeal to national independence and national character,” Lukács writes, “is necessarily connected with a re-awakening of national history, with memories of the past, of past greatness, of moments of national dishonour, whether this results in a progressive or reactionary ideology” (25). Although Lukács’s observations are trained on early nineteenth-century movements in Europe, they are equally applicable to the re-emergence of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq3rh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
