<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3279.H94B73 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Husserl, Edmund, 1859–1938</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fink, Eugen</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Edmund Husserl and Eugen Fink</book-title>
         <subtitle>Beginnings and Ends in Phenomenology, 1928–1938</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BRUZINA</surname>
               <given-names>RONALD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300092097</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0300092091</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300130157</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0300130155</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1nppmd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Eugen Fink was Edmund Husserl's research assistant during the last decade of the renowned phenomenologist's life, a period in which Husserl's philosophical ideas were radically recast. In this landmark book, Ronald Bruzina shows that Fink was actually a collaborator with Husserl, contributing indispensable elements to their common enterprise.Drawing on hundreds of hitherto unknown notes and drafts by Fink, Bruzina highlights the scope and depth of his theories and critiques. He places these philosophical formulations in their historical setting, organizes them around such key themes as the world, time, life, and the concept and methodological place of the "meontic," and demonstrates that they were a pivotal impetus for the renewing of "regress to the origins" in transcendental-constitutive phenomenology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="658"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Contextual Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Freiburg Phenomenology Workshop, 1925–1938</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy is never done nowhere. If it is not the work of a particular someone at a particular time and in a particular place, then it<italic>is</italic>not at all. What we shall be looking into is the philosophy that was done in a special place at a very special time in the history of the twentieth century, but the question of the particular someone is precisely the matter that is at issue. For it was not just one particular person who was involved; there was a second particular someone engaged in this same philosophic endeavor. The two, of course,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Orientation I:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology Beyond the Preliminary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unlike those of us today who wish to study the philosophy of Edmund Husserl, Eugen Fink did not gain his understanding of phenomenology primarily from texts. Whereas we are faced with the massive collection of manuscripts in the Husserl Archives at Louvain and the continuing publication of selections from them in the Husserliana series, Fink listened to Husserl himself, spoke with him, thought with him. It was not the written line of what Plato called “dead discourse” but “the living speech”³ of Husserl’s own teaching that he followed. Roman Ingarden has given a description of how Husserl’s lectures were always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Orientation II:</title>
                     <subtitle>Who Is Phenomenology? Husserl—Heidegger?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The years 1929 and 1930 saw Fink in an extraordinary philosophical situation. Here was Martin Heidegger, lecturing with stunning originality and insightfulness, the chosen successor of Husserl openly taking issue with his once indispensable patron. And here was Husserl, model of intense, meticulous phenomenological study, shocked into recognition that “his” Heidegger was a man other than he had thought him to be and a figure whose philosophical development was a profound challenge to all that Husserl had thought was the secure foundation of his life’s work. And there stood Eugen Fink, fresh with his doctorate gained while listening to both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fundamental Thematics I:</title>
                     <subtitle>The World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the theme of the<italic>world</italic>had to dominate the framing of the central matters to be investigated in phenomenology was not Heidegger’s discovery, and it was not in Heidegger’s lectures that Fink first saw this principle manifest. Transcendental phenomenology<italic>began</italic>in the recognition that the world had to be taken explicitly precisely as an overwhelmingly comprehensive structure that remained yet to be thematized properly in philosophy. The most famous methodological “devices” in Husserl’s phenomenology, the epoché and phenomenological reduction, are precisely moves by which the questioning of the world is to begin authentically, against the unwitting and unquestioned acceptance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Fundamental Thematics II:</title>
                     <subtitle>Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If we would begin the treatment of time and temporality at the level of critical phenomenological consideration sketched out in the previous three chapters, we could simply start with material drawn from Fink’s notes and sketches for the study of time beyond the Bernau texts, that is, from 1933 and 1934 (and later), correlating them with Husserl’s newer work in the C-manuscripts on temporality of 1930 to 1934. For example, the critical insights we considered in chapter 4 are neatly continued in some of the points Fink makes in several outline variants for an “Introduction” to his then projected “time-book.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Fundamental Thematics III:</title>
                     <subtitle>Life and Spirit, and Entry into the Meontic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>316</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>January 1936: In a year and a half Husserl will be stricken with his final illness, and in a little more than two years his life will come to an end. Without knowing it, he has only eighteen months left of productive capability; but he has been renewed by the previous November’s experience of giving his Prague lectures, “The Crisis of European Sciences and Psychology,” and he is in feverish labor over the first part of his “Crisis”-texts. The University of Freiburg, against the standard honoring of emeritus professors, no longer lists him in the roster of its academic personnel,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Critical-Systematic Core:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Meontic—in Methodology and in the Recasting of Metaphysics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Someone once wrote of Beethoven: “His string quartets do not grow from or reflect specific experiences; they summarize; they are his personality abstracted into absolute music.”⁴ If only it were so simple: that thought about the Absolute could indeed be wrested out of the stuff of experienced creation through some wonderful process that would distill from it the pure form by which its being is manifest. On the other hand, perhaps it does get done precisely<italic>in music!</italic>Perhaps music is the Play of Being in its closest coming to that Absolute of Transcendent Form, the Absolute that lies originative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Corollary Thematics I:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>452</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The import of the meontic in determining the function and import of the speculative dimension did not have to wait until the very last to have an effect upon the reconsideration that the phenomenological findings in Husserl’s vast analytic investigations had to undergo. It was already in play from the earliest work that Fink did with and for Husserl, as the long trajectory of the present study has been showing. However, in our following this effort of reconsideration, this reorienting and recasting of descriptive features already disclosed in the investigative analytic that allowed new aspects to come to the fore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Corollary Thematics II:</title>
                     <subtitle>Solitude and Community—Intersubjectivity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>482</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The signal successes that Husserl experienced in the late winter and spring of 1929 marked a high point in his life, the irony of which began to show already in the summer that followed, to become soon afterward—as chapter 1 recounted—more painful yet as the years proceeded, until his life came to a close in 1938. Nevertheless, what began to unfold in February 1929 was a remarkable renewal and a consummate achievement for phenomenology. In that month Husserl had given his “Introduction to Phenomenological Philosophy” at the Sorbonne in the Amphithéâtre Descartes, the very hall named after the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Beginning Again after the End of the Freiburg Phenomenology Workshop, 1938–1946</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>521</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For phenomenology there was a silence in Freiburg. Husserl had died on April 27, 1938, and within a year nothing of what remained of his life and thought was left in that city. Between mid-September and the end of November 1938, thanks to the extraordinary efforts of the young Belgian Franciscan priest, Herman Leo Van Breda, all Husserl’s manuscripts were secretly rescued from Germany and taken to safety in Louvain.³ Fink emigrated to Belgium on March 16, 1939, to be joined by Ludwig Landgrebe from Prague on April 24 and Malvine Husserl on June 20.</p>
                     <p>The long Freiburg conversation, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Longer Notations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>545</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>585</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1nppmd.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>628</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
