<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Hope and the Longing for Utopia</book-title>
         <subtitle>Futures and Illusions in Theology and Narrative</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boscaljon</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175057</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903902</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf and Stock Publisher</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf5h7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>At present the battle over who defines our future is being waged most publicly by secular and religious fundamentalists. 'Hope and the Longing for Utopia' offers an alternative position, disclosing a conceptual path toward potential worlds that resist a limited view of human potential and the gift of religion. In addition to outlining the value of embracing unknown potentialities, these twelve interdisciplinary essays explore why it has become crucial that we commit to hoping for values that resist traditional ideological commitments. Contextualized by contemporary writing on utopia, and drawing from a wealth of times and cultures ranging from Calvin’s Geneva to early twentieth-century Japanese children’s stories to Hollywood cinema, these essays cumulatively disclose the fundamental importance of resisting tantalizing certainties while considering the importance of the unknown and unknowable. Beginning with a set of four essays outlining the importance of hope and utopia as diagnostic concepts, and following with four concrete examples, the collection ends with a set of essays that provide theological speculations on the need to embrace finitude and limitations in a world increasingly enframed by secularizing impulses. Overall, this book discloses how hope and utopia illuminate ways to think past simplified wishes for the future.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Biographical Information for Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Value of Cultivating Longing in a Secularized World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boscaljon</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the blessings of technology, we have infused the twenty-first-century world with matters of the moment: we have acquired a taste for what occurs now and no longer have the patience to suffer our dreams to come to fruition. Marketers create a craving for consumption, convenience, and certainty: they frame digital technologies as tools whose use is restricted to temporarily satiating such demands. eliminating the arduous temporal gap that more ephemeral goods demand, our world provides a series of superficial goods whose certain attainment encourages us to sacrifice the search for that which would provide more authentic fulfillment. Because distractions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Utopia and Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theology between the Boundaries of Overhumanization and Hypertheism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ehret</surname>
                           <given-names>Verna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Religion is the deeply human enterprise of evaluating and interpreting self and others based on what concerns one ultimately. religion simultaneously gives one an image of whom one is meant to be and of a society that promotes this realization in and for others. in other words, religion puts forth a utopic image—the image of a complete human life in relation to culture, society, and civilization as a whole. it is the work of the theologian to engage the changing narratives of religion in order to promote religion’s capacity to work continuously toward this utopic vision of human flourishing.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Hope, Hatred, and the Ambiguities of Utopic Longing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cates</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana Fritz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the beginning of the<italic>Nicomachean Ethics,</italic>Aristotle asks his students to identify the highest good for humans, the content of<italic>eudaimonia</italic>or human flourishing. “Surely,” he says, “knowledge of this good is . . . of great importance for the conduct of our lives, and if, like archers, we have a target [at which to aim], we are more likely to hit the right mark.” ¹ What would it be like for a human being to enjoy the realization of his or her full potential? What would it be like for all humans to thrive, not only individually, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>What Means Utopia to Us?</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconsidering More’s Message</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baggett</surname>
                           <given-names>Marybeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Almost five centuries after<italic>Thomas More’s</italic>publication of<italic>Utopia</italic>, the insights of that work have all but disappeared beneath the mountain of fiction, criticism, and theory that has been built up around it. in many ways, the popular and critical reception of More’s text epitomizes the prediction about the written word plato offers in the<italic>Phaedrus.¹</italic>it has lost the protection of its author, and the many translations, adaptations, and appropriations of More’s material make difficult authentic engagement with his work. Yet, in light of More’s contemporary influence, his historical reputation, and his contribution to the popularization of humanism,<italic>Utopia</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Desiring Utopian Subjects:</title>
                     <subtitle>Collectivity and Its Discontents</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Holly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The status of literary utopias at the turn of the third millennium is fraught with productive complexity. often used colloquially to deride impractical or vaguely hopeful social arrangements, the term “utopia” is still employed to signal a representation of society based on principles that direct human satisfaction. Literary theorist Krishan Kumar reflects that while utopianism is still a lively part of social and cultural life, literary utopia has waned, occluded by its alter identity—dystopian literature.¹ While others contemplate the decline of myth generally or the modern myth of progress specifically, Kumar suggests that utopian fiction may be eclipsed at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>John Calvin, Geneva, and Godly Patriarchs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hope and Reality in the Creation of a Christian Utopia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Plank</surname>
                           <given-names>Ezra L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 17 January 1544, Pierre Rosset appeared before the ecclesiastical disciplinary tribunal in Geneva—the consistory—and was questioned regarding his treatment of his wife, anthoyne. The previous week, she had testified that he regularly beat her. When confronted, pierre claimed that, in fact, he did “not want to live except according to god;” the problem was that his wife did “not want to do what he command[ed] her.” He further asserted that anthoyne insulted him, demonstrating that she “want[ed] to be the master.” in a strong assertion of patriarchal sovereignty that modern readers find appalling, he insisted that he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Fruit, Fossils, Footprints:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cathecting Utopia in the Work of Miyazawa Kenji</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Curley</surname>
                           <given-names>Melissa Anne-Marie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Essays on the Japanese writer Miyazawa Kenji (1896–1933) often begin with an inventory of his interests and accomplishments. The list is irresistible: he was a poet and author, particularly remembered now for his children’s stories, but also a soil scientist, a high school teacher, and a sometime fertilizer salesman. He was the head of an agricultural cooperative founded on the basis of his own theory of peasant aesthetics. He was an amateur geologist, a student of esperanto, and a cellist. He was an avid hiker and cataloguer of things observed while hiking. He was a devout Buddhist and an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Walter Kerr’s Utopia of Re-Creation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hunnicutt</surname>
                           <given-names>Benjamin K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Walter Kerr (1913–96) began his career teaching speech and drama at The Catholic University of america, moving on to write about the theatre for<italic>Commonweal</italic>in the early 1950s. afterwards, he was theatre critic for the<italic>New York Herald Tribune</italic>and then for<italic>The New York Times</italic>until his retirement.He was also a playwright, lyricist, and director of a number of Broadway plays and musicals, the most successful of which was “goldilocks” (1958), which he wrote with his wife Jean Kerr and which won two tony awards. in midcareer, as one of the most influential theatre critics in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Reframed Hope:</title>
                     <subtitle>Transcendent Technology and Spiraling Subjectivity in Dystopian Cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hamner</surname>
                           <given-names>Everett</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>True Religion</italic>, graham Ward argues that “the end [of religion] does not signal the falling into disuse or the oblivion of the religious. Rather, it signals exactly the opposite: the extension and hype of the religious as the ultimate vision of the excessive and the transgressive.”¹ As he observed over a decade ago, early twenty-first- century society is less the product of religion’s disappearance than its immersion in spectacle. foreshadowing much contemporary scholarship, Ward found religion not just in traditional institutional settings, but “in commercial business, gothic and sci-fi fantasy, in health clubs, themed bars and architectural design, of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Who We Are Is God’s Dying:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Real Presence of God’s Absence in Bonhoeffer’s Prison Poems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schroeder</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many times the same dream visited me in my past life, appearing in different forms but saying the same thing. “Socrates,” it said, “get to work and make music. At the time, I took this to mean what I was doing already and assumed the dream was encouraging and urging me on—the way people cheer for members of their own team—to make music. And, philosophy being the greatest music, I was doing that already. But now after the trial, with the religious festival delaying my execution, it occurred to me that if the dream was urging me to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>TechnoTopia:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Convergence of Art and Technology in the Twentieth Century and Beyond</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Elwell</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Sage</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her book<italic>The Concept of Utopia,</italic>Ruth Levitas writes that utopia is “the expression of desire for a better way of living and being.”¹ accepting her formulation as a starting point, the question i raise here is: what informs that “desire for a better way of living and being”? That is, what are the grounding principles that shape a desire for a better way of living and being? in this chapter, I address this question to three artists who self-consciously envisioned an aesthetic and cultural utopia in light of the defining technologies of the twentieth century. At a time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Coming Community:</title>
                     <subtitle>Agamben, Benjamin, and the Hope for a Materialist-Messianic Redemption of the Present</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hall</surname>
                           <given-names>W. David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A chronicler who recites the events without distinguishing between the major and minor ones acts in accordance with the following truth: nothing that has ever happened should be regarded as lost for history. To be sure, only a redeemed mankind receives the fullness of its past—which is to say, only for a redeemed mankind has its past become citable in all its moments. Each moment it has lived becomes a<italic>citation à l’order du jour</italic>— and that day is Judgement day.¹</p>
                     <p>From the mid-sixteenth century onward, the worldview that has come to dominate in those societies that draw their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>No-Places for Sacred Communities:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hope and the Failure of Fight Club</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boscaljon</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In David fincher’s 1998 cult classic<italic>Fight Club,</italic>based on Chuck palahniuk’s 2005 novel, edward norton plays an anonymous protagonist lured away from a corporate life of khakis and power points by the charismatic proclamations of Brad pitt’s tyler durden. durden’s message responds to social conditions in the late twentieth and early twenty-first century, unmasking the twinned ideological frameworks supporting America: consumerism and religion. I base this assessment on paul ricoeur’s discussion of the conservative nature of ideology, which “conserves, in the sense of making firm the human order that could be shattered by natural or historical forces, by external</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5h7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
