<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125vwv</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">yu--17860</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS736 .Y867 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Chinese History and Culture</book-title>
         <subtitle>Seventeenth Century Through Twentieth Century</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Yü</surname>
               <given-names>Ying-shih</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">With the editorial assistance of</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Chiu-Duke</surname>
               <given-names>Josephine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Duke</surname>
               <given-names>Michael S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231542005</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231542003</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/yu--17860"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The recipient of the Kluge Prize for lifetime achievement in the humanities and the Tang Prize for "revolutionary research" in Sinology, Ying-shih Yü is a premier scholar of Chinese studies.<italic>Chinese History and Culture</italic>volumes 1 and 2 bring his extraordinary oeuvre to English-speaking readers. Spanning two thousand years of social, intellectual, and political change, the essays in these volumes investigate two central questions through all aspects of Chinese life: what core values sustained this ancient civilization through centuries of upheaval, and in what ways did these values survive in modern times?</p>
         <p>From Ying-shih Yü's perspective, the<italic>Dao</italic>, or the Way, constitutes the inner core of Chinese civilization. His work explores the unique dynamics between Chinese intellectuals' discourse on the<italic>Dao</italic>, or moral principles for a symbolized ideal world order, and their criticism of contemporary reality throughout Chinese history. Volume 2 of<italic>Chinese History and Culture</italic>completes Ying-shih Yü's systematic reconstruction and exploration of Chinese thought over two millennia and its impact on Chinese identity. Essays address the rise of Qing Confucianism, the development of the Dai Zhen and Zhu Xi traditions, and the response of the historian Zhang Xuecheng to the Dai Zhen approach. They take stock of the thematic importance of Cao Xueqin's eighteenth-century masterpiece<italic>Honglou meng</italic>(<italic>Dream of the Red Chamber</italic>) and the influence of Sun Yat-sen's<italic>Three Principles of the People</italic>, as well as the radicalization of China in the twentieth century and the fundamental upheavals of modernization and revolution. Ying-shih Yü also discusses the decline of elite culture in modern China, the relationships among democracy, human rights, and Confucianism, and changing conceptions of national history. He reflects on the Chinese approach to history in general and the larger political and cultural function of chronological biographies. By situating China's modern encounter with the West in a wider historical frame, this second volume of<italic>Chinese History and Culture</italic>clarifies its more curious turns and contemplates the importance of a renewed interest in the traditional Chinese values recognizing common humanity and human dignity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="448"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AUTHOR’S PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yü</surname>
                           <given-names>Ying-shih</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDITORIAL NOTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CHRONOLOGY OF DYNASTIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Some Preliminary Observations on the Rise of Qing Confucian Intellectualism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a thoroughly revised and much expanded version of a paper first drafted in 1971. Since it was originally intended to serve as an introduction to my book-length study, tentatively entitled<italic>The Rise of Confucian Intellectualism in the Qing</italic>, with it, I tried to cover rather than dig the ground. In rewriting this paper, I have still followed my original plan by avoiding, as much as possible, factual details. The central task I set for myself was to formulate certain conceptual schemes in light of which the internal development of Neo-Confucianism from the Song to the Qing may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Dai Zhen and the Zhu Xi Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his essay “Zhu and Lu” and its “Postscript,” Zhang Xuecheng 章學誠 (1738–1801) made a highly illuminating and original criticism of Dai Zhen 戴震 (1724–1777) with regard to the latter’s intellectual relationship with Zhu Xi 朱熹 (1130–1200). Zhang began by pointing out that in terms of intellectual ancestry, Dai was very much in the Zhu Xi tradition, which had all along stressed classical scholarship as a Confucian calling. Since Dai had the advantage of living and working in the heyday of Qing philology, however, it was natural that, technically, he surpassed Zhu Xi in textual studies. Nevertheless,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Dai Zhen’s Choice Between Philosophy and Philology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dai Zhen 戴震 (1724–1777) presents two entirely different images in the intellectual history of the mid-Qing Period: that of a classical philologist and that of a Confucian philosopher. During his own time, it was Dai the philologist who received universal recognition in the scholarly world. On the other hand, Dai the philosopher was largely ignored or even denounced by his contemporaries. Zhang Xuecheng’s 章學誠 (1738–1801) great appreciation of Dai’s philosophical writings was not shared at all by such common friends as Zhu Yun 朱筠 (1729–1781) and Shao Jinhan 邵晉涵 (1743–1796). In modern times, it is largely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Zhang Xuecheng Versus Dai Zhen:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Study in Intellectual Challenge and Response in Eighteenth-Century China</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the learned judgment of modern intellectual historians, Dai Zhen 戴震 (1724–1777) and Zhang Xuecheng 學誠 (1738–1801) are the two towering scholars in eighteenth-century China.¹ Perhaps nothing would strike the contemporaries of Dai and Zhang, including their common friends, such as Zhu Yun 朱筠 (1729–1781) and Shao Jinhan 邵晉涵 (1743–1796), as more absurd than this modern judgment. In their own times, Dai was widely acknowledged as the foremost leader of the new philological movement in Confucian classical studies, whereas Zhang, though well respected as a serious theorist of history and literature in a small coterie of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Qing Confucianism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The best way to characterize Confucianism in the Qing dynasty (hereafter Qing Confucianism) is to contrast it with what is called Song-Ming Neo-Confucianism. Song-Ming Neo-Confucians were primarily moral philosophers debating among themselves endlessly on metaphysical questions such as whether “moral princi ples” (<italic>li</italic>理) are inherent in “human nature” (<italic>xing</italic>性) or in “human mind” (<italic>xin</italic>心). By contrast, Qing Confucians were, first and foremost, scholars devoting themselves painstakingly to philological explication of classical and historical texts. As a result, the Song-Ming Period witnessed the emergence and development of the rivalry between two major philosophical systems represented,respectively, by the Cheng-Zhu</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Two Worlds of Honglou meng (Dream of the Red Chamber)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two worlds in sharp contrast to each other are created by Cao Xueqin 曹雪芹 (1716?–1763) in his novel<italic>Honglou meng</italic>紅樓夢 (Dream of the Red Chamber), two worlds which, for the sake for distinction, I shall call the “Utopian world” and the “world of real ity.” These two worlds, as embodied in the novel, are the world of Daguanyuan 大觀園¹ and the world that existed outside it. The difference between these two worlds is indicated by a variety of opposing symbols, such as “purity” and “impurity,” “love” and “lust,” “falsity” and “truth,” and the two sides of the Precious</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Sun Yat-sen’s Doctrine and Traditional Chinese Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an autobiographical sketch written in 1923, Sun Yat-sen 孫逸仙 said about his own thought: “Among the various revolutionary ideas I hold, some are adapted from traditional Chinese thought, others are appropriated from theories and practices developed in Europe, and still others are original insights grown out of my own critical reflections.”¹ On the whole, I believe, this self-analysis can be easily borne out by a thorough investigation of his writings. That would lie beyond the scope of this study, however. The aim of the present chapter is rather a modest one. I shall confine my analysis to the first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>The Radicalization of China in the Twentieth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the turn of the century, a radical mode of thinking has dominated the Chinese mind. The history of Chinese thought in the twentieth century may be interpreted as a process of rapid radicalization. As a matter of fact, never in its long intellectual tradition of over 2.5 millennia had China been as thoroughly radicalized as in modern times.</p>
                     <p>Radicalism in the Chinese intellectual tradition, however, has its limits. The critique developed within the tradition is essentially an internal one. Traditional critics in general and Confucians in particular have tended to take the Way (<italic>Dao</italic>) to be immanent in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Neither Renaissance nor Enlightenment:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Historian’s Reflections on the May Fourth Movement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, the May Fourth Movement has generally been identified as the Chinese Enlightenment. When Chinese authors first gave the movement this new identity in the late 1930s and early 1940s, it was clearly intended as a tribute of the highest possible order by way of analogy. Now that the twentieth century is over, however, the honor originally implied in that identity is fast becoming a dubious one. Indeed, now the dark side of the Enlightenment project centering on the idea of rationality is often perceived as a “failure,” or even worse, as a form of “domination.” It is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Modernization Versus Fetishism of Revolution in Twentieth-Century China</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nowadays the term “modernization” has lost much of the popularity it once enjoyed during the 1950s in the heyday of American modernization theory. In recent academic discourse, the place of “modernization” has been taken over by a number of “posts” beginning with “postmodern.” It is significant to note, however, that as early as the 1970s, some of the leading modernization theorists already found it necessary to reformulate the original thesis by way of clarification or modification. As a response to a widespread dissatisfaction with many of the assumptions of initial modernization studies, Daedalus devoted a whole special issue in 1973</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>The Idea of Democracy and the Twilight of the Elite Culture in Modern China</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his famous<italic>Democracy in America</italic>(4 vols., 1835–1840), Alexis de Tocqueville made the following most illuminating observation:</p>
                     <p>If ever a democratic republic similar to that of the United States came to be established in a country in which earlier a single man’s power had introduced administrative centralization and had made it something accepted by custom and by law, I have no hesitation in saying that in such a republic despotism would become more intolerable than in any of the absolute monarchies of Europe. One would have to go over into Asia to find anything with which to compare</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>China’s New Wave of Nationalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Samuel P.Huntington’s idea of the “third wave” of democ ratization has been remarkably influential and continues to figure importantly in democracy studies today. Ironically, by 1993, Huntington had already shifted his attention from the third wave to the clash of civilizations. In his 1991 article “Religion and the Third Wave,” Huntington suggests a causal relationship between Christianity and democracy that anticipates his much-debated thesis of 1993.¹ In his book<italic>The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order</italic>, the third wave is summed up as follows:</p>
                     <p>During the 1970s and 1980s over thirty countries shifted from authoritarian to democratic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Democracy, Human Rights, and Confucian Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As concepts, both “democracy” and “human rights” are of distinctly Western origins, the former being traceable to ancient Greece and the latter to theories of “Natural Law” and “Natural Rights” developed between the Renaissance and the Enlightenment.¹ Since the end of the nineteenth century, however, Chinese intellectuals have become so fascinated with them, together with a host of other related Western concepts or values such as liberty, equality, social contract, etc., that they have made every effort to transplant them to China. It is true that during the entire Mao Zedong era (1949–1976), Chinese intellectuals under the Communist regime</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Changing Conceptions of National History in Twentieth-Century China</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of “national history” in its current Western usage was wholly unfamiliar to Chinese historians before the twentieth century. This was primarily because there was no notion of “nation” in traditional Chinese political parlance. A most revealing illustration may be found in a conversation between a Chinese official and a British trade representative in Canton prior to the outbreak of the Opium War in 1839. The official is reported to have been at a complete loss when the trade representative referred to China as a “nation.”¹ Even after the Treaty of Nanking in 1842, many high-ranking Chinese officials at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Reflections on Chinese Historical Thinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With a historiographical tradition as long and variegated as China’s, any attempt at a sweeping generalization of Chinese historical thought with a view to clearly distinguishing it from its Western counterpart is hazardous. To suggest that there are essential determinate characteristics in Chinese historiography that are wholly absent in the West is to lapse into a false essentialism. The more I know about the history of Western historiography, the less I am sure about the possibility of drawing a sharp distinction between the two traditions. As far as the individual component parts of Chinese and Western historiographies are concerned, they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Modern Chronological Biography and the Conception of Historical Scholarship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chronological biography (<italic>nianpu</italic>) is a special form of Chinese historical writing. Leaving aside the lost<italic>Zibian nianpu</italic>自編年譜 (Autobiographical Compilation) of Bai Juyi 白居易 (772–864), this form of writing can be traced to the Song dynasty (960–1279) beginning with the chronological biographies of Han Yu 韓愈 (768–824) and Liu Zongyuan 柳宗元 (773–819). In the one thousand years since, thousands of<italic>nianpu</italic>, including chronological autobiographies, have been produced in China. More than twelve hundred chronological biographies are listed in Li Shitao’s<italic>Zhongguo lidai mingren nianpu mulu</italic>(Bibliography of Chronological Biographies of Famous Figures by Dynasty).¹ Today, new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>The Study of Chinese History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Retrospect and Prospect</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History has always been the most glorious of all branches of knowledge in the scholarly tradition of China. It has declined markedly nowadays, however. This decline is not an isolated or unusual phenomenon; it is merely a part of the poverty of the Chinese scholarly world in modern times. Not only natural sciences, but social sciences and the humanities have not had adequate opportunities for development during the last fifty or sixty years. Even in philosophy, a subject that has the most to do with raising the intellectual level of the average educated person, research and instruction have not gone</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18.</label>
                     <title>Confucianism and China’s Encounter with the West in Historical Perspective</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The thesis of a “clash of civilizations” has been much debated since Samuel P. Huntington published his famous article in<italic>Foreign Affairs</italic>in 1993.¹ In<italic>The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order</italic>(New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996; page numbers in parentheses for this title only), Huntington gives his original thesis a more detailed documentation and, at the same time, also somewhat modifies some of the sharp formulations in the earlier article. However, the book is essentially an elaboration, not a revision, of the original argument. To avoid distorting Huntington, I would like to present the core</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19.</label>
                     <title>Clio’s New Cultural Turn and the Rediscovery of Tradition in Asia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I deeply appreciate the great honor of being asked to speak before this distinguished assembly of historians of Asia. I must confess, however, that I accepted this important assignment not entirely without hesitation. I hesitated because I was not quite sure that I could find things to say that might interest all of you. By professional training, I am only a tender of the small garden of early Chinese history and wholly ignorant of other vineyards of Asian history in which many of you have productively labored. It seems that the only way for my speech to make some sense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>385</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>ADDRESS OF PROFESSOR YÜ YING-SHIH ON THE OCCASION OF RECEIVING THE JOHN W. KLUGE PRIZE AT THE LIBRARY OF CONGRESS AND ACCEPTANCE SPEECH ON THE OCCASION OF RECEIVING THE TANG PRIZE FOR SINOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">yu--17860.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
