<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Atheist's Primer</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Palmer</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718892975</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718841478</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael Palmer</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdxp0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In The Atheist's Primer, a prominent philosopher, Dr Michael Palmer, reinstates the importance of philosophy in the debate about God's existence. The 'new atheism' of Richard Dawkins and others has been driven by largely Darwinian objections to God's existence, limiting the debate to within a principally scientific framework. This has obscured the philosophical tradition of atheism, in which the main intellectual landmarks in atheism's history are to be found. With an analysis of atheistic thought from the Ancient Greeks to the present day, Palmer explains and comments on the philosophical arguments warranting atheism, discussing issues such as evil, morality, miracles, and the motivations for belief. The emphasis placed on materialism and the limitations of our knowledge might seem disheartening to some; but Palmer concludes on a positive note, arguing – alongside Nietzsche, Marx and Freud and many others – that happiness and personal fulfilment are to be found in the very materialism that religious belief rejects. Michael Palmer first addressed these issues in his student-oriented edition, The Atheist's Creed, of which The Atheist's Primer is a revised abridgement for the general reader. Palmer has now stripped out the primary texts and expanded his commentaries into fluent and concise analyses of the arguments. Free of philosophical jargon and assumptions of prior knowledge, this is an important introduction to a major cultural debate.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="168"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Atheist’s Creed</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Palmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Atheism is currently enjoying the limelight, both in academic circles and in the popular press. The so-called ‘new atheists’ are in vogue, and books like Richard Dawkins’<italic>The God Delusion</italic>(2006), Daniel Dennett’s<italic>Breaking the Spell</italic>(2006), Sam Harris’<italic>The End of Faith</italic>(2004) and his<italic>Letter to a Christian Nation</italic>(2006) and the two volumes published in 2007 by the late Christopher Hitchens –<italic>God is not Great</italic>and his wide-ranging anthology<italic>The Portable Atheist</italic>– have caught the public imagination. Unsurprisingly, believers have not been slow to enter the lists. Alister McGrath has countered with his<italic>The Twilight</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Meaning of Atheism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word ‘atheism’ is a translation of the Greek<italic>atheos</italic>, which combines the prefix<italic>a</italic>(meaning ‘not’ or ‘without’) with<italic>theos</italic>(meaning ‘god’). Accordingly the term is most commonly employed as ‘disbelief in, or denial of, the existence of God’. However, this definition is not as straightforward as it appears. In the first place, and most obviously, what is being disbelieved in or denied will change according to the various definitions of God being employed. Thus atheism from the standpoint of the Christian religion, which believes in a personal God who is the one supreme personal being and creator of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Origins of Atheism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The origins of Western atheism lie in classical antiquity, in which first developed a naturalistic and empirical explanation of the world. Already visible in Greece in the philosophy of the Sophists of the second half of the fifth century B.C., this replacement of divine by natural causation became much more pronounced in the later schools of Epicurean Materialism and Scepticism. It is not easy to say precisely why this occurred, and why the old mythological conception of the gods as the sole agents of creation should have declined so rapidly. Various explanations have been offered. Gaskin suggests that the multiple</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Two Arguments for God’s Existence:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Atheistic Critique</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the positive atheist’s case to succeed, a range of classic arguments for God’s existence must be refuted.¹ Although sometimes called ‘proofs’, only one of them can lay legitimate claim to that name. This is the so-called ontological argument first presented by Anselm of Canterbury (c.1033-1109). Here Anselm argues that, from the definition of God – that ‘God is something than which nothing greater can be conceived’ – one may conclude, as a matter of logic, that God exists, his existence being a necessary requirement of his unsurpassable greatness. The<italic>a priori</italic>character of this argument – which involves no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Evil</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The existence of evil in the world is regarded by most atheists as the principal objection to the existence of God, called by the Roman Catholic theologian Hans Küng the ‘rock of atheism’. By ‘evil’ is meant the fact of pain and suffering and the ‘problem’ that it poses for religious belief is not hard to see. How can evil exist in a world created by an omnipotent and omni-benevolent God? For the positive atheist this question exposes an insuperable inconsistency within religious belief, thereby invalidating the claim that any God exists. Nor, I should add, is discussion confined to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Morality and Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a letter to N.L. Ozmidov, in 1878, Fyodor Dostoevsky writes:</p>
                     <p>Now assume there is no God or immortality of the soul. Now tell me, why should I live righteously and do good deeds if I am to die entirely on earth? And if that is so, why shouldn’t I (as long as I can rely on my cleverness and agility to avoid being caught by the law) cut another man’s throat, rob, and steal …¹</p>
                     <p>Dostoevsky deploys this argument elsewhere in his novels. In<italic>The Brothers Karamazov</italic>(1880), Ivan Karamazov remarks that ‘if there is no God, then everything</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Miracles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term ‘miracle’ (Latin<italic>miraculum</italic>, from<italic>mirari</italic>: to wonder) designates an event (or person) of a particular and most peculiar kind: one that we may regard at the very least as something (or somebody) unusual, extraordinary or contrary to all our expectations. Thus it is that we speak of miraculous escapes, miraculous footballers, miraculous recoveries, miraculous skin creams and so on. For the believer, however, ‘miracle’ has a much more specific meaning. It refers to an occurrence so astounding that only God as its agent can explain it. Here a miracle stands as an external evidence of divine revelation, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Motivations of Belief</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>Journal</italic>John Wesley (1703-1791), founder of the Methodist movement, records the following event:</p>
                     <p>In the evening I went very unwillingly to a society in Aldersgate Street, where one was reading Luther’s preface to the<italic>Epistle to the Romans</italic>. About a quarter before nine, while he was describing the change which God works in the heart through faith in Christ, I felt my heart strangely warmed. I felt I did trust in Christ, Christ alone, for salvation; and an assurance was given me that he had taken away my sins, even mine, and saved me from the law of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The three main authors discussed in this chapter – Feurbach, Marx and Freud – subscribe to the wishful-thinking school of atheism. They maintain that the fundamental purpose of religion is to make human life more bearable by making the suffering endured more understandable; and that the believer achieves this by projection: by transforming the natural human desires for protection and self-affirmation into the consolations provided by a benevolent deity. Each of them – and here we should also include Nietzsche – believed therefore that the religious consciousness was self-deceiving because the impulse to faith was in fact generated by powerful</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Guide to Further Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdxp0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
