<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B105.M4P46 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Meaning (Philosophy)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Quest for Meaning</book-title>
         <subtitle>Friends of Wisdom from Plato to Levinas</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Peperzak</surname>
               <given-names>Adriaan T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823276967</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2kn48"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>One of our most distinguished thinkers, Adriaan Peperzak has masterfully explored the connections between philosophy, ethics, religion, and the social and historical contexts of human experience. He offers a personal gathering of influences on his own work as guides to the uses of philosophy in our search for sense and meaning. In concise, direct, and deeply felt chapters, Peperzak moves from Plato, Plotinus, and the Early Christian theologians to Anselm, Bonaventure, Descartes, Pascal, Leibniz, Hegel, and Levinas. Throughout these carefully linked essays, he touches on the fundamental ideas-from reason and faith to freedom and tradition-that inform the questions his work has consistently addressed, most specifically those concerning philosophy as a practice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="254"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INSTEAD OF AN INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>—Human beings seek meaning.</p>
                     <p>—Isn’t that a bit vague for a definition? -Perhaps; but vagueness is inevitable at the beginning of a search, and a definition is the conclusion of an investigation, rather than its first premise.</p>
                     <p>—Why then do we not seek our point of departure from a well-established definition that has been accepted for centuries:<italic>homo est animal rationale</italic>(“a human being is a rational animal”)?</p>
                     <p>—Do you find this expression clear? Have we not become suspicious about its components? Do we even know what we mean by “homo,” “animal,” and “rational”; do we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Philosophia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relation between philosophy and theology is no longer a hotly debated question among Christians, and yet it is constitutive for the framework in which their thinking develops. Their schools seem to have found a<italic>modus vivendi</italic>for the coexistence of both disciplines, but as far as I know, this coexistence is not supported by a generally accepted metatheory and “philosophico-theological” methodology. In this chapter I would like to challenge a powerful conception of the way in which philosophy and theology are and should be related and to propose a different conception. I will focus here on these disciplines insofar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Why Plato Now?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the<italic>Seventh Letter</italic>, Plato tells us that, as a young man, he had political ambitions and that the situation of Athens seemed to favor them. A revolution had just put an end to the democracy; the aristocracy of the Thirty had gained absolute power and some of Plato’s relatives, who participated in the new government, invited him to join their political efforts. Plato had high hopes: the new regime would transform the formerly unjust<italic>polis</italic>into a community based on justice and internal peace. However, his hopes were cruelly dashed when the rulers committed crimes that were as scandalous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Platonic and Christian Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even a superficial reading of the Gospels will suffice to convince the reader that incarnation is the alpha and—as resurrection of the flesh—the omega of Christian faith. And with the body, involvement in the human world and its history is part of God’s self-revelation in his Word through the Spirit. The Christian community, whose faith is corporeal, communicative, communitarian, and sacramental, participates in this involvement. None of its activities is possible in the ether of incorporeal ghosts or spirits. All prophecies and fulfillments are facts of language; the entire liturgy is visible, tactile, and resounding; rituals have the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fulfillment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unless the claim that one speaks in the name of Christian faith is confined to explications of ecclesiastical dogma, it is likely to be confused with the personal opinion of an individual marked by particular experiences and circumstances. However, even the official doctrine of a Church does not escape the law of historical concretization, according to which all dogma particularizes what it tries to establish by restricting its validity to detennined epochs and milieus. Indeed, Christianity cannot be other than a mixture composed of “the purity of the Gospel,” elements that belong to a culture, particular perspectives that hold sway</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Anselm’s Proslogion and Its Hegelian Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Saint Anselm is the only philosopher of the Middle Ages whom Hegel discusses seriously in his lectures on the history of philosophy and his lectures on the philosophy of religion.¹ There are two main reasons for Hegel’s interest:1. In contrast to those of his colleagues in theology and philosophy who proclaim at every turn that the human mind cannot know God, let alone prove his existence, Hegel agrees with Anselm that genuine faith not merely pennits but requires the believer to seek to understand what he believes. 2. According to Hegel, Anselm’s proof of the existence of God, presented in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Ascent:</title>
                     <subtitle>Plotinian Motifs in Bonaventure’s Itinerary of the Mind to God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marked by the shift from modernity to postmodemity, our epoch shares the ambiguities of both. The hubris of an emancipation that burdened humanity with a superhuman responsibility for the well-being of the entire world; greedy concentration on human, all-too-human needs; generous proclamations of universal human rights and deficient attempts at concretizing them; a humanistic moralism in conjunction with the greatest mass murders of history; a highly ambivalent relationship to religion and faith; a combination of blatant ignorance and repressions with fine scholarship about our past; an exaggerated veneration of science and technology; ruthless exploitation and romantic divinization of nature; the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Bonaventure’s Contribution to the Twentieth-Century Debate on Apophatic Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>God has died, at least in science and philosophy. He is agonizing in religious study, perhaps even in some divinity schools. Atheism and a careful sequestration of God from current business are the two main forms in which academia deals with the long history of religion, which, notwithstanding academic reservations, goes on. For scholarship, faith, God, and religion have become curiosa. The theoretical intention has separated itself from religious commitments; it abhors edifying language and has forgotten or rejected the long history of its association with contemplation.<italic>Curiositas</italic>is the word Bonaventure would use to characterize the study of religion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Life, Science, and Wisdom According to Descartes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If it is true that “the supreme good” of human life is wisdom, then all human endeavors are grounded in the search for wisdom, and all our scientific ventures are oriented by this search.</p>
                     <p>In a letter sent to Elizabeth along with the<italic>Principles of Philosophy</italic>, Rene Descartes defines wisdom as the “firm and powerful resolve to use reason as well as one can and, in all actions, to do whatever one judges to be best.”¹ Wisdom grounds and encompasses “all the virtues” insofar as it is the foundation of the other three cardinal virtues, justice, courage, and temperance (successors</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Philosophy and Christianity (An Hour with Pascal)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone who reflects on the relations between Christianity and philosophy encounters a nwnber of difficult questions, such as the following:</p>
                     <p>1. What do we mean by “Christianity?”</p>
                     <p>2.What is “philosophy?”</p>
                     <p>3.What relations have developed in the past between the different varieties of Christianity and philosophy?</p>
                     <p>4.How are the different versions of Christianity and philosophy currently related to each other?</p>
                     <p>5.What sorts of relations need to be developed between Christianity and philosophy, both now and in the future, and how can these relations contribute to a good and successful life?</p>
                     <p>This chapter will offer only a fragment of the reflection required</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Leibniz on God and Suffering</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1710 Leibniz presented his conception of the relation between God and the evil that disfigures his creation in his<italic>Theodicy</italic>¹. This work does not present a systematic treatise on positive or natural theology but is rather a long series of polemical arguments, the whole of which constitutes a plea for the goodness of God: “it is the case of God that we plead.”² Bayle is the principal prosecutor, and Leibniz takes the defense of the accused, in full confidence that “the assistance of God is not lacking to those who do not lack good will.”</p>
                     <p>The issue that Leibniz</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Hegel and Modern Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although we may agree that we are living through a decisive crisis in our culture, we are not all of the same opinion about the meaning of this crisis. Are we in agony? Are we just passing through one of the many difficult passages that punctuate Western history? What from our past is strong enough to be worthy of survival and what future possibilities are open to us?</p>
                     <p>We belong to the great tradition that is rooted in classical Greece, the Judeo-Christian faith, the Roman empire, and Germanic languages, but we may no longer swear by it. While following traditional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The Significance of Levinas for Christian Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a fact that gives one pause for consideration that in Holland, Belgium, France, Italy, South America, and the United States the work of Emmanuel Levinas has found its greatest readership among Christian philosophers and theologians. Although this work is supported by a long Jewish tradition—even in its strictly philosophical elements—it has impressed many Christians by its orientation, which, despite its great originality, seems familiar to them.¹</p>
                     <p>Levinas’s work rings with the voice of a master, not only in the sense of a teacher who translates a common heritage, but also in the sense of a critic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>—Though this is the “next meeting, for which you set me a task in our first discussion, I will not yet offer you a systematic theory of the basic definitions and connections between human life, reason, opinion, faith, knowledge, perception, intuition, science, argumentation, philosophy, theology, and so on, but rather invite you to reflect with me on the ways in which the master-thinkers presented here tried to make sense of human destiny.</p>
                     <p>—To tell you the truth, most of them struck me-and regularly irritated me—by their pious attitude. You seem to prefer religious minds over rigorous scholars</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED AND EDITIONS USED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kn48.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
