<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B2430 .J283P4413 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Phenomenology Wide Open: After the French Debate</book-title>
         <subtitle>After the French Debate</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JANICAUD</surname>
               <given-names>DOMINIQUE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cabral</surname>
               <given-names>Charles N.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823224463</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275106</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c999gs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book follows up the developments inphenomenology discussed in Phenomenology andthe Theological Turn: The French Debate, attempting toestablish what potentialities in the phenomenologicalmethod exist at present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="126"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Translator’s Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cabral</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>From Controversy to Debate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two nearly antithetical reports are at the origin of this new essay on French-speaking phenomenology.</p>
                     <p>On the one hand, while remaining the target of harsh methodological criticism,¹ phenomenological research has experienced a veritable proliferation which can only encourage the interested scholar to inquire about the various forms of this surprising vitality and to question the reasons for it.</p>
                     <p>On the other hand, this creativity, which claims a phenomenological inspiration with obviously uneven degrees of felicity, extends into greatly divergent directions. The analyses formerly proposed in the “Theological Turn”² and in<italic>La philosophie en Europe</italic>³ have thus proved to be both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>An Atheistic Phenomenology?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a text entitled “Pour une philosophie non théologique,”¹ Mikel Dufrenne noted the profound ambiguity in Heideggerian thought with regard to the theological tradition. On the one hand, Heidegger is the pioneer of the “philosophies of absence,” and he separates the “appearing” from any transcendent or ontic principle. On the other hand (even though he denies it), his argumentation has crypto-theological accents to it: being, which conceals itself in its own names, like the unutterable God of negative theology, safeguarding its truth in a meditative and almost religious experience. Now, this remanence of onto-theology, which Derrida denounced, Dufrenne in turn</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Avatars of First Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That phenomenology is a fundamentally philosophical enterprise and that it is based on a decisive act of bracketing (<italic>mise entre parenthèses</italic>) of the natural attitude—here are two essential elements of the Husserlian legacy that any phenomenology worthy of its name would seem obliged to accept, even today. However, Husserl was even more ambitious: thanks to phenomenology, he was able to champion both the re-foundationof philosophy as a rigorous science and as a first philosophy at the same time. Under what conditions can this ambition be reaffirmed or displaced? And to what extent? Within what limits?</p>
                     <p>Whatever the stated intentions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Articulations/Disarticulations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having noted and analyzed the main aporias and the non-negligible misunderstandings which flow from the will to institute (or to reinstate) phenomenology as first philosophy, it is now time to adopt a more positive point of view by addressing the inevitable question: “Is the phenomenological project amendable?”</p>
                     <p>It is obviously possible to respond negatively to this question and to abandon phenomenology to its historically dated role. This option, however negative as it may be, is both understandable and respectable. That is, as long as this kind of refusal of phenomenology does not schematize the discipline excessively. While not wanting to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Toward a “Minimalist” Phenomenology:</title>
                     <subtitle>The End of Overbidding</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By setting itself up as first philosophy, claiming that it alone occupies the position of a “real” philosophy to come, a certain kind of phenomenology seems to us to have overestimated its capacities. Its presumption consists in seeking to reinstitute the ancient, royal privilege of philosophy over the particular sciences, in speculating excessively upon its very own “possible,” and even in engaging in a tactic of hyperbole in order to win the attention and recognition of the vast majority of nonpositivist philosophers. Whether this is a deliberate plan, a genuine faith in the mission of philosophy, or an illusion sincerely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999gs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
