<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jcx3s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Storytelling in Siberia</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Olonkho Epic in a Changing World</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HARRIS</surname>
               <given-names>ROBIN P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780252041280</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780252099885</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Urbana; Chicago; Springfield</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/j.ctt1wf4d5p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Olonkho , the epic narrative and song tradition of Siberia 's Sakha people, declined to the brink of extinction during the Soviet era. In 2005, UNESCO 's Masterpiece Proclamation sparked a resurgence of interest in olonkho by recognizing its important role in humanity 's oral and intangible heritage. Drawing on her ten years living in the Russian North, Robin P. Harris documents how the Sakha have used the Masterpiece program to revive olonkho and strengthen their cultural identity. Harris 's personal relationships with and primary research among Sakha people provide vivid insights into understanding olonkho and the attenuation, revitalization, transformation, and sustainability of the Sakha 's cultural reemergence. Interdisciplinary in scope, Storytelling in Siberia considers the nature of folklore alongside ethnomusicology, anthropology, comparative literature, and cultural studies to shed light on how marginalized peoples are revitalizing their own intangible cultural heritage.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Transliteration from Russian and Sakha</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Encountering Olonkho</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I sit, enthralled, as the rapid-fire poetic language of the epic narrative flows around me. Outside, the warm breezes fitfully attempt to keep the mosquitoes at bay. Inside, the smooth wood surfaces and the steeply sloping sides of the traditionally styled Sakha dwelling generate a strong echo from the voice of the storyteller. Pyotr Egorovich Reshetnikov, master performer of<italic>olonkho</italic>, the epic song-story tradition of his people, sits a few meters in front of me, his folded hands resting on his crossed knees as he begins to narrate the tale he has created.¹</p>
                     <p>Though I have been connected to Yakutia</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Epic Traditions, Performers, and Audiences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An oral epic tradition composed of alternating sections of narrative poetry and song, olonkho demonstrates many of the characteristics common to other epic narrative traditions that recount at length the adventures of legendary, historical, or mythical heroes surmounting the challenges facing them or their people.¹ The oldest known epic poem, the Babylonian<italic>Epic of Gilgamesh</italic>, dates back to 1700 bce (Abusch 2001, 614). Homer’s<italic>Iliad</italic>and<italic>Odyssey</italic>continue this tradition in a poetic recounting of the events surrounding the Trojan War.² Today, epic poetry can be found in many countries, including India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Mongolia, and Tibet, as well as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Effects of Change during the Soviet Era</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The watershed historical event for cultural revitalization in Yakutia occurred with the dissolution of the Soviet Union in the early 1990s.¹ The surge in freedom of expression for minority peoples during that period of Russian history laid the groundwork for widespread cultural renewal among the Sakha. This new vitality, in turn, contributed to the political and cultural environment necessary for supporting olonkho revitalization.²</p>
                     <p>The resulting effort to rescue olonkho from extinction came in the form of a successful bid for the genre to be recognized by UNESCO as a “Masterpiece of the Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity.” To highlight</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Esteem for a Masterpiece:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Quest for Recognition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the Soviet Union dissolved, the political climate for supporting olonkho revitalization saw a season of thriving and growth. At the same time, Yakutia’s demographics began to change. As Russians fled the North for warmer climes in western Russia, the overall number of people in the republic declined, but the percentage of Sakha people in Yakutia increased. Census results show that the Russian population in Yakutia dropped from 50 percent in 1989 to less than 38 percent in 2010.¹ During the same period, the Sakha population rose from 33 percent to almost 50 percent. These statistics clearly show that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Examining the Role of UNESCO and Intangible Cultural Heritage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>UNESCO’s proclamation in 2005 of the Sakha olonkho as a Masterpiece of the Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity gave the genre special visibility in Yakutia. This prominence launched revitalization programs that changed olonkho’s trajectory in significant ways and led to the establishment of the government-sponsored “Decade of Olonkho.” Although UNESCO’s Intangible Cultural Heritage program has received criticism for some inadequacies (Grant 2014, 41; Labadi 2013, 151) and has not delivered the same positive results in every context, the Masterpiece proclamation for olonkho has had a profoundly energizing effect on the genre’s revitalization.¹ In Yakutia, perceptions of UNESCO values, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Elements of Resilience:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stable and Malleable</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The historical chapters of this work provide a narrative frame that informs this chapter’s discussion of continuity and change in olonkho performance. Measuring change for intangible cultural heritage remains a complicated process, but sociolinguists have found ways to address issues of language shift that may contribute helpful models for assessing music shift as well. Without drawing overly strict, problematic parallels between language and music (Tilley 2014, 487), sociolinguistic and other communication-based models can be modified effectively for measuring change in forms of artistic expression. In addition, these approaches highlight key factors related to resilience, thereby providing strategic insights into encouraging</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Epic Revitalization:</title>
                     <subtitle>Negotiating Identities and Other Challenges</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Attaining the Masterpiece award greatly affected the fate of olonkho, likely turning it back from the brink of permanent disappearance. Still, the future of olonkho remains unclear, and whether to implement ongoing plans for transmission and encourage further innovation in the genre is a decision that rests primarily in the hands of the Sakha people. While they seek to create additional strategies to achieve their goals for olonkho, various historical, global, and political forces have affected olonkho and the entire epic<italic>sreda</italic>for more than a century. These forces will continue to exert pressure on performance practice by changing the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Ensuring Sustainability through Transmission and Innovation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A wise Russian aphorism declares, “You don’t have to be a prophet to predict the demise of a people deprived of their mother tongue.”¹ Many Sakha people feel this way, not only about their language, but also about their arts. In the most potent way possible, these unique artistic expressions energize the self-expression and well-being of the Sakha, pushing back against decades, even centuries, of marginalization. Their arts create a space for breathing, for creating, and for celebrating the unique voices of Sakha people.² And although change is inevitable, many Sakha people desire to see olonkho continue in some form</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary of Russian and Sakha Words</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wf4d5p.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
