<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">FC105.M8F68 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Multiculturalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Genuine Multiculturalism</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Tragedy and Comedy of Diversity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FOSTER</surname>
               <given-names>CECIL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773542556</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773589438</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773589430</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt32b7ds"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While many modern societies are noted for their diversity, the resulting challenge is to determine how citizens from different backgrounds and cultures can see themselves and each other as equals, and be treated equally. In Genuine Multiculturalism, Cecil Foster shows that a society's failure to bridge these differences is the tragedy of modern living and that pretending it is possible to mechanically develop fraternity and solidarity among diverse groups is akin to seeking out comedy. Arguing that genuine multiculturalism is the search for social justice by individuals who have been trapped by ascribed identities or newcomers who have been shut out of perceived ethnic homelands, Foster details how this process, in essence, is the story of the Americas. Reconceptionalizing the terms of multiculturalism, he offers an intervention into Canada's claim that its definition and practice are based on recognizing equality of citizenship. Identifying genuine multiculturalism as an ongoing work in progress, rather than a tightly defined policy position, Foster challenges readers to imagine a greater and more harmonious ideal. A necessary theoretical reconsideration of diversity within society, Genuine Multiculturalism refocuses the debate about ideals and practices in modern societies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="496"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Tragedy of Living, the Comedy of Trying</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about a way of life we call “multiculturalism,” or rather about genuine multiculturalism, in its most idealistic yet pragmatic form. It is about nation building in what we now call “late modernity” or even “the postmodern,” whose hallmarks supposedly include multiculturalism itself. The beauty of<italic>genuine multiculturalism</italic>is that it assumes that nations and states are constructed mechanically, indeed pragmatically, in the moment, by the people, for the people, and of the people – that is,<italic>citizens</italic>.</p>
                     <p>But just imagining this process actually happening is pure idealism. People as persons or citizens and as social actors always come</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Genuine Multiculturalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the dominant mythology of Western societies, the lesser beings in society often remind us of our total and most basic humanity.³ It is the narrative of how those who do not have entitlement – whether from lack of education or money or through other forms of categorization as inferiors, as foreigners, women, or slaves – come to have a sense of belonging or full recognition; how, most important, they become sovereigns. For these are the “codgers,” as Joseph Campbell describes them, even the lowest elements of the folk, who are so central to the production and development of Western myths and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Dramatis personae</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was growing up in the Caribbean paradise of Barbados, there was always a specific character of special note in our society. We called him “Bad John.” Bad Johns were fixtures not only in my native land but, if I can judge from the blues, calypso, mento, reggae, or soca songs that provided our daily carnival, were present in every Caribbean island, and apparently went by the same name everywhere, too. In Jamaica, they are also the Badman, Don, or Rude Boy to name a few of these apocryphal beings in what people generally call “badmanism.” And the blues</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Hegelian – Christian Model</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part I has offered a story of tragedy. In the case of Canada, it is about how the social order, in whatever form it takes, never seems to make sense for some liberal-democratic individuals. This is especially so for those who do not share the dominant culture and find its mores and norms immoral and meaningless. Similarly, citizens who swear by the dominant ideals and ways of life find those of an opposite view equally immoral and even ungrateful, especially if the latter are newcomers. But what I reviewed in part I is also a tale of comedy, of how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Multiculturalism in the Americas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Genuine multiculturalism, then, is more than mere formalism and its seeming common-sense opposites, conformity and coercion – both sides of which I am presenting as twins of the same dialectic, as faces of freedom and slavery. Both have the same beginning, and at times the same genealogy of historical experiences. Their early separation into one or the other occurs as acts of diremption, akin to a biblical fall or to a tumble like a Humpty Dumpty – an apparent degeneration from freedom to slavery.</p>
                     <p>As the Latvian-American philosopher Judith Shklar describes it, this is the splitting of an ego of sorts, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Canada’s Second Covenant:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Charter of Rights</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tragedies often confront us in our daily lives. This is a staple of the human experience or condition, and learning from them is what allows us to come up with theories and rules of life. Perhaps the most philosophical attitude we can take to these trials and tribulations appears in aphorisms such as “What doesn’t kill me strengthens me” and “What evil there is must be for some greater good” – sayings that depict our resignation to the unchanging nature of some things in life and our need to somehow manage. And one social fact of life seems to be always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>When Tragedy Becomes Comedy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a common-sense way, the maxims at the start of the previous chapter capture a contradiction immanent to life. Their irony gives them a generalized truth that is not always the case, while they remind us that we always face the certainty of despair and hope – often from the same source. Despair and hope are dialectical, for they can be opposing, and at times even complementary, parts of the same whole. The sayings also speak to the possibility of change for the better or the worse and to how every thought and act appear pregnant with the possibility of producing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Legacy of the US Civil War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A spectre, a pending destiny, or even fate haunts Canada, and it is all so American: the spectre of the US Civil War, which settled by force issues of sovereignty at the state and individual levels seemingly once and for all. If sovereignty rested effectively in the state, then it was at the universal or federal level as a special type of organism that is almost uniquely that of the Americas; and if this sovereignty belonged to the people, then the very concept of “the people” had changed radically in the Americas – from meaning “European and white” to including all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Canada:</title>
                     <subtitle>Forging a Single Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historically, official multiculturalism in Canada emerged in the early 1970s out of the frustration of various groups trying to determine whether they should all exist according to Anglo conformity, Franco conformity, or no conformity at all.² In the end, they chose none at all – or so we hear, for there are many people who still argue that life in multicultural Canada is an exercise in conformity to the ideals of either a Franco or an Anglo mainstream, or to a hybridized Anglo-French culture.</p>
                     <p>As I see it, what happened back then is instructive: Canadians chose multiculturalism as their identity and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Citizenship with Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>The CBC and I</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 2001, I took part in a most frustrating exercise. The participants may have viewed it as a tragedy; observers who knew more, it might have seen a comedy. CBC Radio, the radio arm of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, had commissioned me for what both it and I thought was a relatively easy project. The aim was to identify differences within multicultural Canada and to isolate power conflicts between groups – or at least that was what I thought.</p>
                     <p>We were “working out the politics of recognition” vis-à-vis immigrants in Canada. I wanted to reveal the difficulties some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Crisis 2001:</title>
                     <subtitle>Not Enough People!</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Immigration, including the role of immigrants in Canadian culture, became a national issue by the summer of 2001, when Statistics Canada reported an ethnic and demographic makeover under way. The impact was analogous to the point in Hegelian analysis when Eve had to teach the facts of life to a rationalist and self-centred Adam, an archetypal Bad John. Just like the exemplary Adam, Canada was coming to know itself as a tragic hero: it was ageing and dying but wanted to live forever. As a self-consciousness, it had to realize that it was ultimately a<italic>desire</italic>, which has led it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Massey and Culture:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Bi to Multi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is then perceptually a problem with Canada as a practical and pragmatic entity, and there are problems in the way that we as citizens and critics imagined multiculturalism and its achievements. A being or consciousness is – in Hegel’s sense – in need of a tragic ending that offers an escape. The classical strain of thought in Western philosophy privileges acts and forbearances that are moral and ethical, qualities that we associate with the supersensible and with God, the absolute, the unchangeable, reason, and rationalism in a world that we thus treat as if it is the product of dual systems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Tyranny v. Freedom:</title>
                     <subtitle>Strauss v. Kojève</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a famous exchange about the time Canadians were examining the idea of official multiculturalism, two leading theorists – conservative US philosopher Leo Strauss and left-leaning French philosopher Alexandre Kojève – debated about what it took to produce wise and good government in a modern state. Strauss wrestled with the question of the sovereign individual and whether one can remain authentic while living in a society – can he or she live happily ever after? Strauss starts always with the desires of the individual in discussing freedom and tyranny. He sees a “crisis in modernity” because neither the individual nor the state knows</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Rawls and Trudeau’s Just Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Beginning in the 1970s, the government of Canada became officially multicultural, constructing a modern, pluralist nation-state. Canadians renewed their social contract to make it more inclusive and less a fragment of Europe.² Pierre Trudeau’s leadership (prime minister 1968–80, 1981–4) featured repatriation of the constitution with, at last, an amending formula, and entrenchment of the Charter of Rights and Freedoms. Trudeau spoke of a new beginning for Canada, with negotiations among individuals, not groups: “The liberal philosophy sets the highest value on the freedom of the individual, by which we mean the total individual, the individual as a member</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Rethinking the CBC and Me:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Tragedy to Comedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the story I told above in chapters 9 and 10 about my experiences with CBC Radio, I started with the narrative assumption that both the broadcaster and I were free to make our choices and to come up with our own ways of producing a series on immigration. I also supposed that both of us were operating in an environment that desired, welcomed, and accepted change and where one could challenge, even reformulate, the existing order. My assumption, equally, was that both CBC and I felt we were trying to help Canada, its citizens, and immigrants to achieve collectively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Tragedy:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Comedic Folk Saviour</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>398</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is usually describe as the politics of recognition is then nothing more than grasping for a form of sense-certainty in the mistaken belief that it is the most sensuous form of knowing. We think we know who we are as Canadians through our determination or social imagining of what a Canadian is. And whether or not we derive this through such laws as the Canadian Citizenship Act (1947) or the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (2001), we do not end up with a concrete definition that seems to fulfil our requirement. For example, the Citizenship Act can go only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b7ds.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
