<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Our Bodies Are Selves</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hefner</surname>
               <given-names>Philip</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pederson</surname>
               <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Barreto</surname>
               <given-names>Susan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718894221</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718844486</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Philip Hefner</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Ann Milliken Pederson</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Susan Barreto</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt197059n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Our Bodies Are Selves is a look at what it means to be human in a world where medical technology and emerging ethical insight force us to rethink the boundaries of humanity/spirit and man/machine. This book gives us a fresh look at how our expanding biological views of ourselves and our shared evolutionary history shows us a picture that may not always illumine who and where we are as Christians. Offering up Christian theological views of embodiment, the authors give everyday examples of lives of love, faith, and bodily realities that offer the potential to create new definitions of what it means to be a faith community in an increasingly technological age of medicine.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A New Paradigm:</title>
                     <subtitle>Body-Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hefner</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are exploring a change in how we think and how we relate to our world as we learn to live as embodied persons, engaging our bodies, listening to them, and listening as well to our Christian traditions of faith. We are on a journey: one that begins with the body, traverses several landscapes, and returns to where we started, our bodies now understood in new ways that point to the paradigm shift we seek. We are persuaded that on this journey of accessing our bodies, we are companions along the journey of God’s incarnation in the world.</p>
                     <p>We think</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Getting Around:</title>
                     <subtitle>Disability and Life in the Spirit</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hefner</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For me, it’s all about mobility.¹ Since, until very recently, I was so favored as to be virtually without pain, it’s the challenge of getting around. “Disabled” or “handicapped” are abstractions that take shape for me in what politically correct jargon might call “mobility-challenged.” This is my personal story, not a treatise on disability; I try to avoid generalizations. Not that generalizations shouldn’t be made, but since it is individuals who are struck with infirmity and each one has a distinctive story, abstractions must always be held accountable according to their impact on actual persons. If my story has broader</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Personal Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>Living in the Middle Years</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Memories can be like paintings in a gallery that we can stroll through, gazing at them and then pausing to examine the details. Or memories can come and go, unexpectedly; they interrupt us in the middle of our story. Suddenly, scenes send us reeling into our past. I can feel those memories in my body when I think about why my knees bother me now almost forty years later from carrying forty-five pound packs up trails in the mountains. Or the tenderness I sense in my hands whenever I try to practice the piano but can’t because of too many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>In the Early Years:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tiny Promises</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barreto</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One early frosty Saturday morning in mid-December, one mom and dad were initially told that there was a 25 percent chance that their third child, a newborn baby girl, would live. This was simply due to the fact that she was born in 1973, happened to weigh 2 pounds 1 ounce, was born weeks early, and was in a hospital in rural Northwestern Illinois. Quickly realizing the situation’s seriousness, a local pediatrician suggested transporting the baby to the nearest state-run hospital with a preemie center in Peoria, Illinois.</p>
                     <p>If the statistics would have been bleaker, there would have been little</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Discovering Our Culture’s Script:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Manifesto about Our Cultural Views of Bodyselves</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We simultaneously idolize the human body and desecrate it. Americans export highly sexualized, exploited, objectified, and violent images of bodies throughout the world, dressed in the clothes of our consumerism. We know what sells. Magazines advertise how to reduce flabby muscles and how to make decadent desserts, all in the same issue. Young boys and girls receive mixed messages about being strong and healthy and yet they are seduced by the advertisements sexualizing every part of them. While our “parts” may tell the story, they do so in an un-wholly manner. We must rediscover the parts within our whole, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Where Medicine and Christianity Collide</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In light of medical science and biotechnologies, what does it mean to be a human person? In light of the biblical narrative and Christian tradition(s), what does it mean to be a human person? For most Christians, those questions don’t come together into the same focus unless they experience a crisis or life-changing event regarding their health. In exploring both questions, the convergence of what is happening in medical science and biotechnologies and in the readings of the Christian tradition will reveal that we are amazing, complex bodyselves who are called to be creatures of God, alongside the rest of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A Scientific Take on Our Bodyselves:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Science Tells Us about Our Bodies and Ourselves</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hefner</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evolutionary science establishes—unassailably—that self is body. In this chapter we explore how science makes this point and what it means for us. Some years ago, I had an experience that brought it home to me in an unforgettable way. A young man, who showed promise to become an exceptional pastor, arrived in his first call after graduation from seminary. At every step of his preparation, he had proved himself to be unusually well-suited for parish ministry—everyone expected great things from him. It was a shock when in the first months of this activity he was unexpectedly overwhelmed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Human Journey</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hefner</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Clearly, when we speak of bodies, we are speaking of ourselves, and furthermore our bodies as they are embedded in technology. Rather than thinking of ourselves as abstractions, our selves are a rich mix of dimensions that defy separation—they exist together in ways that our words and concept struggle to understand. The central issue is human identity. It’s about the struggle to arrive at the meaning of being human today, or theological anthropology. The struggle to arrive at human meaning is the grappling with our own human creativity, particularly in its technological expression. This struggle is at the heart</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Nature, Mystery, and God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hefner</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nature is an epic historical narrative—from cosmic beginnings 13 billion years ago in the Big Bang to the emergence of planet earth, its life forms, and the emergence of humans and our culture. A focus on specific segments of the epic may lose sight of the grand epic narrative, which presents us with unimaginable diversity, from cosmic origins to the molecular structure of life, the amazing gamut of living creatures, primates, and human culture. Our basic assumption is that this is one process, one natural hiMstory—nature’s epic. We can speak of it as a drama in several acts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Luther on the Body:</title>
                     <subtitle>Incarnation, Sacrament, Technoself, and Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We know that our identity emerges from the entangled and extended relationships in which our bodyselves are embedded. We are technobody selves, tethered in, with, and under the technologies and social media that create our personhood. Many of us embody multiple identities and selves: virtual, real, male, female, inter-sex, poor, rich, middle-class, young, older, dying, birthing, viable, fetus, embryo, child, and adult. We will resist being explained by “nothing buts” and simplistic labels. We can celebrate the multidimensional nature of our bodyselves, whose relationship to the world, both past and into the future, emerges through entangled and extended webs of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Body of Christ</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pederson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann Milliken</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I’ve always wanted to be a part of the body of Christ, but the body of Christ has not always wanted me in it. I grew up in the Lutheran church: attending Sunday school, singing in the choir, and going to camp in the summer. In junior high school, when someone asked me what I wanted to do when I grew up, I could answer: I want to be a pastor. The church, however, did not always inspire my love of the church. In confirmation, our pastor told us to sit in every other seat and we were rarely allowed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>S.B</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>P.H</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>A.M.P</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We began by saying that this book would offer no comprehensive, conceptually spelled out view of the body, and we kept that promise. Rather we have offered a series of<italic>takes</italic>on the body—from different angles, caught up in a variety of movements, simple and complex, straightforward and yet at the same time defying comprehension. These takes need follow no particular order—you can dip into the book at any chapter.</p>
                     <p>You may wish we had provided more about the body, but we hope you will agree that what is here is authentic, pertinent, fascinating, and produces endless chains</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggestions for Further Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt197059n.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
