<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">inne17060</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Governance in the New Global Disorder</book-title>
         <subtitle>Politics for a Post-Sovereign Society</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>INNERARITY</surname>
               <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KINGERY</surname>
               <given-names>SANDRA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SASSEN</surname>
               <given-names>SASKIA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231542258</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231542259</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/inne17060"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>When we talk about globalization, we tend to focus on its social and economic benefits. In<italic>Governance in the New Global Disorder</italic>, the political philosopher Daniel Innerarity considers its unsettling and largely unacknowledged consequences. The "opening" of different societies to new ideas, products, and forms of prosperity has introduced a persistent uncertainty, or disorder, into everyday life. Multinational corporations have weakened sovereignty. We no longer know who is in control or who is responsible. Economies can collapse without sufficient warning, and the effort to rebuild can drag on for years. Piracy is everywhere. Is there any way to balance the interests of state, marketplace, and society in this new construct of power?</p>
         <p>Since national economies have become deterritorialized and political interdependencies aggravate our common vulnerabilities, Innerarity contends that there is no other solution except to move toward global governance and a denationalization of justice. Globalization tries to unify the world through technologies, the economy, and cultural products and styles, but it cannot articulate or regulate political and legal equivalents. Everyone faces the same risks to their security, food supply, health, financial stability, and environment, and these risks demand a new global politics of humanity. In her foreword, the sociologist Saskia Sassen isolates the key takeaways from Innerarity's argument and the solutions they present to growing global tensions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SASSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>SASKIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this passionate and original book, Daniel Innerarity unsettles a range of typical or familiar contrasts. In this process he repositions the familiar as part of a new interpretation. Nothing is left standing where it once stood. Key categories are evicted from their conventional anchors. But it is an eviction that entails making new meanings.</p>
                     <p>As I read through this book, there was one image that kept recurring in my mind, albeit not one used by the author—it was more my applying Innerarity’s method to some of my work. The image is that the immigrant<italic>makes</italic>new ground for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whose World Is It?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today’s world is full of paradoxes, many of which could be summarized by the idea that it is a world belonging to everyone and to no one. There are many issues that are everyone’s (they affect all of us and demand coordinated actions), but at the same time, no one can or wants to be in charge of them (either there is no competent authority or no one shoulders the responsibility). What is the difference between something held in common and something that is ungovernable, between shared responsibility and generalized irresponsibility? How do we distinguish that which belongs to everyone</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE RETURN OF PIRATES IN THE GLOBAL ERA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his famous book<italic>The History of Piracy</italic>, Philip Gosse (1989 [1932], 298) recalls that people, at the end of the nineteenth century, believed the disappearance of pirates was imminent. It was the dream of a world where there is no territory without sovereignty, in other words, no one distanced from the rules of the state (Thompson 1994; Anderson 1997). Subsequent history seems to flatly disprove this prediction. Piracy has stopped being a historical curiosity or a simple metaphor. Pirates are among us and taking on diverse forms in many different realms: pirates of the air and seas, radio pirates,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>HUMANITY THREATENED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Ulrich Beck says, unlike other previous civilizations, we cannot attribute everything that threatens us to external causes; societies are in conflict with themselves, with the production of that which they do not desire. Explaining this characteristic contrasts with our common sense, which tends to establish net causalities, distinguishes subjects from objects, thinks in terms of hierarchy, and explains the idea of defense in terms of spatial protection. To identify and understand the nature of threats in a world that belongs to everyone and to no one, we have no choice but to make a “metaphorological” effort. I am going</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>GLOBAL FEAR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When you want to understand a society, it is more useful to examine its fears than its desires. We could say: Tell me whom you are afraid of and I will tell you who you are. We can now register a fear with new characteristics in the fear taxonomy, and we could call it global fear, in other words, fear of the consequences of the process of globalization. It is a question of risks that have to be governed and from which we have the right to be protected. At the same time, unreasonable reactions to some of the concerns</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A WALLED WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The current transformation of many of our borders into walls is a clear indicator of the ambiguity of the process of globalization, which combines opening and fragmentation, delimitation and closure. This issue places crucial aspects of our humanity at stake since borders and boundaries are linked to the realities of inside and outside, inclusion and exclusion, questions of identity and difference. The current tendency of multiplying strategies for closure reveals that we have significant difficulties when it comes to different ways of configuring everything that has to do with the legal-political realm, citizenship, identity, or security. Perhaps it is time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE OBSERVATION SOCIETY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Power has always meant an ability to observe, conceal, and even conceal oneself. Seeing implies social control; generally, to the extent that the possibilities of observation are increased, the likelihood of being seen decreases. That is why power has always come with the construction of watchtowers and observatories, or with increased sophistication of society’s observation techniques, like censuses and polls.</p>
                     <p>The search for power still motivates people in the world today and may even have improved the techniques of control, but in a knowledge and information society, the technology that makes these observational operations possible is equally at the disposal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>FROM SOVEREIGNTY TO RESPONSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A world that belongs to everyone and to no one is a world that must be conceived and governed with categories other than those applied to the nation-state. Must we abandon the idea of a world that is organized in accordance with democratic values and principles of justice or can we imagine democracy on a global scale? Is intervention in “other people’s” affairs legitimate or are we compelled to accept anything that is carried out in the name of sovereignty? Are there criteria for global justice or must we accept that justice is a value that only measures relationships within</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>CLIMATIC JUSTICE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The atmosphere is one of humanity’s common goods, and it carries a central value for life and the survival of human beings on planet Earth. The complex causes of climate change, the diverse impacts and different responsibilities of a variety of agents, the determination of what can be demanded of each individual agent place us squarely in the camp of what we could call “complex justice.” It cannot be resolved with allocations according to the rules of the market but requires specific political agreements. Among the institutions that share some type of responsibility in the fight against climate change and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A POLITICS OF HUMANITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reality has been<italic>communist</italic>for a few years now. The Cold War was won by capitalism, but current events are imposing problems that place care for the<italic>communal</italic>rather than care for the individual at the center of our concerns. Globalization is often associated with privatization (with economic liberalization or the movement of certain goods and services toward the marketplace), but it can also be understood as an increase in what is public, the fact that societies are more interdependent. The political agenda is now full of common problems, of universal public goods. I am not talking about a battle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Us and Them</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a world like ours that belongs to everyone and to no one, a world of shared threats and common goods, where ownership should be reexamined, and demands for cooperation are stronger and stronger, a world that opens and protects itself, in which we are all equally exposed and which lacks outskirts, wrapped in interdependence and contagions, the most difficult and at the same time most demanding questions are: Who are we? How should we who live in this common world conceive of ourselves and how should we act? Making the distinction between us and them is crucial to determining</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">inne17060.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
