<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7hbg3w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HX264.7.S27B57 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sartre, Jean Paul, 1905</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political and social views</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Communism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Communism and philosophy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Communism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Soviet Union</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectuals</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Political activity</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sartre Against Stalinism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Birchall</surname>
               <given-names>Ian H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782389736</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782389733</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ian H. Birchall</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btbwzh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Most critics of the political evolution of Jean-Paul Sartre have laid emphasis on his allegedly sympathetic and uncritical attitude to Stalinist Communism due, to a large extent, to their equation of Marxism with Stalinism. It is true that Sartre was guilty of many serious misjudgements with regard to the USSR and the French Communist Party. But his relationship with the Marxist Left was much more complex and co tradictory than most accounts admit. This book offers a political defence of Sartre and shows how, from a relatively apolitical stance in the 1930s, Sartre became increasingly involved in the politics of the Left; though he always distrusted Stalinism, he was sometimes driven to ally himself with it because of the force of its argument.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Birchall</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliographical Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chronology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Claiming the Corpse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone proposing to write yet another book about Jean-Paul Sartre must do so with a certain sense of guilt. Given the huge number of books and articles that already exist, what justification can there be for adding to them? Moreover, any writer on Sartre lives with the melancholy awareness that Sartre himself insisted that he had never learnt anything from any of the books written about him.¹ Yet such is the richness and complexity of Sartre’s work that there are still things that have not been said – as well, unfortunately, as some that have been said all too often,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>‘La Communiste’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sartre has repeatedly insisted in interviews that he was apolitical until 1939 and that it was the experience of the Second World War that transformed him into a committed thinker and writer. Most commentators have accepted his claims at face value, and in a sense they are quite right to do so. Yet the question depends on what definition of ‘political’ is used. Before 1939 Sartre joined no organisation, participated in no campaign; but he thought, read and talked about power and wealth, about oppression and about how society might be better organised.</p>
                     <p>Indeed, if we want to understand how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Threat of Fascism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most crucial influence on Sartre in the 1930s was that of events themselves. The decade was marked by the rise and consolidation of fascism in Italy, Germany and then Spain. Sartre developed a deep loathing of fascism, beginning from the year he spent in Berlin when Hitler’s regime was consolidating itself.¹</p>
                     <p>In the short term Sartre was little affected by the experience of Nazi Berlin. But this may be less surprising than it seems. Most of the European left was confused and disoriented by Hitler’s victory. The Comintern, having allowed Hitler to take power by refusing to build a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>War within War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘So now I’m cured of socialism, if I needed to be cured’. Thus Sartre wrote in his notebook on 14 September 1939.¹ For Sartre the Second World War had begun with the Hitler–Stalin Pact of 23 August 1939. It is important to remember just what a shock the Pact was for all those on the left, whether inside or outside the PCF. For nearly five years the PCF’s strategy had been centred on the idea of the Popular Front; it had argued indefatigably that the struggle against fascism must take priority over everything else, including the struggle for socialism,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>The Better Choice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When his friend Merleau-Ponty died in 1961, Sartre wrote a long tribute to him, which contained a detailed account of the magazine they had launched together in 1945,<italic>Les Temps modernes</italic>. It also contained a frank assessment by Sartre of the choices available at the Liberation:</p>
                     <p>In 1945 it was possible to choose between two positions. Just two, no more. The first and better one was to address the Marxists, and them alone, and to denounce the aborted revolution, the murdered Resistance, and the fragmentation of the left. Some periodicals courageously took up this position and vanished unheard: those were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Materialism or Revolution?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 28 October 1945 at the Club Maintenant, Sartre gave the famous lecture known under the title<italic>L’Existentialisme est un humanisme</italic>. Maurice Nadeau, in an article that was sympathetic but not without irony, described the huge crowd that turned up: ‘Those present are now gripped by an anguish which is not existential. We are going to die of suffocation’.¹</p>
                     <p>The hall was so packed that no discussion was possible; as a result the lecture was repeated in private to enable debate to take place. Among those who attended this second lecture it was Pierre Naville who made an extended critique</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>The Spectre of Trotsky</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After completing ‘Matérialisme et révolution’, Sartre’s quest continued. Philosophically and politically dissatisfied with the PCF, he wished to establish a revolutionary alternative. Yet Naville’s anti-Stalinist materialism was clearly not what he was looking for. In this context a major influence was his fellow-editor of<italic>Les Temps modernes</italic>, Maurice Merleau-Ponty, who was usually the author of editorial statements signed ‘T.M’., to which Sartre gave his consent,¹ apparently recognising that Merleau-Ponty was more politically sophisticated than he was. Merleau-Ponty was not a Trotskyist, but he had had a number of friends and contacts in the Trotskyist movement since before the war.²</p>
                     <p>And</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>The RDR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1947 saw the outbreak of the Cold War, and the exclusion of the PCF from government. This opened up a new situation in which Sartre had to reorient himself. In so doing he involved himself in a movement, which, very briefly, seemed to have the potential for making a real political impact.</p>
                     <p>In 1948 the Cold War intensified, leading to the Communist takeover in Czechoslovakia and the Berlin blockade; the outbreak of a new European war seemed increasingly probable. In France it was a year of bitter industrial struggle. Sartre had little hope of cooperation with the PCF,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Which Camp?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While Sartre was still apparently disoriented and disillusioned with the collapse of the RDR, Rousset had already moved on to the next stage of his political itinerary. On 12 November 1949<italic>Le Figaro littéraire</italic>appeared with its entire front page devoted to an appeal:</p>
                     <p>HELP THOSE DEPORTED in Soviet camps.</p>
                     <p>AN APPEAL BY DAVID ROUSSET to the survivors of deportation to the Nazi camps.¹</p>
                     <p>Rousset presented recently published information on the Russian labour camps and made numerous comparisons with the Nazi camps, of which he had already written extensively on the basis of personal experience. But he did not confine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>Reorientation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the collapse of the RDR, Sartre seems to have been politically disoriented. Some of the survivors of the RDR formed the CAGI (<italic>Comité d’action des gauches indépendantes</italic>), which ran candidates in the 1951 elections. But for the moment Sartre had no stomach for another attempt to organise the independent left; he retreated back to his literary and philosophical preoccupations, and wrote little of direct political significance for the next two years.</p>
                     <p>He was, moreover, increasingly isolated. In the RDR he had been working with people like Rousset, Rosenthal, Altman and Chauvin, who had considerably more political experience than himself.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>Dangerous Liaison</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sartre’s four-year romance with the PCF between 1952 and 1956 was not the most creditable period of his life, and it was certainly the one that provided most ammunition to his anti-Communist critics. A great many of the criticisms that have been made of Sartre’s political conduct during this period are fully justified. Yet his position was complex and contradictory; to appreciate it fully it is necessary to place it in context. Sartre’s political evolution in the 1950s is often presented as though it were simply a dialogue between two protagonists – Sartre and the Stalinist PCF. That dialogue did</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>Debate with the Far Left</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Sartre, as we have seen, ‘an anti-Communist is a dog’. But he did go so far as to recognise that there was more than one breed of the species. In fact, in<italic>Les Communistes et la paix</italic>he carefully distinguished between ‘left’ and ‘right’ varieties, while arguing for their essential symmetry:</p>
                     <p>The ‘left’ anti-Communist doesn’t want to hear any mention of working-class weariness: he shows us a proletariat of steel plunged to the hilt into the corpse of the bourgeoisie. The ‘right’ anti-Communist shows us the bourgeoisie in the form of a young giantess holding in her arms a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 13</label>
                     <title>Laying the Ghost</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1956 was to be a momentous one, in which the hegemony of Moscow over the international Communist movement was severely shaken, though not destroyed. The fixed certainties of the map of the left were undermined, and the prospects for an independent anti-Stalinist left improved markedly. Sartre’s<italic>rapprochement</italic>with the PCF was coming to an end. As a result he was obliged to seek new allies and to redefine his relations with both the PCF and the anti-Stalinist left.</p>
                     <p>Already at the beginning of the year there were signs of growing friction. In January, Pierre Hervé, a leading PCF</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 14</label>
                     <title>From Practice to Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During his period of<italic>rapprochement</italic>with the PCF Sartre’s political writings had been of a polemical nature; precisely because of the profound contradictions in his position he had not attempted to give a theoretical exposition of his views. But the crisis of 1956 forced him to return to theory. Indeed, it was the questions posed by 1956 that provided the impetus for the theoretical labours of the next two decades – the<italic>Critique de la raison dialectique</italic>with its unpublished second volume, and the massive but also incomplete biographical study of Flaubert,<italic>L’Idiot de la famille</italic>(1971–72).</p>
                     <p>The starting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 15</label>
                     <title>The Battle over Algeria</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The war for Algerian independence (1954–62) was bloody and protracted, fought ruthlessly on both sides, but with the defenders of French rule lapsing into the worst savageries of torture and mass repression. Like the Vietnam War for the United States a decade later, it tore through the very fabric of French society, and destroyed the fragile institutions of the Fourth Republic, bringing de Gaulle to power in 1958. Sartre again found himself in a triangular relation with the PCF and the anti-Stalinist left. Above all, the war led to a profound and lasting radicalisation of Sartre’s position.</p>
                     <p>Between 1939</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 16</label>
                     <title>Rebuilding the Left</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the Algerian War, Sartre’s conduct was that of an exemplary anti-imperialist. Even the PCF no longer dared to vilify him in the old way. But the broader task of rebuilding the French left proved more intractable. Here Sartre was still bound by the contradictions of his own past. In particular, he had not resolved the question of how to relate to the PCF.</p>
                     <p>And so, once the blood had dried on the pavements of Budapest, it was back to the hesitation waltz. Already by 1958 Sartre was making tentative moves towards renewed dialogue with the PCF, a process accelerated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 17</label>
                     <title>May to December</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The events of 1968, often ignorantly dismissed as no more than a year of ‘student revolt’, undermined the political certainties that had endured since 1945. In Vietnam, the world’s strongest power was proved vulnerable in face of a national liberation struggle. The Russian invasion of Czechoslovakia marked a definitive end to Moscow’s hegemony over the world’s Communist Parties. In France a general strike of over nine million workers, the biggest general strike in human history, showed that the power of the working class could not be ignored; an anti-Stalinist left that had been confined to the margins of political life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 18</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sartre’s Century?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Revolutionaries of the J.-P. Sartre style have never disturbed the sleep of any banker in the world’.¹ So asserted Raymond Aron in 1952, and in the absence of any more extensive research on insomnia in the financial services industry we shall have to take his word for it. Yet bankers, by the nature of their trade, are immersed in the short term, the day-to-day fluctuations of the market. They are not the most sensitive judges of the longterm permeation of ideas and values which can eventually have a major impact on social change.</p>
                     <p>An honest assessment of Sartre’s achievements and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbwzh.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
