<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1936.D65 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">One-person shows (Performing arts)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Monodrama</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theater</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Utopia in Performance</book-title>
         <subtitle>Finding Hope at the Theater</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dolan</surname>
               <given-names>Jill</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472099078</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472025572</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.119520"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"Jill Dolan is the theatre's most astute critic, and this new book is perhaps her most important. Utopia in Performance argues with eloquence and insight how theatre makes a difference, and in the process demonstrates that scholarship matters, too. It is a book that readers will cherish and hold close as a personal favorite, and that scholars will cite for years to come."---David Román, University of Southern CaliforniaWhat is it about performance that draws people to sit and listen attentively in a theater, hoping to be moved and provoked, challenged and comforted? In<italic>Utopia in Performance</italic>, Jill Dolan traces the sense of visceral, emotional, and social connection that we experience at such times, connections that allow us to feel for a moment not what a better world might look like, but what it might feel like, and how that hopeful utopic sentiment might become motivation for social change.She traces these "utopian performatives" in a range of performances, including the solo performances of feminist artists Holly Hughes, Deb Margolin, and Peggy Shaw; multicharacter solo performances by Lily Tomlin, Danny Hoch, and Anna Deavere Smith; the slam poetry event Def Poetry Jam; The Laramie Project; Blanket, a performance by postmodern choreographer Ann Carlson; Metamorphoses by Mary Zimmerman; and Deborah Warner's production of Medea starring Fiona Shaw. While the book richly captures moments of "feeling utopia" found within specific performances, it also celebrates the broad potential that performance has to provide a forum for being human together; for feeling love, hope, and commonality in particular and historical (rather than universal and transcendent) ways.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter one</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Feeling the Potential of Elsewhere</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Utopia in Performance</italic>argues that live performance provides a place where people come together, embodied and passionate, to share experiences of meaning making and imagination that can describe or capture fleeting intimations of a better world.<italic>Utopia in Performance</italic>tries to find, at the theater, a way to reinvest our energies in a different future, one full of hope and reanimated by a new, more radical humanism. This book investigates the potential of different kinds of performance to inspire moments in which audiences feel themselves allied with each other, and with a broader, more capacious sense of a public, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter two</label>
                     <title>“A Femme, a Butch, a Jew”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Feminist Autobiographical Solo Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can performance, in itself, be a utopian gesture? Why do people come together to watch other people labor on stage, when contemporary culture solicits their attention with myriad other forms of representation and opportunities for social gathering? Why do people continue to seek the liveness, the present-tenseness that performance and theater offer? Is the desire to be there, in the moment, the expression of a utopian impulse? Certainly, people are drawn to theater and performance by fashion and by taste, by the need to collect the cultural capital that theatergoing provides. Live theater remains a powerful site at which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter three</label>
                     <title>Finding Our Feet in One Another’s Shoes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Multiple-Character Solo Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Utopia can be a placeholder for social change, a no-place that the apparatus of theater—its liveness, the potential it holds for real social exchange, its mortality, its openness to human interactions that life outside this magical space prohibits—can model productively. In the last chapter, I found these feelings of utopia in Holly Hughes, Peggy Shaw, and Deb Margolin’s interactions with their audiences. Their stories directly addressed spectators and modeled an ephemeral but powerful intersubjectivity that let spectators experience affectively, if fleetingly, what utopia might feel like. This chapter considers multiple-character solo performances by comedienne and film and stage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter four</label>
                     <title>Def Poetry Jam:</title>
                     <subtitle>Performance as Public Practice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Performance, as I argued by discussing monopolylogue performers in the last chapter, offers a way to practice imagining new forms of social relationships. I believe in theater’s use value as a place to fantasize how peace and justice, equality and truly participatory democracy might take hold sometime in a near or distant future, as well as in theater’s value as a place in which to connect emotionally and spiritually with other people. Seeing performance requires that we listen attentively to the speech of others, that we hear people speak and feel their humanity and its connections with our own. Performance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter five</label>
                     <title>The Laramie Project:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rehearsing for the Example</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Laramie Project</italic>uses the idiom of performance to construct a public with which to examine the flaw in the social fabric illuminated by the murder of Matthew Shepard. On October 6, 1998, the twenty-one-year-old gay college student, out searching for a semblance of a queer life for himself in Laramie, Wyoming, was picked up in a bar by two local toughs who robbed Shepard, pistol-whipped him nearly to death, tied his wrists to a fence beside an isolated rural road, and abandoned him. Shepard was found the next day by a bicyclist, who called the local police. He was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>chapter six</label>
                     <title>Militant Optimism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Approaching Humanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I find myself with a keen desire to reclaim a commitment to human commonality. I know that gender, race, sexuality, ability, class, and other vectors of identity remain entrenched as discriminatory benchmarks in public discourse and in the distribution of social and political power. But more and more, I find myself feeling affinity without regard to the specifics of identity. As performance scholars Josh Abrams and Janelle Reinelt have both remarked, the ethical move in current politics and culture seems toward a responsibility to each other as each other, both in our radical differences and in our common capacity to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Finding Hope at the Theater</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout<italic>Utopia in Performance,</italic>I’ve suggested that moments of liminal clarity and communion, fleeting, briefly transcendent bits of profound human feeling and connection, spring from alchemy between performers and spectators and their mutual confrontation with a historical present that lets them imagine a different, putatively better future. In my attempt to recapture those moments of communitas, of spectacular yet subtle beauty and grace in the performances I chronicle here, I’ve been challenged to write in a way that in itself mirrors the alchemical combustions of those utopian performatives. In critical reflection and writerly speculation, I’ve been inspired by reimagining and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.119520.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
