<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bgz9g0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>From Violence to Speaking Out</book-title>
         <subtitle>Apocalypse and Expression in Foucault, Derrida and Deleuze</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lawlor</surname>
               <given-names>Leonard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474418249</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474418263</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Leonard Lawlor</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g050g2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Drawing on a career-long exploration of 1960s French philosophy, Leonard Lawlor seeks a solution to 'the problem of the worst violence'. Lawlor argues all violence must itself be reduced to its lowest level. He engages with Foucault, Derrida and Deleuze and Guattari to create new ways of speaking to best achieve the least violence.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Violence to Speaking Out</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Merleau-Ponty, we can speak of signs. There is one contemporary sign that we must consider: globalization. The expansion of globalization is limitless. The sign “globalization” signifies a will to establish control over the whole world and apparently other planets (“interplanetary tourism”). In other words, globalization wants to place the earth within a sphere with a determinate shape, within an enclosure called “the globe.” As it pursues its conquest of other cultures and lands, globalization acts in the name of peace. If globalization could speak and it would speak in English, it would say that “Capitalism has brought more people</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A New Possibility of Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Experience of Powerlessness as a Solution to the Problem of the Worst Violence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we announced in the Introduction, the problem of the worst violence is a limitless reaction to fundamental violence. However, as a limitless reaction, the worst violence arises from the essential nature of a limit. The essence of all limits is divisibility, which means, to say this immediately, that any attempt to reach a haven unscathed by violence, any attempt to reach a place behind an impervious wall, is impossible. Now, by means of the essential divisibility of any limit, we shall be able to present the formal structure of the problem. As we shall see in a moment, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>What Happened?</title>
                     <subtitle>What Is Going to Happen? An Essay on the Experience of the Event</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nietzsche’s simple definition of the reversal of Platonism is well-known. To reverse Platonism means that we value this world in itself, immanently, and no longer value it in relation to transcendent forms such as the Platonic idea of the good. In other words, the revaluation of existence means that existence is measured neither in terms of an origin from which existence might be said to have fallen nor in terms of an end toward which existence might be said to be advancing. More precisely, we must say that the reversal of Platonism means that the duration of existence has no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Is it Happening?</title>
                     <subtitle>Or, the Implications of Immanence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us begin with the following proposition from<italic>The Critique of Pure Reason</italic>: “We assert,” Kant says, “that the conditions of the<italic>possibility of experience</italic>in general are at the same time [<italic>sind zugleich</italic>] conditions of the<italic>possibility of the objects of experience</italic>” (Kant 1998: 283, B197/A158, Kant’s italics [Heidegger 1997: 84, §24]).¹ We know that this proposition opened the way for the circular path of the Hegelian dialectic.² But, closer to our time, and cited so often across the twentieth century, Heidegger’s Kant book taught us how to deconstruct the Kantian correlation between the possibility of experience and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Flipside of Violence, or Beyond the Thought of Good Enough</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In one of his earliest and most significant texts, his 1964 “Violence and Metaphysics,” Jacques Derrida says the following. The context for this quotation is Derrida’s discussion of Levinas’ thought of the other in relation to Husserl’s phenomenology of the other. Derrida says:</p>
                     <p>Every reduction of the other to a<italic>real</italic>moment of<italic>my</italic>life, its reduction to the state of an empirical alter-ego, is a possibility, or rather an empirical eventuality, which is called violence; and violence [that is, empirical or real violence] presupposes … necessary eidetic [or ideal] relationships. [However,] there is a transcendental … violence, an (in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Auto-Affection and Becoming:</title>
                     <subtitle>Following the Rats</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we pointed out in Chapter 1, globalization defines the epoch in which we are living right now. As we noted, the word “globalization” means that the earth has been or is trying to be enclosed within a globe. Enclosing the earth in a globe means that all the ways out have been closed, so that one species, the human, is able to dominate all the other species. What justifies, what gives us the right to dominate the animals? The answer to this question is well-known: humans believe they have the right to dominate because humans believe that they possess</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Origin of Parrēsia in Foucault’s Thinking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Truth and Freedom in The History of Madness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Published in 1961, the<italic>History of Madness</italic>is a monumental study of madness in the “Classical Age” (that is, in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, primarily in France). In its original form, the<italic>History of Madness</italic>displays a debt to phenomenology as it was interpreted in France after World War II. This debt is most apparent in Foucault’s use of the word “experience,” a use that Foucault later will call “enigmatic” (Foucault 1972: 16) and “floating” (Foucault 1984: 336). It is perhaps the vestiges of phenomenological thinking in the<italic>History of Madness</italic>that leads to Derrida’s 1963 criticism of Foucault,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Speaking Out for Others:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophy’s Activity in Deleuze and Foucault (and Heidegger)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many obvious intersections between Deleuze and Foucault: the relation of desire and pleasure; the structures of<italic>agencement</italic>and<italic>dispositif</italic>; and, the self-relation as the fold. These intersections are especially evident and determinable insofar as Deleuze wrote about Foucault and Foucault wrote about Deleuze. Yet, it is remarkable that<italic>both</italic>Deleuze and Foucault, each at the end of his life, wrote about philosophy itself. Of course, Deleuze’s last great book (written with Guattari), appearing in 1991, is called<italic>What is Philosophy?</italic>Yet, Foucault’s last two courses at the Collège de France from 1982 to 1984 aim to answer the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“The Dream of an Unusable Friendship”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Temptation of Evil and the Chance for Love in Derrida’s Politics of Friendship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is perhaps impossible to overestimate the importance of Heidegger’s 1929<italic>Kant and the Problem of Metaphysics</italic>(Heidegger 1997). Through his interpretation of Kant’s First Critique, Heidegger led us to the “hidden art” of the schematism. The core of Heidegger’s interpretation consists in showing that the schematism, lying in the middle between the faculties of the sensibility and the understanding, must be understood as a pure form of auto-affection, and that auto-affection must be understood through the flow of time. Heidegger shows us that the temporal movement of auto-affection contains a difference that cannot be closed off from becoming other.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Three Ways of Speaking, or “Let Others be Free”:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Foucault’s “Speaking-Freely”; Derrida’s “Speaking-Distantly”; and Deleuze’s “Speaking in Tongues”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Foucault, Derrida, and Deleuze have recognized the originality of the idea of the performative (Austin 1962).¹ Chronologically, Foucault comes first. In his 1969<italic>The Archaeology of Knowledge</italic>, he turns to the “speech act” as “one last possibility, and the most probable of all, of defining the statement [<italic>l’énoncé</italic>]” (Foucault 1972: 82).² After describing the performative, Foucault concludes that a “bi-univocal relation” between the statement and the performative cannot exist (Foucault 1972: 83). There is one primary reason, according to Foucault, why the performative cannot define the statement. Even if one says that an illocutionary act is complete, one has to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Speaking Out Against Violence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The spiritual director (the figure of Plato), the living fool, and the teacher of metamorphosis provide us with images of life that must be contrasted with or even opposed to those of the hate criminal and the suicide bomber. Unlike the hate criminal who wants to reduce the speech of others to silence (complete and final silence), the teacher of metamorphosis wants to speak out, and loudly for the freedom of others: “Let others be ends in themselves!” As we saw with our investigation of the GIP, the teacher even wants to let others speak for themselves. Recall that “speaking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g050g2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
