<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B945.C141 P88 2018</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, American</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, American</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Essential Caputo</book-title>
         <subtitle>Selected Writings</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PUTT</surname>
               <given-names>B. KEITH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253032225</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253032232</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253032237</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005tww"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This landmark collection features selected writings by John D. Caputo, one of the most creative and influential thinkers working in the philosophy of religion today. B Keith Putt presents 21 of Caputo's most significant contributions from his distinguished 40-year career. Putt's thoughtful editing and arrangement highlights how Caputo's multidimensional thought has evolved from radical hermeneutics to radical theology. A guiding introduction situates Caputo's corpus within the context of debates in the Continental philosophy of religion and exclusive interview with him adds valuable information about his own views of his work.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="504"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Repetition of Sacred Anarchy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Risking a Reading of Radical Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PUTT</surname>
                           <given-names>B. KEITH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In February 1990, a good friend and I decided to journey to Conception Seminary in northwest Missouri in order to attend a conference on Catholic philosophy and deconstruction. Little did I realize how consequential those three days at that Benedictine monastery would be for me, personally and professionally. It was there and then that I first met and began to read John D. (Jack) Caputo. Jack initiated the weekend conference by delivering the first keynote address, a lecture entitled “Sacred Anarchy: Fragments of a Postmodern Ethics.” Although I did not know it at the time, I later realized that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>From Sacred Anarchy to Political Theology:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Interview with John D. Caputo</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CROCKETT</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAYTON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CLAYTON CROCKETT (HEREAFTER CC): According to the editor B. Keith Putt, the notion of “sacred anarchy” is the hidden thread that animates your work from<italic>Radical Hermeneutics</italic>up to the present. Can you explain in your terms what you mean by sacred anarchy, and do you agree with Keith’s insistence on the importance of this theme for your thought? JOHN D. CAPUTO (HEREAFTER JDC): Let me say first of all that this is Keith’s interpretation. It is his responsibility to demonstrate it, to carry it through. I am, structurally speaking, in no better position to comment upon it than Keith.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Becoming Possible of the Impossible:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Interview with Jacques Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOOLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MARK DOOLEY (HEREAFTER MD): You once remarked that Jack Caputo reads you the way you love to be read. Why is that so?</p>
                     <p>JACQUES DERRIDA (HEREAFTER JD): I have many reasons for saying this. Firstly, he reads me the way I not only enjoy being read, but also in the way I strive to read others—that is, in a way which is generous to the extent that it tries to credit the text and the other as much as possible, not in order to incorporate, replace, or to identify with the other, but to “countersign” the text, so to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Meister Eckhart and the Later Heidegger:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mystical Element in Heidegger’s Thought, Part One</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction to his habilitation dissertation at Freiburg,<italic>The Doctrine of Categories and of Meaning in Duns Scotus</italic>(1916), the young Martin Heidegger praised the “objective” orientation of medieval philosophy: “Scholastic psychology, precisely inasmuch as it is not focused upon the dynamic and flowing reality of the psychical remains in its fundamental problems oriented toward the objective and noematic, a circumstance which greatly favors setting one’s sight on the phenomenon of intentionality” (<italic>DS</italic>, 15).¹ While modern philosophy is characterized by a keen sense of subjective experience, the Scholastic thinker is concerned primarily with the object of knowledge, with “being.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Meister Eckhart and the Later Heidegger:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Mystical Element in Heidegger’s Thought, Part Two</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Space does not permit us to pursue Eckhart’s thought in any greater detail. We must instead turn to Martin Heidegger and develop the striking parallel of the latter’s thought to that of the mystic of Hochheim.</p>
                     <p>Both Eckhart and Heidegger reject any merely “anthropological” account of the essence of man. Neither is content to say that man is one being among others, differentiated by his “rational faculty.” Man must be understood instead in relationship to something which transcends beings altogether. The essential “greatness” of man is nothing human or anthropological, but rests in his being the privileged “place” (<italic>Stätte</italic>[<italic>Q</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Heidegger’s “Dif-ference” and the Distinction between Esse and Ens in St. Thomas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of Western metaphysics, according to Martin Heidegger, is a centuries-old “oblivion of Being” (<italic>Seinsvergessenheit</italic>), the shadow of which reaches all the way from Anaximander to Nietzsche (<italic>WM</italic>, l l/210).¹ If Heidegger himself claims to have recalled Being itself, Being in its truth, Western metaphysics has contented itself with various counterfeits for Being, either with generic categorizations of beings in general, or with a causal first-being, a being which causes other beings. No matter how loudly it protests to the contrary, in metaphysics Being is forsaken in favor of beings. Yet the followers of Thomas Aquinas have argued with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Demythologizing Heidegger:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aletheia and the History of Being</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Martin Heidegger could never resist a good story. He could never resist giving what he had discovered about<italic>aletheia</italic>and the oblivion of Being a narrative form. In<italic>Being and Time</italic>, we were promised a story—which was to be written backwards—of the “destruction of the history of ontology.” Beginning at the end, with Kant, it was to feel its way back through the tradition in a deconstructive gesture, looking for what had all along been blocking the discovery of the temporal meaning of Being which had at last begun to emerge in Kant. In the later works this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Hermeneutics as the Recovery of Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Constantine Constantius—the Kierkegaardian pseudonym—undertook a return trip to Berlin, he made an experiment in “repetition” which was, I want to argue, of some consequence for hermeneutics. I believe that what we nowadays call “hermeneutics”—Heideggerian and post-Heideggerian hermeneutics—defends the view that repetition is possible and indeed that everything in hermeneutics turns on its possibility. On this account, hermeneutics is always a work of retrieval (<italic>Wiederholung</italic>), a laying out (<italic>auslegen</italic>) which fetches back (<italic>wiederholen</italic>), an explicating which retrieves what is latent and puts it into words for the first time, as Heidegger says (<italic>SZ</italic>, § 63, 314</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Heidegger and Derrida:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cold Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to undertake here a double-reading of Martin Heidegger and Jacques Derrida. I do not intend a comparison, in any usual sense. Rather I want to let the texts of Heidegger and Derrida mingle with each other to the point of infiltrating and subverting each other. I want first to let Derrida insinuate his way into Heidegger and then, in a return movement, to let Heidegger insinuate his way into Derrida. Heidegger and Derrida: by that I do not intend an Aufhebung but rather a double-cross in which each, taking the side of the other, is co-opted and corrupted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>On Not Knowing Who We Are:</title>
                     <subtitle>Madness, Hermeneutics, and the Night of Truth in Foucault</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay, which I take as the point of departure for the present study, from which indeed the whole has drawn its name, I argue that Michel Foucault’s thought is best construed as a hermeneutics of<italic>not knowing</italic>who we are. I construe Foucault’s work to operate according to what Jacques Derrida calls the logic of the sans. That means that we get the best results by proceeding<italic>sans voir</italic>,<italic>sans avoir</italic>,<italic>sans savoir</italic>, without sight, without savvy, and without seizing hold of what we love. This is a bit of a perversity, turning as it does, not on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Beyond Aestheticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida’s Responsible Anarchy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deconstruction is sometimes accused of being a version of aestheticism. It appears to be frivolous and playful, to abdicate its duty to read literary and philosophical texts responsibly, and perversely to prefer arbitrary misreadings to serious interpretation. Viewed thus, Derrida sounds like the aesthete in Kierkegaard’s Either/Or who advises us to situate ourselves at a point prior to the principle of contradiction, anterior to its field of force, so that, exempted from the harshness of having to choose between its terms, we will be free to frolic in a world without consequences. On this rendering, deconstruction practices its own version</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>On Not Circumventing the Quasi-Transcendental:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Rorty and Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Richard Rorty has given up the traditional idea of “philosophical knowledge,” the idea that there is some sort or entity or principle or condition which philosophers can come up with, so long as they argue carefully, that “explains” or “grounds” what the rest of us are doing. Rorty has given up the Kantian idea that there is a “philosophical tribunal”¹ whose job it is to adjudicate conflicting claims about science or morals or art, in virtue of something that philosophers know and that nobody else knows, not unless they become philosophers, too. He rejects the idea that philosophers, in virtue</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Shedding Tears beyond Being:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida’s Confession of Prayer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The resources and strategies of negative theology, its “detours, locutions and syntax” (<italic>Marg</italic>., 6/6),² have always fascinated Jacques Derrida, and that is because for Derrida, as for negative theology, our desire beyond desire is for what lies “beyond being,” to use a venerable expression from Christian Neoplatonism. But what lies “beyond being” for Derrida is tears, prayers and tears, tears shed beyond being (<italic>V</italic>, 42/40), prayers sent like sighs beyond being, truth, and knowledge. That produces, on the one hand, a remarkable proximity of his work to negative theology, even as, on the other hand, it opens up an abyss</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Good News about Alterity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida and Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Derrida’s work is often mistakenly criticized as a kind of linguistic subjective idealism which traps us inside a chain of linguistic signifiers, unable to do anything but play vainly with linguistic strings. In fact, Derrida’s thought is through and through a philosophy of “alterity,” of openness to the other, which provides a rich and vigorous catalyst for religious thought. After demonstrating the wrongheadedness of the subjectivist reading of Derrida, I go on to show the richness of this philosophy of alterity for theology: first, in terms of the negative theology, where alterity refers to God as the absolutely Other; and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>The Time of Giving and Forgiving/Edifying Divertissement No. 3</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The gift, one might say, is<italic>how</italic>things “come,” how<italic>the</italic>impossible happens.</p>
                     <p>The gift is an event,<italic>é-venir</italic>, something that really happens, something we deeply desire, just because it escapes the closed circle of checks and balances, the calculus that accounts for everything, in which every equation is balanced. The circle prevents the event, blocks the incoming of the new, tethers the<italic>tout autre</italic>to the horizon of the same. The tighter the circle is drawn, the less there is of gift. For when a gift produces a debt of gratitude—and when does it not?—it puts the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Toward a Postmodern Theology of the Cross:</title>
                     <subtitle>Augustine, Heidegger, Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this age of the death of God, it is of no little interest and significance that two of the major European philosophers of this century, two of the masters of postmodernity, if this is a word we still can use, have chosen (at different points in their work: one very early on, the other only later) to comment on the ageless power and beauty of Augustine’s<italic>Confessions</italic>. In the summer semester of 1921, at the very beginning of his work, when he was still thinking within a Christian context, the young Heidegger (then thirty-two years old) devoted a lecture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Jacques Derrida (1930–2004)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the death of Jacques Derrida on October 8, 2004, some thirty-seven years after he first burst upon the scene in 1967 with three explosive books of philosophy, the world lost one of its deepest, most original, and most provocative figures. Born of an assimilated Frenchspeaking Jewish family in Algeria on July 15, 1930, he immigrated to France to study philosophy in 1950 and in 1957 made his first visit to the United States, to which he would be linked by the stars. Named after the American child movie star Jackie Coogan—his birth name was “Jackie”—he was to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Sacred Anarchy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fragments of a Postmodern Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Postmodernism,” on my reading, is the issue of a crisis in hermeneutics. It is a radicalization of the problem of<italic>hermeneusis</italic>that faces up to the fact that hermeneutics has no metaphysical backup, no Hegelian assurances that the truth is inevitably working itself out, continually being reappropriated again and again. It is a more merciless hermeneutics that does not so much deny “tradition,” as its critics charge, as redefine tradition as a highly factical, fortuitous, and almost hopelessly complex accumulation of competing subtraditions, power plays, and incommensurable language games, along with a dash of wisdom here and there. (Whose wisdom?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>In Search of a Sacred Anarchy:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Experiment in Danish Deconstruction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Martin Heidegger, like many of us, Calvin Schrag has had a theological point of departure. His earliest work,<italic>Existence and Freedom</italic>, published some forty years ago, undertook one of the first important confrontations of Heidegger and Kierkegaard in English. 1 Schrag understood that a great deal of Continental philosophy originated in the decision made by Kierkegaard to expose philosophy to biblical categories, on the premise that if the categories of Greek philosophy are all we have, then the poor existing individual is lost. It was in no small part from that decision that Heidegger’s<italic>Being and Time</italic>emerged, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>The Experience of God and the Axiology of the Impossible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who would not want to have an experience of God? But if no one has seen God and lived, who would want to risk it? Would this experience be some very extraordinary and deathdefying event, like landing on the moon or being abducted by aliens? Or would it rather be a much calmer, cooler, and more calculating affair, like trying to read extremely complex computer data from the Galileo telescope that only a few highly trained experts can understand? What would “experience” mean if one had an experience of God? For that matter, what would “ God” mean if God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Without Sovereignty, Without Being:</title>
                     <subtitle>Unconditionality, the Coming God, and Derrida’s Democracy to Come</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is there something “unconditional” that is nonetheless without “sovereignty”? Is there something that makes an unconditional claim without laying claim to unconditional force or power? Is there something that, even if it were a certain power or force, would be at most a “force without force” or a “power of powerlessness”? Is there something unconditional that would neither be nor be something ? Does the unconditional resist the very language of being in which we pose this question? Might it be that the unconditional would not really have a seat in being, that the conditions that obtain in being would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>“Lazarus, Come Out”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rebirth and Resurrection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once, during the time that Jesus was using Bethany as a base of operations, staying with his close friends Mary and Martha, he had left town for a short spell when Lazarus, the brother of Mary and Martha, became ill. The two sisters, whom Jesus loved, sent him a message to return at once. By the time Jesus got back, however, he found that Lazarus had been dead for four days. At his approach to Bethany, Martha had gone out to meet him on the road into town and as much as rebuked him for having been away at this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>A Prayer for the Impossible:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Catechumen’s Guide to Deconstruction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the things Derrida means by a text or a tradition is that it keeps “happening” (<italic>arriver</italic>) without ever quite “arriving” at a final, fixed, and finished destination. We cannot simply “derive” (dériver ) direct instruction from it, but we must instead allow it a certain drift or free play (<italic>dérive</italic>), which allows that tradition to be creative and reinvent itself so that it can be, as Augustine said of God, ever ancient yet ever new. That, as I pointed out, does not scuttle the figure of walking “in the steps” of someone, but it does give it some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>God, Perhaps:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fear of One Small Word</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I dream of learning how to say “perhaps.” I have the same dream, night after night, of a<italic>tolle, lege</italic>experience, in which I open a book—I cannot make out the title—always to the same sentence, “Peut-être—il faut toujours dire peut-être pour . . . ” In the morning I cannot remember the rest of the sentence. I am dreaming of a new species of theologians, of theologians to come, theologians of the “perhaps,” a new society of friends of a dangerous “perhaps.” I would like to think we are, perhaps, already a little like these theologians</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005tww.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>409</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
