<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt234wk8</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B2430.L484H376 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lévinas, Emmanuel</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Prophetic Politics</book-title>
         <subtitle>Emmanuel Levinas and the Sanctification of Suffering</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HAROLD</surname>
               <given-names>PHILIP J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780821443156</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0821443151</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ATHENS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ohio University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j7x78v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>Prophetic Politics</italic>,Philip J. Haroldoffers an original interpretation of the political dimension of Emmanuel Levinas's thought. Harold argues that Levinas's mature position in<italic>Otherwise Than Being</italic>breaks radically with the dialogical inclinations of his earlier<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>and that transformation manifests itself most clearly in the peculiar nature of Levinas's relationship to politics.Levinas's philosophy is concerned not with the ethical per se, in either its applied or its transcendent forms, but with the source of ethics. Once this source is revealed to be an anarchic interruption of our efforts to think the ethical, Levinas's political claims cannot be read as straightforward ideological positions or principles for political action. They are instead to be understood "prophetically," a position that Harold finds comparable to the communitarian critique of liberalism offered by such writers as Alasdair MacIntyre and Charles Taylor. In developing this interpretation, which runs counter to formative influences from the phenomenological tradition, Harold traces Levinas's debt to phenomenological descriptions of such experiences as empathy and playfulness.<italic>Prophetic Politics</italic>will highlight the relevance of the phenomenological tradition to contemporary ethical and political thought-a long-standing goal of the series-while also making a significant and original contribution to Levinas scholarship.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emmanuel Levinas (1906–95) is a thinker who challenges the fundamental pretension of political philosophy to<italic>evaluate</italic>politics. In Levinas’s mature thought, what is said to be “ethical” is a pre-theoretical and even pre-rational vulnerability or exposure to the “other.” As soon as we start to think about ethics, this otherness or alterity of the other, which is the source of ethics, dissipates. All theory, all philosophy, and all conscious thought is only spinning its wheels trying to reach what is properly ethical, of which it can only be a betrayal. Levinas generates a vocabulary for talking about what is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>DEATH, ESCAPE, AND THINKING BEYOND BEING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the outset of his first original philosophical work,<italic>On Escape</italic>, Levinas traces the path taken by modern philosophy. The modern approach begins with human freedom and the limitations the real imposes on that freedom—the “non-I” restricts the I, and the I “revolts” against this constraint. Subjectivity is understood as a substantial subject lying behind its accidental modifications: “The simplicity of the subject lies beyond the struggles that tear it apart.” These struggles are heroic attempts to overcome obstacles to fulfillment, understood as self-sufficiency. Being itself is thus conceived as sufficiency; and the subject enhances its being by becoming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>PLAY AND RESPONSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’s use of the term<italic>ethics</italic>is a novel one. Ethics is the study of morality, an answer to the question “What are we to do?” In the vulgar sense of the term, when I am concerned for how my actions affect others—when I am put in question, as Levinas says—I have an ethical attitude. I can of course have a variety of other attitudes: professional, profit-maximizing, theoretical, and intimate all come to mind. As a discipline, ethics takes all of these into consideration, and is incomplete without the study of politics, as Aristotle taught. Ethics, and ultimately</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>THE PHILOSOPHICAL ETHICS OF TOTALITY AND INFINITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout my interpretation of Levinas I have been opposing the interpretation that takes his thought to be a moral philosophy. Such a reading is ubiquitous in the literature. The I is a subject, under this view, enjoying itself selfishly until it meets another person, the “other” who breaks into my closed realm, decenters me, but also gives me a new (moral) identity deeper and more fulfilling than before. As Silvia Benso writes, “To renounce one’s own ontological power as an ego means to receive back the ethical power of the Me.”¹ Robert Gibbs puts it: “I become myself—I become</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>THE TURNING POINT:</title>
                     <subtitle>“VIOLENCE AND METAPHYSICS”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his discussion of “the move” to the third party and justice, Simon Critchley describes an interpretation of Levinas that would argue in the following way: “<italic>if</italic>I inhabited an angelic I-Thou relation without a relation to others—ethics without politics—then there would be no problem and no question of raising a question.”¹ It is an interpretation that errs, Critchley points out, since the third party is already there. However, it errs for a deeper reason: the relation to the other alone, a saying without the said, is in no way “angelic.” The saying is horrible, frightful, and under</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>TRADITION AND FINITE FREEDOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his book<italic>The Parallax View</italic>Slavoj Žižek brings up a common refrain in the lament for a too-permissive age: that children lack firm limits and this lack of stability leads to license and excess. The reaction of a conservative desire for the imposition of strict standards on the young might not only be counterproductive, he writes, but also a manifestation of a desire to maintain an illusion and avoid the real paradox of freedom—the paradox that an absence of limits causes the loss of an illusion of freedom found in the violation of those very limits.¹ There is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>THE POLITICAL REVERSAL OF SUBSTITUTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emmanuel Levinas is typically thought of as an ethical thinker, with his thought involving a tension between “ethics” and “politics.”¹ Certainly Levinas’s formulations seem to lend themselves to be thought in this way, as he speaks of an infinite responsibility for the other person that goes beyond all politics and all power systems, the latter arising only with the interruption of this face-to-face relationship by the “third,” which would delimit this responsibility and even betray it.² I have been arguing that Levinas has never been an ethicist in the traditional sense. Levinas says as much: “What guides our research, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>JUSTICE AND INCOMMUNICABLE SUFFERING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question concerning the essence of justice is the opening question of Plato’s Πολιτεία, in which there appears in book 6 the idea of a good-beyond-being, the idea that has oriented all of Levinas’s original research from its inception.¹ This original question is not straightaway pursued in Plato’s text. Socrates in book 1 fends off the definitions of justice by the older Cephalus (who simply leaves before being questioned), the younger Polemarchus, and the “new man” Thrasymachus. The question at that point gets diverted from<italic>what</italic>justice is, to whether justice is<italic>better</italic>than injustice. Socrates’ claims at the end</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x78v.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
