<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR604.K47 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reason in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Poetic Argument</book-title>
         <subtitle>Studies in Modern Poetry</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KERTZER</surname>
               <given-names>JONATHAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1989</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773506794</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773561892</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Kingston; London; Montreal</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1988</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen's University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zt2s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Beginning with an essay on the history and theory of poetic argument, he traces its patterns through Romantic and Modernist literature. He divides his subject into three areas: the paradoxes of reason, language, and argument.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Poetic Argument</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a defence of reason in poetry. It does not follow the “moralistic” and “absolutist” principles proposed by Yvor Winters in<italic>In Defense of Reason</italic>; it is closer to the cautionary critique of avant-garde “unreality” offered more recently by Gerald Graff in<italic>Literature Against Itself</italic>. My main purpose is to trace the fate of reason as it engages in and is challenged by the arguments of modernist poetry. Such poetry argues with itself, within itself, with its resources, with its author, and with its readers. As I intend to show, it grows argumentative by making paradoxical demands of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Marianne Moore</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An argument is an inferential pattern, a train of ideas that are logically connected and lead to a conclusion entailed by the premises originally accepted and unifying the preceding discourse into a meaningful, satisfying whole. When I first offered this definition, I noted how it reveals the motive and shape of poetic argument, as manifested in linguistic power and aesthetic form. However, in the light of the first chapter we can discern in it all the terms of our discussion. It suggests that an argument is an admirably logical, rhetorical, and dramatic structure, stretched vulnerably between a point of departure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Edward Thomas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If poetry is the “lion’s leap,” where is its lair? In other words: in poetic arguments, where is the dramatic stage on which the rhetorical festival of logic is performed? The poetry of Edward and Dylan Thomas offers two contrasting ways of providing an unstable but productive locus for argument. I have shown in the first chapter that modernist theories must propose a poetic context or scene of writing in which arguments can arise and in which they can operate in their aggressive fashion. That field can be expressed in various ways, depending on the poet's manner of systematically defying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Dylan Thomas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a letter complaining about the composition of<italic>Under Milk Wood,</italic>Dylan Thomas noted that through “the complicated violence of the words” his comedy was turning into “some savage and devious metaphysical lyric” (SL, 364).¹ The phrase more accurately describes his poetry, which deviously and energetically argues about questions of life and death in a manner that is nevertheless lyrical. Although never a learned thinker,² he was fascinated by thought and by the intensity and intricacy of its operation; that is, he had a passionate mind, which wrestled with ideas and delighted in ingenious means of expressing this conflict. Like</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>T.S. Eliot</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout this book I have used the ungainly term “unreason” to suggest and to challenge a number of questionable assumptions of modernist theory. In different ways for different poets and critics, unreason is whatever necessitates and permits the unreasonable aggression of poetic argument. It is the special means by which, in Octavio Paz’s phrase, poetry liberates thought; or it is the contradictory ability of thought to think the unthinkable and say the unsayable; or it is the fundamental life of the mind prior to rational organization, whether understood as intuition, experience, subjectivity, or the inner self; or it is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Wallace Stevens</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because Wallace Stevens is one of the most argumentative of modern poets, he allows us to recapitulate our terms of discussion by reviewing the logical, rhetorical, and dramatic resources of poetic argument. His arguments move between the poles of immanence and transcendence, correlative limits of thought, which, he suggests, can only be imagined by means of unreason. In a sense they move between the inward and outward extremes proposed by Edward Thomas and T.S. Eliot and scrupulously surveyed by Marianne Moore, but Stevens addresses those limits rather differently. On the one hand, he, too, believes that poetry requires unreason: it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zt2s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
