<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125x1p</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">liao13798</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS799.712.T38 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Taiwan</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Taiwan</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Japanese influences</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Taiwan Under Japanese Colonial Rule, 1895-1945</book-title>
         <subtitle>History, Culture, Memory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PING-HUI</surname>
               <given-names>LIAO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WANG</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID DER-WEI</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231510813</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231510810</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/liao13798"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first study of colonial Taiwan in English, this volume brings together seventeen essays by leading scholars to construct a comprehensive cultural history of Taiwan under Japanese rule. Contributors from the United States, Japan, and Taiwan explore a number of topics through a variety of theoretical, comparative, and postcolonial perspectives, painting a complex and nuanced portrait of a pivotal time in the formation of Taiwanese national identity.</p>
         <p>Essays are grouped into four categories: rethinking colonialism and modernity; colonial policy and cultural change; visual culture and literary expressions; and from colonial rule to postcolonial independence. Their unique analysis considers all elements of the Taiwanese colonial experience, concentrating on land surveys and the census; transcolonial coordination; the education and recruitment of the cultural elite; the evolution of print culture and national literature; the effects of subjugation, coercion, discrimination, and governmentality; and the root causes of the ethnic violence that dominated the postcolonial era.</p>
         <p>The contributors encourage readers to rethink issues concerning history and ethnicity, cultural hegemony and resistance, tradition and modernity, and the romancing of racial identity. Their examination not only provides a singular understanding of Taiwan's colonial past, but also offers insight into Taiwan's relationship with China, Japan, and the United States today. Focusing on a crucial period in which the culture and language of Taiwan, China, and Japan became inextricably linked,<italic>Taiwan Under Japanese Colonial Rule</italic>effectively broadens the critique of colonialism and modernity in East Asia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ping-hui</surname>
                           <given-names>Liao</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wang</surname>
                           <given-names>David Der-wei</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TAIWAN UNDER JAPANESE COLONIAL RULE, 1895–1945:</title>
                     <subtitle>HISTORY, CULTURE, MEMORY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PING-HUI</surname>
                           <given-names>LIAO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume represents a first attempt to discuss colonialism and modernity in East Asia from the perspective of subjects very different from those that continue to occupy the attention of postcolonial scholars—with the probable exceptions of Gayatri Spivak and of Prasenjit Duara, who have recently begun to map territories that did not attract European imperial forces.¹ For many reasons Taiwan should regularly be featured in comparative colonial and postcolonial studies, but, regrettably, it has managed only to catch the eye of social scientists, who have considered Taiwan alternately as a window on China, a cold war bastion of freedom</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A PERSPECTIVE ON STUDIES OF TAIWANESE POLITICAL HISTORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconsidering the Postwar Japanese Historiography of Japanese Colonial Rule in Taiwan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MASAHIRO</surname>
                           <given-names>WAKABAYASHI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is well known that in the 1980s, when Taiwan underwent significant political changes, Taiwanese history suddenly began to generate a great deal of domestic and international academic interest. Particularly in Taiwan considerable time and material resources have been invested in this field of study.</p>
                     <p>It is worth noting that prior to this, however, the Japanese colonial period received relatively little academic attention (Chang 1983:15–16). This was the result of both historical and political factors. Most historians of the subject have hurriedly explored merely the frequent shifts of political rulers and have come to the premature conclusion that Taiwanese</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>THE JAPANESE COLONIAL STATE AND ITS FORM OF KNOWLEDGE IN TAIWAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JEN-TO</surname>
                           <given-names>YAO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As alien rulers who hardly knew anything about Taiwan before they landed on the island at the end of the nineteenth century, the members of the Japanese colonial government inevitably encountered two fundamental difficulties, which can be encapsulated in the universal questions posed by Bruno Latour in another context: “how to be familiar with things, people and events which are distant,” and, in turn, “how to act at a distance on unfamiliar events, places, and people” (Latour 1987:220, 223). Latour’s answer to these questions is, of course, already well known: by appealing to “some mobile, stable and combinable means to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE FORMATION OF TAIWANESE IDENTITY AND THE CULTURAL POLICY OF VARIOUS OUTSIDE REGIMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHŌZŌ</surname>
                           <given-names>FUJII</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a dialogue with the Japanese writer Shiba Ryōtarō 司馬遼太良 published in May 1994, Lee Tenghui 李登輝 noted that “up until today, those who have held power over Taiwan were all foreign regimes.” In the same dialogue, he also talked about the sadness of being “born as a Taiwanese who cannot do anything for Taiwan.”¹</p>
                     <p>A year before this dialogue took place, Japanese political scientist of East Asia Itō Kiyoshi 伊藤潔 published<italic>Taiwan: Four Hundred Years of History and Its Outlook</italic>(Chūkō shinsho series). There Itō describes his mother, Liu Zhu, who lives in Taiwan and is part of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>PRINT CULTURE AND THE EMERGENT PUBLIC SPHERE IN COLONIAL TAIWAN, 1895–1945</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PING-HUI</surname>
                           <given-names>LIAO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On March 6, 1929, the renowned German botanist Otto Penzig (1856–1929) died in Genoa, Italy, leaving behind him a rich collection of old books and periodicals on citrus fruits and other related subjects that contained studies dating from antiquity up to the era of Carolus Linnaeus (1707–1778). Among the 2,446 titles and 3,326 volumes,¹ four are especially valuable, as they were printed between 1480 and 1499, only a few decades after the Gutenberg Bible (1456):<italic>Regimen sanitatis salernitanum</italic>(Venice, 1480) by Arnaldi de Villanova (1240–1311);<italic>Il Libro della agricultura</italic>(Vicenza, 1490) by Pietro de Crescenzi;<italic>Etymologiarum</italic>et</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>SHAPING ADMINISTRATION IN COLONIAL TAIWAN, 1895–1945</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAROLINE</surname>
                           <given-names>TS’AI HUI-YU</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper examines how the colonial administration was shaped in the specific context of Taiwan under Japanese rule. From the beginning of Japanese rule in Taiwan, the colonial government mapped, reworked, and created a series of organizations based on natural villages, and actively sought to integrate these colonial spaces, themselves structured and overlapping, into the hierarchy of the colonial administrative mechanism. The Japanese colonial bureaucracy imposed a discipline of order on Taiwan, and by the 1930s wartime concerns reshaped this order, thus turning Taiwan into not only a disciplined but also a disciplinary society.</p>
                     <p>To decipher the operational network of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>THE STATE OF TAIWANESE CULTURE AND TAIWANESE NEW LITERATURE IN 1937:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues on Banning Chinese Newspaper Sections and Abolishing Chinese Writings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ISAO</surname>
                           <given-names>KAWAHARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On March 1, 1937, the second page of the<italic>Taiwan Daily News</italic>printed the following announcement:</p>
                     <p>The following four newspapers jointly announce that due to the current state of affairs we have decided to abolish the Chinese section. It has been over forty years since Japan took over Taiwan. In the light of the thoroughness of imperialization and the flourishing of cultural activities, we believe there is no hindrance to the complete abolition of the Chinese section. Beginning on April 1, the<italic>Taiwan News, Tainan News</italic>, and<italic>Taiwan Daily News</italic>will drop their Chinese sections;<italic>Taiwan shinminpō</italic>台灣新民報 will cut</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>COLONIAL MODERNITY FOR AN ELITE TAIWANESE, LIM BO-SENG:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Labyrinth of Cosmopolitanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAKESHI</surname>
                           <given-names>KOMAGOME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the context of Taiwanese history it is important to analyze the concept of colonial modernity, understanding both the attraction and the oppression of modernity, without regarding it simply as evidence of historical progress. Like so many other fashionable terms, however, the term “colonial modernity” is ambiguous: its meaning depends on each writer. Before we proceed we must first make clear what is meant by the term here.</p>
                     <p>As Leo Ching has pointed out, one of the intended effects of the term “colonial modernity” is to draw attention to structural similarities between Western imperialism and Japanese imperialism, and to emphasize</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>HEGEMONY AND IDENTITY IN THE COLONIAL EXPERIENCE OF TAIWAN, 1895–1945</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHIAW-CHIAN</surname>
                           <given-names>FONG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prior to the 1990s, the story of colonial Taiwan under Japanese rule was rarely heard in the English-speaking world; it also lacked an audience in Taiwan itself. With its democratization, which also removed pan-Chinese ideology, people on the island began to show interest in their own history. A space was thus created in which colonial experience could be researched and its stories told. However, since the time for intensive research has been relatively short thus far, the stories of both the colonizer and the colonized, particularly in regard to cultural domains, remain rudimentary, and not entirely precise in many details.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>CONFRONTATION AND COLLABORATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Traditional Taiwanese Writers’ Canonical Reflection and Cultural Thinking on the New-Old Literatures Debate During the Japanese Colonial Period</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MEI-ER</surname>
                           <given-names>HUANG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the history of cultural development, massive changes in language have often occurred, especially in times of ideological transition and cultural upheaval. These changes can for instance be seen in the Renaissance and the Japanese Meiji period. Similar occurrences have also been noted in China. The vernacular (<italic>baihua</italic>白話) movement initiated by Hu Shih 胡適(1891–1962)¹ in 1917 proposed the adoption of spoken Chinese in formal writing, in place of the traditional, archaic form (<italic>wenyan</italic>文言). This later triggered confrontation and debate among proponents of the new and old literary schools. Due to then-prevailing educational policies adopted by the Chinese</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>COLONIALISM AND THE PREDICAMENT OF IDENTITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Liu Na’ou and Yang Kui as Men of the World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HSIAO-YEN</surname>
                           <given-names>PENG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On May 5, 1927, Liu Na’ou 劉吶鷗 (1905–1940), watching his younger brother leave for Tokyo from their home in Tainan 臺南, wrote in his diary, “Bon Voyage! O! frère!”¹ (Happy voyage! O, brother!; Liu’s French). He himself, though thirsting to return to Shanghai, had to remain in Tainan until his grandmother’s funeral. Inspired by Baudelaire,² Liu’s seafaring feeling sounds a mumbo jumbo of cultural blending and affectation.</p>
                     <p>Born into a landlord’s household and having lost his father when he was twelve, Liu Na’ou always had a problem with his mother, who represented the “feudal system” to him. Fortunately enough,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>COLONIAL TAIWAN AND THE CONSTRUCTION OF LANDSCAPE PAINTING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHUAN-YING</surname>
                           <given-names>YEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In modern times appreciation of the Taiwanese landscape, or the “construction” of landscape painting, gradually began taking shape after Japan established the colonial government, which then provided subjective and institutional guidance. The leading figure in the early phase of this process, and the person whose perceptions were most important, was Ishikawa Kinichirō 石川欽一郎 (1871–1945), who continuously used his watercolors and essays to report on what he observed in Taiwan, starting from the time of his first arrival in 1907.</p>
                     <p>Ishikawa was a multitalented individual, gifted as both a watercolorist and a writer. His loyal followers in Taiwan praised him</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>AN AUTHOR LISTENING TO VOICES FROM THE NETHERWORLD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lu Heruo and the Kuso Realism Debate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHIE</surname>
                           <given-names>TARUMI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>262</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lu Heruo 吕赫若¹ (1914–1950) is one of the Taiwanese authors who best represents prewar Taiwanese literature. In January 1935 Lu made his debut in the Japanese proletarian magazine<italic>Bungaku hyōron</italic>文学评论 with “Gyūsha 牛車,” a tragedy set in colonial Taiwan and indicting modernization. Further, Lu enthusiastically helped lead the 1930s Taiwan New Literature movement as an influential writer and during the 1940s he was active as a singer in the Tōhō performance troop, which gained popular favor with their enterprising combination of Greater East Asian Co-Prosperity Sphere ideology and orientalism. When he returned to Taiwan, Lu played a leading</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>REVERSE EXPORTATION FROM JAPAN OF THE TALE OF “THE BELL OF SAYON”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Central Drama Group’s Taiwanese Performance and Wu Man-sha’s The Bell of Sayon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SAKUJIRŌ</surname>
                           <given-names>SHIMOMURA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of the “The Bell of Sayon 莎秧” is based on the true tragic accident of a girl from the Atayal tribe. The accident occurred on September 27, 1938, when this young girl, carrying the luggage of her respected teacher, who was on his way to war, slipped off a log bridge near the stream of Nanao (present day region of Nanao and Suao of Yilan prefecture) and disappeared after being swept away by the raging river. The name of this story originates from “The Bell of the Patriotic Maiden Sayon,” which is engraved on a hanging bell that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>GENDER, ETHNOGRAPHY, AND COLONIAL CULTURAL PRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nishikawa Mitsuru’s Discourse on Taiwan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KLEEMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>FAYE YUAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Colonial enterprises and colonial encounters generate the need to produce and possess the knowledge of other(s). There is an urgent need for the colonizing subject to acquire information on the colonized people, in order to aid in the management of its newly acquired territory, and it is equally pressing for the colonized to gain knowledge of their overlord. This transculturation, or the exchange of colonial knowledge, is nevertheless a reluctant liaison fraught with asymmetrical, nonreciprocal, and at times dangerous misreadings. As Said so clearly demonstrated in his<italic>Orientalism</italic>, the production of the Orient created a writing subject and a narrated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>WERE TAIWANESE BEING “ENSLAVED”?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Entanglement of Sinicization, Japanization, and Westernization</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>YING-CHE</surname>
                           <given-names>HUANG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The end of World War II resulted in the defeat of Japan and the end of Japanese colonial rule in Taiwan. The government of the Republic of China (hence-forth, the Nationalist government) took over Taiwan from Japan.¹ During the half-century of colonial rule, the Japanese colonial government aggressively promoted assimilation policies, employing state coercion to transfer Japanese culture to Taiwan in order to make Japanese culture dominant in the colony. Japanese nationalism was introduced through educational institutions on various levels. The assimilation policy was further intensified after the outbreak of the Sino-Japanese War in 1937; the imperial subjugation movement banned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>READING THE NUMBERS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethnicity, Violence, and Wartime Mobilization in Colonial Taiwan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIX</surname>
                           <given-names>DOUGLAS L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fall of 1945—after the announcement of Japan’s surrender to the Allied Forces but prior to the formal takeover of Taiwan—some two or three hundred incidents of assault and theft in Taiwan were reported by the colonial police bureau.¹ Although contemporary newspapers, as well as latter-day memoirs and oral histories, briefly mention these incidents, few historians have given them much attention.</p>
                     <p>Contemporary and historical accounts provide various explanations for this unlawful activity. A leaflet distributed in September 1945 in mid-Taiwan (with the intent of curtailing this activity) stated:</p>
                     <p>Ignorant and stupid brothers, watching for the chance to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>THE NATURE OF MINZOKU TAIWAN AND THE CONTEXT IN WHICH IT WAS PUBLISHED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MICHA</surname>
                           <given-names>WU</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>358</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Minzoku Taiwan</italic>民俗台湾, a journal in ethnology published during the war, has always enjoyed a positive response in both Taiwan and Japan. However, in July 1996, with the publication of<italic>The Fiction and Fact of “Greater East Asian Ethnology”</italic>『大東亞民俗學』の虛實, the Japanese literary critic Kawamura Minato 川村湊 contradicted this accepted opinion, generating controversy.</p>
                     <p>Kawamura picked up the term “Greater East Asian ethnology” for his book title from the transcript of a symposium published in the December 1943 issue of<italic>Minzoku Taiwan</italic>entitled “The construction of Greater East Asian ethnology and the mission of<italic>Minzoku Taiwan.</italic>” In his book Kawamura attempts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">liao13798.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
