<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Modernist Party</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McLoughlin</surname>
               <given-names>Kate</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748647316</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748647323</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748647325</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Edinburgh University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt3fgtd7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Leading international scholars explore the party's significance to ModernismHave you ever been struck by the number of parties in Modernist literature? Mrs. Ramsay drowns in anguish at the dinner-party she gives in Woolf's To The Lighthouse. Death is a guest in Katherine Mansfield's 'The Garden Party'. Politics sour the evening party in Joyce's 'The Dead'. Have you also noticed the role played by parties in the public intellectual culture of Modernism? A party held in London by Amy Lowell on 17 July 1914, attended by Ezra Pound, Ford Madox Ford, H.D. and Richard Aldington, degenerated into an argument over the nature of Imagism. On 18 May 1922, Proust, Joyce, Picasso, Stravinsky and Diaghilev met at a post-ballet party at Paris's Hotel Majestic: an unrepeatable encounter between Modernism's leading figures. In The Modernist Party, internationally distinguished scholars explore the party both as a literary device and as a social setting in which the movement's creative values were developed.Key Features:* Develops the concept of space, currently of central concern to Modernist scholars* Explores the tensions between Modernism as an aesthetics of intensity and Modernism as a movement of the everyday* Adds a new and vital area of research to investigations of Modernism as the product of intellectual and social networksKeywords: Modernism, Literature, Party, Social Network, Collaboration, Space</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note of Thanks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McLoughlin</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Guest List</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Welcome from the Host</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McLoughlin</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Anthropology from a Pragmatic Point of View</italic>(1798), Immanuel Kant describes how to throw the perfect dinner-party. The company must not number fewer than the graces or more than the muses: a number from three to nine is ‘just enough to keep the conversation from slackening or the guests from dividing into separate small groups with those sitting next to them’.¹ The conversation should proceed through three stages: ‘narration’ (which concerns the news of the day), ‘arguing’ (the exchange of opinions, which ‘stirs up the appetite for food and drink’) and ‘jesting’ (‘the mere play of wit’).² Governing all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>‘The dinner was indeed quiet’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Domestic Parties in the Work of Joseph Conrad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph Conrad’s reputation predominantly rests on his proto-modernist exploration of the individual male consciousness. Throughout his fiction, protagonists such as Charlie Marlow, Lord Jim, Razumov and Axel Heyst are preoccupied with (frequently failed) quests for identity, isolated figures grappling with a troubled psychology, trying to make sense of their situation in a hostile or unwelcoming community. In this context, parties (other than political ones) do not immediately spring to mind as familiar locations or sources for Conrad’s narratives, and when they do occur they are not always markers of social harmony in his work.¹ His emphasis on the relationship between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Prufrock, Party-Goer:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tongue-Tied at Tea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McLoughlin</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>J. Alfred Prufrock would not rank highly on anyone’s list of party-guests. Distinctly lacking in conviviality, the protagonist of T. S. Eliot’s poem anticipates ‘the taking of a toast and tea’ as an excruciating occasion on which the ‘overwhelming question’ he wishes to pose will be, even if he can bring himself to pose it, painfully misunderstood.² The work’s critics have attributed the problem to Prufrock (or Eliot) himself,³ analysing his internal wrestling in terms of fear of female (and male) sexuality,⁴ hysteria and other psychological disorders,⁵ Matthew Arnold’s ‘buried life’,⁶ Sigmund Freud’s notion of the uncanny⁷ and Henri Bergson’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Party Joyce:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the ‘Dead’ to When We ‘Wake’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rabaté</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Michel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Hades episode of<italic>Ulysses</italic>(1922), Bloom and a group of acquaintances are sitting in a horse-drawn carriage that will take them to Prospect cemetery in Glasnevin. They are travelling together to bring their friend Dignam to his final rest. After a short while, they notice disquieting details. Martin Cunningham brushes some crumbs from under his thighs, and Mr Power avers: ‘Someone seems to have been making a picnic party here lately.’² What follows provides one of the numerous narrative ellipses of this section:</p>
                     <p>All raised their thighs and eyed with disfavour the mildewed buttonless leather of the seats.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>‘Looking at the party with you’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pivotal Moments in Katherine Mansfield’s Party Stories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Angela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a sketch called ‘Sunday Lunch’ (1912) written for the little magazine<italic>Rhythm</italic>, Katherine Mansfield seems to show her bohemian credentials. She knows her way around the avant-garde smart set, for this is no sedate British traditional roast followed by apple pie as its title might suggest. Here the party-guests smoke and flirt in an atmosphere ‘of agitating intimacy’.¹ Their host manipulates his male guests: ‘“Glad you came.” Takes guest aside. “I say, that French dancing woman’s here. Over there – on the leopard skin – with the Chinese fan. Pitch into her, there’s a good chap.”’² This evokes shades of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Virginia Woolf’s Idea of a Party</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Randall</surname>
                           <given-names>Bryony</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rhythm of Virginia Woolf’s daily existence in early adulthood was largely dictated by the social obligations of a young English woman of her class, a round of activities including regular attendance at, and hosting of, a variety of different parties. Lunch- and tea-parties she often found simply dull; evening-parties, however, were much more difficult for both Woolf and her sister Vanessa. It was not only that the young women frequently felt awkward and out of place at such events (in a diary entry for 15 July 1903, Virginia claims that she and Vanessa frequently spoke to no-one for an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Proustian Peristalsis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parties Before, During and After</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ellison</surname>
                           <given-names>David R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The reader might wonder whether John Steinbeck’s amusing statement on ‘the nature of parties’ applies exclusively to the novel in which it appears, or whether it has a broader applicability.<italic>Cannery Row</italic>(1945), set in Monterey, California, during the Great Depression, is a concatenation of short scenes tied together by two parties – one which takes place about halfway through the book, and which is disastrous in its results, and a second one, which is planned as an act of atonement for the first one. A group of unemployed or underemployed men usually referred to as ‘The Boys’ by the narrator</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>‘Ezra through the open door’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Parties of Natalie Barney, Adrienne Monnier and Sylvia Beach as Lesbian Modernist Cultural Production</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Winning</surname>
                           <given-names>Joanne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her discussion of the so-called ‘Lost Generation’ of the 1920s, Noel Riley Fitch cites F. Scott Fitzgerald’s laconic description of the summer of 1925 as the summer of ‘1,000 parties and no work’.¹ Yet the summer of 1925, as she rightly notes, occurs in ‘a year of great literary productivity’, which includes, among other things, the publication of Fitzgerald’s own<italic>The Great Gatsby</italic>in the April and Virginia Woolf’s<italic>Mrs Dalloway</italic>in the May.² Contra to Fitzgerald’s account of the division between party-going and literary production, this chapter will explore the extent to which the modernist party might be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>‘Indeed everybody did come’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parties, Publicity and Intimacy in Gertrude Stein’s Plays</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goody</surname>
                           <given-names>Alex</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is concerned with Gertrude Stein’s response to two modernist parties, one a dinner-party given by the English painter Harry Phelan Gibb and his wife Bridget in Paris in April 1913 to which Gertrude Stein and her companion Alice Toklas were invited by the host, and one a cocktail-party in Hollywood given by Lillian May Ehrman in Stein’s honour in April 1935. These parties span the period of modernism, taking us from the expatriate, avant-garde fervour of 1910s Paris to the popular American culture of the 1930s and, crucially, they provide a means through which to approach the more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>The Interracial Party of Modernist Primitivism and the Black ‘After-Party’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crawford</surname>
                           <given-names>Margo Natalie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Harlem Renaissance of the 1920s and 1930s, in some of the 1960s and 1970s Black Arts Movement critiques, was an artistic movement of African Americans frolicking with the oppressors. Whereas the salons and sociability of Gertrude Stein, Muriel Draper and other modernists have been celebrated as the gathering of kindred spirits, the Black Arts Movement’s assessments of the Harlem Renaissance set it up as an interracial party or spectacle of assimilation, in which the self-determination of the Negro was constantly jeopardised. Black Arts Movement writers critiqued the role of white patrons in the Harlem Renaissance and an alleged desire,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>The Party In Extremis in D. H. Lawrence’s Women in Love</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Norris</surname>
                           <given-names>Margot</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Women in Love</italic>,¹ D. H. Lawrence created some of the most intense representations of early twentieth-century English parties to be found. Published in 1920, the novel had been completed in 1917, and it was difficult for contemporaries not to read the party sequences as recreations of the author’s interactions with Lady Ottoline Morrell and her circle at her Oxfordshire country home, Garsington Manor.² Lawrence and his wife Frieda were among the very first guests invited to Garsington – to attend a small birthday-party for Morrell on 16 June 1915 – and they were frequent and sometimes contentious guests there in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>Bohemian Retrospects:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ford Madox Ford, Post-War Memory and the Cabaret Theatre Club</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Waddell</surname>
                           <given-names>Nathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The English dramatist Ashley Dukes wrote in<italic>The Scene Is Changed</italic>(1942) that immediately before the First World War he frequented the Café Royal on Regent Street in London, where, with such artists as Jacob Epstein, Henri Gaudier-Brzeska, Christopher Nevinson and Robert Bevan, among others, he would talk ‘about the world, the inevitability of war, Marinetti’s futurism or Ezra Pound’s verse, or the paper that Wyndham Lewis was bringing out called<italic>Blast</italic>’.² This ‘lucky’ time, as Dukes put it, of intermingling artists and impresarios sharply contrasted with the world to come after 1918, a world ambivalently characterised by ‘deliverance and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>‘Pleasure too often repeated’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aldous Huxley’s Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shiach</surname>
                           <given-names>Morag</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an essay published in 1923, Aldous Huxley suggested that ‘of all the various poisons which modern civilization, by a process of autointoxication, brews quietly up within its own bowels, few are more deadly [. . .] than that curious and appalling thing that is technically known as “pleasure”.’² By ‘pleasure’, Huxley here clearly meant something other than simple enjoyment. His use of inverted commas around the word and his description of pleasure as ‘curious and appalling’ signal a profound and significant unease, which I will argue can be fully understood only when considered in relation to Huxley’s sense of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtd7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
