<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1njjmz</collection-id>
      <volume>90</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Constructing Feminine Poetics in the Works of a Late-20th-Century Catalan Woman Poet: Maria-Mercè Marçal</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Vicedo</surname>
               <given-names>Noelia Díaz</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781781880005</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781881705</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Modern Humanities Research Association</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Modern Humanities Research Association</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qfbjk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This study focuses upon the work of the Catalan woman poet Maria-Mercè Marçal. It analyses the interaction between body and language in her first five books of poetry. Drawing on the Italian feminist thought of il pensiero della differenza sessuale, it examines the ways in which Marçal’s poetic images display her Catalan feminine subjectivity, including the function of the poet, the space of poetry and the representation of love. It also explores the potentiality of the space of poetry to reconstruct female identity and reconfigure reality. In addition, it unravels the way in which the poet uses poetry to express the love for the other whilst also extending the boundaries of the self. The central concern is to bridge the fissure between female experience and universal precepts on the art of poetry through the predominance of an embodied and natural iconography. This study presents Marçal’s poetic compositions within the international panorama of poetry and feminist studies and aims to open up new terrains of discussion in the field of language, body and writing.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="222"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A NOTE ON REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book analyses questions of the female body, writing and poetry in the works of Catalan poet Maria-Mercè Marçal (1952–1998) through the in-depth study of the corpus composed between 1973 and 1988 —<italic>Cau de llunes, Bruixa de dol, Sal oberta, Terra de Mai, La germana, l’estrangera</italic>and<italic>Desglaç</italic>. It aims, firstly, to introduce the complex and innovative work of a prominent Catalan female author within a broader panorama of both Hispanic and international literary traditions, through a detailed analysis of some aspects of her work such as love, passion, the figure of the poet and the space of poetry.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutics of the Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I examine Maria-Mercè Marçal’s distinctive feminist thought and her contribution to the scope of Catalan feminism. I also argue how this feminist dimension results from a profound meditation on her experience as a woman and the consequent dialectic relationship with the process of writing. I attempt to demonstrate how in Marçal’s aesthetics, feminism and poetry become inextricably linked and interdependent, and how both converge in a profoundly heuristic process of the place and space of the female body. In her own words: ‘Que hi ha una relació entre el fet de tenir un cos de dona i</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Poiesis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapter has explored the theoretical framework and direction that the paradigm of the body takes in relation to language in Marçal’s poems. Through various perspectives and insights, I have explored how the body connects poetry and feminism in her work and how feminism is based on praxis rather than theory. By juxtaposing<italic>differenza sessuale</italic>with Judith Butler’s theorization of gender, I have discussed the means by which the body conditions Marçal’s composition and how its presence in the texts should be taken as the poet’s particular experience of being.</p>
                     <p>In this chapter, I turn to how Marçal’s literary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Poetics of Space:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconfiguring Reality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Through a detailed analysis of Marçal’s poetic evolution in the previous chapter, I have examined the conceptual and iconic frameworks that allow the poet to reelaborate her experience around the concept of being, particularly of her<italic>ser dona</italic>. As a result, the dynamic poetic space and form shapes this remaking, rewriting and rereading of the self. Furthermore, it highlights the system of structures (linguistic and semiotic) that merge in the process of poetically reinscribing female identity. In this third chapter, I consider how the literary space of poetry harnesses the possibility of becoming a subject, formed and conceptualized in alternative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Love and Passion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards the Process of Self-Transcendence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In maintaining the character of Marçal’s poetry as praxis, in Chapter Three I examined poetry as the space where the process of the reconfiguration of reality takes place. Moving from myth to the various levels of reality, I have shown that Marçal concentrated her agency as a writer upon the action of<italic>mettere al mondo il mondo</italic>. The results attestes to her emergence as a woman poet, and reveales the prevalence of poetic action upon the theme of birth as Marçal’s specific form of creating a novel iconographic female universe. As a writer, she reappropriates the female body and repositions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Marçal’s Feminine Poetics as a Powerful Principle of Being</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has explored, through the analysis of contested images, the convergence between language and body in Marçal’s poetry and has considered the extent to which its poetic effects reveal the possibilities of theorizing the construction of a feminine poetics within the Catalan context. This research on Marçal’s work is situated within the field of Catalan feminist studies in the Peninsula, which has seen the exploration of sexual difference in critical theory and literature. My contribution to the existing debate has been the consideration of the body as a point of reflection in order to redefine the boundaries of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qfbjk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
