<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BP173.J8W38 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Islam</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Relations</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Relations</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Islam</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jews</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Islamic Empire</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Islamic Empire</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Between Muslim and Jew</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Problem of Symbiosis under Early Islam</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WASSERSTROM</surname>
               <given-names>STEVEN M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400864133</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400864135</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zvsxn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Steven Wasserstrom undertakes a detailed analysis of the "creative symbiosis" that existed between Jewish and Muslim religious thought in the eighth through tenth centuries. Wasserstrom brings the disciplinary approaches of religious studies to bear on questions that have been examined previously by historians and by specialists in Judaism and Islam. His thematic approach provides an example of how difficult questions of influence might be opened up for broader examination.</p>
         <p>In Part I, "Trajectories," the author explores early Jewish-Muslim interactions, studying such areas as messianism, professions, authority, and class structure and showing how they were reshaped during the first centuries of Islam. Part II, "Constructions," looks at influences of Judaism on the development of the emerging Shi'ite community. This is tied to the wider issue of how early Muslims conceptualized "the Jew." In Part III, "Intimacies," the author tackles the complex "esoteric symbiosis" between Muslim and Jewish theologies. An investigation of the milieu in which Jews and Muslims interacted sheds new light on their shared religious imaginings. Throughout, Wasserstrom expands on the work of social and political historians to include symbolic and conceptual aspects of interreligious symbiosis. This book will interest scholars of Judaism and Islam, as well as those who are attracted by the larger issues exposed by its methodology.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1995.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="308"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The late Shlomo Dov (Fritz) Goitcin (1900–1985) characterized the central relationship of Jews with Muslims in the first centuries of Islam as one of “creative symbiosis.” This usage has been institutionalized in the study of Judeo-Arabica, and shows no immediate signs of being dislodged from its preeminence.¹ The concept<italic>symbiosis</italic>was first transposed from biology to the study of Jewish history by German Jewish intellectuals. Its most salient usage was in reference to their own cultural situation.² Alex Bein’s influential study, “Discourse on the Term ‘German-Jewish Symbiosis,’” appeared at that time, as an appendix to his essay (revealingly enough)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Who Were the Jews?</title>
                     <subtitle>PROBLEMS IN PROFILING THE JEWISH COMMUNITY UNDER EARLY ISLAM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The end of late antiquity is a period of Jewish history best known for being unknown. Salo Baron emphasizes the darkness of this terra incognita: “In the first three and one half dark and inarticulate centuries after the conclusion of the Talmud (500–850), Jewish intellectual leadership laid the foundations upon which the vocal and creative generations of the following three and one half centuries (850–1200) erected the magnificent structure of medieval Jewish biblical learning.”¹ S. D. Goitein likewise states unequivocally that “the centuries both preceding and following the rise of Islam are the most obscure in Jewish history.”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Jewish Messiahs of Early Islam</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Muhammad proclaimed himself the last Apostle of God, and not a Messiah. He thus did not impose a conclusion on history. His Islam, to be sure, did end antiquity—and in so doing, initiated something epochally new. The lawfulness, the continuity, and the grand sweep of this new dispensation proved overwhelmingly persuasive while remaining irrefutably within recognizably human history.</p>
                     <p>The victory of Muhammad’s “human” apostolicity—as opposed to a “divine” Messiahship—was particularly disorienting to Jews and Christians expecting a Messiah. The successful prophethood of Muhammad thereby forced rival Jewish and Christian redeemer figures into taking up unprecedented guises. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Shi‛ite and Jew between History and Myth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “symbiosis” of Jew and Shi‛ite does not appear in the famous pages of Ignaz Goldziher’s<italic>Introduction to Islamic Theology and Law</italic>. Rather, the “doctor maximus” of turn-of-the-century Islamic Studies observed merely that on “examining the legal documents, we find that the Shi‛i legal position towards other faiths is much harsher and stiffer than that taken by Sunni Muslims.” The pages following that observation then enumerate the precise horrors of Shi‛ite purity laws. S. D. Goitein, Goldziher’s successor as master Orientalist in the realm of Judeo-Arabica, also neglected the possibility of Judeo-Shi‛ite symbiosis. Thus, after his memorable firsthand account of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Jewish Studies and Comparative Religion in the Islamicate Renaissance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The thinkers of early Islam faced extraordinary intellectual challenges. They routinely confronted a bewildering array of serious opponents whose doctrines were well established and carefully defended. Among these, Jews and Shi‛is were the closest in theory and in practice to the defenders of Sunni Islam. Indeed, the very closeness of these groups presented the gravest danger to the self-understanding of the people of the Sunna of Muhammad. And intimate intellectual intercourse between these three groups persisted despite doctrinal and social obstacles. In part because Jews, Shi‛is, and Sunnis were themselves not monolithic units, individuals from among various subgroups could find</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Origins and Angels:</title>
                     <subtitle>Popular and Esoteric Literature in Jewish-Muslim Symbiosis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A prophet, as a young child, attends school for the first time. The teacher prompts him, “Say<italic>A</italic>!” to which the child-prophet responds “<italic>A</italic>.” The teacher then proceeds, “Say<italic>B</italic>!” to which the wise child answers, “Tell me the meaning of<italic>A</italic>and I will tell you<italic>B</italic>!” The dumbfounded teacher faints. The child then recitcs the meaning of the entire alphabet, with a mystical meaning attached to each letter. The prophet-child’s knowledge is a priori to education.</p>
                     <p>This story is told of the Buddha;¹ of Jesus;² of the Shi‛itc Fifth Imam;³ of the Jewish Ben Sira;⁴ of the Sikh</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>REFLECTIONS ON THE HISTORY AND PHILOSOPHY OF SYMBIOSIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the beginning of this book I surveyed scholarly opinion concerning the obscurity of the early Islamic period in the historical study of Judaism. Having now investigated several dimensions of the symbiosis between Muslim and Jew, I find it remains remarkable how few personalities emerged from this study. It is not only that the preponderance of figures studied here (necessarily) remain anonymous. The impossibility of ascertaining the social location, much less the specific identity, of many of the actors in the social drama of symbiosis should not, however, incapacitate the student of symbiosis—for the symbiosis, on my conception, constituted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvsxn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
