<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccfq</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2615.52 .H69 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. John</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, Narrative</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>How John Works</book-title>
         <subtitle>Storytelling in the Fourth Gospel</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Estes</surname>
               <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sheridan</surname>
               <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884141488</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884141471</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g69w8s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Essential classroom resource for New Testament courses</p>
         <p>In this book, a group of international scholars go in detail to explain how the author of the Gospel of John uses a variety of narrative strategies to best tell his story. More than a commentary, this book offers a glimpse at the way an ancient author created and used narrative features such as genre, character, style, persuasion, and even time and space to shape a dramatic story of the life of Jesus.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>An introduction to the Fourth Gospel through its narrative features and dynamicsFifteen features of story design that comprise the Gospel of JohnShort, targeted essays about how John works that can be used as starting points for the study of other Gospels/texts</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Estes</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel of John is arguably the most read book of the New Testament. So prominent is this gospel that it would be difficult to overstate its impact on world culture. We only need to consider a particular snippet of Jesus’s speech in John—what we today refer to as John 3:16—to see how great an impact the<italic>words</italic>of John have had on our world. Yet below these words exists a powerful<italic>story</italic>that has had a similar, incalculable impact. Just saying the phrase “water into wine” draws all hearers within range of Western tradition to reference the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Genre</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Attridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Harold W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Crafting a literary work does not happen in isolation. Imitation and creative adaptation of extant models are regular parts of the creative process. Imitation and adaptation result in the formation of literary “genres” or types that conform to certain patterns, generating expectations on the part of readers.¹ Genres are thus inevitable wherever literature is created.² In some contexts, generic patterns may be more formally recognized and described by theorists, but genres are operating whether formally recognized or not.</p>
                     <p>The development of well-defined genres played an important role in the history of classical literature. Reflecting on how these literary types functioned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Style</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nässelqvist</surname>
                           <given-names>Dan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Style has been a feature of the study of the Fourth Gospel for a long time. It has rarely been examined on its own terms, however; primarily, it has been used in a supporting function within source-critical research. This application of style focuses upon identifying and demarcating sources in and behind the text in its current form. The idea is that some parts of the Fourth Gospel exhibit a style that is inconsistent with the prevalent style of the Fourth Evangelist. In the history of source criticism, stylistic features have thus been used to prove (or, by critics, to disprove)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Estes</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Narratives need time to tell their stories. In fact, without time, a narrative is not a narrative. This is because in order to tell a story, the storyteller must relay to the hearer or reader at least one process or event. For example, “Everett” is not a narrative. “Everett walks” is not much of a narrative, though the present tense “walks” in English implies a motion that occurs in time. A better narrative would be, “Everett drove the car to the store, picked up groceries, and came home.” This is the beginning of a “real” narrative because it entails multiple</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Space</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Luther</surname>
                           <given-names>Susanne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Space in the Gospel of John denotes narrative space, which is all the topographical and topological information given in the text that serves to create the setting for the narrative action as well as a narrative world in the reader’s mind.¹ Narrative space can be created through reference to geographical spaces like “Jerusalem” or “Galilee”; through the naming of concrete spaces like “synagogue,” “praetorium,” or “Jacob’s well”; or through descriptive (“inside,” “outside”) or deictic (“here,” “there”) expressions. However, only fragments of the narrated world are provided through the words of the narrator and the characters of the story. The reader</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Point of View</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Resseguie</surname>
                           <given-names>James L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Point of view “signifies the way a story gets told.”¹ It elaborates the relationship between the storyteller and the story and the reception of the story by developing the way the author or narrator presents the reader with the characters, dialogue, actions, setting, and events of the story.² It is a multifaceted concept that biblical critics avoid—perhaps because it seems confusing or even irrelevant to the text’s meaning—yet nothing could be more important to the study of a biblical narrative text than the way the story gets told and the mode or modes by which the reader receives</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Plot</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Larsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Kasper Bro</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel of John is a narrative with a plot: “For God so loved the world that he gave his only Son” (John 3:16).¹ According to Peter Brooks, scholar of comparative literature, human beings “read for the plot” in order to satisfy their desire for meaning.² Human existence is a series of disparate episodes; but narratives, with a beginning, a plot, and an ending, project a sense of direction and meaning onto our lives, be it on a small scale in autobiographical posts on Facebook and shared family tales at the dinner table or on a larger scale in artistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Characterization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Skinner</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understanding John’s characters and the ways the Fourth Gospel employs characterization is crucial to appreciating both its story and Christology.¹ Studies of Johannine characterization have proliferated in recent years, and the result is that much helpful light has been shed on a previously overlooked topic.² This chapter is devoted to helping the reader come to terms with the function and significance of Johannine characters other than Jesus. Since Jesus is the protagonist of the story, we are given access to a tremendous amount of information about his background and identity (1:1–18), and we are occasionally told what he thinks,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Protagonist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stibbe</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark W. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John’s portrayal of Jesus is notable for many reasons, but one of the most intriguing is the fact that Jesus knows what is going on in other characters’ minds and hearts, while these same characters have no grasp of what is going on in his. This means that the Johannine Jesus appears elusive throughout the story John tells, just as he has done throughout history.</p>
                     <p>In my earlier years writing about John’s narrative art, I emphasized the elusiveness of John’s Jesus.¹ I pointed out that John portrays Jesus as evasive both in his speech and his actions. At both levels—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Imagery</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lee</surname>
                           <given-names>Dorothy A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Images in literary works are words that appeal to the senses to conjure up a corresponding picture in the mind of the reader. By definition, such images appeal to the reader’s imagination, which has the capacity both to visualize and to interpret. The Gospel of John uses a remarkable number of sensory images to tell its story and express its unique perspective on faith. Many of these images, through the course of the Johannine narrative, take on the character of religious symbols: vehicles of the divine world. Appealing to the imagination, image and symbol make it possible for the implied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Scripture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chennattu</surname>
                           <given-names>Rekha M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter illustrates how the Fourth Evangelist uses and interprets Scripture to develop the Johannine narrative of Jesus in a unique manner in order to make John’s Gospel truly credible and normative. In what follows, we shall first examine the use of Old Testament theological motifs, metaphors, imageries, allusions, festivals, and structural frameworks in John’s Gospel. We shall then explore the use and interpretation of direct and indirect Old Testament citations as well as references to the law in the gospel. An investigation of the understanding of the words as well as commandments of Jesus in the gospel will follow.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Myers</surname>
                           <given-names>Alicia D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the Gospel of John is rhetorical is not debated among recent narrative and literary-minded interpreters. Pointing to the gospel’s thesis statement at 20:30–31, these readers often argue that the gospel’s rhetorical goal is to affirm that Jesus is the Christ and the Son of God.¹ Beginning with the acknowledgement of the gospel’s rhetorical nature enables us to ask more questions about the types of rhetoric the gospel uses as well as their potential impact on the gospel audience. The present chapter will focus primarily on John’s relationship to classical rhetoric, meaning the tools of rhetoric used by speakers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Persuasion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sheridan</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John’s Gospel is an inherently persuasive narrative text. Toward the end of the gospel story, the narrator famously explains his purpose in writing his account of Jesus’s life: “Now Jesus did many other signs in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book. But these are written so that you [pl.] may come to believe that Jesus is the Messiah, the Son of God, and that through believing you may have life in his name” (John 20:30–31).¹ To assist its readers in believing, the gospel narrative employs a variety of literary and rhetorical techniques. For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Closure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moloney</surname>
                           <given-names>Francis J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tracing<italic>how</italic>John draws his narrative to closure is fraught with challenges, due to the unresolved debate concerning<italic>where</italic>his story ended. For many scholars and commentators, the words of the narrator to the audience in 20:30–31 mark the end of the original Johannine Gospel.¹ Increasingly, however, interpreters regard 21:1–25 as part of the original gospel. Most contemporary literary critics insist on the importance of interpreting a narrative in the form that it has come down to us over almost two thousand years. They regard the final chapter as an integral part of the story that must be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Audience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Klink</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward W.</given-names>
                           <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every story is written for an audience. Every story seeks to capture its audience, directing them along an intended textual path and sharing with them a purposeful communication. The story told by the Gospel of John is no different. John speaks<italic>about</italic>a topic, the life and ministry of Jesus, but also<italic>to</italic>an audience, one for whom Jesus is intended to be made both relevant and personal. Since an audience is implied whenever a text is created, it becomes an essential component in its interpretation. To interpret John, then, is to interpret its use of audience.</p>
                     <p>Before we explore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hill</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As even the casual reader knows, there is something different about John’s Gospel. No, there are lots of things about it that are different. Many of the literary traits that help make John’s Gospel what it is and which serve to differentiate it from other books and even from other gospels have been identified and explored in the present volume. Genre, style, time and space, imagery, characterization, protagonist, plot, point of view, use of Scripture, rhetoric, persuasion, closure, audience: each plays a part in shaping the story of the gospel, helping to reveal “how John works.”</p>
                     <p>But can we know,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69w8s.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
