<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vms</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>At the Limits of Memory</book-title>
         <subtitle>Legacies of Slavery in the Francophone World</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Frith</surname>
               <given-names>Nicola</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hodgson</surname>
               <given-names>Kate</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781781381595</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781387580</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Liverpool University Press</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Society for Francophone Postcolonial Studies</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gpcb4p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Recent years have seen a growing body of literature dedicated to memories of slavery in the Anglophone world, yet little has been done to approach this subject from Francophone perspectives. This collection responds to the urgent need to contribute to current research on slavery and memory studies by focusing specifically on the Francophone world. Featuring the scholarship of leading academics in France, Britain, the United States and Canada, the collection reflects upon contemporary commemorative practices that relate to the history of slavery and the slave trade, and questions how they function in relationship to other, less memorialized histories of exploitation, such as indentured and forced labour. The volume is set against the context of France’s growing body of memory legislation, as well as its close cultural and political connections to its former empire, all of which make it an influential player in how slavery continues to be memorialized and conceptualized in the public sphere. Contributors retrace and redraw the narrative map of slavery and its legacies in the Francophone world through a comparative understanding of how these different, but interconnected forms of labour exploitation have been remembered and/or forgotten from European, West African, Indian Ocean and Caribbean perspectives.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Slavery and Its Legacies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering Labour Exploitation in the Francophone World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frith</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicola</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hodgson</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past decade, the field of memory studies has given rise to a growing body of literature that has responded to the recent boom in memories of slavery and the slave trade. The proliferation of memorial sites relating to Europe’s slaving past has largely coincided with two key commemorative dates relating to abolitionism: the Abolition of the Slave Trade in 1807 (UK) and the Abolition of Slavery in 1848 (France). The accompanying literature – not least of which are the extensive studies conducted by Christine Chivallon and Françoise Vergès which bookend the current volume¹ – has served to enrich</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Representing the Slave Past:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Limits of Museographical and Patrimonial Discourses</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chivallon</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is concerned with the development of new patrimonial and museographical practices relating to transatlantic slavery in France and its far-flung overseas departments in the Caribbean.² From the outset, it is worth recalling that these departments consist of micro-societies that were born out of slavery and whose historical trajectory has yet to find its rightful place within that of the French nation. What follows may therefore appear surprising since the proposed analysis chimes a dissonant note amid the increasing clamour for action at a museal level for the creation of places to collect, remember and honour the memory of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Telling Stories of Slavery:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cultural Re-appropriations of Slave Memory in the French Caribbean Today</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reinhardt</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘What images does the word slavery bring to your mind?’ was the starting point that initiated my interviews of Guadeloupians in the summer of 2013. ‘Shame’, ‘suffering’, ‘misery’, ‘fear’, ‘chains’, ‘whips’ and ‘sugarcane fields with overseers’ were the immediate, instinctive replies. From these premises, the interviewees delved further into their perceptions of how slavery has been remembered, commemorated and taught in Guadeloupe for the past twenty years. I was interested in their personal appreciation of erected memorials, statues and museums, and in their ability to identify with the yearly celebrations marking the anniversary of the abolition of slavery on 27</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Art of Reconciliation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Memorial to the Abolition of Slavery in Nantes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frith</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicola</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 1 May 1998, a statue created by an art student, Lisa Marcault-Dérouard, in honour of the abolition of slavery in 1848 was found desecrated on the quayside in the city of Nantes.¹ It had been inaugurated six days earlier as part of the nation-wide celebrations of the 150th anniversary of the 1848 Abolition Act. Commissioned without the authorization of the municipal council by a group of citizen-led associations, the statue’s illicit unveiling in the midst of a state-led ceremony was intended to alert Nantes’s politicians to the need for a permanent memorial site (Chérel, 2012: 58). The violence subsequently</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shaping Representations of the Past in a Former Slave-Trade Port:</title>
                     <subtitle>Slavery Remembrance Day (10 May) in Nantes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hourcade</surname>
                           <given-names>Renaud</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2005, the French government chose 10 May as the annual date for its national day for remembering the slave trade, slavery and their abolitions. The creation of this official day of remembrance fulfilled one of the criteria set out in the so-called Taubira law (2001), which sought to inscribe the slave trade, slavery and their abolitions into national memory. Since the 1983 decree under François Mitterrand, each of France’s overseas departments and former slave colonies has had its own official commemorative date to celebrate abolition. But until 2005, France as a nation had neither a specific date nor any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Haiti and the Memorial Discourses of Slavery after 1804</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hodgson</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all of the countries of the Americas, the people of Haiti have to go the furthest back in time to access collectively the ‘souvenirs amers’ [‘bitter memories’] of colonial slavery. The beginning of the end of plantation slavery in the Americas occurred there, in August 1791, when a mass revolt broke out across the northern plain of what was then the French colony of Saint Domingue. Hundreds of sugar and coffee plantations were razed to the ground, and the de facto end of slavery began, as the former slaves-turned-revolutionaries deserted the ruins, forming rebel camps in the hills. By</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cette île n’est pas une île:</title>
                     <subtitle>Locating Gorée</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Forsdick</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Just less than half a mile away from the International Slavery Museum in Liverpool’s Albert Dock, in the shadow of the buildings on the Pier Head known as the Three Graces, is a sign for the area known as the Gorée Piazza. This was originally the site of the Gorée Warehouses, built in 1793 and demolished in the late 1940s after they had suffered significant damage during the Second World War. In his semi-autobiographical novel<italic>Ultramarine</italic>(2005 [1933]), the Wirral-born poet and novelist Malcolm Lowry alludes to a local tradition according to which the iron hoops on the walls here</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Multiple Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Slavery and Indenture in Mauritian Literature in French</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ravi</surname>
                           <given-names>Srilata</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of Mauritius, an island with no indigenous populations, is the history of sequential colonialisms and successive immigrations. The Portuguese are credited with the discovery of Mauritius in the early sixteenth century, but they showed little interest in colonizing the island. The Dutch came later, but were unsuccessful in their efforts to found a colony. After their withdrawal in 1710, French colonists, adventurers and merchants transformed the island into a prosperous and flourishing sugarcane-producing colony with the help of slaves who came mainly from Madagascar and East Africa (Addison and Hazareesingh, 1999: 25). General Decaen’s capitulation in 1810 transformed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Speaking of Slavery:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representations of Domestic Slavery in the Oral Epics of Francophone West Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Omuku</surname>
                           <given-names>Sotonye</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The institution of slavery and the practice of slave trading in Africa have been the subject of increasing debate over the past few decades, with historians and anthropologists considering the relationship between domestic slavery and the trans-Saharan and transatlantic slave trades, as well as the impact of these external trades on the traffic of slaves within Africa. Forced migration patterns across the Atlantic form the majority of the commemorative discourses on slavery in West Africa. Conversely, domestic slavery, which not only pre-dated and co-existed with the transatlantic and trans-Saharan trades, but has also outlived both, is often relegated to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From Forgetting to Remembrance:</title>
                     <subtitle>Slavery and Forced Labour in Tunisia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dali</surname>
                           <given-names>Inès Mrad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At least since the modern period, Morocco and the Regencies of Algiers, Tunis and Tripoli were among the regions directly implicated in the enslavement and displacement of sub-Saharan African peoples, and were used either as platforms for their transit towards Europe or as territories seeking domestic and agricultural labour. In the case of Tunisia, slaves were brought overland as part of trans-Saharan business and trade, but they could also be transported by sea, the trans-Mediterranean trade completing the trans-Saharan trade. Domestic slavery concerned large urban areas, as well as the rural world, but there remained some specificities relating to certain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imaging the Present:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Iconography of Slavery in Contemporary African Art</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffiths</surname>
                           <given-names>Claire</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As memories of slavery re-emerge in recent historiographies of the transatlantic slave trade, contemporary visual culture from Francophone Africa is participating in this reassessment of the past as part of an on-going discussion of ‘development’ in present-day Africa. By engaging with the history of the slave trade and exploring its connections with the use of African labour in contemporary modes of production in West Africa, recent art works from the region that once formed the heartland of the French slave trade can be seen to offer a discursive platform on which to foreground ‘alternative memorial practices and forms of memory-making’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cartographies of Memory, Politics of Emancipation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vergès</surname>
                           <given-names>Françoise</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the 1960s in Martinique, French Guiana, Guadeloupe and Réunion, and since 1998 in metropolitan France, memories of the slave trade and colonial slavery have mobilized associations, artists and scholars. After a long period of marginalization in French history and culture, colonial slavery has become a point of reference for the women, children and men who identify with those who were enslaved in the French colonies. It has been used to question the French national narrative and its pervasive inequalities, to explore the role and place of racial thinking in the making of French society and culture, and to analyse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gpcb4p.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
