<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Muriel Rukeyser and Documentary</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Poetics of Connection</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gander</surname>
               <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748670536</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748670543</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748670548</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Catherine Gander</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt3fgt6b"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This study of twentieth-century American poet Muriel Rukeyser explores the multiple avenues of her ‘poetics of connection’ to reveal a profound engagement with the equally intertextual documentary genre. It examines previously overlooked photo narratives, poetry, prose and archival material and demonstrates an enduring dialogue between the poet’s relational aesthetics and documentary’s similarly interdisciplinary and creative approach to the world. By considering the sources of documentary in Rukeyser’s work, the study provides insight into her guiding poetic principles, situating her as a vital figure in the history of twentieth-century American literature and culture, and as a pioneering personality in the development of American Studies.Key Features: Provides a new, interdisciplinary perspective on a critically neglected author, situating her firmly within the canon of essential twentieth century American poetsExamines previously overlooked material, including photo narratives, poetry, prose, and archival materialHighlights Rukeyser’s role in the formation of American StudiesOutlines the development of documentary in the 1930s, and its role in the formation of an American literary and cultural aesthetic</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Muriel Rukeyser – poet, biographer, novelist and playwright – remains surprisingly neglected by scholars of American literature and culture. Although a handful of scholars (whose important scholarship will be referred to in the course of this book) are helping to initiate a recovery of her work, Rukeyser is too often omitted from academic reading lists, library bookshelves and poetry anthologies. My reason for writing this book was principally to address this lack and to help instigate a proper reclamation of Rukeyser’s writing, situating her firmly in the canon of essential twentieth-century American poets and acknowledging her role as a critical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The Photo-text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the mid- to late 1930s, a new sub-genre of documentary developed in America. Magazine articles reporting the effects of the Depression were relying increasingly on the immediacy of visual impact, and the FSA’s photographic file soon became the primary source of images. In January 1936,<italic>Survey Graphic</italic>was the first non-governmental magazine to feature an extended article on the programmes of what was then the Resettlement Administration, publishing photographs of sharecroppers and tenant farmers in the South. By the end of 1936, other picture magazines, notably those of the Luce empire,<italic>Fortune</italic>,<italic>Life</italic>and<italic>Look</italic>, had also featured RA</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Lives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter further explores Rukeyser’s use of the human portrait, analysing her methods of documenting what she termed ‘exemplary lives’, and examining the extent to which the 1930s documentary impulse towards the aesthetic, ethical and iconographical representation of human beings informed Rukeyser’s own methods of biographical representation. Rukeyser said, ‘[t]he poem seems to me a meeting place just as a person’s life is a meeting place.’¹ By investigating the ways in which Rukeyser depicts human lives as ‘meeting places’, I will demonstrate how the biographies, individually and as a group, represent the coming together of several of the figures who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Documentary and the Emergence of American Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is necessary at this point to locate the sources of Rukeyser’s engagement with documentary within a larger intellectual sphere of influence. This chapter examines Rukeyser’s poetics as they developed contemporaneously with a new academic discipline, American Studies. By examining Rukeyser’s work in the context of a burgeoning scholarly discourse and intellectual re-visioning of American literary and cultural history, I wish to provide a larger framework within which to locate her involvement with documentary than has hitherto been discussed, as well as allowing for a broader understanding of documentary expression in America beyond its arguable culmination in the art and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Landscape, Navigation and Cartography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Exploring and documenting the American landscape, topologically and historically, remained a priority for Rukeyser throughout her working life. By examining the ways in which Rukeyser became involved with and manipulated the forms and techniques of travel reportage and tour guiding – two closely related documentary genres that developed during the 1930s and pervaded writing and image-making well into the 1940s – this chapter will illustrate how she pioneered a poetic cartography that provided witness to both the past and the present.</p>
                     <p>Throughout the chapter, I refer to Rukeyser’s visualisation and utilisation of the landscape as site of ‘cultural practice’. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rukeyser begins<italic>The Life of Poetry</italic>with a call to arms and an affirmation: ‘In time of crisis, we summon up our strength.’¹ This ‘strength’, she asserts, may be derived from ‘every forgotten image … every memory that can make us know our power’.² For Rukeyser, in a manner similar to that discovered by Francis Galton when conducting his experiments into language and mental imagery, the singular image of a boat generates and communicates a vast network of imaginative associations.³ Summoning the memory of her evacuation from Spain, Rukeyser writes simply, ‘I think now of a boat on which I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>illustrations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sources Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgt6b.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
