<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL458.P48 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Women and religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminist theory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Philosophy, Feminism, and Faith</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GROENHOUT</surname>
               <given-names>RUTH E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BOWER</surname>
               <given-names>MARYA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253341778</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253109668</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253109663</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzdbv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"The stories are powerful, sometimes heart-rending, sometimes lyrical, but always deeply personal. And there is some very good philosophizing as part of the bargain." -Merold Westphal</p>
         <p>How can the seemingly separate lives of philosopher, feminist, and follower of a religious tradition come together in one person's life? How does religious commitment affect philosophy or feminism? How does feminism play out in religious or philosophical commitment? Wrestling with answers to these questions, women who balance philosophy, feminism, and faith write about their lives. The voices gathered here from several different traditions-Catholic, Protestant, Quaker, Jewish, and Muslim-represent diverse ethnicities, races, and ages. The challenging and poignant reflections in Philosophy, Feminism, and Faith show how critical thought can successfully mesh with religious faith and social responsibility.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="312"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Commitment to any one of the terms listed in the title of this volume seems to preclude commitment to either of the other two. Philosophical skepticism seems inimical to religious faith. Traditional religious faith is often understood as standing over against feminism. And feminist theories have frequently placed themselves in opposition to male-stream philosophy. So how can one live with the seemingly immiscible combination of being a philosopher, belonging to a traditional religion, and being a feminist? How can we make sense of being, as Diana Tietjens Meyers phrases it, “intersectional selves”¹ when those selves are at the intersection of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Judaism and the Love of Reason</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NUSSBAUM</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am an Enlightenment Jew. My Judaism is marked by a commitment to the primacy of the moral, to the authority of truth and reason, and to the equal worth of all human beings. That this Judaism is both feminist and cosmopolitan follows from its commitment to these three great organizing values. Like the intellectual leaders who gave rise to Reform Judaism in Germany, I conceive of God’s kingdom as the kingdom of ends, a virtual polity, containing both true autonomy and true community, that organizes our moral hopes and efforts in this world of confusion, herdlike obedience, and unenlightened</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Feminism, Socialism, and Christianity Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHOWALD</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nearly three decades ago, I wrote an article in which I identified myself as ideologically committed to feminism, socialism, and Christianity.¹ The invitation to contribute to this book provides me with an opportunity to review those commitments and what they mean to me now. As then, I acknowledge the gap between my theory and my practice.</p>
                     <p>In that early essay, the crucial distinction I used to sketch the understandings of feminism, socialism, and Christianity to which I was committed was between individualistic and communalistic interpretations of the three terms. I defined an individualistic interpretation as one that emphasizes self-interest, whether</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>“Philosophizing on Saturday”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Faith and the Philosophical Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAMB</surname>
                           <given-names>WINIFRED WING HAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Good philosophies have typically been constructed by authors “with at least one eye out for the human condition,” and part of the human condition is a sense of alienation and tension between “that intuition of ourselves as one with the whole . . . and that [of ourselves] as separate beings. . . .”¹ According to the philosopher David Cooper, it is out of this latent tension that good philosophy arises and the failure to resolve it is not only an intellectual debacle, it is also a human tragedy.</p>
                     <p>As a Eurasian Christian woman from Hong Kong doing philosophy in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Three Aspects of Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORKOVSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A believer who came to feminism through philosophy—that is how I would characterize myself. Chronologically, I was born into a Roman Catholic family and baptized as an infant; after becoming a religious Sister, I was trained in philosophy; and in the 1980s I became aware of and content with the fact that I am a feminist. Some autobiographical details will explain how this unfolded. Then I will discuss the tensions and rewards that ensued.</p>
                     <p>My family of origin is from Moravia in the Czech Republic. Mother was born there and emigrated to Texas at the age of five. Raised</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Reflections on Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ELSHTAIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN BETHKE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was a graduate student of medieval and reformation history, I picked up and read a work that had a rather dramatic impact on me as an academic-in-training in the human sciences who was soon to find herself stifling within the confines of the then-dominant positivistic and behaviorist models in social science. That book was Erik Erikson’s<italic>Young Man Luther.</italic>¹ When<italic>Young Man Luther</italic>was first published, there were a number of excited discussions about “psycho-history” and restoring a rich understanding of human subjects in the social sciences. Although the book was not assigned in any of my graduate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Yes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SAWICKI</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Yes has a lot of no in it, or so I have found during my five decades on this planet. I must say some no's to the common premises of this anthology, so that I can profoundly and genuinely affirm its spirit of commitment to philosophy, faith, and feminism. Thus, I start with three refusals.</p>
                     <p>First, I am no daughter of Sophia. The project that would become this volume began as a family affair. Invitations went out to any who might count herself “among Sophia’s daughters.” I wanted in, but I wanted out too. Sophia is not my mother. We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Into the Crucible:</title>
                     <subtitle>My Art of Living</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCOTT</surname>
                           <given-names>JACQUELINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I think of philosophy, feminism, and Judaism as communities to which I belong because I have made commitments to them, but also because they have made investments in me. It is less the case that I chose to join them, and more accurate to say that they chose me. The relationship I have with them is often frustrating, and yet generally enlightening. They are the burden I “can neither bear nor throw off.”¹ At the same time, they are integral to my identity, and so perhaps, “burden” is entirely too strong a word. As with my race, there are times</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Learning to Question</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOHNSON</surname>
                           <given-names>PATRICIA ALTENBERND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Beginning graduate school in philosophy was a deciding point in my life. I majored in philosophy as an undergraduate, went on to a masters degree in comparative religion, married, taught pre-school, and worked as a live-in house-parent for ten boys, most of whom were young teenagers. The first day of the graduate program at the University of Toronto was spent taking written examinations. The following day, students faced a short oral examination based on those written examinations. At the end of the oral examinations determinations were made as to what each student would be required to take. Connected with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>I Can’t Say No:</title>
                     <subtitle>Self-Sacrifice and an Ethics of Care</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GROENHOUT</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTH E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Care ethics strikes a deep chord with me. It picks out aspects of ethics that have been overlooked or downplayed in most contemporary ethical theories, it arises out of a concern for building a theory from the perspective of women’s experiences, and it mandates behavior that seems the behavior an ethical theory ought to require. More than this, it meshes fairly well with my faith; the call to Care and the call to love one’s neighbor as oneself are very close, and Care’s emphasis on meeting the needs of the other fits well with the portrait of Christ one finds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Seduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Does How You Get to “Yes” Still Matter?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMON</surname>
                           <given-names>CAROLINE J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Whatever we wear, wherever we go, ‘yes’ means yes and ‘no’ means no!” So goes the chant heard at many a “Take Back the Night” march. The slogan is meant as a corrective to centuries of enculturated misunderstanding between the sexes.¹ Male sexuality does not underwrite a “point of no return” in arousal; women should renounce coy negatives that are meant as implicit come-ons; everyone should be emphatically discouraged from taking refusal for assent.</p>
                     <p>Issues of assault and acquaintance rape are important. Explicating the sort of ethic of consent needed to adjudicate such issues is useful and necessary. For the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Living within Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAPLAN</surname>
                           <given-names>LAURA DUHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A colleague invited me to write an essay about some of the difficulties I face in trying to reconcile my philosophy, my feminism, and my faith. After two botched attempts to outline such an essay, I came to realize that I had nothing to say on the topic because I have no difficulties reconciling philosophy, feminism, and faith. Instead, all three pursuits converge in my understanding of tradition. This understanding is not an intellectual achievement, but a way of life. It is difficult for me to rip this way of life far enough out of its context to articulate it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Hagar on My Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AL-HIBRI</surname>
                           <given-names>AZIZAH Y.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am an American Muslim immigrant. I come from an ancient corner of the world—the Middle East. My history goes back a few thousand years, for I am a descendent of Hagar, the mother of all Arabs. As years pass by in these United States, I find myself reading about Hagar, imagining her face, her hands, her life, her emotions. An Egyptian princess alone in the hot Arabian desert, twice an immigrant, with a crying infant and no food or water, not even breast milk to nurse. I close my eyes and feel the dry sand of the desert</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>A Skeptical Spirituality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NODDINGS</surname>
                           <given-names>NEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we try to answer the question whether philosophy, feminism, and faith can be reconciled, we see that many people have attempted the reconciliation, and quite a few have done so to their own satisfaction. Despite the multitude of personally satisfying accounts, no universally accepted reconciliation has ever been constructed. To argue for the compatibility of philosophy, feminism, and faith, then, is not a mathematical sort of task—one that can be completed to the satisfaction of some professionally constituted public. Part of the difficulty lies in the fact that neither philosophy nor feminism is a unitary body of thought.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Faith, Philosophy, Passions, and Feminism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dangerous Attractions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHERER</surname>
                           <given-names>IRMGARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To “profess”<italic>philosophic</italic>the love of wisdom, as a teacher in the classroom and as a scholar in intellectual pursuits, faithful to one’s life experiences and deeply held private beliefs, can be a high calling, a sacred mission, and a great need all in one. But most of all it is a delicate balancing act of competing demands in one’s own soul. The attempt to “steer one’s own rudder true,” for example to live a life of religious faith in private, but divorce it from one’s public<italic>profession</italic>which is based on different categories is, as the Existentialists have insisted,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>On Being a Christian Philosopher and Not a Feminist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOTHA</surname>
                           <given-names>M. ELAINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I recall vividly the utter astonishment of a fellow traveler on a flight from New York to San Francisco, when she discovered that I claimed to be a believer, a philosopher, and a teacher of Christian philosophy at a Christian university in South Africa. In her perception, the mix of womanhood, philosophy, and religion seemed incongruous, not to mention the even stranger notion of a woman claiming to teach Christian philosophy at a Christian university in a country with a political reputation which at the time certainly raised questions about the authenticity of Christianity. In her mind none of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Toward a Visionary Politics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology, Psychoanalytic Feminism, and Transcendence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NISSIM-SABAT</surname>
                           <given-names>MARILYN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We need, and our society needs, to create a vision of our human future and to actualize that vision in practice. I believe that just such a vision can emerge from a synthesis of feminist, philosophical, and spiritual resources. While the project of constituting such a vision is implicit in the work of writers and activists in a variety of fields, I hope in this paper to make a contribution by making the project of synthesis explicit and discussing some of its theoretical and concrete ramifications. The following remarks explain how I came to embark on this project.</p>
                     <p>I am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>My Life Speaks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EBENRECK</surname>
                           <given-names>SARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shortly after finishing my doctoral dissertation in 1976, I bought a small table loom and took a summer course in weaving. Quickly I saw how strikingly diverse colors drawn into a fabric brought it alive for me. So it has been for contrasting elements of my life. I am a feminist, a philosopher, and a woman of faith. Each of these strands of my life are enmeshed with the other, not out of their own inner necessity, but because I want to draw these aspects of my being into a fabric marked by integrity, beauty, and vivacity. Unlike the process</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzdbv.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
