<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3519.O2625 A9535 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Johnson, James Weldon, 1871–1938. Autobiography of an ex-colored man</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African American men in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Race in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>New Perspectives on James Weldon Johnson's "The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man"</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Morrissette</surname>
               <given-names>Noelle</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780820350967</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0820350966</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Georgia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ATHENS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Georgia Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2kmgz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>James Weldon Johnson (1871-1938) exemplified the ideal of the American public intellectual as a writer, educator, songwriter, diplomat, key figure of the Harlem Renaissance, and first African American executive of the NAACP. Originally published anonymously in 1912, Johnson's novel<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>is considered one of the foundational works of twentieth-century African American literature, and its themes and forms have been taken up by other writers, from Ralph Ellison to Teju Cole.</p>
         <p>Johnson's novel provocatively engages with political and cultural strains still prevalent in American discourse today, and it remains in print over a century after its initial publication.<italic>New Perspectives</italic>contains fresh essays that analyze the book's reverberations, the contexts within which it was created and received, the aesthetic and intellectual developments of its author, and its continuing influence on American literature and global culture.</p>
         <p>Contributors:Bruce Barnhart, Lori Brooks, Ben Glaser, Jeff Karem, Daphne Lamothe, Noelle Morrissette, Michael Nowlin, Lawrence J. Oliver, Diana Paulin, Amritjit Singh, Robert B. Stepto</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Biography of an Author, Biography of a Text: James Weldon Johnson’s Ultimate American Work</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORRISSETTE</surname>
                           <given-names>NOELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When James Weldon Johnson wrote these words, he possessed not only the hindsight of sixty-two years in America but a carefully considered knowledge of centuries of New World blacks. His knowledge was familial and represented an expansive geography, based on his mother’s Bahamian and Haitian heritage and his father’s experiences as a free black man in Virginia who worked at hotels for wintering vacationers in Florida and had family in New York City. Johnson’s knowledge was personal, based on his experiences with Jim Crow and with the geographic, linguistic, and visual diversity of New World black cultures: Cuban itinerant workers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Stepping across the Confines of Language and Race”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Brander Matthews, James Weldon Johnson, and Racial Cosmopolitanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLIVER</surname>
                           <given-names>LAWRENCE J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his autobiography,<italic>Along This Way</italic>, James Weldon Johnson relates that after he moved from Jacksonville to New York City in 1902, intent on making his career as a songwriter with his brother, Rosamond, and Bob Cole, he began taking literature classes at Columbia University (then Columbia College) from Brander Matthews (1852–1929), whose writing he had read. Johnson’s description of his first meeting with Matthews leaves no doubt that it was a critical event in his literary career. Matthews received him cordially, and Johnson was flattered to discover that the professor was familiar with his work in musical comedy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man Became an Unlikely Literary Classic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NOWLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first major interview he gave after winning the National Book Award for<italic>Invisible Man</italic>, Ralph Ellison was asked whether he thought his novel would still be around in twenty years. “I doubt it,” he answered. “It’s not an important novel. I failed of eloquence, and many of the immediate issues are rapidly fading away. If it does last, it will be simply because there are things going on in its depth that are of more permanent interest than on its surface. I hope so, anyway.”¹ The humility rings a bit false here, even with the benefit of hindsight.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Authenticity and Transparency in The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAREM</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFF</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critical discussions of authenticity in<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>have been curiously bounded by either the text’s complex provenance or the putative cultural (in)authenticity of the title character. The novel’s initial reception as a genuine autobiography has made the text a touchstone for debates about African American authorship, genre, and social change at the dawn of the twentieth century. Robert Stepto and William Andrews were among the first to note that Johnson’s text appears to join the historical tradition of African American self-authorship, only to break from it by constructing a “false” self and a “false” text in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Futurity of Miscegenation:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Weldon Johnson’s The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man and Pauline Hopkins’s Of One Blood</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PAULIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DIANA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although both Hopkins’s<italic>Of One Blood</italic>(1902–3) and Johnson’s<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>(1912) are now considered canonical African American literary texts, they have been examined most extensively in terms of their contributions to African American literary representation, including their excavations of the undocumented past and their complex depictions of self-discovery, interiority, passing, and racial hybridity.¹ Interdisciplinary scholarship has added to current understandings of the interactivity of these texts with diverse forms of African American, black diasporic, and transnational cultural production, like Susan Gillman’s work on Hopkins and the occult and Siobhan Somerville’s queer readings of both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Blackness Written, Erased, Rewritten:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Weldon Johnson, Teju Cole, and the Palimpsest of Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAMOTHE</surname>
                           <given-names>DAPHNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One hundred years separate the publications of James Weldon Johnson’s<italic>Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>(1912) and Teju Cole’s<italic>Open City</italic>(2012), compelling me to ask if these novels can speak to each other across the span of time and, if so, what meanings they reveal to readers about the similarities and diff erences between the modernist New Negro era and the postmodern era of post-blackness.¹ I and other critics have argued that African American modernism is characterized by the eff orts of progressive artists, activists, and intellectuals to construct a pluralist cultural nationalism.² This thesis necessarily assumes that early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dead Ambitions and Repeated Interruptions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Economies of Race and Temporality in The Autobiography of an Ex-Coloured Man</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARNHART</surname>
                           <given-names>BRUCE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At a particularly important moment in his life, the narrator of James Weldon Johnson’s<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Coloured Man</italic>finds himself on the receiving end of some rather bleak advice. In an attempt to discourage the narrator from returning to the United States, his wealthy patron tells him: “to attempt to right the wrongs and ease the sufferings of the world in general is a waste of effort. You had just as well try to bale [<italic>sic</italic>] the Atlantic by pouring the water into the Pacific.” The narrator has just told the patron of his ambition to compose a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Autobiography as Ars Poetica:</title>
                     <subtitle>Satire and Rhythmic Exegesis in “Saint Peter Relates an Incident”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLASER</surname>
                           <given-names>BEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a survey of 1935’ s black literature for<italic>Opportunity</italic>magazine, Alain Locke develops a criterion for black poetry that may seem surprising: not James Weldon Johnson’s famous call for “symbols from within” comparable to the achievement of Synge and Yeats, not a call for native rhythms and folk forms, and not Langston Hughes’s turn to the “eternal tomtom beating in the Negro soul—the tom-tom of revolt against weariness in a white world.”¹ Rather, Locke sought “ the full flavor of tragic or comic irony as applied to Negro experience” that he had found in the “sturdy, incisive verse”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Composer versus the “Perfessor”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Writing Race and (Rag)Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BROOKS</surname>
                           <given-names>LORI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the sixth chapter of James Weldon Johnson’s<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>, the protagonist arrives starry-eyed in New York City and offers an account of its black nightlife, including his first encounter with ragtime music: “the stout man at the piano began to run his fingers up and down the keyboard. This he did in a manner that indicated that he was a master of a good deal of technique. Then he began to play; and such playing! . . . It was music of a kind I had never heard before. It was music that demanded physical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>James Weldon Johnson’s The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man, Archived and Live</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORRISSETTE</surname>
                           <given-names>NOELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On June 3, 1886, a young James Johnson received an award recognizing his “general proficiency, regular attendance and good conduct” in “Eighth Grade Jacksonville Graded School.” Stanton School, Jacksonville, was the city’s grade school for African Americans; Johnson’s prize was<italic>The Life and Times of Frederick Douglass</italic>.¹ Later that year Johnson had the rare opportunity of hearing Douglass speak in Jacksonville, an event that resoundingly shaped his aspiration to create an archive adequate to the task of reflecting the speech, performance, and “elusive undertone” of African American culture.² “I wanted to hear him speak and catch his words,” Johnson recalled.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART FOUR Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essay included in this collection was originally delivered as part of the 2009 W. E. B. Du Bois Lecture Series at Harvard University. Stepto discusses several scenes of racial education, both fictional and autobiographical, from major works by twentieth-century African American authors: Johnson’s<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>, Du Bois’s<italic>The Souls of Black Folk</italic>, Zora Neale Hurston’s<italic>Their Eyes Were Watching God</italic>, and Barack Obama’s<italic>Dreams from My Father</italic>. The “search for race” involves the recognition and navigation of racial tropes by subjects who find themselves made into objects at the center of the racial lesson. Yracing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>W. E. B. Du Bois, Barack Obama, and the Search for Race:</title>
                     <subtitle>School House Blues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STEPTO</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The schoolhouse episode is a staple event in African American narratives no doubt because it is remembered or imagined as a formative first scene of racial self-awareness. It is not a moment when race is adopted—that may come later; it is instead a moment when race is imposed. The episode may involve a graduation exercise, with all the attendant questions regarding what, exactly, is commencing. Though set in a hotel ballroom, the battle royal in the first chapter of Ralph Ellison’s Invisible Man is one such monumental episode. More likely, though, the episode is an earlier moment, perhaps the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ex-Colored Man for a New Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORRISSETTE</surname>
                           <given-names>NOELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SINGH</surname>
                           <given-names>AMRITJIT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>James Weldon Johnson, who thought of<italic>The Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</italic>as a living, moving work— a “biography of the race”—no doubt would have had much to add to his novel as he viewed more than a century of African American experiences following its publication. The novel has proven prescient in the way it anticipated the ongoing story of African American life. This story, still unfolding in the twenty-first century, is central to everything the United States as a nation stands for. As Ralph Ellison reminds readers in his essay “Twentieth-Century Fiction and the Black Mask of Humanity,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SUGGESTED FURTHER READING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmgz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
