<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn31sb</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Media and Memory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Garde-Hansen</surname>
               <given-names>Joanne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748640348</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748647071</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>George Square, Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Joanne Garde-Hansen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r25r9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How do we rely on media for remembering? In exploring the complex ways that media converge to support our desire to capture, store and retrieve memories, this textbook offers analyses of representations of memorable events, media tools for remembering and forgetting, media technologies for archiving and the role of media producers in making memories.Theories of memory and media are covered alongside an accessible range of case studies focusing on memory in relation to radio, television, pop music, celebrity, digital media and mobile phones. Ethnographic and production culture research, including interviews with members of the public and industry professionals, is also included. Offering a comprehensive introduction to the connections and disconnections in the study of media and memory, this is the perfect textbook for media studies students.Key Features* Presents a thorough and detailed overview of key writers, theories and debates* Case studies enrich the text, offering innovative approaches and insights on methodology * Covers a range of 'old' and 'new' media including: from radio, television, film, photography, digital media, mobile phones and popular music* Explores discourses, forms and practices of media and memory with active learning exercises that engage readers</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="184"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mediating the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Apart from mandatory history lessons at school that may inspire a minority to pursue historical studies at a higher level and beyond, where do the rest of us get an understanding of the past? It is safe to say, as we stand firmly established in the twenty-first century, that our engagement with history has become almost entirely mediated. Media, in the form of print, television, film, photography, radio and increasingly the Internet, are the main sources for recording, constructing, archiving and disseminating public and private histories in the early twenty-first century. They provide the most compelling devices for accessing information</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Memory Studies and Media Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>There is a long history of thinkers who have, to certain degrees, evaluated, reflected upon and tried to explain memory and remembering. Not surprisingly, this extends as far back as Plato and Aristotle as well as being found in the more recent philosophical thinking of writers as diverse as Friedrich Nietzsche (1844–1900), Sigmund Freud (1856–1939), Émile Durkheim (1858–1917), Henri Bergson (1859–1941) and Walter Benjamin (1892–1940). It has developed from early sixteenth-century beliefs that ‘memory could offer unmediated access to experience or to external reality’ (Radstone and Hodgkin 2005: 9) to late nineteenth-century challenges; as ‘modernity’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Personal, Collective, Mediated and New Memory Discourses</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Before providing a critical overview of key theories of memory (personal, collective, mediated and new), let us take a well-known example that elicits the discourses on media and memory this chapter is concerned with. This will help us to understand the ways in which memory operates as extrapolated by Paul Connerton in <italic>How Societies Remember</italic> (1989): through cognitive and performative modes. In the cognitive mode, the past is past and we retrieve events and experiences from the past into the present: through the act of remembering. In the performative, the past is brought into the present as a commemorative act</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Using Media to Make Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Institutions, Forms and Practices</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Media can represent lions or hunters. However, powerful media and cultural institutions whose business it is to record, archive and make accessible the everyday life, major events and social and cultural heritage of nations and communities, invariably write those narratives in ways that glorify not only themselves but the cultural hegemony of the societies they serve. They need to keep their customers, readers, audiences and users happy. They control their own archives even if they are actually only the custodians and not the full rightful owners of a nation’s heritage. This is the case with the publicly funded broadcaster in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Digital Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Democratisation of Archives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Media and the development and history of media from the printing press to the blogosphere have been caught in a tension between democracy and control. Pierre Nora has argued that a ‘democratization of history’ can occur if emancipatory versions of the past surface: ‘Unlike history, which has always been in the hands of the public authorities, of scholars and specialised peer groups, memory has acquired all the new privileges and prestige of a popular protest movement’ (2002: 6). Therefore a free and creative media brings with it democracy, or at least the possibility of democratisation. New media technologies of digital</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Voicing the Past:</title>
                     <subtitle>BBC Radio 4 and the Aberfan Disaster of 1963</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>There is a tendency within media studies to ignore sound. The visual image has dominated: art, photography, advertising, film, television, video games, online media, mobile phones. Just compare the amount of scholarly texts on television to radio, on cinema and gaming rather than soundtracks and soundscapes. Even the mobile phone, which is essentially a listening device, has only become interesting to media studies since it has a screen interface of applications, games, graphics, e-mail, photos and videos. When it comes to memory we assume that the visual dominates and structures our understanding of the world. We do not assume that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>(Re)Media Events:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remixing War on YouTube</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One of the key ways in which mediated memory has transformed in the last decade is through the developments in digital and online media. Wulf Kansteiner (2002) has persuasively argued that when considering the production of personal, collective, cultural and social memory in the early twenty-first century we need to fully embrace the methods and tools of media studies and understand this production in terms of the increased media literacy of audiences:</p>
                     <p>As a result, the history of collective memory would be recast as a complex process of cultural production and consumption that acknowledges the persistence of cultural traditions as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Madonna Archive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Celebrity, Ageing and Fan Nostalgia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The previous case study chapters have drawn upon particular examples of memory being articulated through the broadcast media of radio and television as well as post-broadcast media platforms such as YouTube. The emphasis has been on the mediation (van Dijck 2007) and mediatisation (Livingstone 2008) of history and memory in terms of local, national and international events or persons. As each chapter has progressed, so too has the consideration of the level and extent of audience involvement in the construction of making mediated memories. It would be very easy for any book on media and memory to get struck in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Towards a Concept of Connected Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Photo Album Goes Mobile</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>My Facebook page is awash with unremarkable images of conventionality: new babies, weddings, beloved pets, children on the beach, families skiing, gatherings, nights out, concerts, gardens, home improvements and hobbies. The vast majority of these I am not in. Some of these I have felt compelled to add to but most are produced by an online collection of individuals who may or may not be networked to each other and most likely have not been connected to me in the real world for quite some time. They are ‘dormant memories’ as Hoskins describes them (2010). Ceaselessly streaming this data of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r25r9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
