<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PG3096.U94C56 1993</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Russian fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Utopias in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Experimental fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Russia (Federation)</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Russian Experimental Fiction</book-title>
         <subtitle>Resisting Ideology after Utopia</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Clowes</surname>
               <given-names>Edith W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400863532</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400863538</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1993</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztgwq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the three decades following Stalin's death, major underground Russian writers have subverted Soviet ideology by using parody to draw attention to its basis in utopian thought. Referring to utopian writing as diverse as Defoe's<italic>Robinson Crusoe</italic>, Dostoevsky's<italic>Notes from Underground</italic>, and Orwell's<italic>Animal Farm</italic>, they have tested notions of truth, reality, and representation. They have gone beyond their precursors by experimenting with the tensions between ludic and didactic art. Edith Clowes explores these "meta-utopian" narratives, which address a wide range of attitudes toward utopia, to expose the challenge that literary play poses to dogmatism and to elucidate the sense of renewal it can bring to social imagination. Using both structural analysis and reception theory, she introduces readers outside Russia to a fascinating body of literature that includes Aleksandr Zinoviev's<italic>The Yawning Heights</italic>, Abram Terts's<italic>Liubimov</italic>, Vladimir Voinovich's<italic>Moscow 2042</italic>, and Liudmila Petrushevskaia's "The New Robinsons.".</p>
         <p>Not advocating its own utopian alternative to current social realities, meta-utopian fiction investigates the function of a deep human impulse to imagine, project, and enforce alternative social orders. Clowes examines the technical innovations meta-utopian writers have made in style, image, and narrative structure that inform fresh modes of social imagination. Her analysis leads to an inquiry into the intended and real audiences of this fiction, and into the ways its authors try to move them toward more sophisticated social discourse.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1993.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="252"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Note on Transliteration and Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Meta-utopian Writing:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE PROBLEM OF UTOPIA AS IDEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the short period since 1987 when Gorbachev made his speech about filling in the “blank passages” of Soviet Russian history, Russian intellectuals have confronted a serious crisis of social imagination. While it is clear that the old monopolistic, authoritarian communist ideology is in retreat, many people, and not just the old hardliners, fear that the absence of an authoritarian hierarchy portends an apocalypse, the onslaught of complete political and economic disorder. On the other hand, particularly since the failed coup of August 1991, a significant number of citizens have proved that they are probing some wholly different notion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Publishing the Dystopian Heritage:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE GLASNOST DEBATE ABOUT LITERARY EXPERIMENT AND UTOPIAN IDEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During glasnost among the strongest forms that the rethinking of social and cultural values has taken is a backlash against the utopian premises informing Soviet ideology. Such formulations are, in part, a response to the sudden appearance in Soviet journals of a large number of early- and mid-twentieth-century dystopian novels. The list is astounding. The year 1986 saw the publication of Platonov’s “Juvenalian Sea” (“Iuvenil’noe more”) in<italic>Znamia</italic>. In 1987 his<italic>Foundation Pit</italic>(<italic>Kotlovan</italic>) appeared in<italic>Novyi mir</italic>. In 1988 three more novels were published: Platonov’s rather meta-utopian<italic>Chevengur</italic>in<italic>Druzhba narodov</italic>, Orwell’s<italic>Animal Farm</italic>(<italic>Skotnyi dvor</italic>) in<italic>Rodnik</italic>in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Charting Meta-utopia:</title>
                     <subtitle>CHRONOTOPES OF DISORIENTATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the canonical markers of utopian writing is the ambiguous location of the ideal society in space and time. Thus, a good point of departure for a discussion of meta-utopian fiction will be a definition of it in terms of its treatment of spatial and temporal dimensions. Moreover, the positioning of plot events in a matrix of space and time, what Bakhtin calls “chronotope,” lays the coordinates for a sustained valuative framework.¹ Chronotopes can give a palpable sense of the ideological project central to meta-utopian fiction. This fiction is about liberation from spatial and temporal stasis. It is about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Science, Ideology, and the Structure of Meta-utopian Narrative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The modern Western tradition of utopian writing, rooted in More’s<italic>Utopia</italic>, is very much the product of a “scientific” mentality that has emerged over the last five hundred years. Although this mentality has been variously characterized, one of its firm bases is the epistemological concern for verifiable ways of knowing and measuring reality. Tracing the beginnings of this way of thinking in the late Middle Ages and early Renaissance, the comparatist Timothy J. Reiss defines an “analytico-referential” discourse founded on repeatable acts of mediated perception of the world, enabled by some invented instrument or mechanism.¹ Reiss draws particular attention to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Meta-utopian Language Problem, or Utopia as a Bump on a -log-</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That language and consciousness are intimately bound up with one another is a commonplace. How they interact is harder to ascertain. Post-Saussurian literary theorists claim perhaps too much for the priority of language over consciousness.¹ Philosophers concerned with this issue, such as Nietzsche or Wittgenstein, also acknowledge the impact of language on consciousness but stress the restrictions that linguistic structures and functions put on thinking. For example, in<italic>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</italic>Wittgenstein writes: “<italic>The limits of my language</italic>mean the limits of my world.”² Perhaps these restrictions are best characterized by tautology, the ultimate, absurd limit of language, an indication of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Meta-utopian Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A consideration of consciousness provides an appropriate end point for understanding the interaction between aesthetic experiment and ideological critique in meta-utopian fiction. In its challenge to exclusivist modes of social imagination and practice there emerges in this art a different mentality characterized by an insistence on balancing public and private modes of discourse, a love of ideological play, and an acknowledgment of the thinking, discerning person. The meta-utopian consciousness is built on a distinction between apparent ideological differences (for example, the looking-glass war between modes of realism) and significant valuative oppositions and choices (for example, between didactic and ludic art,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Making Meta-utopia Accessible:</title>
                     <subtitle>ZINOVIEV’S THE RADIANT FUTURE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can narrative innovation, ideological challenge, and popular appeal coexist in one work of art? According to Irving Howe, one of the major historians of Western modernism, the answer is—no. Literature can no longer be avant-garde if it has become popular.¹ Once it gains broad appeal and is frequently imitated, it loses its “otherness” and becomes simply a marker of the existing ideology. It is by definition no longer new. But according to more recent critics, the Russian apologist for literary experiment V. O. Ksepma or the Canadian theorist of postmodernism Linda Hutcheon, the answer is—yes. Innovative, ludic art</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Utopia, Imagination, and Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE STRUGATSKY BROTHERS’ THE UGLY SWANS, TENDRIAKOV’S A POTSHOT AT MIRAGES, AND AKSËNOV’S THE ISLAND OF CRIMEA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During a roundtable discussion on fresh departures in literary theory held in 1987, the Soviet critic Mikhail Epstein had the following to say about how utopian thinking can curtail creative imagination: “Imagination is the chief among liberating forces that move humanity forward; but when such archaic instincts as the will to power or [the desire for] universal leveling are attached onto the imagination like cars onto a locomotive, then imagination turns into utopia, sets limits for itself, stopping at some one, unshakable, and absolutely ‘correct’ vision of the future. Utopia is the suicide of the imagination: convening the masses of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Parody of Popular Forms in Iskander’s Rabbits and Boa Constrictors and Voinovich’s Moscow 2042</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout the Soviet period two popular genres, the fable and the science fiction novel, have been used as vehicles for legitimizing communist ideology.¹ Maksim Gorky before the revolution and Demian Bednyi after were among the most prolific of writers of political fables, and I. A. Efremov and the Strugatsky brothers wrote a kind of science fiction in the late 1950s and early 1960s that conveyed a youthful optimism about the communist future.² During the 1960s, of course, both forms changed and became a good deal more ambiguous with relation to the ideology they had earlier supported. Animal figures from fables,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Play with Closure in Petrushevskaia’s “The New Robinsons” and Kabakov’s “The Deserter”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Meta-utopian fiction written since 1987 is, as might be expected, more radically reductive than its forebears, finding naked coercion behind all but the most locally defined ideologies. It exposes a similar matrix of responses as the critical discussion about utopia. On the one hand, it harbors the same fear of the abyss as the only real alternative to stable, if oppressive, order, while, on the other, it is strongly concerned with reopening language to untried possibility, with reexamining deep social scripts, and with probing automatized readerly expectations. Two “best-selling” pieces, Liudmila Petrushevskaia’s short story “The New Robinsons” (“Novye Robinzony: Khronika</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>The Utopian Impulse after 1968: RUSSIAN ΜΕΤΑ-UTOPIAN FICTION IN A EUROPEAN CONTEXT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where does meta-utopian narrative stand in the general crisis of social imagination and the parallel crisis of representational aesthetics? Born in isolation, Russian meta-utopian fiction is certainly not an isolated phenomenon. It parallels the renewed attention to language, semiotic play, and narrative structure that has figured so importantly in the West in opening up new insight into ideological structures. Its challenge to maximalist, bipolar thinking and its argument for the middle ground makes meta-utopian fiction very much of a piece with current social, literary, and philosophical discourse. Indeed, if anything, it forces us to raise the question of social imagination,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztgwq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
