<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1fzhh18</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Library Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Research Methods for Cultural Studies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pickering</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748625772</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748631193</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748631194</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Edinburgh University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b2nv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This new textbook addresses the neglect of practical research methods in cultural studies. It provides readers with clearly written overviews of research methods in cultural studies, along with guidelines on how to put these methods into operation. It advocates a multi-method approach, with students drawing from a pool of techniques and approaches suitable for their own topics of investigation.</p>
         <p>The book covers the following main areas:</p>
         <p>Drawing on experience, and studying how narratives make sense of experience.Investigating production processes in the cultural industries, and the consumption and assimilation of cultural products by audiences and fans.Taking both quantitative and qualitative approaches to the study of cultural life.Analysing visual images and both spoken and written forms of discourse.Exploring cultural memory and historical representation.</p>
         <p>Key Features</p>
         <p>A unique guide to research methods in Cultural StudiesExplores key methods of research, with examples of how to pursue (or not to pursue) a particular method.Expert contributors include Martin Barker, Aeron Davis, David Deacon, Emily Keightley, Steph Lawler, Anneke Meyer, Virginia Nightingale and Sarah Pink.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pickering</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There has long been a reluctance to bring any explicit discussion of methods and methodology into cultural studies. This can be explained in various ways. We can see it first of all as connected with the field’s renegade character, and its conscious dissociation from established academic disciplines. Developing and adhering to a particular set of methods was considered to be characteristic of those disciplines and somehow compromised by an unexamined notion of empirical enquiry. Cultural studies has preferred to borrow techniques and methods from established disciplines without subscribing to any disciplinary credentials itself. Empirical enquiry has been treated with suspicion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Experience and the Social World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pickering</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Experience is central to cultural studies. It is a key category of analysis within the field, and has been drawn on as concrete material for many of the issues which cultural studies has pursued. It has also become a recognised dimension of research practice itself. Its value has nevertheless been contested, both as a form of research data and as an analytical concept. This was particularly the case during the ascendancy of poststructuralism in cultural studies, but more broadly how it should be used as a resource and what place it has as evidence are questions that have generated considerable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Stories and the Social World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lawler</surname>
                           <given-names>Steph</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Barbara Hardy, among others, has noted, narratives are integral to social life (1975). People continually tell stories to themselves and to others, gathering up fragments of the day to make a coherent whole, or fragments of occurrences in a life to make a coherent life story. Even though most people will not write autobiographies, all of us are engaged in the projects of our own autobiography, which we manifest every time we tell others about our lives, attend an interview, or simply engage in processes of thinking about and understanding the world and our place within it. In all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Investigating Cultural Producers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davis</surname>
                           <given-names>Aeron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is in four parts. Each of the first three parts offers a brief overview of the more common research approaches used to investigate cultural production. These are broadly categorised here as political economy, textual analysis and sociological/ethnographic work. The fourth part then concentrates on the third of these and the practical considerations involved. In both parts the discussion and examples draw on my own experiences of researching cultural production in the news industry and within the subcultures of financial and political elite networks. At the time of writing I have interviewed over 250 professionals employed in journalism, public</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Investigating Cultural Consumers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Anneke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consumption in its many forms is not a new phenomenon (Storey 1999), but since the end of the Second World War, consumption in industrialised countries has proliferated to such an extent that the phrase ‘consumer society’ was coined. Arguably,<italic>cultural</italic>consumption has especially increased because technological advances have led to the development and spread of new forms of media and information and communication technologies (ICTs). These have in turn generated new forms of cultural texts and made cultural consumption more accessible. The term ‘cultural consumer’ refers to those who consume cultural texts or engage in cultural practices involving consumption. Key</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Why Counting Counts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deacon</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contemporary field of cultural studies has little interest in, or engagement with, quantitative analysis. If you don’t believe me, here are some numbers.</p>
                     <p>As preparation for this chapter – which explores the reasons for this disengagement and its detrimental implications – I conducted a content analysis of 130 refereed articles published in six recent editions of three major cultural studies journals.¹ In this analysis, I counted all and any references made to either primary quantitative data (that is, author-generated data) or secondary quantitative data (that is, statistics produced by other academic, official or corporate sources).²</p>
                     <p>The finding that 34</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Why Observing Matters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nightingale</surname>
                           <given-names>Virginia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Observation-based research relies on interactions and exchanges between researcher and research participants, and it is this expanded vision of observation – observation that explicitly designs and accounts for the impact of the research process on the fieldwork experience and the data it produces – that the chapter explores. It is based on the premise that communication is a material process in the sense that it is something that can be observed, recorded, documented, analysed and written about. Fieldwork involves finding ways to transform the fleeting character of communication and social relations into durable analysable forms. Other research practices – for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Analysing Visual Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pink</surname>
                           <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I arrived at David and Anne’s house one morning in autumn 2005, to interview them about the community garden project David was involved in. I was ready with the tool kit of a contemporary visual researcher: digital video and stills cameras, audio recorder, and pen and notebook. My research involved photography, audio-recording our interview and collaboratively exploring the garden site with David on video. It also led me to attend closely to the visual elements of the project itself. When I interview people about their experiences, projects and passions, they usually pull out visual images with which to tell me</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Analysing Discourse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barker</surname>
                           <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The seemingly inexorable rise of the concept of ‘discourse’ has made it almost unavoidable for cultural studies researchers, particularly since its invitation to theorise culture as ‘like a language’ coincides with so many impulses within our field. But not without substantial costs. Looking at the cultural studies field from my angle as an audience researcher, some troubling features within discourse work come into view. For all the multiplicity of approaches, and the attendant variations in attached modes of ‘discourse analysis’, there are some powerful unifying features in ‘discourse talk’; and these features presume the<italic>very things</italic>that as an audience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Engaging with Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keightley</surname>
                           <given-names>Emily</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Memory has enjoyed a well charted resurgence in the postwar period in cultural production, social life and academic study (see Huyssen 2000; Misztal 2003; Radstone 2000). The social dislocations that occurred in the aftermath of the world wars, and the radical trauma of the Holocaust, threw into sharp relief issues of remembrance and commemoration (Wolf 2004; Margalit 20002). In more recent years, a growing disillusionment with the rhetoric of progress which has been so central to modernity has required a reconsideration of pasts that had been hurriedly discarded. At this historical juncture memory is becoming an increasingly key feature of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Engaging with History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pickering</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Engaging with history is a popular experience. It is popular in the sense that it is widespread and has huge appeal. It involves a variety of activities that include visiting museums and heritage sites, watching history programmes on television, collecting antiques and compiling a family history. Over the past thirty years, the development of popular interest in the past, in these and many other ways, has grown up alongside the development in academic life of a sceptical questioning of the value of historical enquiry and a drastic suspicion about the very grounds on which history is represented. There is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b2nv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
