<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PSB513.A593Z87 1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Gallant, Mavis, 1922-</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Munro, Alice, 1931-</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Grief in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Figuring Grief</book-title>
         <subtitle>Gallant, Munro, and the Poetics of Elegy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SMYTHE</surname>
               <given-names>KAREN E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>1992</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773509399</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773563612</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Buffalo</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1992</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt818sp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The title, Figuring Grief, refers to the narrative process whereby mourning is depicted. In her textual analysis, Smythe explores various connections between representation and consolation. Drawing on genre and narratological theory, she outlines the development of the "fiction-elegy" as a sub-genre and suggests that the modernist writings of Woolf and Joyce are paradigmatic examples of the form. She then uses these paradigms as suggestive "reading models" for the interpretation of works by Gallant, Munro, and other contemporary fiction-elegists. Figuring Grief offers new readings of specific works and suggests that new ways of reading are both demanded and rewarded by a poetics of elegy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Towards a Theory of Fiction-Elegy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a brief study of melancholia and depression (recently expanded into a book,<italic>Black Sun</italic>) Julia Kristeva posits a general theory of the usefulness of literature, and states that literary representation is a “staging of affects” which “possesses a real and imaginary efficacy that, cathartic more than of the order of elaboration, is a therapeutic method utilized in all societies through the ages.”¹ Though this statement as a generalization about all literature might make the reader sceptical, it may be accurately applied to the specific genre of elegy: elegy<italic>is</italic>a verbal presentation or staging of emotion, wherein the detached</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Gallant’s Sad Stories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though Mavis Gallant’s fiction has received a great deal of critical attention in the last ten or twelve years, much of that criticism has been limited to noting Gallant’s main themes: W.J. Keith states that “the concept of abandonment or betrayal” is central,¹ and Janice Kulyk Keefer and Neil K. Besner focus on the role that memory plays in her characters’ and narrators’ worlds. But few have attempted to relate the form of Gallant’s fictions to their content. A special issue of<italic>Essays on Canadian Writing</italic>— the “Mavis Gallant Issue” — was published recently, and therein several articles explore structural and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Gallant and the Ethics of Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 2 I argued that Gallant figures the elegiac in her fiction in a variety of ways, including the use of plot as trope, experimentation with contrasting points of view, and the subversion of sequential chronology. The work of mourning is demonstrated in Gallant’s stories to be a form of “narrative thinking,” which, according to John Robinson and Linda Hawpe, “consists of creating a fit between a situation and the story schema. Establishing a fit, that is, making a story out of experience, is a heuristic process,” they continue, “one which requires skill, judgment, and experience.”¹ The reader, too,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Munro and Mordern Elegy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In answer to Alan Twigg’s question, “How much do you think your own writing is a compensation for loss of the past?” Munro states: “My writing has become a way of dealing with life, hanging onto it by re[-]creation. That’s important. But it’s also a way of getting on top of experience. We all have life rushing in on us. A writer pretends, by writing about it, to have control. Of course a writer has no more control than anybody else.”¹ Munro’s subject-matter, like the aesthetic her answer implies, is fundamentally elegiac in that an effort to control loss often</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Munrovian Melancholy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have been arguing that Munro’s fiction, with its emphasis on loss and on the importance of story-telling as a method of gaining knowledge of the past, reveals and enacts a poetics of elegy. Munro, like Gallant, insists that the past must be evaluated and re-evaluated and that memory — though not equivalent to truth — is the most important source of knowledge, of a necessarily fictional truth. Gallant’s characters often learn very little of the lessons she urges her readers to learn; we acquire insights about memory, history, truth, and writing by interpreting the ironic narrative stance employed in her fiction.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Forms of Loss:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Fiction-Elegy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this study I have argued that Mavis Gallant and Alice Munro have adapted conventions of elegy within fictional frameworks, a practice refined by modernist fiction-elegists such as Virginia Woolf and James Joyce. A digressive structure, the focus on the self (on the narrator-elegist or character-elegist as survivor), and a tendency towards selfreflexivity are characteristics of both modern and late modern fiction-elegies. But where Woolf and Joyce employ self-reflexivity as a trope of consolation and suggest that the work of art is an immortal and idealized product achieved at the end of the work of mourning, Gallant and Munro use</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt818sp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
