<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Feminist Phenomenology Futures</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FIELDING</surname>
               <given-names>HELEN A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>OLKOWSKI</surname>
               <given-names>DOROTHEA E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253029621</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253030115</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253030110</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005vm7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Distinguished feminist philosophers consider the future of their field and chart its political and ethical course in this forward-looking volume. Engaging with themes such as the historical trajectory of feminist phenomenology, ways of perceiving and making sense of the contemporary world, and the feminist body in health and ethics, these essays affirm the base of the discipline as well as open new theoretical spaces for work that bridges bioethics, social identity, physical ability, and the very nature and boundaries of the female body. Entanglements with thinkers such as Heidegger, Merleau-Ponty, Beauvoir, and Arendt are evident and reveal new directions for productive philosophical work. Grounded in the richness of the feminist philosophical tradition, this work represents a significant opening to the possible futures of feminist phenomenological research.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="400"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A FEMINIST PHENOMENOLOGY MANIFESTO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIELDING</surname>
                           <given-names>HELEN A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this volume we situate the future directions of feminist phenomenology in the here and now. We contend that in this moment feminist phenomenology is well positioned to take a leading role, not simply in terms of consolidating existing feminist methodologies but also in engaging the difficult task of thinking through the actual in the fullness of its relational, agential, ontological, experiential, and fleshly being, thereby opening up future possibilities. We also think there is some urgency to this claim. For many, faith in the rational human subject has been shattered by the events of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLKOWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHEA E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIELDING</surname>
                           <given-names>HELEN A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The future is now.” Google this phrase and you might be surprised to see at least 854 million results, many of which seem to announce advances in technology, although there are some song titles high in the rankings. Yet in scrolling through them, it appears that none of the results define or explain what this phrase means. The philosopher Ludwig Feuerbach did not address the future as now, but he did write about “the philosophy of the future” in a critique of G.W.F. Hegel that proposes to look at being, not as an abstraction, but as sensuous, a being involved</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>USING OUR INTUITION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Creating the Future Phenomenological Plane of Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLKOWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHEA E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is intuition? Both philosophical and psychological understandings of the idea of intuition may have left feminist philosophy with more questions than answers. Is intuition a sixth sense? Is it cognitive or sensory or something else? Michèle Le Doeuff has pointed out that intuition, in classical philosophical language, designates a mode of immediate apprehension, a direct<italic>intellectual grasp</italic>as opposed to mediated knowledge achieved through reasoning, discussion, internal debate, dialectic, experimentation, deduction, language, or proofs. Given this definition, intuition was once thought to be a valid mode of knowledge. It was thought to cooperate with these various methods of inquiry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>JUST THROW LIKE A BLEEDING PHILOSOPHER:</title>
                     <subtitle>Menstrual Pauses and Poses, Betwixt Hypatia and Bhubaneswari, Half Visible, Almost Illegible</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEE</surname>
                           <given-names>KYOO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is this thing, that stuff underneath of which some of us would talk only softly, quietly, killingly?</p>
                     <p>“Speaking of which, do you happen to have a tampon with you?,” whispers a fellow conference-goer, or -comer, to me, gingerly, prompting me to rummage through my 24/7 emergency Ziploc in my daypack, where usually three tampons of three sizes are found lying promiscuously betwixt pens, pencils, erasers, clips, maybe trying to blend in, hidingly, yes, yes, I do, ain’t I a woman ready to go?</p>
                     <p>First, FACT #1: Menstruation as a monthly corporeal event, the cyclical shedding of the uterine lining</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>TRANSFORMATIVE LINES OF FLIGHT:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Deleuze to Masoch</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRIEDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>LYAT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Simone de Beauvoir’s<italic>The Second Sex</italic>poses a challenge: Because “humanity is male, and man defines woman, not in herself, but in relation to himself,” then, we must ask, Can women define themselves, in themselves, without falling into the trap set up by such prior definitions.¹ Can one overcome dyads such as male–female, subject–object, culture–nature in order to demarcate difference in non-negating terms? Can differences be understood without reimposing opposites? It is a simple challenge, and yet complex, as de Beauvoir notes:</p>
                     <p>The categories masculine and feminine appear as symmetrical in a formal way on town hall</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>CRAFTING CONTINGENCY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McCANN</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thirteen years into the twenty-first century, much of the promise of the postmodern era has begun to materialize for the field of architecture. Technology has caught up with imagination, and our tolerance for evanescence, contingency, and multiplicity has found consonances in a world of informatics and bioengineering that transgress old boundaries of form, order, and identity. In the field of architecture, the chaotic character of earlier decades (when we drew sharp angles with dissonant relationships to show that we were no longer seeking a singular truth) is morphing into an appreciation and understanding of deep pattern. In contrast to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>OPEN FUTURE, REGAINING POSSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIELDING</surname>
                           <given-names>HELEN A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Openness to the world and to the future belongs to personal time intertwined with impersonal or natural time, which is at the heart of phenomenology. Humans, as phenomenal subjects, make sense of the world they encounter, and in so doing they have the potential to enact change. However, as embodied, they also have the ability to be shaped by it—and in this age the world that shapes humans is largely indifferent to this phenomenal potential. They gear into a world that too often does not connect personal and impersonal time with the processes or systems in which they are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>OF WOMEN AND SLAVES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERGOFFEN</surname>
                           <given-names>DEBRA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the sentence “On ne nait pas femme: on le devient,” translated in 1952 by H.M. Parshley as “One is not born but becomes a woman,” and by Constance Borde and Sheila Malovany-Chevallier in 2010 as “One is not born but becomes woman,” is considered the most famous feminist legacy of Simone de Beauvoir’s<italic>The Second Sex</italic>, the category of the Other may stand as its most enduring bequest to the philosophy of oppression. Its value, however, depends on attending to its nuances, for if we fail to see that Beauvoir provides different accounts of the ways that a person</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>UNHAPPY SPEECH AND HEARING WELL:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contributions of Feminist Speech Act Theory to Feminist Phenomenology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STAWARSKA</surname>
                           <given-names>BEATA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is an attempt to grapple with an experience I had upon entering the academic profession about a decade ago and teaching a large undergraduate lecture class at a state university for the first time in my career. I often felt that my speech during my lectures sounded hollow, that it lacked resonance with my audience (composed in part of students with a strong sense of white male entitlement, compounded with commitment to stereotypical gender norms, ageism, and expectations of a familiar “native” accent), despite the fact that I enunciated well and occupied an official position of authority in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>ADVENTURES IN THE HYPERDIALECTIC</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMMS</surname>
                           <given-names>EVA-MARIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an early feminist phenomenological paper, Jeffner Allen interpreted Maurice Merleau-Ponty’s “hyperdialectic” or “good dialectic” through the I–other, men–women opposition and criticized Merleau-Ponty for his androcentric, sexist assumptions of a gender-neutral body as the foundation for his ontology.¹ Since then phenomenological feminists have stayed away from Merleau-Ponty’s concept of the hyperdialectic, even though Allen, at the end of her paper, points out possibilities for a new beginning for the “good dialectic” in feminist thinking.</p>
                     <p>Despite a consistent critique of Merleau-Ponty’s androcentrism, feminist thinkers have found his philosophy to be productive because it provides conceptual access to the field</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>THE MURMURATION OF BIRDS:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Anishinaabe Ontology of Mnidoo-Worlding</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MANNING</surname>
                           <given-names>DOLLEEN TISAWII’ASHII</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter sketches out precursory notes on the entangled ontology of the North American Algonquian language family, particularly regarding<italic>mnidoo</italic>(spirit/mystery, “potency, potential”),¹ animacy, and other-than-human persons.² Since this concept mnidoo is difficult to translate linguistically with all of its intricacies intact, I conduct here a phenomenological—that is, an experientially embodied—translation, which, in my view, is more in keeping with everyday lived-indigeneities.³ We begin with a schematic drawing and a perplexing annotation on presence and consciousness to be investigated from a number of approaches throughout. These range from the navigational acuity of flocks of birds, to the poetics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>TRANS-SUBJECTIVITY/TRANS-OBJECTIVITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAIGLE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My work, whether it is grounded in Nietzsche, Sartre, Beauvoir, or others, is informed by a desire to understand the human being’s presence in the world and seek to establish grounds for an ethics of flourishing. However, an ethical theory can be successful only if it is grounded in an adequate theory of subjectivity. Like many other feminist critics, I fail to be convinced by traditional rationalistic philosophy that paints a portrait of the relation between individual and world as straightforward and easily conceived. Instead I draw on the work of existentialists and phenomenologists, as well as structuralists and post-structuralists,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>THE “NORMAL ABNORMALITIES” OF DISABILITY AND AGING:</title>
                     <subtitle>Merleau-Ponty and Beauvoir</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weiss</surname>
                           <given-names>Gail</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two of the most slippery yet well-established divisions that have traditionally distinguished human beings from one another are age and disability, respectively. With respect to the former, even a cursory examination of different cultures and different historical time periods reveals how widely societies vary in their identifications of youth, middle age, and old age, much less in the roles and responsibilities that are deemed appropriate for each period of life. This cultural and historical variability is clearly due to many complex factors, chief among them being the average life expectancy for a particular group of people and the specific habitus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>THE TRANSHUMAN PARADIGM AND THE MEANING OF LIFE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHÜES</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reproductive and transplantation medicine, genetics and molecular biology provide the means for intervening in the body and for interchanging living tissues, organs, or other body materials between human beings. Examples include organ or stem cell transplantations, the genetic determination of embryos in reproductive genetics, or receptor-specific psychopharmaceuticals. However, biotechnological interventions not only aim at the materiality and functionality of the human body, but they also transform the familial and social relations among humans. This means that biotechnologies can be profound interventions into human experiences and lives. The paradigmatic profoundness of these technologies of the later twentieth and early twenty-first centuries</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>THE SECOND-PERSON PERSPECTIVE IN NARRATIVE PHENOMENOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALSEMA</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNEMIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SLATMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is it that happens in interviews that aim at exploring people’s lived experiences? In a recently conducted empirical study, we interviewed women just after they were surgically treated for breast cancer.¹ In these interviews we focused on how they gave meaning to bodily changes and to their scars, thus employing a phenomenological approach. Phenomenology is mostly seen as an investigation of the first-person perspective, because it seeks to make explicit the process of world-disclosure.² Because of its sensitivity to the way patients experience their illnesses, phenomenology has been developed as a research method in its own right that is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>HANNAH ARENDT AND PREGNANCY IN THE PUBLIC SPHERE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FULFER</surname>
                           <given-names>KATY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although reproduction was once thought to be a paradigmatic private activity, it seems common now to accept that it is part of the public realm. Pregnancy often takes place in public institutions of hospitals or other medical facilities. Public policy may regulate reproduction and infertility services in places where health care is provided by the state, or in places that seek through legislation to restrict or protect women’s access to reproductive and sexual health services. Further, as Amy Mullin has emphasized, pregnant people not only make physical adjustments to their changing bodies, but they also must make accommodations within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>IS DIRECT PERCEPTION ARROGANT PERCEPTION?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Critical, Playful Intercorporeity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>APRIL</surname>
                           <given-names>FLAKNE N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Feminist phenomenology promises numerous futures. In this essay, I will consider what emerging interactionist approaches to embodied social cognition might offer to feminist phenomenologists. For the sake of convenience, I will refer to a group of related, phenomenologically inspired approaches to embodied social cognition as “direct perception” (DP).¹ I use this overarching term not to ignore significant differences between the various strands, but to focus on their central, shared claim—namely, that our perception is “smart” enough to perceive “directly” that there are other minds as well as a great deal of what supposedly goes on “in” those other minds.²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>LEADERSHIP IN THE WORLD THROUGH AN ARENDTIAN LENS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GARDINER</surname>
                           <given-names>RITA A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As more women move into leadership roles within the public sphere, there is a need for feminist phenomenologists to investigate how current leadership research fails to account sufficiently for gender and for the myriad ways we live and lead in the world. Instead, many leadership scholars focus on developing abstract models. One such model I explore here is that of authentic leadership. Specifically, in placing authentic leadership scholars in conversation with Hannah Arendt, I show how her more expansive view of leadership offers insight into the complexities regarding what it might mean to lead authentically. My main contention is that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>IDENTITY-IN-DIFFERENCE TO AVOID INDIFFERENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEE</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILY S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sexual and racial differences matter. Indeed, rejecting facile understandings of sameness at the heart of universalism, philosophers of race speculate that racial differences are ontologically relevant. At the same time, absolute difference can slip into indifference. For example, Glen Loury points to disparate statistics among racial groups that occasion no alarm from the majority populations.¹ As Maria Lugones describes such indifference, “The more independent I am, the more independent I am left to be. Their world and their integrity do not require me at all.”² My concern is that although we have yet to fully understand what difference means and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>WHAT IS FEMINIST PHENOMENOLOGY?</title>
                     <subtitle>Looking Backward and Into the Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STOLLER</surname>
                           <given-names>SILVIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>328</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question “What is feminist phenomenology?” is not as easily answered as it might first seem. To some extent, this has to do with the term itself, since in the academic field two different terms are regularly used to designate more or less the same area: “feminist phenomenology” and “phenomenological feminism.” Strictly speaking, feminist phenomenology is a feminist-oriented phenomenology, whereas phenomenological feminism can be characterized as a phenomenologically oriented feminism. In her early essay “Sexual Ideology and Phenomenological Description,” Judith Butler speaks of “phenomenological feminism,” whereas in her encyclopedia article Dorothea Olkowski speaks of “phenomenologically-oriented feminists” and of “feminist phenomenologists”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005vm7.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
