<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Dialogical Spirit</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christian Reason and Theological Method in the Third Millennium</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Yong</surname>
               <given-names>Amos</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175200</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227904350</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Amos Yong</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf6g6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Contemporary proposals for Christian theology from post-liberalism to Radical Orthodoxy and beyond have espoused their own methodological paradigms. Those who have ventured into this domain of theological method, however, have usually had to stake their claims vis-à-vis trends in what may be called the contemporary "post-al" age, whether of the post-modern, post-Christendom, post-Enlightenment, post-Western, or post-colonial varieties. This volume is unique among offerings in this arena in suggesting a way forward that engages on each of these fronts, and does so from a particularistic Christian perspective without giving up on Christian theology's traditional claims to universality. This is accomplished through the articulation of a distinctive dialogical methodology informed by both Pentecostalism and Evangelicalism, one rooted in the Christian salvation-history narrative of Incarnation and Pentecost that is yet open to the world in its many and various cultural, ethnic, religious, and disciplinary discourses. Amos Yong here engages with twelve different interlocutors representing different ecumenical, religious, and disciplinary perspectives. 'The Dialogical Spirit' thus not only proffers a model for Christian theological method suitable for the twenty-first century global context but also exemplifies this methodological approach through its interactions across the contemporary scholarly, inter-religious, and theological landscape.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Soon after completing my PhD thesis I wrote a book on theological method,<italic>Spirit-Word-Community: Theological Hermeneutics in Trinitarian Perspective</italic>.¹ I was motivated in this direction in part because the theological academy was caught up, around the turn of the millennium, on questions related to method,² and in part because my own graduate training under a philosophical theologian alerted me to the importance of providing methodological argumentation in a time when theological claims were no longer being received merely because they were asserted. Both trends were reactions to the post-Enlightenment world that had been emerging with increasing clarity across the last</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Demise of Foundationalism and the Retention of Truth:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Evangelicals Can Learn from C. S. Peirce</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent essay entitled “ The Postpositivist Choice: Tracy or Lindbeck?,” Richard Lints suggests that there are basically two methodological options available to contemporary theology: either the postmodern approach that highlights the public or universal character of theological rationality or the postliberal emphasis on intertextuality, narrative, and the cultural-linguistic framework of all knowledge.¹ Although Lints writes from within the evangelical tradition, a movement well known for taking a stand for the truth, he refrains from offering an answer to the question posed in the title, preferring instead to provide a descriptive survey of the two options.² As part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Pragmatist and Pragmaticist Trajectories for a Postmodern Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pragmatism, even if limited to its specifically North American and philosophical trajectories, is quite diverse.¹ Not only are pragmatist philosophers working in various areas—e.g., philosophy of science, linguistics, logic, social theory—but they are also debating issues of validity and legitimacy regarding developments within the tradition itself. It is inevitable that the classical pragmatism of Peirce, Royce, and James would have inspired a wide spectrum of philosophical projects, and that these would have been extended by the legacy of “middle pragmatists” such as Dewey, G. H. Mead, C. I. Lewis, and the Chicago School.² Even so, pragmatism was eclipsed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>In Search of Foundations:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Oeuvre of Donald L. Gelpi, S.J., and Its Significance for Pentecostal Theology and Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past three and a half decades, Donald L. Gelpi, S.J., was one of the few individuals working at the intersections of theology and philosophy, and who had been, at the same time, involved with the charismatic movement (the Catholic Charismatic Renewal, in his case). Among other results has been the emergence of a systematic philosophical theology and spirituality that is imbued with intuitions derived from the charismatic experience, which continue to be appreciated as such by charismatic scholars working in these areas. In the past few years, Gelpi’s overall project, begun in earnest with the trilogy of<italic>Charism</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The “Baptist Vision” of James Wm. McClendon Jr.:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Wesleyan-Pentecostal Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 30 October 2000, shortly after completing the final pages of his<italic>Systematic Theology</italic>, James William McClendon Jr., Distinguished Scholar in Residence at Fuller Theological Seminary, returned home to be with the Lord.¹ The following review, reflection, and response to McClendon’s “baptist vision” is written in recognition of its importance for contemporary Christian theology. At the same time, insofar as it seeks to participate in, complement, and extend the theological conversation to which McClendon had devoted his life’s work, it should also be considered as a tribute to his legacy. Part one of this chapter will summarize some of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Whither Evangelical Theology?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Work of Veli-Matti Kärkkäinen as a Case Study of Contemporary Trajectories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was the appearance of Veli-Matti Kärkkäinen’s most recent book [as of the time of writing],<italic>One with God: Salvation as Deification and Justification</italic>, that occasioned the invitation to review his larger corpus in the pages of this journal.¹ My long-standing appreciation for Kärkkäinen’s theological work had previously been registered in my collecting, editing, and publishing a set of his essays in book form a few years ago.² In the editor’s introduction to that book, I noted that Kärkkäinen was fast becoming one of the more important theologians to be reckoned with in our time. He had not only already</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Radically Orthodox, Reformed, and Pentecostal:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rethinking the Intersection of Post/Modernity and the Religions in Conversation with James K. A. Smith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As “the most heavyweight theological movement twentieth-century Christianity in England has produced” (<italic>Theology</italic>), Radical Orthodoxy has gained increasing attention and momentum in the North American theological academy. Its most recent spokesperson, James K. A. Smith, has attempted to extend the Radical Orthodoxy vision in dialogue with the Dutch Reformed tradition.¹ Clearly, the central features of “Reformed” Radical Orthodoxy empower a kind of prophetic engagement with the cultural, political, economic, and ideological domains of modern Western society. At another level, however, the globalizing features of our late modern world context mean that the dominant pagan deities are not just secularism, nihilism,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>From Quantum Mechanics to the Eucharistic Meal:</title>
                     <subtitle>John Polkinghorne’s “Bottom-up” Vision of Science and Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rev Dr. John Polkinghorne, KBE, FRS needs no extended introduction to Metanexus<italic>Online</italic>readers.¹ In brief, he has had two successive careers, first as an elementary particle physicist at Edinburgh and then Cambridge (1956–1979), and then as an Anglican priest (1981–present), during which he has served in a variety of ecclesial positions (as curate, vicar, and chaplain) as well as being president of Queen’s College (1989–1996). Since entering the priesthood, Polkinghorne has worked tirelessly at the frontiers of the science and theology conversation, having authored, coauthored, or edited more than twenty-five books on various related topics. His</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Mind and Life, Religion and Science:</title>
                     <subtitle>His Holiness the Dalai Lama and the Buddhist-Christian-Science Trilogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I explore what happens to the Buddhist-Christian dialogue when another party is introduced into the conversation, in this case, the sciences. My question concerns how the interface between religion and science is related to the Buddhist-Christian encounter and vice versa. I take up this question in four steps, correlating with the four parts of this chapter. First, I sketch a brief overview of the Buddhist-science encounter, and then turn my attention more specifically to the recent exchanges in the Mind and Life Dialogues involving Western scientists and philosophers and Tibetan Buddhist practitioners, including His Holiness the Dalai</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Tibetan Buddhism Going Global?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study of a Contemporary Buddhist Encounter with Science</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a growing awareness of Tibetan Buddhism as one viable representative of the Buddhist tradition in global context.¹ In this chapter, I want to add to the case for viewing Tibetan Buddhism as a global Buddhist tradition by focusing on its contemporary encounter with science. More specifically, I suggest that the recent Tibetan Buddhist dialogue with the sciences provides one avenue to understand the dynamic character of this tradition as an emerging global presence.</p>
                     <p>Elsewhere, I have argued a similar thesis by analyzing the dialogues between His Holiness the Dalai Lama and Western scientists.² Here I want to focus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>The True Believers?</title>
                     <subtitle>Francis X. Clooney and “Dual Religious Belonging” in the Comparative Theological Enterprise</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last twenty-plus years, Francis X. Clooney, SJ, has emerged as perhaps one of the most important theologians in our contemporary global Christian context through his work on reading Hindu and Christian texts side by side. Yet despite his remarkable output, Clooney’s work has received little attention from evangelical thinkers or theologians. I would urge, however, that evangelicals neglect interacting with Clooney’s work to their loss; rather, Clooney’s project is important precisely because of his concerns about maintaining confessional integrity as a Christian theologian (in his case as a lifelong Roman Catholic priest) while crossing over into and taking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Observation-Participation-Subjunctivation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Methodological Play and Meaning-Making in the Study of Religion and Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discussion about the insider-outsider “problem” continues to unfold in the academic study of religion.² This chapter sketches a threefold taxonomy of methodological options—methodological atheism or naturalism, methodological agnosticism, and methodological theism—prevalent in this field, and then explores whether anthropologist André Droogers’s methodological ludism provides for a posture that allows for simultaneous embrace of all three types, as he suggests it might. The concluding section will reflect on these methodological alternatives from a theological perspective.</p>
                     <p>In anticipation of the specifically theological discussion at the end of this chapter, some authorial self-disclosure is warranted. Although I have been trained in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Toward a Relational Apologetics in Global Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Review Essay of Benno van den Toren’s Christian Apologetics as Cross-Cultural Dialogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me say up front that van den Toren’s book takes the discussion of apologetics to a whole new level.¹ In the distant background is a Kampen Theological University (Dutch-language) PhD thesis on Barth and apologetics,² from which the central ideas have been leavened by eight years of living and teaching in the Central African Republic. The work of at least four or five other books later, many of these interfacing with the theme of apologetics as well as with a broad spectrum of approaches to apologetics, informs the present contribution by this current dean of the faculty at Wycliffe</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Christian Theological Method: Toward a Pneumatological Imagination for the Third Millennium</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is now time to quickly review where we have come from in order to situate where we have arrived and anticipate next steps. The preceding has attempted to do theology dialogically, with twelve conversation partners, in order to exemplify an effective model of Christian theological inquiry at the beginning of the third millennium. I have also shown that such a dialogical approach is theologically funded by a pneumatological imagination as manifest particularly in the Acts narrative. Further, such a pneumatologically inspired dialogical method may be uniquely suited to enable navigation of our postfoundationalist, post-Christendom, postsecular, postmodern, and pluralistic landscape.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6g6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
