<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Education</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Atheism for Beginners</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Coursebook for Schools and Colleges</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Palmer</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718892913</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718840785</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael Palmer</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cg4jp3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The word ‘atheism’ is derived from the Greek: a meaning ‘not’ is conjoined with theos meaning ‘god’. So atheism may be defined as follows: it is the belief that there is no God. Unfortunately definition of terms is rarely this straightforward. In this educational book, Michael Palmer undertakes to analyse, develop and discuss the complex and too often reduced notion of atheism. In spite of the consciously atheist point of view adopted by the author, the volume remains critical and objective, making religious, philosophical and political concepts around atheism understandable. Even though the book clearly addresses a young audience, any kind of reader will find food for thought in this vivid and detailed work.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Atheist’s Creed</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Palmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The distinguished author Philip Pullman, writing in<italic>The Independent Education Supplement</italic>in March 2006, complained about the lack of atheistic education in schools, and more particularly about how this general deficiency had allowed young people to be ‘taken in by religious people claiming that science is a faith position no different in kind from Christianity. Science is not a matter of faith, and too many people are being allowed to get away with claiming that it is, and that my “belief” in evolution is a thing of the same kind as their “belief” in miracles. What we need in schools,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Meaning of Atheism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word ‘atheism’ is derived from the Greek:<italic>a</italic>meaning ‘not’ is conjoined with<italic>theos</italic>meaning ‘god’. So we may define atheism as follows: it is the belief<italic>that there is no God</italic>. Unfortunately definition of terms is rarely this straightforward and here too we find different shades of meaning. For example, there is:</p>
                     <p>Constructive atheism</p>
                     <p>Epistemological atheism</p>
                     <p>Practical atheism</p>
                     <p>Nihilistic atheism</p>
                     <p>Axiological Atheism</p>
                     <p>Reductionary Atheism</p>
                     <p>and many others besides….</p>
                     <p>We shall encounter some of these forms of atheism as we proceed through this book. I wish, however, to keep matters simple. So let us divide atheism into two types:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Creation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth. The earth was without form and void, and darkness was upon the face of the deep; and the Spirit of God was moving over the face of the waters.¹</p>
                     <p>So begins the Old Testament story of creation set out in the opening chapter of the Book of Genesis – literally, the book of ‘origin’, ‘generation’ and ‘birth’. As the history unfolds, we are told that within six miraculous days and by the power of divine speech alone (‘And God said…’²) our world appears out of nothing. Within this short span</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>The Design of the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1925, in Dayton, Tennessee, John Scopes, a high school biology teacher in Clark County, was brought to trial for violating the Butler Act, which prohibited the teaching of evolution. The statute made it unlawful ‘to teach any theory that denies the story of divine creation as taught by the Bible and to teach instead that man was descended from a lower order of animals.’ The trial was a national sensation, not least because the special prosecutor was William Jennings Bryan – the three-time Democratic presidential candidate and a former Secretary of State – and the defence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>The Argument from Evil</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the history of atheism one argument against God stands head and shoulders above all others. This is the so-called ‘argument from evil’ – the term ‘evil’ being used here as shorthand for the existence of pain and suffering. We briefly referred to this argument in Chapter One: the indisputable fact that an innocent child dies of cancer is, so the atheist argues, incompatible with any notion of God as an omnipotent and benevolent being.¹ Any counter theistic attempt to resolve this alleged incompatibility is, to borrow a term from the German philosopher, Gottfried Leibniz (1648-1716), technically known as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>The Moral Argument</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between the 6<sup>th</sup>and 10<sup>th</sup>of August 2011, several London boroughs and districts of cities and towns across England witnessed unprecedented levels of rioting, looting and arson, the most serious civil unrest for a generation. Prompted by the police shooting of a 29-year-old man, Mark Duggan – a suspected member of a local criminal gang – the rioting spread to Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol and Liverpool. Five people were killed, and by 15 August over 3000 people had been arrested, with over 1000 charged. Many reasons were given for these events. Some blamed decades of politically-correct policing, some blamed the government’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Miracles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If asked to name the two favourite saints of Catholic Italy, one’s first candidate would be predictable enough. It is Giovanni Francesco di Bernardone (c. 1181-1226), otherwise known as St Francis of Assisi, founder of the Franciscan order and one of the most venerated of all religious figures, probably second only to Jesus himself within the Christian tradition. The double-tiered Basilica of Assisi, built over the crypt housing the saint’s body, was completed just twenty-seven years after St Francis’ death. Designed by one of his disciples, Brother Elia Bombardone, it is one of the great buildings of the world, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>The Impulse to Believe.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most famous conversion in the history of Christianity is that of St Paul on the road to Damascus. Previously a well-known persecutor of early Christians and witness to the stoning of Stephen in Jerusalem, Paul himself briefly describes what happened in his letters; but the most detailed account is given in the Book of Acts 9: 3-9.</p>
                     <p>And as he journeyed, it came to pass that he drew nigh unto Damascus: and suddenly there shone round about him a light out of heaven: and he fell upon the earth, and heard a voice saying unto him, Saul, Saul, why</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Disproving God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have so far encountered various theistic explanations of why our world is as it is: why it exists in the first place (Chapter Two); why it has its particular organized form (Chapter Three); why suffering exists (Chapter Four); why moral laws exist (Chapter Five); why there can be sudden and miraculous disruptions of natural law (Chapter Six); and why certain people appear to be so different from the rest of us in having some experience of another dimension entirely (Chapter Seven). And against each of these arguments has been levelled serious objections. So – to rehearse some of them</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix</title>
                     <subtitle>Select Biographies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4jp3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
