<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">hamm17058</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B2430.L484 H35 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lévinas, Emmanuel</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Derrida, Jacques</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Broken Tablets</book-title>
         <subtitle>Levinas, Derrida, and the Literary Afterlife of Religion</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HAMMERSCHLAG</surname>
               <given-names>SARAH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231542135</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231542135</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/hamm17058"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Over a span of thirty years, twentieth-century French philosophers Emmanuel Levinas and Jacques Derrida held a conversation across texts. Sharing a Jewish heritage and a background in phenomenology, both came to situate their work at the margins of philosophy, articulating this placement through religion and literature. Chronicling the interactions between these thinkers, Sarah Hammerschlag argues that the stakes in their respective positions were more than philosophical. They were also political. Levinas's investments were born out in his writings on Judaism and ultimately in an evolving conviction that the young state of Israel held the best possibility for achieving such an ideal. For Derrida, the Jewish question was literary. The stakes of Jewish survival could only be approached through reflections on modern literature's religious legacy, a line of thinking that provided him the means to reconceive democracy. Hammerschlag's reexamination of Derrida and Levinas's textual exchange not only produces a new account of this friendship but also has significant ramifications for debates within Continental philosophy, the study of religion, and political theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“WHAT MUST A JEWISH THINKER BE?”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her 1994 biography of Emmanuel Levinas, Marie-Anne Lescourret described the scene of the Colloque des intellectuels juifs de langue française, the nearly annual meetings of which Levinas was one of the founding members and arguably its animating spirit. She reproduced the terms of its debates and articulated the aims of its participants: “to use their experience of Judaism, to draw from the Jewish tradition a wisdom, and comprehension of the human predicament.” She listed the eminent figures who participated, including Edmond Fleg, Jean Wahl, Vladimir Jankélévitch, and Raymond Aron, and then noted in an aside, “that among attending French</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>LEVINAS, LITERATURE, AND THE RUIN OF THE WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1975, eleven years after Derrida published “Violence and Metaphysics,” Levinas declared poststructuralism the “ruin of the world.” This new “philosophical literature,” Levinas wrote “prefers to play with verbal signs rather than to take seriously the system registered in their said” (<italic>EN</italic>76, 61). However, along with communicating a disgruntled impression that disorder had become the name of the game in politics as well as philosophy, Levinas saw an opportunity in this disorder for a truth perhaps older than the world. “In this rupture, and in this awakening, and in this expiation, and in this exaltation, the divine comedy of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>BETWEEN THE JEW AND WRITING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>However we read the relationship between Derrida and Levinas, the lasting impact of Derrida’s first encounter with Levinas’s work is hard to dispute. Even in his final years, Derrida treated it as one of his life’s decisive turning points. In a letter written to Paul Ricoeur in January of 1996, less than two weeks after Emmanuel Levinas’s death, Derrida recalled its importance by reminding Ricoeur that it was he who first introduced Derrida to the thought of the Lithuanian phenomenologist.¹ It was 1961 or 1962, Derrida recalled, and they were walking in Ricoeur’s garden.<italic>Totality and Infinity</italic>had just been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>TO LOSE ONE’S HEAD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literature and the Democracy to Come</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1968 Jacques Derrida accepted an invitation from Johns Hopkins University to teach a seminar on the topic “Literature and Truth.” The project of the seminar was to consider how literature has been conceived, constructed, and maintained from Plato on as imitation and thus construed as secondary in order to protect the status of philosophy and, more broadly, science as the province of truth. Derrida developed the argument to show that the representative arts had been subsequently burdened with the task of effacing their position as copy by cultivating the value of originality, thus reproducing the very logic that established</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>LITERATURE AND THE POLITICAL-THEOLOGICAL REMAINS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Claude Lefort’s essay “Permanence of the Theologico-Political?” in answering the question as to why political philosophers in the modern era make recourse to theological language, suggests that democracy makes possible the identifiable sphere of the political as such through the very appearance of an empty place of sovereignty. As Lefort puts it, “The formula ‘power belongs to no one’ can also be translated into the formula ‘power belongs to none of us.’”¹ This itself generates the need for a symbolic register, a vacuum into which the religious enters, not necessarily as the guarantor of power itself but as a marker</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>“There Is Not a Pin to Choose Between Us”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ten pages into<italic>Gift of Death</italic>there is an intriguing note to Derrida’s 1991 seminar on the secret: “Literature concerning the secret is almost always organized around scenes and intrigues that deal with death,” it begins. This is a theme, he adds, that he had attempted to demonstrate in the seminar, “referring most often to ‘American’ examples.”¹ His list includes Poe’s “The Purloined Letter,” Melville’s “Bartleby the Scrivener,” and Henry James’s<italic>The Aspern Papers</italic>and “The Figure in the Carpet.” There are numerous traces of Derrida’s readings of the first two stories in his published works, but, as far as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">hamm17058.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
