<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kft8r3</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN212.P67 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Postclassical Narratology</book-title>
         <subtitle>Approaches and Analyses</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ALBER</surname>
               <given-names>JAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FLUDERNIK</surname>
               <given-names>MONIKA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780814211427</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780814270981</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>COLUMBUS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Ohio State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqw6k"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this volume, an international group of contributors presents new perspectives on narrative. Using David Herman's 1999 definition of "postclassical narratology" from Narratologies: New Perspectives on Narrative Analysis (OSUP) as their launching point, these eleven essayists explore the various ways in which new approaches overlap and interrelate to form new ways of understanding narrative texts.</p>
         <p>Postclassical narratology has reached a new phase of consolidation but also continued diversification. This collection therefore discriminates between what one could call a critical but frame-abiding and a more radical frame-transcending or frame-shattering handling of the structuralist paradigm. Postclassical Narratology: Approaches and Analyses discusses a large variety of different aspects of narrative, such as extensions of classical narratology, new generic applications (autobiography, oral narratives, poetry, painting, and film), the history of narratology, the issue of fictionality, the role of cognition, and questions of authorship and authority, as well as thematic matters related to ethics, gender, and queering. Additionally, it uses a wide spectrum of critical approaches, including feminism, psychoanalysis, media studies, the rhetorical theory of narrative, unnatural narratology, and cognitive studies. In this manner the essays manage to produce new insights into many key issues in narratology.</p>
         <p>The contributors also demonstrate that narratologists nowadays see the object of their research as more variegated than was the case twenty years ago: they resort to a number of different methods in combination when approaching a problem, and they tend to ground their analyses in a rich contextual framework.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALBER</surname>
                           <given-names>JAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLUDERNIK</surname>
                           <given-names>MONIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this collection of recent narratological work,<italic>Postclassical Narratology: Approaches and Analyses</italic>, openly alludes to David Herman’s seminal bimillennial volume<italic>Narratologies: New Perspectives on Narrative Analysis</italic>(1999b), in which he introduced the term postclassical narratology¹ and defined it as follows:</p>
                     <p>Postclassical narratology (which should not be conflated with poststructuralist theories of narrative) contains classical narratology as one of its “moments” but is marked by a profusion of new methodologies and research hypotheses: the result is a host of new perspectives on the forms and functions of narrative itself. Further, in its postclassical phase, research on narrative does not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Person, Level, Voice:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Rhetorical Reconsideration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WALSH</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My purpose in this essay is to critique the concept of narrative voice from the vantage point of a rhetorical model of fictive representation. In its core sense, narrative voice is concerned with the narrating instance, the various manifestations of which are usually categorized in terms of person and level. These distinctions provide for a typology of narrating instances which is conventionally understood within a communicative model of narration—a model in which the narrating instance is situated within the structure of narrative representation, as a literal communicative act (that is, as a discursive event that forms part of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Mise en cadre—A Neglected Counterpart to Mise en abyme:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Frame-Theoretical and Intermedial Complement to Classical Narratology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WOLF</surname>
                           <given-names>WERNER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part of the present “state of the art” of contemporary narratology seems to be a paradox, for rather than presenting a static profile, this “state” of the art is characterized by a highly dynamic situation. Indeed, narratology currently appears to be undergoing a major paradigm shift: most narratologists have recently announced the demise of classical, structuralist narratology and proclaimed the emergence of a “post-classical” era.¹ The manifold alleged or genuinely new developments in this post-classical narratology fall into three categories. There is firstly, as the most radical and also most questionable development, the deconstruction of narratology as a logocentric enterprise,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Large Intermental Units in Middlemarch</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PALMER</surname>
                           <given-names>ALAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Intermental thought</italic>is joint, group, shared or collective thought, as opposed to intramental, or individual or private thought. It is also known as<italic>socially distributed, situated,</italic>or<italic>extended cognition</italic>, and also as<italic>intersubjectivity</italic>. Intermental thought is a crucially important component of fictional narrative because much of the mental functioning that occurs in novels is done by large organizations, small groups, work colleagues, friends, families, couples and other intermental units. It could plausibly be argued that a large amount of the subject matter of novels is the formation, development and breakdown of these intermental systems.¹ However, this aspect of narrative has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Mediacy, Mediation, and Focalization:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Squaring of Terminological Circles</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLUDERNIK</surname>
                           <given-names>MONIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The issue to be discussed in this essay concerns narratological terminology, but involves different conceptualizations of theoretical design as well. The essay will be concerned with the relationship between Stanzel’s fundamental defining feature of narrative, its<italic>mediacy</italic>, on the one hand, and the discussions of narrative<italic>mediation</italic>or<italic>transmission</italic>(Chatman) on the other. While Stanzel’s<italic>mediacy</italic>focuses on the mediateness of narrative, on the fact that the story (<italic>histoire</italic>) is mediated through the narrative report (<italic>Erzählerbericht</italic>) of a narrator figure, Chatman’s<italic>transmission</italic>and what has recently come to be called<italic>mediation</italic>concern the process of (re) medialization of one<italic>histoire</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Directions in Cognitive Narratology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Triangulating Stories, Media, and the Mind</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing in 1991, on the brink of what Alan Richardson and Francis Steen (2002) subsequently termed “the cognitive revolution” in literary research, Mark Turner presciently argued in his book<italic>Reading Minds</italic>that English studies needs to set itself new goals in the age of cognitive science. Specifically, Turner suggested that “[o]ur profession touches home base when it contributes to the systematic inquiry into [. . . ] linguistic and literary acts as acts of the human mind” (18). To quote Turner more fully:</p>
                     <p>I propose that what the profession lacks is a concept of language and literature as acts of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Hypothetical Intentionalism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cinematic Narration Reconsidered</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALBER</surname>
                           <given-names>JAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cinematic narration figures prominently in the work of several narratologists. Basically, three schools of thought exist. The first, represented by David Bordwell, argues that film has narration but no narrator (1985: 61). According to Bordwell, cinematic narration is created by the<italic>viewer</italic>, who uses cognitive schemata to transform the film’s visual images and sounds into a series of perceptible configurations, which he or she then interprets as a story.¹ In contrast to Bordwell’s approach, the second school, represented by Seymour Chatman, argues that films are narrated by a<italic>cinematic narrator</italic>. Chatman defines this narrator in terms of “the organizational and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Sapphic Dialogics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Historical Narratology and the Sexuality of Form</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANSER</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary critics have long acknowledged that form is (a kind of) content and, as such, socially meaningful. Even scholars whose focus is hermeneutic rather than poetic cannot wholly escape attending to the formal elements that shape—and arguably<italic>are</italic>—the text. It would seem, then, that narratologists and interpreters of narrative would acknowledge considerable common ground. Yet the relationship between narratology and studies of the novel—to take one example—still remains something of a standoff, and nowhere more vividly than on the turf of history. As Monika Fludernik observes, narratologists have demonstrated “comparatively little interest on a theoretical level</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Narrators, Narratees, and Mimetic Desire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARCUS</surname>
                           <given-names>AMIT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Girard’s thesis of mimetic desire (also called “triangular” or “metaphysical” desire)¹ has aroused much theoretical interest among literary scholars, who have expanded and expounded his theory, while at the same time criticizing its universal pretensions and its blurring of differences between different types of desire (e.g., male vs. female, heterosexual vs. homosexual).² Literary interpretations that apply Girard’s ideas from his work<italic>Deceit, Desire, and the Novel</italic>(1965) to fictional narratives focus on the dynamics of mimetic desire and rivalry between two (or more) characters on the story level: the desiring subject, the mediator (or rival), and the desired object.</p>
                     <p>In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Narratology and the Social Sciences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MILDORF</surname>
                           <given-names>JARMILA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social science disciplines such as sociology, psychology, anthropology, education, and so on have long had an interest in narrative as a human cognitive and discursive device for sense-making and for ordering one’s life experiences. The underlying assumption is that narratives are “<italic>social products</italic>produced by people within the context of specific social, historical and cultural locations. They are related to the experience that people have of their lives, but they are not transparent carriers of that experience. Rather, they are interpretive devices, through which people represent themselves, both to themselves and to others” (Lawler 2002: 242; emphasis in original). These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Postclassical Narratology and the Theory of Autobiography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LÖSCHNIGG</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the theory of autobiography, theoretical developments in literary studies are clearly reflected. From an earlier mimetic understanding of the genre as the representation of an autonomous and homogeneous self the pendulum swung to the deconstructionist view, dominant in the late 1970s and early 1980s. According to deconstructionist tenets, there can be no representation of self in language, but only an illusion of “self” generated by a purely textual subject. It was at this point that theorists like Michael Sprinker even went as far as to proclaim the “end of autobiography” (Sprinker 1980). Since the late 1980s, however, the pendulum</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Natural Authors, Unnatural Narration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NIELSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>HENRIK SKOV</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hardly anything is more familiar to literary scholars than fictional narrative. Yet this simple term contains a slight tension between the<italic>invention</italic>associated with fiction, from its root in the Latin<italic>fictio</italic>, and the<italic>knowing</italic>associated with narration and its root in the Latin<italic>gnarus</italic>. How can you invent what you know or know what you invent? In all standard models of narratology, the answer to this question has been to split the tasks and distinguish between the narrator who knows and the author who<italic>invents</italic>, and this is the case particularly in the framework of Gérard Genette.²</p>
                     <p>The present</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw6k.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
