<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>New Thinking in Islam</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Jihad for Democracy, Freedom and Women’s Rights</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>AMIRPUR</surname>
               <given-names>KATAJUN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated from the German by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ormsby</surname>
               <given-names>Eric</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781909942738</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781909942745</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Gingko Library</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Eric Ormsby</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1h4mh5h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>Rethinking Islam</italic>, Katajun Amirpur argues that the West's impression of Islam as a backward-looking faith, resistant to post-Enlightenment thinking, is misleading and-due to its effects on political discourse-damaging. Introducing readers to key thinkers and activists-such as Abu Zaid, a free-thinking Egyptian Qur'an scholar; Abdolkarim Soroush, an academic and former member of Khomeini's Cultural Revolution Committee; and Amina Wadud, an American feminist who was the first woman to lead the faithful in Friday Prayer-Amirpur reveals a powerful yet lesser-known tradition of inquiry and dissent within Islam, one that is committed to democracy and human rights. By examining these and many other similar figures' ideas, she reveals the many ways they reject fundamentalist assertions and instead call for a diversity of opinion, greater freedom, and equality of the sexes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this brief essay the Egyptian literary scholar Nasr Hamid Abu Zaid (1943–2009) expressed what is perhaps the most significant point on the agenda of reform Islam: namely, that one can read the Qur’an differently, if one only has a mind to do so, and that it is the perspective of the exegete that predetermines the outcome. The Qur’an is thus open to interpretation.</p>
                     <p>In addition, Muslims ought to “listen to the Word and follow what is good in it”, as verse 39:18 states. Hence, the Qur’an itself exhorts humans to read it in the best possible way. To</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>On the Way to the Modern</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the nineteenth century Jamal al-Din al-Afghani (1838/39–1897), Muhammad ‘Abduh (1849–1905) and Rashid Rida (1865–1935), who are today considered the founders of Islamic reform, were already urging an inner reform of Islam. Underlying their efforts was a sense of subordination to the West. For all three, the backwardness of the Islamic world had been caused, and exclusively so, by a fixed, inflexible understanding of Islam and the blind imitation of its forefathers. For this reason they demanded a modern interpretation of the Qur’an and of Islamic law that would be appropriate for the altered circumstances. This effort,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Islamic Reformers Today</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary Iranian reformers oppose just such compulsion and declare, as does the Mullah Mohsen Kadivar (b. 1959), that a human being cannot be bundled off to paradise in chains. Reformers like him dismiss Khomeini’s understanding of Islam and in its place strive to reconcile Islam and democracy.</p>
                     <p>Kadivar’s main thesis, which identifies him as a post-Islamist intellectual, can be summarized as follows: people expect that religion will put principles and values within their grasp while practical matters belong more properly to the realm of so-called human experience – a formulation that may be code for secular norms.</p>
                     <p>In his writings,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Nasr Hamid Abu Zaid:</title>
                     <subtitle>Who’s the Heretic Here?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nasr Hamid Abu Zaid was born in 1943, two years before the end of the Second World War, in Tanta, a small village in the Nile Delta. His father named him Nasr, meaning “victory”, because he was an optimist. He believed that the Allies would be victorious in the war. All of his friends, however, were for the Axis powers because the latter fought against England, the much-hated occupying power. Abu Zaid was born into humble circumstances. His father had a shop and because he had problems with his heart, the son had to help out from an early age.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fazlur Rahman:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Qur’an to Life, and Back Again to the Qur’an</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fazlur Rahman (i.e., Fazl ur-Rahman Malik), one of the most important voices within the discussion of the reform of Islamic thought in the twentieth century, was born on 21 September 1919 in the province of Hazara, now located in Pakistan. His father, Mawlana Shihab al-Din, was an<italic>‘alim</italic>, a religious scholar, and it was from him that Rahman received an education in the classical disciplines of the Islamic sciences, namely, in<italic>tafsir</italic>“exegesis”, hadith “traditions of the Prophet”,<italic>fiqh</italic>“jurisprudence”,<italic>usul al-fiqh</italic>“theoretical jurisprudence”,<italic>kalam</italic>“theology” and<italic>falsafa</italic>“philosophy”. After receiving his high school diploma he attended Punjab University in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Amina Wadud:</title>
                     <subtitle>In the Midst of the Gender Jihad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This daughter of a Methodist pastor was born Mary Teasley in Bethesda, Maryland, in 1952. She grew up with five brothers and one sister in a country where there was a marked awareness of injustice. The idea that God might be connected with oppression was foreign to her, she has said. “As a minister my father taught me to understand the close connection between freedom and faith, God and righteousness.”¹</p>
                     <p>She describes her father as very devout and calls him her spiritual mentor. Her mother, whom Wadud describes, by contrast, as oppressive and violent, nevertheless held the family together. Wadud</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Asma Barlas:</title>
                     <subtitle>As Though Only Men Were Objective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the suppression of women stands in contradiction to the Qur’an is also Asma Barlas’ credo. Like Amina Wadud, she interprets the Qur’an as a liberating text that can show women a way out of suppression – under specific conditions:</p>
                     <p>The meaning of the text cannot be understood on its own terms. Everyone must give it a meaning. In this regard I note that the Qur’an has been interpreted exclusively by men for 1400 years, and always within a patriarchal society.¹</p>
                     <p>Born in Pakistan and now living in the US, she has achieved fame there through her book<italic>Believing Women</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>‘Abdolkarim Soroush:</title>
                     <subtitle>More than Ideology and State</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Abdolkarim Soroush, born in Tehran in 1945, is today one of the most important Muslim intellectuals in the world. In 2005<italic>Time</italic>magazine called him one of the most significant intellectuals worldwide. He comes from a traditional religious family as Farajollah Hajj Husayn Dabbaq, his full name, shows. He was born on<italic>‘Ashura</italic>, the day of the Shi‘ite Imam Husayn’s death. He was named Husayn for that reason. His pseudonym is composed of the names of two of his sons; Karim is one of the 99 “beautiful names of God”. The prefix<italic>‘abd</italic>means “slave” or “servant”; taken together, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Mohammad Mojtahed Shabestari:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Prophet Reads the World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the notion that a reform of Islamic thinking is, by and large, not a matter for clerics, Mohammad Mojtahed Shabestari may stand as a living counter-proof. In addition, Shabestari proves that to think about Islam in a new way doesn’t invariably lead to exile. Shabestari is a Shi‘ite cleric who holds the rank of<italic>hojjat al-Islam</italic>“authority on Islam”. Thus, he stands in the clerical hierarchy just one step below an Ayatollah. Shabestari was born in 1936 in comfortable circumstances in the vicinity of Tabriz, that is, in the Iranian part of Azerbaijan. His father and grandfather were also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Future of Islam</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The thinkers presented here have confronted a central problem of modern Islamic theology, namely, how to deal with specific Qur’anic statements. For us Muslims today this is an existential question since many Qur’anic statements do not agree with what we accept as values – at least when these statements remain uninterpreted. This complex of problems taken in itself can be discussed and a new way of interpretation devised and developed, for example, one that is favorable to women. But it can also be placed within the context of a more far-reaching question and an answer can be attempted as to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mh5h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Persons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
