<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In Praise of Heteronomy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Making Room for Revelation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Westphal</surname>
               <given-names>Merold</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253026385</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253026613</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025302661X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Merold Westphal</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz1pf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Recognizing the essential heteronomy of postmodern philosophy of religion, Merold Westphal argues against the assumption that human reason is universal, neutral, and devoid of presupposition. Instead, Westphal contends that any philosophy is a matter of faith and the philosophical encounter with theology arises from the very act of thinking. Relying on the work of Spinoza, Kant, and Hegel, Westphal discovers that their theologies render them mutually incompatible and their claims to be the voice of autonomous and universal reason look dubious. Westphal grapples with this plural nature of human thought in the philosophy of religion and he forwards the idea that any appeal to the divine must rest on a historical and phenomenological analysis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SIGLA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>EXECUTIVE AND LEGISLATIVE AUTONOMY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Abraham Lincoln concluded his famous Cooper Union speech in 1860 with these words: “Let us have faith that right makes might, and in that faith, let us, to the end, dare to do our duty as we understand it.”¹ Five years and much tragedy later, he concluded his Second Inaugural Address with similar but importantly different words: “With malice toward none, with charity for all, with firmness in the right as God gives us to see the right, let us strive on to finish the work we are in. . . .”² On the “crucial difference” between “our duty as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>SPINOZA’S THEOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kant first develops his notion of autonomy in a<italic>political sense</italic>as a plea for freedom to publish without censorship.¹ But in “What Is Enlightenment?” there are already overtones of a more far-reaching claim, and, as we have seen, Kant expands his concept of autonomy considerably in the context of his<italic>moral philosophy</italic>. But the most extensive and systematic development of his theory of autonomy occurs in his<italic>philosophy of religion</italic>, most particularly in<italic>Religion Within the Boundaries of Mere Reason or Religion Within the Limits of Reason Alone</italic>.² This title, however rendered, signifies far more than a book published</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>SPINOZA’S HERMENEUTICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we turn to the<italic>Theological-Political Treatise</italic>we find the theological part, primarily the theory and practice of interpreting the Bible, sandwiched between political bookends. At the heart of the theological argument is a plea for the autonomy of philosophy from theology, and, indeed, the hegemony of the former over the latter, relocating religion within the limits of reason alone. At the heart of the political part is a plea for the autonomy of the state from religion (religious authorities), and, indeed, the hegemony over the former over the latter. For Spinoza felt unjustly oppressed by the theocratic form of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>KANT’S THEOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kant developed his concept of autonomy first in a political context, as a plea for freedom of the press; then in the context of his moral philosophy, in both its executive and legislative dimensions; and finally, in his philosophy of religion, his contribution to the Enlightenment project in philosophy of religion that I call “religion within the limits of reason alone,”¹ borrowing the title of his “fourth Critique.”</p>
                     <p>He makes a double claim about the relation of religion to morality. First, a moral agent “is in need neither of the idea of another being above him in order that he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>KANT’S HERMENEUTICS I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was suggested in the last chapter that two decisive marks of a personal God are agency and speech. Both are affirmed by mere Christianity; neither by Spinoza. So far we have seen Kant to be a deist of restricted divine agency, thereby separating himself from Spinoza and (as we shall see) from Hegel by affirming God as an agent and not merely a cause, and also separating himself from Abrahamic monotheism (Jewish, Christian, or Muslim) by virtue of the restrictions. In this chapter, we look further into his account of divine agency, but in the context of his ideas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>KANT’S HERMENEUTICS II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kant’s hermeneutics can be summarized in terms of five theses: hegemony, means/end, dispensability, recollection, and harmony. Utterly fundamental is the<italic>hegemony thesis</italic>, the claim that the pure, that is the a priori and presuppositionless religion of practical reason is the norm or criterion for interpreting biblical texts and ecclesiastical traditions governing both beliefs and practices, doctrine and devotion—the whole of “revealed” or “learned” religion. Thus “ECCLESIASTICAL FAITH HAS THE PURE FAITH OF RELIGION FOR ITS SUPREME INTERPRETER” (R , 142, 6.109).¹ Scripture is the norm for ecclesiastical faith, but Scripture itself, in turn, has “no other expositor . .</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>HEGEL’S THEOLOGY I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hegel’s theology begins its development in a series of drafts and fragments from his student and tutor years at Tübingen, Berne, and Frankfurt. They are dated from 1793 to 1800 and thus precede his philosophical appointment at Jena in 1801. Many of these were first published in 1907 by Nohl in<italic>Hegel’s theologische Jugendschriften</italic>. Most of them are translated by T. M. Knox in G. W. F. Hegel,<italic>Early Theological Writings</italic>, bearing the titles given them by Nohl.¹ They lay the theological foundations for Hegel’s mature thought that is at once a philosophical and a political theology.</p>
                     <p>It has been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>HEGEL’S THEOLOGY II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The usual story is that Hegel is the culmination of German Idealism, drawing on and revising the work of Kant, Fichte, Schelling, and a few others. There is much truth in this approach.¹ But it is also true that Hegel tells us “thought must<italic>begin</italic>by placing itself at the standpoint of Spinozism; to be a follower of Spinoza is the essential<italic>commencement</italic>of all Philosophy . . . when a man begins to philosophize, the soul must<italic>commence</italic>by bathing in this ether of the One Substance” (<italic>HP/S</italic>, III, 257; emphasis added).</p>
                     <p>One doesn’t have to know a lot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>HEGEL’S HERMENEUTICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us see where we are with regard to Hegel’s theology and hermeneutical theory. We have seen him turn away from the theism of a personal God, a Creator, Lawgiver, and Redeemer of a world distinct from God, a world separated and united by creation, separated by the fall, and reunited in redemption. As Luther puts it, commenting on Psalm 51, “That gigantic mountain of divine wrath that so separates God and David, he crosses by trust in mercy and joins himself to God.”¹</p>
                     <p>Although Hegel claims to be a Lutheran, 2 he finds such a theology to embody an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>THE INEVITABILITY OF HETERONOMY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its original, modern mode, religion within the limits of reason alone regularly presents itself as the voice of a single, universally operative reason. The actual, substantial differences among various versions of this project undermine this claim and show human reason to speak with a variety of quite particular voices, each one relative to the paradigm that it presupposes. In the absence of any evidently universal reason, even the criteria for choosing among alternatives appear to be more nearly internal to the different theologies than “neutral” or “objective.” Epistemically speaking, we are operating within one of many possible hermeneutical circles.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>HETERONOMY AS FREEDOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far, the argument against the autonomy project or, more specifically, the religion-within-the-limits-of-reason-alone project has proceeded in two stages, unequal in length. First, a crucial premise of the enterprise has shown itself to be unsustainable. It is the assumption that human reason is universal, part of the standard equipment of human nature. As such, it is presumed to be objective, neutral, presuppositionless, the only source of reliable knowledge. As such, it is “nonsectarian” by contrast with the plurality of “religions of the book,” those that appeal to the authority of some particular divine revelation and are in this way heteronomous.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz1pf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
