<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN871.K88 2001</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Comparative</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Living Prism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Itineraries in Comparative Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KUSHNER</surname>
               <given-names>EVA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773521483</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773568969</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt801kq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>She discusses the current state of comparative literary studies and the renewed role of comparative literature in a world that is at once more plural and more globalized, as well as some of the debates now taking place within literary criticism as a whole, including the interchange between comparative literature and cultural studies, the re-envisaging of the Renaissance, the work of Northrop Frye, myth and literature at the end of the twentieth century, modern drama, and post-colonialism. To play an important role in the human sciences, comparative literature had first to free itself of a number of restrictive habits, such as an insufficiently critical literary history. In order to do this, it had to think theoretically, but without yielding to the temptation of letting theory become an end in itself. Kushner demonstrates that, while under strong pressures to be a more rigourous science, comparative literature has realized that in the human sciences the validation of knowledge has to seek its own tests and criteria, becoming increasingly more open to individuality, difference, and life situations and controlling its tendency to universalize. With its emphasis on whether literary history is possible and the problems it raises for literary theory and for comparative literature in particular, The Living Prism adds an important dimension to the ongoing debate about criticism and comparative literary studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword:</title>
                     <subtitle>Knowledge, Empathy, and Global Village: The Comparative Discourse of Eva Kushner</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KRYSINSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>WLADIMIR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the beginning of her university career as a scholar in French literature and as a comparatist, the author of<italic>The Living Prism</italic>has been committed to the multicultural and multicontextual approach to literature. For Eva Kushner the comparative ethos has always implied understanding through comparison. Understanding what? Worlds and literatures, subjective discourses and collective memories, values, structures and ideas, works and movements, writers in their social, biographical, and individual totality, cognitive passions, legacies, and history.</p>
                     <p>If the didactic and scholarly practice of comparative literature places Canada today among a few avant-garde countries in which this discipline gave rise to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The unity of this book lies not in any answers it may bring but in the persistence of its questionings. The circumstances of life, study, and work had led me to the humanities: a smattering of Protestant theology, followed by philosophy, followed in turn by French literature of the twentieth century but gradually also of the sixteenth; and, along these paths, the discovery of comparative literature. These were – and are – widely separate disciplines, guarded by specialists who would view any border trespassing with suspicion. My transgressions were due to the availability of certain programs of study rather than others, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Literature in the Global Village</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From their earliest days comparative literature studies have lived in a paradox: they presuppose universals at work within human literatures and cultures, and seek to bring them to light through the examination of the diversity of these literatures and cultures. In recent decades the entire field of literary studies has undergone a vast movement of self-examination and self-legitimation as part of a wider movement among the human sciences to demonstrate both their scientific worth and their relevance to the situation and psyche of mankind. The question remains, however, whether this search for truth, necessarily underpinned by questioning the process of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Is Comparative Literature Ready for the Twenty–first Century?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I confess to being haunted by the constant intellectual challenge of the changing nature of our field of knowledge. My title is meant to underscore that challenge rather than to exaggerate the importance of the turn of the century, useful only as a metaphor for possible continuities and discontinuities in the near future. As well, it is a risky attention-getting device, in that any generalization is a construct and can be suspected of trying to impose a common metanarrative on a community that may not even perceive itself as a community. I am dutifully wary of such pretensions; my thoughts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Towards a Typology of Comparative Literature Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It would be absurdly ambitious even to attempt to give a brief survey of the map of existing approaches in comparative literature. I merely wish to voice the need for such a map, and to indicate why I consider that it should be of a typological nature if comparative literature is truly to fulfil its international calling. This simply means taking one programmatic step in the direction in which the present diversity of our field is taking us, and stating what groupings and alliances, new and old, some expected, some unexpected, emerge as the most obvious from that initial vantage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Literary Studies, Cultural Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case for a Cease-Fire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Admittedly, my title dramatizes the tension that has been observed for some time between “literary” and “cultural” studies. A state of tension is not necessarily negative, but it does signal a need for attention. In this case it requires that special thought be given to the present and future orientation of comparative literature studies since the outcome may have profound repercussions upon this field of endeavour, from both an intellectual and a professional viewpoint.</p>
                     <p>One may legitimately wonder whether the very obvious recent growth of cultural studies is not mostly a US phenomenon. It is well known that, periodically, intellectual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Comparative Literature in Canada:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whence and Whither?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canada is a vast country with a relatively small but hugely diverse population. Its educational system is largely entrusted to provincial rather than federal authorities. It is therefore even more perilous to generalize about the state of a discipline in Canada than in countries where higher education is more evenly dispensed, structured, supported. The scholars, works, and events presented here are meant to be a set of representative examples rather than a hierarchical listing in any sense.</p>
                     <p>Comparative literature in Canada is attuned, generally speaking, to the international perspectives of the discipline. However, there is at present no unified international</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Theory, Theories, Theorizing, and Cultural Relativism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>Les Morales de l’histoire</italic>Tzvetan Todorov pinpoints the reason why the human sciences will forever fail to reach a healthy division of functions between “subjectivity” and “objectivity” the more they try to avoid deformations in both directions. No matter how careful we are to treat the object of our study scientifically, it will at some point want to “speak” to us; such is its specificity. This kind of statement confirms the trajectory of many contemporary scholars who have been profoundly concerned with establishing the validity of our knowledge prior to attempting any new construction.</p>
                     <p>Admittedly, the process of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Diachrony and Structure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thoughts on Renewals in the Theory of Literary History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There can be no doubt that literary history is and has been for several decades under a scrutiny so severe that only a thorough theoretical and epistemological re-examination can restore it to its place in literary scholarship, provided also that a renewed practice follows upon this re-examination. That the demand for it stems from the various “intrinsic” approaches to the study of literature is a well-known fact: Russian Formalism, the Prague Circle, New Criticism,<italic>Nouvelle critique</italic>, as well as the structuralist and semiotic approaches have all tended to lead the literary scholar towards a close reading and analysis of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>From “Time Lost” to “Time Regained” in Literary History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Proustian origin of this title requires no explanation. It expresses a set of creative tensions: the time that is lost is that of life lived and spent in the instant – raw, yet infinitely rich and complex material for retrieval in memory. To live is forever to transform experience into memory; and even this statement oversimplifies, inasmuch as memory re-enters experience and adds to the given that is to be transformed. Proust’s characters reawaken, through reminiscence nourished by insistent sensorial signals, time, or life, that is past:</p>
                     <p>cette réalité loin de laquelle nous vivons, de laquelle nous nous écartons de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>On Renaissance Literary Historiography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is devoted to a living experiment in early modern literary historiography – the Renaissance part, in four volumes, of the<italic>Comparative History of Literature in European Languages</italic>– and more particularly to the theoretical and methodological aspects of the project.</p>
                     <p>Though this may be implicit in the very nature of the entire series and not only its Renaissance volumes, it should be pointed out that both bear witness to the permanence of literary history within literary scholarship and to the determination of a group of scholars to renew literary history in the light of recent theoretical thought. Obviously this does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Comparative Literary History among the Human Sciences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As is well known, in recent decades literary studies, and more particularly comparative literary studies, have undergone a process of reexamination, for reasons of their own as well as for reasons linked to the challenge of other disciplines, those designated today “the human sciences.” My title implies, in hope at least, a change of emphasis: the impact of such disciplines as linguistics, psychoanalysis, sociology, and cultural anthropology has often been perceived as potentially aggressive, and harmful, with respect to the specificity of literary studies. But literary studies have emerged from this test not only without loss of specificity but having</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Comparative Literary History as Dialogue among Nations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Along with other human sciences, literary studies have been undergoing a phase of intense self–legitimation and self-justification. According to Linda Hutcheon this is part of a postmodern situation in which no values are embodied a<italic>priori</italic>in any set of texts or in the study of any set of texts, and literary studies are, therefore, in a situation resembling exactly those of all other methodological and theoretical forms of discourse, trying to find their legitimacy in themselves. If that is so, literary scholars have reason to rejoice in the self-examination and autocriticism that is required of them, the need</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>History and the Power of Metaphor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My title connotes far more than a mere essay can cover; let both the title and the content simply express a set of attitudes concerning the relationship of “history” and “theory” with respect, more particularly, to the study of literature.</p>
                     <p>Literary theory has been functioning as the legitimating and validating mental activity alongside our discourse, the keystone, as it were, of reflection upon literary studies; but it can justify itself in this role only as long as it does not lose sight of its own historicity. The moment it begins to construct a monument in which to enshrine its own</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Comparative Literary History in the Era of Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How compatible is the intellectual project of a comparative literary history with a postmodern culture? My title signals a potential contradiction from which comparative literary history may, or may not, emerge as still a creative and stimulating area within literary studies and the humanities at large. The contradiction arises if, embracing difference not only as a<italic>fait accompli</italic>but as a value sustaining of cultural identities, we set up the comparative viewpoint and activity as, somehow, its philosophical opposite, because of its inevitably universalizing frame of mind (or perhaps merely its universalizing image). In a well-known article on the emergence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Distant Voices:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Call of Early Modern Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How does the postmodern literary historian make contact with the premodern world? Much present-day theorization regarding literary history (and quite relevant to history in general) begins with that question. I use the expression postmodern not as a philosophical or aesthetic label but by way of recognizing that we live in postmodernity, remembering that the status of this concept is itself problematic in that it resists being regarded as a period comparable to previous ones, sees itself more as a set of conditions of variable temporal dimensions, weakening and dissolving the very fabric of comfortable generalization. Thus, more than ever before,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>History and the Absent Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the fact that collective identities (whether in terms of gender or culture or ethnicity) claim to exist, and to have the right to exist for the sake of the development of the individual self, that claim is often little more than window-dressing. Yet what can one hope to accomplish by showing that the subject of the subject has received insufficient attention or the wrong kind of attention? Even if it were only clarification, it would be time well spent. But humanists have more at stake in this questioning than just clear categories because it matters supremely – without any play</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>The Emergence of the Paradoxical Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few actions, few pronouncements are as symbolical of their age as Luther’s, confronting the Diet of Worms. In attempting to understand – perhaps merely in concrete and individual terms at the outset – the situation of the early modern self, it is helpful to reflect upon the mental and emotional tension experienced by Luther as he faced that august, severe assembly and uttered his famous words of resistance. Often, one reads abridged versions of his statement. Let us consider it in its entirety:</p>
                     <p>Unless I am convinced by the testimony of scriptures or by clear reason (for I do not trust either</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Renewed Meaning of the Renaissance Dialogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To work in the humanities, particularly in early modern studies, forces upon us a double sense of time: on the one hand, all documents and monuments from even the most distant past, at least those that have been stored, preserved, printed, discovered, reclaimed, are at our disposal in a kind of eternal present, and we feel a kinship with all these creations of human imagination; on the other, when we attempt to make them our own, we very quickly discover the immensity of distance to be bridged and that, in order to exist in history, the phenomena of the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Erasmus and the Paradox of Subjectivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is paradoxical about subjectivity, and how does this question relate to the thought of Erasmus? As a philosophical issue the problematic of subjectivity is very present in our time: undeniably the struggles of the postmodern self help to ignite inquiries into the early modern past of this rich and elusive concept, paradoxical or so regarded inasmuch as (according to philosophies, and often within the same philosophy) the self both is and is not its own origin. While Renaissance humanism promoted and privileged the perfecting of the human person as a cherished ideal, it did not often envisage that self</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>In Search of the Obverse Side of Petrarchism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The search I wish to describe is not directed, as the title might suggest, towards the anti-Petrarchan tradition, which has been a rich source of obverse images of the idealized Other – usually woman – so characteristic of Petrarchism itself. Where Petrarch and his followers idealize and even worship, anti-Petrarchism levels, satirizes, and ridicules. Where Petrarch and his followers create a myth, anti-Petrarchism demythologizes and demystifies. It is a trend that its idealistic counterpart almost seems to demand, and their duality seems omnipresent in European literature as part of the even more basic duality between idealistic and realistic traditions from classical times</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Imagining the Renaissance Child</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>232</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To this vast subject I shall not attempt to bring answers but merely to raise questions and to devise, only programmatically, a conceptual framework. Many of the recent findings of social history contradict certain admittedly naïve expectations regarding the accomplishments of the Renaissance. Simplistically one might say that there has been a gap between theoretical visions of the Renaissance and its practices. I suspect there is much more to be said, and that pursuing the discrepancies is a necessary part of rewriting and rereading the Renaissance so as to uproot, destabilize, complexify our images of Renaissance children both in concept</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Northrop Frye and the Possibility of Intercultural Dialogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As it happens, Canada’s two best-known contemporary thinkers, Marshall McLuhan and Northrop Frye, taught throughout their respective careers at the University of Toronto. Marshall McLuhan, as a theoretician of communication, coined a certain number of felicitous expressions to describe the world of today, including “the global village,” a formula that so dramatically telescopes together all populations and all cultures by the power of the media. Northrop Frye, as a theoretician of literature, inventoried and systematized the creations of the human imagination as expressed and organized in written form. One might be tempted to say that both writers took universals and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Northrop Frye and the Historicity of Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pondering the legacy of Northrop Frye necessarily leads to recognizing its scope, which goes far beyond the study of the literary system alone; this in turn entails recognizing the philosophical status of his thought. In<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>, once he established the specificity of the critical activity among intellectual disciplines, Frye showed little interest in the labels others would apply to his sphere of activity: critic or historian or theorist or philosopher. In practice, however, he always dealt, explicitly or by implication, with the whole universe of human culture, emphasizing the role of works of imagination within it. The philosophical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>The Social Thought of Northrop Frye</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More, perhaps, than any other contemporary thinker, Northrop Frye has made us reflect upon culture in general and Canadian culture in particular. Undoubtedly, the<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>innovated, in 1957, by its manner of articulating the literary system as well as its reflection upon the literary system. Yet if we follow Frye’s thought all the way, we begin to perceive how it links the understanding of literature with an even more fundamental quest for intelligibility.</p>
                     <p>The<italic>Anatomy</italic>begins by magnificently establishing the specificity of the literary pursuit, in terms both of literary works and of the critical and theoretical study</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>Liberating Children’s Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fictionality, whether intended for children or adults, by multiplying possible worlds has a liberating effect, but also works better than the didactic imposition of moral lessons; this is no more than a restatement of Horace’s still valid conjoining of the pleasant and the useful.</p>
                     <p>It is now a commonly accepted fact that the development of feminist readings, by dint of providing different appropriations of literary texts than those that have long been taken for granted, have had a strong impact upon the theory of literature in general, since it became apparent that if reception and interpretation will vary with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>Myth and Literature:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Example of Modern Drama</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Responding to a request for a course-outline proposal, this essay will be a set of prolegomena pointing out the pedagogic and theoretical potential of reflecting on myth in its multiple relationships to literature in any culture. The course would begin with an attempt to delineate literariness in relation to the already familiar materials (from the past near or far of the writer’s own culture, from the oral tradition, from the past and present of other civilizations, and so on) proposed by the collective imagination to the writer’s creativity. We would also explore the common ground of myth and literature as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>Greek Myths in Modern Drama:</title>
                     <subtitle>Paths of Transformation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>300</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To study the reappearances of myth in literature is to encounter the paradox of permanence and transformation. The haunting question that arises for the critic and the historian as well as for the theoretician of literature and those who study the anthropological, psychological, and sociological aspects of imagination is that of the resilience of myths. How is it that these ancient narratives – very often Greek myths in the case of the literatures of the West – survive and revive with ever-renewed meaning for writers, readers, and spectators of subsequent periods? What is the source of their power of resurgence? It is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>Victor Segalen and China:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Dialectic of Reality and Imagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a type of topic that today is no longer considered truly to pertain to the discipline of comparative literature: the kind that probes the overall impact of a foreign country and its literature upon a given author. In this case, if I were to write about the “influence” of China upon the early twentieth-century French poet Victor Segalen, or the image of China in his poetry, I would simply be contributing to the history of French literature the study of the poetic transformations of Segalen’s experiences of Chinese culture and travel in China. In other words, there would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801kq.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
