<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN228.M4D65 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanities</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Missing Link</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Evolution of Metaphor and the Metaphor of Evolution</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DONALDSON</surname>
               <given-names>JEFFERY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773545182</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773581968</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773581960</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt14bs0fz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>We look for missing links in the sciences and humanities, but the essential missing link - metaphor - is always in front of us. In Missing Link, Jeffery Donaldson unites literary criticism and evolutionary and cognitive science to show how metaphor has been with us since the beginning of time as a seed in the nature of things. With examples from centuries of poets, critics, philosophers, and scientists, he details how metaphor is a chemistry, an exchange of energies forming and dissolving, and an openness in the spaces between things. He considers the ways in which DNA learns how to liken things that have been, how mutation makes errors and then tries them on, and how evolution is hypothesis - nature's way of "thinking more." The mind is a matrix of relations: neural synapses cascade into ever-changing pathways and patterns. Metaphor is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen. It is the unbroken thread between matter and spirit. Whether offering analysis of a turn of phrase or chemical reaction, Missing Link presents a vision of literature that is also a vision of the cosmos, and vice versa. It enters the debate between evolution and religion, and challenges scientists, literary theorists, and religious advocates to rethink the relations between their disciplines.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It begins with metaphor, with A = B. It begins with identity and difference, with forms attracting and repelling. It begins with the spaces between things, between things and us, and between ourselves and each other. It begins with the gaps that hold us apart and with the binding energies that dwell in gaps. It begins with patterns and unities, with change and possibility, with transgression and impertinence. Metaphor makes us what we are. It is how we got here. It is how we live, how we act, how we think and dream. Metaphor has bequeathed to us the tensions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“Combinatorial Algorithms”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The makings of metaphor appeared in the world when the world first appeared, and to what degree<italic>ex nihilo</italic>we may still speculate. The initiative passed through myriad incarnations that have led up to and become ourselves. This book might do well to follow a similar procedure, with an introduction of metaphor per se, a conjuring of it<italic>ex nihilo</italic>: what metaphor is thought to be, how it is thought to work. With each chapter that follows, we will have occasion to draw out unique features of metaphoric behaviour as they become relevant. To avoid repeating myself too much, I’m</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“Peyne and Wo”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metaphor among the Discourses</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Metaphor is often seen as lower fruit on the language tree. We have a pretty confident sense of its use and place among our core language tools. When it comes to using words for getting at truths, metaphor is the handy gadget for special uses. It is like the angled ratchet attachment that helps you get at fasteners in hard-to-reach places: too delicate and unwieldy for those tough, straight-forward bolts that we spend most of our time wrestling with. This attitude is strongest among disciplines in which language is a necessary but sometimes frustrating instrument of communication, and where any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Chemistry:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dualities that Enliven</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In our beginning is our end” (<italic>Complete</italic>, 177). T.S. Eliot’s Alpha-and-Omega shell game is sometimes used as a first salvo in long arguments; it makes my case succinctly, so I’m pressing it into service again. Whatever end we human beings currently represent as evolved metaphoric thinkers is already present and active in whatever beginning the Big Bang represents for our universe. The launching of the metaphoric initiative and the launching of the universe are one and the same event. They consist of the same fabric, a material condition and a pattern of behaviour, a content and a form, as one.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>DNA and the Three R’s</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The metaphoric initiative was on the move. Getting its big boost from the Big Bang, it expanded, as tensions within gaps are like to do, and quickly constituted the laws of attraction and repulsion among subatomic particles. Metaphoric relation came to inform both the limits and the content of the cosmos. Fostered by an environment that determined its behaviours, the chemicals that burst from the Big Bang bonded with one another and made molecules, the molecules bonded to make compounds, gaseous, liquid, and solid. Nature became a realm of interacting forces of mutual transformation and exchange, dizzyingly complex in its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Graceful Errors:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Mutation of Metaphor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For decades, Richard Wilbur’s poem “Mind” has been admired by both literary critics and thinkers in a variety of fields. Wilbur is one of those poets who develops a poem’s evocative potential by embodying the subject in the poem’s procedures. Here he offers a scene where a mind flits playfully about inside a world of stony recalcitrance. At the same time he<italic>plays with</italic>a metaphor (the very one that says “the mind is like some bat”), and lets it flit about within the confines of three constrained stanzas, until it comes to the point where it “turns” to examine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Possibility Naturalized:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Story of Evolution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Someday I’d like to write an article on the rhetoric of book and chapter titles, a fairly typical example of which you see above. We are drawn towards this kind of hinged twofold structure: there is a metaphoric or playful gesture on one side, and a discursive statement on the other telling us what the work is “really” about. The two halves are related: the discursive element participates in its metaphoric resonances, with the metaphoric resonances grounded in the discursive ballast. The colon represents an axis, a bonding agent in the juxtaposition, metaphor as part of the grammar of thinking.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Metaphor and Cognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We’re at the half-way point in this book. If we were pilots on a trans-Atlantic flight crossing the gap between two continents, we’d be somewhere around the Point of No Return. No land in sight on either horizon. We would be crossing an important line and yet, if we looked out on the ocean, we would see no line at all. I consider in my argument two distinct and related contexts for the evolution of the metaphoric initiative. We have been thinking about how it has been at work<italic>in</italic>and<italic>as</italic>the material world from its outset. The reality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A Word Aside:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Detour that Became a Thoroughfare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We take a big leap at this point, a metaphoric leap, a leap that is no leap at all. We move from relatively simple cascades of computing neurons to our existential experience of consciousness. In the last chapter, we worked up some of the tools we need to achieve conscious thinking. We kept it simple, but the rudiments were there. I see this movement then from relatively elementary forms of thinking to more sophisticated symbolic modes and the qualia of mind they present to us as a question of degree rather than of kind. The nature of the neuron does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Metaphor of Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our brains store memories, images, pictures of things, feelings and ideas, words, the information and knowhow you need to tie your shoe and sound out the letter “K.” But you must have puzzled over this question at some point already in this book. How does a neuron, or even a network of neurons store things like pictures and sounds and ideas? If at some point we were able to isolate a network of neurons where an image of your house was stored, would we see a little image of your house inside it? Is there a network of neurons that,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Megaphors:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Seeing As Tool</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It often happens when you approach them, that what you thought were pinnacles become thresholds. We have worked through the metaphor of consciousness (subjective genitive, the metaphor that consciousness is). Our A = B has issued in symbolic thinking and it has assumed the echoic properties of sentient awareness. We may be inclined to think that our individual minds are the be-all and end-all so far as metaphor is concerned, that metaphor can’t do any better than produce self-reflexive thinkers like ourselves. But in truth, it may just be getting started. It is still expanding and taking on new forms.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Natural and Design Evolution in Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We spent most of the last chapter getting the metaphoric initiative turned around, like a heavy cannon, so that our salvos were no longer directed at the inwardness of human being but back outside, where we can see how that inwardness participates in the world around it. The material world is both concrete<italic>and</italic>symbolic, and we’ve come to recognize in the fictions of a functioning ego the potential for self-reinvention. We want to feel that we control our own destiny. Such a freedom evolves, Dennett has argued, and we have seen how metaphoric thinking makes this possible. How are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The Evolution of Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>328</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our tracking of the metaphoric initiative, we have seen how processes of natural evolution unfold via a logic of replication, genetic causes and effects, governed by the principle of natural selection. We asked the following questions. Is this same unconscious process at work in culture? If it is, how are we to understand ourselves as free and self-determining? If it is not, that is, if the terms and conditions of evolutionary change have themselves changed in the cultural domain, what power of agency or self-determination, if any, do we gain? Can we understand those mechanisms of change better, control</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Spirit and Its Metaphoric Environment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>356</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our symbolic thinker, human being, has set out to design a world that gives it survival advantage. Thinking ahead, testing and deliberating, it has striven to build and inhabit a world that, it would hope, makes sense. The thick cream of its society has been whipped into myriad shapes that stand on their own. At the same time, that most characteristic of human being’s talents, its prowess for symbolic thinking, has evolved a domain unique to itself, where the symbol as symbol has come to the fore, where hypothetical thinking has become a survival-enhancing end in its own right, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>“Til the Ductile Anchor Hold”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Allowing Conditions of Metaphor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are nearing the point where two ends meet. One is the end of the book. The other is the end of the metaphoric unfolding that we have been tracking throughout. That end is, in plainest terms, metaphor, the enabling and embodying initiative that like the dog in Rilke’s “Orpheus. Euridyce. Hermes” scampers impatiently to the next rise, where it appears to see views still farther beyond, even while it waits for us to catch up with it.</p>
                     <p>In one sense, it appears that we have been moving to the heart of a concentric circle, from all-encompassing nature to culture,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bs0fz.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
