<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR888.N3557K35 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">National characteristics, English, in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cities and towns in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social classes in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Community in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth fiction (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Cities of Affluence and Anger</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Literary Geography of Modern Englishness</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KALLINEY</surname>
               <given-names>PETER J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813939001</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813939003</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CHARLOTTESVILLE; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183q3bk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Providing a compact literary history of the twentieth century in England, Cities of Affluence and Anger studies the problematic terms of national identity during England's transition from an imperial power to its integration in the global cultural marketplace. While the countryside had been the dominant symbol of Englishness throughout the previous century, modern literature began to turn more and more to the city to redraw the boundaries of a contemporary cultural polity. The urban class system, paradoxically, still functioned as a marker of wealth, status, and hierarchy throughout this long period of self-examination, but it also became a way to project a common culture and mitigate other forms of difference. Local class politics were transformed in such a way that enabled the English to reframe a highly provisional national unity in the context of imperial disintegration, postcolonial immigration, and, later, globalization.Kalliney plots the decline of the country-house novel through an analysis of Forster's Howards End and Waugh's Brideshead Revisited, each ruthless in its sabotage of the trope of bucolic harmony. The traditionally pastoral focus of English fiction gives way to a high-modernist urban narrative, exemplified by Woolf's Mrs. Dalloway, and, later, to realists such as Osborne and Sillitoe, through whose work Kalliney explores postwar urban expansion and the cultural politics of the welfare state. Offering fresh new readings of Lessing's The Golden Notebook and Rushdie's The Satanic Verses, the author considers the postwar appropriation of domesticity, the emergence of postcolonial literature, and the renovation of travel narratives in the context of globalization. Kalliney suggests that it is largely one city--London--through which national identity has been reframed. How and why this transition came about is a process that Cities of Affluence and Anger depicts with exceptional insight and originality.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>ENGLISH, ALL TOO ENGLISH:</title>
                     <subtitle>NATIONAL EXCEPTIONALISM AND THE URBAN CLASS SYSTEM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1936 Victor Gollancz asked George Orwell to take a tour of England’s northern industrial cities and write a documentary about his experiences among working-class people. The results of that journey were published a year later as<italic>The Road to Wigan Pier,</italic>carrying the imprint of Gollancz’s Left Book Club. Although the subscription book society boasted some 38,000 regular members before the outbreak of World War II, Orwell’s contribution is one of the few offerings to remain in continuous circulation, owing its durability partly to the fame of its author and partly to the text’s searching, desperately funny critiques of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>BROKEN FENCES:</title>
                     <subtitle>FORSTER, WAUGH, AND THE GARDEN CITIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A cursory survey of nineteenth-century fiction indicates that few English writers were willing to represent the urban class system as a site of national cohesion. Read selectively, the novels of Charles Dickens, Elizabeth Gaskell, William Makepeace Thackeray, and Thomas Hardy, for instance, imply that the cultural and political differences arising from the class system and industrialism may ultimately threaten the long-term stability of the nation. In<italic>Sybil; or, The Two Nations</italic>(1845), to take the most pointed example, Benjamin Disraeli describes a society in which the rich and poor form two distinct cultural and political entities, “between whom there is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>STRANGERS IN THE PARK:</title>
                     <subtitle>WOOLF, SELVON, AND THE TRAFFIC IN MODERNISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an essay on Oxford Street, the longtime center of London’s gaudy, cut-price shopping district, Virginia Woolf casually remarks that “the charm of modern London is that it is not built to last; it is built to pass.” Woolf surprisingly chooses Oxford Street, rather than one of London’s innumerable historic sites, as an emblem of the capital precisely because it foregrounds the transitory qualities of modern urban life. London’s historic houses and monuments, bestowed on the city by aristocratic patrons, “required the illusion of permanence.” By contrast, Woolf delights in the ephemerality of the city’s tacky, cacophonous, ostentatious retail industry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>CITIES OF AFFLUENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>DOMESTICITY, CLASS, AND THE ANGRY YOUNG MEN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1956<italic>Look Back in Anger</italic>opened at the Royal Court Theatre, enjoying an extraordinary run before moving to Broadway, where it won the Drama Critics Award for Best New Play in 1957. A short two years later, John Osborne’s play debuted as a successful film with a young Richard Burton in the lead role. In the words of one enthusiastic reviewer, it had such wide appeal because “it is intense, angry, feverish, undisciplined. It is even crazy. But it is young, young, young.”¹ Though it borrows some of its techniques and themes from Strindberg and Beckett, the play must</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>THE ELUSIVE ENGLISHMAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>DORIS LESSING GOES TO LONDON TOWN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ability to imagine Englishness as a repository of class affect is not the exclusive property of writers born and bred in England itself.<italic>In Pursuit of the English</italic>(1960), Doris Lessing’s autobiographical account of her first years in London, is obsessed with the location, meaning, and function of English culture, finding its essence in the convoluted folds of a class society. After living in the metropole for two years, the semifictional narrator, Doris, complains that she has yet to stumble upon any genuine, bonafide Englishmen. “I don’t think I’ve met any,” she moans to a friend, explaining, “London is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>MAD GOAT IN THE ATTIC:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SATANIC VERSES AND GLOBAL ENGLISHNESS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most academics read<italic>The Satanic Verses</italic>(1988) as an extended meditation on cultural hybridity. As Gayatri Spivak argues, its mode of representation is “citation, reinscription, re-routing the historical,“epitomizing postcoloniality because it systematically dislodges “every metropolitan definition” (104). The novel is predicated on this trope of postcolonial disruption, foregrounding the political and cultural fallout of imperial contraction and the immigration of former colonial subjects to the metropole. In<italic>The Location of Culture,</italic>Homi Bhabha famously reads Rushdie’s novel as a testament to “culture’s [inherent]<italic>hybridity</italic>” and the “indeterminacy of diasporic identity” (38, 225). Its main character, Saladin Chamcha, he says, “stands,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the past ten or fifteen years, there has been an upsurge of scholarly and popular interest in Englishness, London, and the special relationship between the two. Witness, for instance, Peter Ackroyd’s recent work in London:<italic>The Biography</italic>(2000) and<italic>Albion: The Origins of the English Imagination</italic>(2002). Pointing out the various peoples and cultures that have settled and influenced England, he observes that this ineffable sense of national belonging “has more to do with location and with territory, therefore, than with any atavistic native impulses.” The country’s painting, literature, music, and architecture, like the people themselves, may be the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183q3bk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
