<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1340.E85 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Existentialist ethics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Existentialism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Existentialist Thinkers and Ethics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DAIGLE</surname>
               <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773531062</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773585751</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill–Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zw0q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Twentieth-century existential thinkers, critical of traditional, overly rationalistic approaches to ethics, sought to provide a better account of what it means to be human in the world. They articulated ethical views that respected the individual yet were fundamentally concerned with the Other and the ethical value of an authentic life. Their philosophy has often been dismissed as unsuccessful.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="200"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>The Problem of Ethics for Existentialism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAIGLE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection of essays presents an inquiry into the possibility of existentialist ethics. A variety of existentialist thinkers, both theistic and atheistic, are known to have been highly critical of the philosophical and ethical traditions they inherited. Their views, as diverse as they are, all strive to offer an alternative to the overtly rational and, what they like to coin, an “inhumane” philosophical approach. Their aim is to provide a better account of what it is to be a human being in this world. This phenomenological task necessarily offers some ethical developments regarding our being-in-the-world as acting, encountering, socially living</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Exception as Reinforcement of the Ethical Norm:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Figures of Abraham and Job in Kierkegaard’s Ethical Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DESROCHES</surname>
                           <given-names>DOMINIC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his existential topology (aesthetic, ethical, and religious), Kierkegaard conceives of ethics as “universal” (<italic>det Almene</italic>), that is to say, a sphere marked by language, where norms are universally valid. Indeed, in this scheme of the spheres of existence, Kierkegaard always conceives of ethics in its dialectical relationship with the aesthetic and religious spheres. Ethics is a transitory sphere (<italic>Gjennemgangssphære</italic>), as it is intermediate in the topology. This topology is first expressed in<italic>Either/Or</italic>, where, in the second part of the volume, Judge William writes two long letters addressed to<italic>A</italic>, the young defender of the aesthetic of the first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Nietzschean Solution to Ethical Relativism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOLDBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We live in an age of ethical relativism gone rampant, an age in which adjudication between moral positions has been undermined and thrown into doubt. One of the repercussions of postmodern thinking has been the dissolution of that conceptual certainty that modern philosophy and its philosophic predecessors reveled in: an envisioned certainty that enabled previous generations to condone or condemn moral positions outright and with a certitude that bordered on arrogance.¹ But as our world grows rapidly smaller, our contemporary view (especially within the United States) is one that expects divergence of moral positionings and finds it instanced in actions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Politics of Authentic Existence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAVIN</surname>
                           <given-names>TODD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The main thesis of this chapter is that only in and through collective social action can<italic>Dasein</italic>win its own self. I do not mean to distort or cover over the fundamental<italic>Jemeinigkeit</italic>, or “mineness,” of<italic>Dasein</italic>– that is, its having its being entrusted to it, to win or lose it, to choose or abandon it to the “They,” and I affirm with Heidegger that the being that we ourselves are “is always<italic>mine</italic>.”¹ Yet, to win itself, to choose itself in its being, Dasein must complement its “individuation”² with collective action. I propose that the existential project of selfhood</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Yes, She Is an Ethicist:</title>
                     <subtitle>Arendt, Responsibility, and Existentialism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHULMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hannah Arendt is almost always considered a political thinker, and she is often considered a phenomenologist; she is rarely considered either an existentialist or an ethicist. This is not a surprise, because in some ways Arendt does not look like either one. Unlike most ethicists, for example, she is not primarily concerned with how human beings should act. Furthermore, unlike most existentialists, she is not concerned with death or anxiety, and she focuses on the “public,” as opposed to individuals outside of their relations with others.</p>
                     <p>Because this book is about existentialist ethics and because it is generally easier to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Sartre on Atheism, Freedom, and Morality in The Humanism of Existentialism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRADDOCK</surname>
                           <given-names>GLENN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the space of one paragraph at the end of<italic>The Humanism of Existentialism</italic>, Jean-Paul Sartre makes two apparently conflicting claims. He says in one sentence that, “Existentialism is nothing else than an attempt to draw all the consequences of a coherent atheistic position.” Three sentences later, he tells us that existentialism “declares that even if God did exist, that would change nothing. There you’ve got our point of view. Not that we believe thatGod exists, but that we think that the problem of His existence is not the issue.”¹</p>
                     <p>Well, we might ask, which is it? Is atheism the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>An Ethics of Measure:</title>
                     <subtitle>Camus and Rousseau</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KNEE</surname>
                           <given-names>PHILIP</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite Camus’ refusal to be labelled an existentialist, his early thought in<italic>The Outsider</italic>and<italic>The Myth of Sisyphus</italic>is sometimes seen as an example of existentialism’s incapacity to avoid ethical nihilism. Rather than discussing (once again) the accuracy of such judgments, I want to offer some reflections on the positive ethics Camus provided a few years later in<italic>The Rebel</italic>. To do this, I will compare it with certain aspects of Rousseau’s thought, however paradoxical this comparison may at first appear.</p>
                     <p>Even more than Hegel or Marx, Rousseau symbolizes the political folly that<italic>The Rebel</italic>opposes. What Camus sees</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Ambiguous Ethics of Beauvoir</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAIGLE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the conclusion of his major treatise,<italic>Being and Nothingness</italic>, Jean-Paul Sartre announces that his next endeavour will be to deal with ethics. In the last section, “Ethical Implications,” he tells of how ontology and existential psychoanalysis can inform the individual that he or she is free and the source of all values. However, ontology and existential psychoanalysis cannot give moral prescriptions. All questions relative to freedom and how this freedom will deal with its situation are questions “which refer us to a pure and not an accessory reflection, [and] can find their reply only on the ethical plane. We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Merleau-Ponty’s Embodied Ethics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rethinking Traditional Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MACLAREN</surname>
                           <given-names>KYM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Merleau-Ponty offers us an existentialist philosophy that understands our freedom and responsibility as inseparable from our embodiment. Though he does not explicitly and systematically articulate an ethics, his notion of embodiment nonetheless implies a certain existentialist ethics. For, according to Merleau-Ponty, to be embodied is to be inherently in relation to others, and thus, as I will argue, it is to be implicated in and moved by an imperative to strive for mutual recognition. This paper seeks to elucidate this embodied ethics of mutual recognition.</p>
                     <p>Merleau-Ponty’s thought tends, in general, to move by way of a dialectical rethinking of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Ethical to the Political</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAIGLE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays in this book have all demonstrated the genuine possibility of an existentialist ethics. Moreover, they have shown that there are various ways to approach ethics from an existentialist standpoint and that these ethical endeavours present viable programs. It has thus been established that the existentialist enterprise in practical matters is neither a nihilistic dead end nor a relativistic or purely individualistic project. Every contributor to this collection has in one way or another shown that existentialist ethics implies a fundamental concern with the Other.</p>
                     <p>Sharing a similar conception of being-in-the-world, the existentialist thinkers discussed in this volume all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw0q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
