<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8wwkwg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>French Fiction into the Twenty-First Century</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Return to the Story</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kemp</surname>
               <given-names>Simon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780708322734</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780708322741</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Wales Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CARDIFF</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Simon Kemp</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qhfv3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book examines contemporary French literature in the light of a widely-held critical notion that it exists ‘in the wake’ of a period in which avant-garde experimental literature and postmodern writing-about-writing held sway.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Editors’ Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Diamond</surname>
                           <given-names>Hanna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gorrara</surname>
                           <given-names>Claire</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of the 1980s a term began to crop up in the French literary press to describe a newly perceptible trend in fiction:<italic>le retour au récit</italic>, or the return to the story. One of the earliest appearances comes in a special issue of<italic>La Quinzaine littéraire</italic>in May 1989 devoted to the question, ‘Where is French literature heading?’ In his editorial, Maurice Nadeau figures the current literary scene as a collection of ‘returns’ to literature’s traditional concerns in the wake of a period of textual experiment and theoretical formalism: ‘A return to history, a return to stories,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Annie Ernaux and the Narrating of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since her first publication in 1974, Annie Ernaux (b.1940) has garnered increasing success and critical controversy with each stage of her oeuvre. To date she has published sixteen texts, which divide into four distinct categories. There are the three semiautobiographical novels with which she began her career,<italic>Les Armoires vides</italic>(1974),<italic>Ce qu’ils disent ou rien</italic>(1977) and<italic>La Femme gelée</italic>(1981), first-person narratives dealing with issues of class and gender as the characters become distanced from their working-class origins through education, and experience oppression in social and domestic spheres. There are then the seven non-fiction texts on which her</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Pascal Quignard and the Fringes of Narrative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few writers have combined such renown with such eclecticism, such a wide readership for certain texts with such obscurity in others, as has Pascal Quignard (b.1948). He has been at the heart of French literary publishing with twenty-five years working for Gallimard, from professional reader to<italic>secrétaire général des Éditions</italic>, and has been awarded French literature’s most prestigious honour, the Goncourt Prize (for<italic>Les Ombres errantes</italic>, 2002). He writes substantial novels of modern French life in a broadly traditional, realist manner (<italic>Le Salon du Wurtemberg</italic>, 1986;<italic>Les Escaliers de Chambord</italic>, 1989), as well as sober, reflective historical novels like<italic>Tous</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Marie Darrieussecq and the Voice of the Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marie Darrieussecq (b.1969) is the youngest of the five writers, and has at the time of writing barely a decade to her career as a published author. In this short time, however, she has established herself as a significant voice in European literature. Following the<italic>succès de scandale</italic>of her first novel,<italic>Truismes</italic>(1996), which divided critics yet went on to become the kind of publishing sensation not seen in France since Françoise Sagan’s<italic>Bonjour Tristesse</italic>(1954), Darrieussecq has produced six further novels, along with several shorter pieces and non-fiction works.¹ The later novels, which will be our main concern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Jean Echenoz and the Uses of Digression</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the five novelists on which this study focuses, Jean Echenoz (b.1947) is most frequently compared with the experimenters of Oulipo and the<italic>nouveau roman</italic>, perhaps in part due to his position as the most prominent author at<italic>Les Éditions de Minuit</italic>since the<italic>nouveaux romanciers</italic>firmly established the publishing house’s avantgarde credentials in the 1950s. Such comparisons are not always apt: when, in 1979, Jérôme Lindon first welcomed the aspiring author to<italic>Minuit</italic>, Echenoz was told, ‘“You like Robbe–Grillet, of course” … as if it were obvious, as if my book stemmed naturally from this influence’, leaving the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Patrick Modiano and the Problem of Endings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the five authors in this study Patrick Modiano (b.1945) has the longest career as a published writer, beginning with<italic>La Place de l’étoile</italic>in 1968, and has maintained a high literary profile ever since, combining critical acclaim with popularity among the reading public.¹ The twenty-three novels and non-fiction narratives he has so far produced, up to<italic>Dans le café de la jeunesse perdue</italic>in 2007, regularly exceed 150,000 copies in sales; his 1978 Goncourt winner,<italic>Rue des Boutiques Obscures</italic>, sold 470,000.² With his other literary prizes including the Prix Fénéon (1968, for<italic>La Place de l’étoile</italic>), the Grand prix</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Return to the Story</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an interview marking the publication of<italic>La Possibilité d’une île</italic>(2005), Michel Houellebecq, France’s best-selling literary novelist and the only writer of his generation to achieve major fame beyond the French-speaking world, told the<italic>Nouvel Observateur</italic>: ‘You must believe that I count myself in the tradition of those French writers who ask questions of today’s world and do not renounce Balzacian narration.’¹ Frédéric Beigbeder, author of similarly provocative and successful critiques of contemporary mores, recalls in his 9/11 memoir,<italic>Windows on the World</italic>, meeting Alain Robbe-Grillet, then aged 80, near the scene of the attacks:</p>
                     <p>‘<italic>Why come to New</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qhfv3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
