<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8m3</collection-id>
      <volume>249</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PL2296.D96 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chinese literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ming dynasty, 1368–1644</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chinese literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Qing dynasty, 1644–1912</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Dynastic Crisis and Cultural Innovation</book-title>
         <subtitle>From the Late Ming to the Late Qing and Beyond</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wang</surname>
               <given-names>David Der-wei</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wei</surname>
               <given-names>Shang</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674017818</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684174140</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684174147</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tg5hxm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume addresses cultural and literary transformation in the late Ming (1550–1644) and late Qing (1851–1911) eras. Although conventionally associated with a devastating sociopolitical crisis, each of these periods was also a time when Chinese culture was rejuvenated. Focusing on the twin themes of crisis and innovation, the seventeen chapters in this book aim to illuminate the late Ming and late Qing as eras of literary-cultural innovation during periods of imperial disintegration; to analyze linkages between the two periods and the radical heritage they bequeathed to the modern imagination; and to rethink the “premodernity" of the late Ming and late Qing in the context of the end of the age of modernism. The chapters touch on a remarkably wide spectrum of works, some never before discussed in English, such as poetry, drama, full-length novels, short stories, tanci narratives, newspaper articles, miscellanies, sketches, familiar essays, and public and private historical accounts. More important, they intersect on issues ranging from testimony about dynastic decline to the negotiation of authorial subjectivity, from the introduction of cultural technology to the renewal of literary convention.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="644"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wang</surname>
                           <given-names>David Der-wei</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wei</surname>
                           <given-names>Shang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume addresses issues of cultural and literary transformation in the Ming (1368–1644) and Qing (1644–I911) dynasties by examining two periods of accelerated change—the late Ming (1550-1644) and the late Qing (185I–I911).¹ Although conventionally associated with increasingly deepening and devastating sociopolitical crises, each of these two periods represents a crucial stage in which Chinese culture was rejuvenated. Focusing on the twin themes of crisis and innovation, this book aims to illuminate linkages between the two periods, beginning with the representation of cultural politics and the reform of narrative discourse and culminating in the radical heritage bequeathed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Texts, Tutors, and Fathers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pedagogy and Pedants in Tang Xianzu’s Mudan ting</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Volpp</surname>
                           <given-names>Sophie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Completed in 1598, Tang Xianzu’s 湯顯祖 (1550–1616)<italic>Mudan ting</italic>牡丹亭 (The peony pavilion) was an overnight sensation.¹ The plot is well known: the education of its heroine, Du Liniang 杜麗娘, the only child of an official, goes awry on her first day of lessons. Her tutor’s exposition of “Guanguan jujiu” 關關雎鳩 (Fishhawk), the first poem in the<italic>Shi jing</italic>等經 (Classic of poetry), sets Du Liniang on a path of desire that leads to her death and resurrection. The poem inspires her to dream of being ravished in a garden by a scholar named Liu Mengmei 柳夢梅. Upon awakening,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Making of the Everyday World:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jin Ping Mei cihua and Encyclopedias for Daily Use</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wei</surname>
                           <given-names>Shang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unlike such earlier novels as<italic>Sanguo yanyi</italic>三國演義 (The romance of the Three Kingdoms),<italic>Shuihu zhuan</italic>水滸傳 (The water margin), and<italic>Xiyou ji</italic>西遊記 (The journey to the west), which were concerned with dynastic cycles, military affairs, heroic adventures, and religious journeys,<italic>Jin Ping Mei cihua</italic>金瓶梅詞話 (The plum in the golden vase, preface dated 1617 or 1618; hereafter,<italic>Jin Ping Mei</italic>) offers a comprehensive and meticulous representation of daily life.¹ It is distinctive in using streets, brothels, and a merchant household as the main stages for its characters, who are by no means historical personages or larger-than-life heroes. From</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Women as Emblems of Dynastic Fall in Qing Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Li</surname>
                           <given-names>Wai-yee</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary representations of momentous historical events often focus on the experiences, emotions, perceptions, and understanding of individuals; perhaps only thus can empathy be realized in acts of writing and reading. The individual’s perspective also allows one to ponder the margins of agency and responsibility. In the context of the fall of the Ming dynasty, the images of women proposed in this chapter—the femme fatale, the victim, the hero—represent a spectrum of attitudes on the relationship between the individual and larger historical processes. The femme fatale whose beauty and seductive wiles lure the ruler from his duties and spell</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Return of the Palace Lady:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Historical Ghost Story and Dynastic Fall</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zeitlin</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter deals with a specific type of ghost story, “the historical ghost tale.” By historical ghost tale, I mean a ghost story about a traumatic historical event rather than a problem of individual mortality. The event is usually of a political nature, especially dynastic fall and conquest. I am inspired here by Paul Ricoeur’s concept of “historical time,” which mediates between the lived time of the individual and the cosmic time of the universe.¹ Although the ghost story about history is most effective when it centers on one or more individualized ghost characters as “sufferers” or victims of history,²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Daughter’s Vision of National Crisis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tianyuhua and a Woman Writer’s Construction of the Late Ming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hu</surname>
                           <given-names>Siao-chen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among literary<italic>tanci</italic>texts with romantic and domestic inclinations,<italic>Tianyuhua</italic>天雨花 stands out for its strong political statement. Since the work addresses late Ming political events and ends with a martyrdom, it is often labeled a loyalist text.¹ What may come between<italic>Tianyuhua</italic>the text and the idea of loyalism, however, is the identity of the author. The literary<italic>tanci</italic>is often said to have a close connection with women, as both readers and writers, and many of the most famous literary<italic>tanci</italic>are known to have women authors. However, as with narrative fiction, the authorship of<italic>tanci</italic>is often difficult</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ethics of Form:</title>
                     <subtitle>Qing and Narrative Excess in Guwangyan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Xu</surname>
                           <given-names>Gang Gary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The transition from the late Ming to the early Qing witnessed a boom in fictional narratives with explicit sexual content. Notable titles include<italic>Ruyijun zhuan</italic>如意君傳<italic>Jin Ping Mei</italic>金瓶梅,<italic>Rou putuan</italic>肉蒲團,<italic>Langshi</italic>浪史,<italic>Bian er chai</italic>弁而釵, and<italic>Yichun xiangzhi</italic>宜春香質. These works variously present obscene versions of court history, tell stories about excessive sexual enjoyment and transgressions by townspeople, focus on male-male sexual relations, or parody scholar-beauty motifs by replacing poetic exchanges with sexual encounters between scholars and beauties. Despite the thematic differences, they have at least one thing in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jinghua yuan:</title>
                     <subtitle>Where the Late Late Ming Meets the Early Late Qing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Widmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Ellen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Jinghua yuan</italic>鏡花緣 combines stylistic features of late Ming fiction with a critical vision that anticipates the late Qing. This combination calls for a complex strategy of reading. On one hand, the novel’s debt to late Ming fiction,<italic>Shuihu zhuan</italic>水滸傳 in particular, leads to an ending that appears to nullify all that has gone before. Accordingly, Wu Zetian’s 武則天 regime and its support of female learning seem to crumble at the end of the book. Yet, as in<italic>Shuihu,</italic>this arrangement is unstable, leaving readers uncertain whether Li Ruzhen 李汝珍 (1763–1830) was or was not supportive of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Coin of Gender in Pinhua baojian</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rojas</surname>
                           <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Near the beginning of Chen Sen’s 陳森 1849 novel<italic>Precious Mirror for Evaluating Flowers (Pinhua baojian</italic>品花寶鑒), several maidservants have gathered in the bedroom of one of the novel’s protagonists, the opera patron Mei Ziyu 梅子玉, and are admiring the exquisiteness of its decoration. Then, we are told that although maidservant Ba has never seen Ziyu, she is nevertheless fascinated by the portrait of the</p>
                     <p>young beauty painted on the mirrored screen (jingping 鏡屏). He had a powdered face and rouged lips, refined elegance and blinding splendor<italic>(guanghua yaomu</italic>光華耀目), and she felt as if she had never seen with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Fall of the God of Money:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Chinese Account of Opium Addiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McMahon</surname>
                           <given-names>Keith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Around 1878 an otherwise obscure writer named Zhang Changjia 張昌甲 published “Opium Talk” (“ Yanhua” 煙話), a collection of comments and short narratives about his experience of opium addiction. Like many writers of his time, he firmly embedded the phenomenon of addiction in the cross-cultural aura of the nineteenth century. The intrusion of Westerners into China, he wrote, coincided with the arrival of opium, both Westerners and opium signaling irreversible transformation. “The rise of the opium demon has led to the fall of the god of money”<italic>(yangui xing er qianshen jiuci wuquan yi</italic>煙鬼興而錢神就此無權矣; that is, no one can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Newspaper, zhiguai, and the Sorcery Epidemic of 1876</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huntington</surname>
                           <given-names>Rania</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can tales of the anomalous and strange contribute to the comparison of two periods of dynastic decline and cultural innovation?¹ The<italic>yi</italic>異 (strange) has both ahistorical and historical aspects. The anomaly can be a surplus element, outside the patterned narrative of history, that must be recorded in other genres. Moreover, the motifs of ghosts and monsters, gods and omens, can be durable, recurring with relatively little change across the course of history. On the other hand, one of the oldest justifications for recording anomalous events was to read them as omens of historical change: like their predecessors, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A New Mode of Literary Production in the Late Qing:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Invention of the Installment Plan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Des Forges</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>388</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the mid-1870s, the narrative<italic>Xinxi xiantan</italic>昕夕閑談 (Idle chats morning and evening; translated from Edward Bulwer-Lytton’s<italic>Night and Morning</italic>) and other miscellaneous works appeared in installments in various literary periodicals published by the Shenbao Press 申報館 in Shanghai. In 1882, the lengthy novel<italic>Yesou puyan</italic>(A humble rustic’s simple words) was published in installments in the Shanghai newspaper<italic>Hubao</italic>滬報. Later in the 1880s, travel narratives and other accounts in literary Chinese were serialized in the illustrated magazine<italic>Dianshizhai huabao</italic>點石齋畫報¹ These early serial presentations represent an important moment in late Qing publication history; at the time, however</p>
                     <p>a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Narrator’s Voice Before the “Fiction Revolution”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanan</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>420</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The crises at the end of the Ming and Qing dynasties, crises caused by dynastic weakness and the threat of foreign domination, had obvious effects on the writing of vernacular fiction, drawing in new authors and giving rise to new themes and new techniques.¹ Of the two crises, the late Qing was the more complex, with economic and cultural challenges superimposed on the military and political threats. Moreover, two additional factors were at work in this period: the new media of newspapers and journals, and foreign fiction, available in translation for the first time.</p>
                     <p>In this chapter, I examine nineteenth-century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Creating Subjectivity in Wu Jianren’s The Sea of Regret</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huters</surname>
                           <given-names>Theodore</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>451</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At least since the publication of Jaroslav PrůŠek’ s path breaking work of the 1950s and 196os on the transformation of narrative modes in modern and late traditional Chinese literature, the question of the introduction of new sorts of subjectivity (or what critics now would be more inclined to refer to as “interiority”)¹ into modern Chinese literature has inspired much further analysis.² Průšek’s work was part of his broader effort to ascertain a world trend in literary writing, a tendency that many later critics would label a function of an unacknowledged impulse to establish the universal validity of narrative developments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Subject of Pain</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ko</surname>
                           <given-names>Dorothy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>478</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter analyzes a variety of narrative modes that describe, reveal, picture, or convey the experience of pain, especially that of the female body, in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Focusing on the discourses of pain popularized by the anti–footbinding movement, I explore the novel conditions that allowed female pain to be narrated, by women or others on their behalf, and the terms of this narration. My main argument is that these conditions and terms bespeak the difficulties involved in the formation of the female “voice” and female “agency”—attributes of the modern female subject—in late</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Women’s Poetic Witnessing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Late Ming and Late Qing Examples</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chang</surname>
                           <given-names>Kang-i Sun</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>504</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In traditional Chinese poetry, the task of witnessing-especially on the subject of war and other political issues-was generally assumed to be male territory. But, in fact, the earliest important work of political witnessing in Chinese poetry was attributed to a woman. In a poem written at the end of the Han dynasty (late second century BeE) and entitled “Beifen shi” 悲憤詩 (Poem of lament and indignation), Cai Yan 蔡琰 narrated her unfortunate experiences during the upheavals of the Dong Zhuo rebellion, including her capture by “barbarian” Xiongnu and her many subsequent dilemmas, experiences over which she had little or no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Judgments on the Ends of Times</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hegel</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>523</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the focus of this chapter is the literary representations of and reactions to the fall of the Ming in the seventeenth century, I will refer to two later ends of time(s) by way of contrast: when read against the fall of real dynasties, unconventional conclusions in Ming and Qing works of historical fiction reveal levels of political engagement and significance often overlooked by other readings. I begin by examining the beginnings of two novels.</p>
                     <p>Predictions of Dynastic Renewal My first example consists of three short but very famous lines, which have colored the reading of the novel they begin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Second Haunting</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wang</surname>
                           <given-names>David Der-wei</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>549</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Yang Siwen Yanshan feng guren”楊思溫燕山逢故人(Yang Siwen encounters old acquaintances in Yanshan), a story in Feng Menglong’s ；馬夢龍 (1574-1646)<italic>huaben</italic>collection<italic>Yushi mingyan</italic>喩世明言(Illustrious tales to instruct the world, 162o), relates events that take place in n29 CE, three years after the fall of the Northern Song dynasty to the Nüzhen Tartars. On the night of the Lantern Festival, the protagonist Yang Siwen runs into a familiar-looking woman. Like many northerners who did not flee to the south, Yang has submitted to Tartar rule and is making a modest living in Yanshan, the new capitaltha. woman turns out to be zheng yiniang</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>595</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tg5hxm.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>621</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
