<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">alle17272</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B105.B64A45 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human body (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mind and body</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Martial arts</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Striking Beauty</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Philosophical Look at the Asian Martial Arts</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ALLEN</surname>
               <given-names>BARRY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231539340</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231539347</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/alle17272"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first book to focus on the intersection of Western philosophy and the Asian martial arts,<italic>Striking Beauty</italic>comparatively studies the historical and philosophical traditions of martial arts practice and their ethical value in the modern world. Expanding Western philosophy's global outlook, the book forces a theoretical reckoning with the concerns of Chinese philosophy and the aesthetic and technical dimensions of martial arts practice.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Striking Beauty</italic>explains the relationship between Asian martial arts and the Chinese philosophical traditions of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Daoism, in addition to Sunzi's<italic>Art of War</italic>. It connects martial arts practice to the Western concepts of mind-body dualism and materialism, sports aesthetics, and the ethics of violence. The work ameliorates Western philosophy's hostility toward the body, emphasizing the pleasure of watching and engaging in martial arts, along with their beauty and the ethical problem of their violence.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE DAO OF ASIAN MARTIAL ARTS</title>
                     <subtitle>Themes from Chinese Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What the world knows as the Asian martial arts began in China. China is not the only civilization to have spiritualized combat arts; there are other, no less ancient, examples in India and Mesopotamia. Yet the Chinese, drawing on the resources of a mature civilization, merged their arts of armed and unarmed combat with Buddhist meditation and Daoist inner alchemy, two of the most dynamic currents of their postclassical culture. Creatively synthesizing combative arts with these prestigious teachings reinvented their practice as a way of self-cultivation. Indeed, scholars increasingly recognize that “without reliable research and informed commentary on the martial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>FROM DUALISM TO THE DARWINIAN BODY</title>
                     <subtitle>Themes from Western Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I say little in this chapter about the Asian martial arts. Instead, I explain why a chapter on Western philosophy<italic>cannot</italic>have much to say to these arts, not for accidental reasons of language and geography, but because this philosophy tends to be struck mute before anything as corporeal as the martial arts. Philosophy began in the West as a movement of nature rationalism, conceiving nature as a rational order, a cosmos with a principle that is both intelligible and intelligent. The early Greek philosophers, figures like Xenophanes, Heraclitus, and Parmenides, invented the idea of knowledge as the Truth of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>POWER AND GRACE</title>
                     <subtitle>Martial Arts Aesthetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Martial arts practice is like sport but not sport and dancelike but not dance. It constantly refers to violence but refuses it a place in the training. The training is athletic, as it is in sport and professional dance, yet the competence that the martial arts teach stands apart from those of sport or dance by means of its external, instrumental value as a weapon. It is precisely this external, instrumental effectiveness, the weapons potential of martial arts, that accounts for the striking beauty of its movements.</p>
                     <p>There is more than one paradox in that précis of my argument, so</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>WHAT A BODY CAN DO</title>
                     <subtitle>Martial Arts Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The techniques that the Asian martial arts teach are weapons. There is no other way to put it, which means that training in these arts is training in the use of weapons. They are special weapons, of course, and ineffective against many other weapons or against various threats. But what weapon is not specialized in some way and ineffectual in certain situations? People who train in martial arts might never actually use these weapons, just as many people who own a gun never fire it in self-defense. But they might, and unless they have prepared themselves, they might be disagreeably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE</title>
                     <subtitle>Martial Arts and Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An aesthetic paradox of Asian martial arts is that something so warlike in conception should be beautiful to watch and joyful to perform. While designed for violence and visibly expressing that functionality, the martial arts are not practiced with a violent purpose and do no harm (although they certainly could). By suspending the dread of violence, the practice creates a theater in which to contemplate movements combining artful design with eloquent efficacy. But if you remove the training conventions and introduce unfeigned violence (as in boxing), the aesthetic serenity will vanish into the sometimes irrepressibly fascinating chaos of violence.</p>
                     <p>Hence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CHINESE – ENGLISH GLOSSARY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">alle17272.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
