<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B171 .S85 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Ancient</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Divination</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intuition</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Divination and Human Nature</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Cognitive History of Intuition in Classical Antiquity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Struck</surname>
               <given-names>Peter T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400881116</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400881110</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1q1xs0v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Divination and Human Nature</italic>casts a new perspective on the rich tradition of ancient divination-the reading of divine signs in oracles, omens, and dreams. Popular attitudes during classical antiquity saw these readings as signs from the gods while modern scholars have treated such beliefs as primitive superstitions. In this book, Peter Struck reveals instead that such phenomena provoked an entirely different accounting from the ancient philosophers. These philosophers produced subtle studies into what was an odd but observable fact-that humans could sometimes have uncanny insights-and their work signifies an early chapter in the cognitive history of intuition.</p>
         <p>Examining the writings of Plato, Aristotle, the Stoics, and the Neoplatonists, Struck demonstrates that they all observed how, setting aside the charlatans and swindlers, some people had premonitions defying the typical bounds of rationality. Given the wide differences among these ancient thinkers, Struck notes that they converged on seeing this surplus insight as an artifact of human nature, projections produced under specific conditions by our physiology. For the philosophers, such unexplained insights invited a speculative search for an alternative and more naturalistic system of cognition.</p>
         <p>Recovering a lost piece of an ancient tradition,<italic>Divination and Human Nature</italic>illustrates how philosophers of the classical era interpreted the phenomena of divination as a practice closer to intuition and instinct than magic.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Divination and the History of Surplus Knowledge</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From all corners of the ancient Mediterranean, people that had run up against the limits of their own knowledge brought their remaining questions to a frail, illiterate woman housed in a massive stone temple at Delphi. She was Apollo’s human embodiment on earth and the most revered source of wisdom in the classical world. As they prepared for their consultation with the mysterious Pythia, seekers would have read an enigmatic, deceptively simple two-word sentence cut into the temple wall, “Know yourself.”¹ No one could remember where the saying came from or what exactly it was supposed to mean, but this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Plato on Divination and Nondiscursive Knowing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his most vivid narrative of his hero’s life story, Plato has Socrates center his autobiography on an act of divination. The<italic>Apology</italic>shows a man driven by a provocative pronouncement from the Delphic oracle to devote his life to solving its riddle. Pleading his own defense before an Athenian jury, Socrates presents a carefully constructed speech, rich in mythological allusions. He compares himself to Achilles (28c) and likens his life’s work to a Herculean labor (22a).¹ A more subtle and also more powerful point of reference is another figure, the Theban hero Oedipus, whose life was as profoundly shaped</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Aristotle on Foresight through Dreams</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In contrast to Plato, the surviving portion of Aristotle’s corpus is made up of his esoteric works—lectures, essays, and sometimes apparently just notes, meant for an audience already at the advanced stage. One salutary aspect is immediately apparent. Aristotle has little use for dramatic irony and deals with issues more directly and systematically than Plato does. On the other hand, the particular challenges for Aristotle’s readers are apparent as well. Whereas Plato could be said to present sometimes too many words, elaborating long and intricate lines of argument in which his investment remains indeterminate, Aristotle nearly always presents too</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Posidonius and Other Stoics on Extra-Sensory Knowledge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen, Plato and Aristotle treat divinatory insight as a curiosity, an epiphenomenon of human anatomy and cognition. For them, building a theory of it means proposing an alternative system of information-processing, paratactic to the everyday rational system. They revert to the lower orders of the soul by a process of elimination. Since divination seems not to have a place in the normal modes of thinking, they propose that some other form of insight dwells in the soul’s other parts, situated closely to our creaturely selves. In Plato’s case, we have the appetitive soul on occasion finding its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Iamblichus on Divine Divination and Human Intuition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One may enter the world of the Neoplatonists expecting that traditional divinatory thinking will find fertile ground. This ancient school, after all, advanced ideas on union with the divine, spiritual ascent through contemplative<italic>askêsis</italic>, and the practice of theurgy. But the expectation is not exactly met. It is something of a enigma, which the prior work allows us to understand better. The most serious Neoplatonic thinker on the question, Iamblichus, will advance restrained views toward traditional divination, and will even be ready to toss aside the whole practice. He expresses these nuances while vigorously embracing a newly configured notion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconsidering Penelope</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though they have different ideas on how exactly it works and how to value it, the Greek philosophers considered here show a consistent understanding of traditional divinatory insight as the result of an ancillary form of cognition that takes place outside our self-conscious, purposive thinking. It enters into our awareness and offers incremental insight into what is around the corner. They construe it as a feature of human nature, as embedded in physiological processes that have to do with our status as embodied organisms situated in a surrounding atmosphere of stimuli. It relies on mechanisms buried deep in our natural</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX LOCORUM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xs0v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SUBJECT INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
