<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnn8d8</collection-id>
      <volume>72</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL467.B73 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ancestor worship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ancestral Memory in Early China</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brashier</surname>
               <given-names>K. E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674056077</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684170562</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684170567</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dnnb5m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ancestral ritual in early China was an orchestrated dance between what was present (the offerings and the living) and what was absent (the ancestors). The interconnections among the tangible elements of the sacrifice were overt and almost mechanical, but extending those connections to the invisible guests required a medium that was itself invisible. Thus in early China, ancestral sacrifice was associated with focused thinking about the ancestors, with a structured mental effort by the living to reach out to the absent forebears and to give them shape and existence. Thinking about the ancestors—about those who had become distant—required active deliberation and meditation, qualities that had to be nurtured and learned. This study is a history of the early Chinese ancestral cult, particularly its cognitive aspects. Its goals are to excavate the cult’s color and vitality and to quell assumptions that it was no more than a simplistic and uninspired exchange of food for longevity, of prayers for prosperity. Ancestor worship was not, the author contends, merely mechanical and thoughtless. Rather, it was an idea system that aroused serious debates about the nature of postmortem existence, served as the religious backbone to Confucianism, and may even have been the forerunner of Daoist and Buddhist meditation practices.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>K. E. B.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tables and Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conventions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Han Tree of Knowledge</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Near the end of the<italic>Huainanzi</italic>淮南子 compiled in the mid-second century bce, the ideal exemplary ruler is likened to a person who quietly plays the role of ancestral spirit in a sacrifice. The sacrificers bustle around him as they ready their offerings, but he himself remains motionless in dignified stillness like the eye at the center of a storm:</p>
                     <p>今夫祭者，屠割烹殺，剝狗燒豕，調平五味，庖也；陳簠簋，列尊 俎，設籩豆者，祝也；齊明盛服，淵默而不言，神之所依者，尸也。</p>
                     <p>In sacrifice, it is the cook who butchers and hacks, boils and pares, who skins the dog and roasts the pig, who blends and balances the five flavors. It is the invocator who sets out the round and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part I</label>
                     <title>An Imaginary Yardstick for Ritual Performance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alongside the hundreds of definitions for religion in modern scholarship, there are almost as many explanations for ritual. That is, not only is there no consensus as to what religion is, but there is just as little agreement as to what constitutes the practice of it. Among the structuralist, functionalist, phenomenologist and psychoanalytical approaches to ritual, the relatively recent discussions on “performance theory” have been most promising in terms of usefulness, likening ritual to a kind of interactive theater that highlights 1.) ritual’s experiential side, 2.) its framing techniques and 3.) the seemingly complete microcosm it endeavors to offer. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part II</label>
                     <title>A History of Remembering and Forgetting Imperial Ancestors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In plumbing the nature of early Chinese religions, the Introduction focused upon how diverse idea systems were regarded as springing up from a common root; in probing the role of ritual, Part I drew upon modern performance theory, which highlights ritual’s experiential side, its framing techniques and the microcosm it endeavors to offer. Yet besides saying that ritual is the “doing” of religion, how does the religion in the Introduction ultimately relate to performance ritual in Part I? The anthropologist Roy Rappaport has fruitfully unpacked the content of religion and related it to ritual by sorting out its elements into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part III</label>
                     <title>A Spectrum of Interpretations on Afterlife Existence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a<italic>Songs canon</italic>hymn entitled “Fullness” (“Na” 那), the filial descendant offers up a musical invitation to the spirits using drums, pipes and bells—invitational music that “lets us realize our thoughts” (<italic>sui wo si cheng</italic>綏我 思成).¹ In another hymn entitled “Illustrious ancestors” (“Liezu” 烈祖), alcoholic offerings bring the spirits down to us and again “allow us to realize our thoughts” (<italic>lai wo si cheng</italic>賚我思成).² By channeling the mind, music invited the spirits. According to the influential commentary by the Eastern Han exegete Zheng Xuan, the pacified mind first endured several days of pre-sacrificial meditations and abstentions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part IV</label>
                     <title>The Context of Early Chinese Performative Thinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When discussing texts that closely intertwine memory and spirits, Part III used the phrase “performative thinking” for thinking that, in and of itself, directly impacts the environment outside the thinker. As already noted, I adapted this notion from J. D. Austin’s “performative utterances,” utterances that, by Austin’s own definition, do not merely report about or stimulate an act but are the very execution of the act itself, such as when someone pledges “I do” in a marriage ceremony or is pronounced “Guilty!” at a trial.¹ The celebratory wedding or the courtroom drama are highly ritualized institutions in modern society, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part V</label>
                     <title>The Symbolic Language of Fading Memories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because cultures express ideas using more than just written words, textoriented historians can have great difficulty in understanding and communicating the “meaning” of some of the most basic components of experiences past. Past experiences are often measured in difficult-to-articulate symbols rather than words, and Lakoff and Johnson argue that humans tend to rely more upon such symbols when a particular idea cannot be clearly defined by experience in any direct fashion. They write that “we tend to structure the less concrete and inherently vaguer concepts (like those for the emotions) in terms of more concrete concepts, which are more clearly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>Mind the Gap</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>346</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Death naturally entails absence in terms of both space, because the dead are no longer within sight, and time, because the point of death ever recedes into the past. But what else can be said about how this absence is manifested? For the surviving lineage, the lacuna may require restructuring family authority; for the individual descendant, it leads to forgetfulness as details about the dead gradually fade and memories blur. Furthermore this absence brought about by death is of course an<italic>undesired</italic>occurrence. The spatial and temporal absence, the disrupted lineage, the fading memory and our feelings of loss are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>439</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>465</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dnnb5m.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
