<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT701.3 .O23 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theological anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Children of God in the World</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>O’Callaghan</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229003</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229010</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1hrdn0m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Children of God in the World is a textbook of theological anthropology structured in four parts. The first attempts to clarify the relationship between theology, philosophy and science in their respective approaches to anthropology, and establishes the fundamental principle of the text, stated in Vatican II's Gaudium et spes, n. 22, "Christ manifests man to man." The second part provides a historical overview of the doctrine of grace: in Scripture (especially the teaching of the book of Genesis on humans 'made in the image of God', as well as Paul and John), among the Fathers (in particular the oriental doctrine of 'divinization' and Augustine), during the Middle Ages (especially Thomas Aquinas) and the Reformation period (centered particularly on Luther and the Council of Trent), right up to modern times. The third part of the text, the central one, provides a systematic understanding of Christian grace in terms of the God's life present in human believers by which they become children of God, disciples, friends and brothers of Christ, temples of the Holy Spirit. This section also provides a reflection on the theological virtues (faith, hope and charity), on the relationship between grace and human freedom, on the role of the Church and Christian apostolate in the communication of grace, and on the need humans have for divine grace. After considering the relationship between the natural and the supernatural order, the fourth and last part deals with different philosophical aspects of the human condition, in the light of Christian faith: the union between body and soul, humans as free, historical, social, sexual and working beings. The last chapter concludes with a consideration of the human person, Christianity's greatest and most enduring contribution to human thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PRINCIPAL ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This treatise on theological anthropology works off of five presuppositions. The first is that<italic>it is based on a search for unity and integrity</italic>. As we inquire into human identity, we commonly experience a wearying sense of complexity and incertitude. However, this does not mean that our explanation of human nature and of the human person need be involved or complicated. In fact, anthropology seeks above all a once-off, simple, unitary, integrated explanation of human identity. The search for truth, in fact, is always a search for unity, for simplicity, for harmony, for coherence. In other words, in order to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>SITUATING ANTHROPOLOGY AMONG SCIENCE, PHILOSOPHY, AND THEOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Humans inevitably want to know themselves, they want to know about the meaning of their life, they want to know their identity, their inner truth, their destiny. On the basis of this knowledge they desire and attempt to achieve their ultimate identity, to realize themselves. I have used the terms “to know” and “to achieve” because all persons, as they know themselves and act, experience a discrepancy between the concrete situation they are in (their present identity or situation, concrete, finite, and mundane) and an ultimate ideal to which they aspire (a fullness of identity that is definitive, ideal, or,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>HISTORICAL PERSPECTIVES ON HUMANITY IN SEARCH OF IMMORTALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first chapter we considered anthropology from a phenomenological angle, attempting to answer three questions. What is the human being? Who is the human being? Why do we do anthropology? In this chapter we shall consider human nature from the standpoint of history: what different philosophies and religions have said of the human being. G. K. Chesterton spoke in a vivid way of the “democracy of the dead,” that is, of the contribution that epochs past can and should make to our understanding of the world and of history.⁴ Likewise, the philosopher Wilhelm Dilthey declared that “it is only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>JESUS CHRIST, THE REDEEMER:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Living Perspective for a Christian Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the constitution of Vatican Council II,<italic>Gaudium et Spes</italic>, we read the following programmatic text: “In reality it is only in the mystery of the Word made flesh that the mystery of man truly becomes clear. For Adam, the first man, was a type of him who was to come, Christ the Lord. Christ the new Adam, in the very revelation of the mystery of the Father and of his love, fully reveals man to himself and brings to light his most high calling.”² Karol Wojtyła, later Pope John Paul II, considers this text as “a key point of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>THE HUMAN BEING ACCORDING TO SCRIPTURE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Image of God and Son of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scripture does not have a developed and systematic anthropology. Yet both Testaments speak of the human being in a wide variety of ways.³ This is especially so in the first book of the Bible, Genesis, which recounts the creation of the universe, the first stage of the Covenant that God established with his people and with humanity as a whole regarding its origin, its life, its Fall, and the promise of salvation. The fact that these texts are situated at the very beginning of scripture, though they are not the earliest ones of the Old Testament, is not without significance.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>GRACE AND JUSTIFICATION OF THE SINNER IN PAUL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us now consider the doctrine of grace in the<italic>corpus paulinum</italic>.¹ In the face of human sinfulness and the presumptuous attitude humans often have in performing “good works,” the apostle to the Gentiles insists above all on humans’ absolute need for the grace of Christ, God’s pure gift, in order to be saved. Grace places us in a new state by means of a “new creation” in which we become children of God through the power of the Holy Spirit and are freed from sin and slavery, introduced into a new life, and moved to witness our faith before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>GRACE AS “ETERNAL LIFE” IN JOHN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The letters of John speak of divine grace in a variety of ways. On the one hand, the evangelist seldom uses the term “grace”; he does so only on three occasions, in fact.¹ The first is in John 1:14: “And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, full of grace and truth.” It is interesting to note how “grace” and “truth” are closely associated in this passage.² The second is as follows: “From his fullness we have all received, grace upon grace” (Jn 1:16): what the Word possesses in fullness, grace, he communicates generously to humanity. And on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>DIVINIZING GRACE IN THE EASTERN PATRISTIC TRADITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early centuries of Christian theology, the doctrine of grace developed in two principal, fundamentally convergent, directions. First, as a maturation of the teaching of Paul and John in the light of the pastoral and intellectual challenges of the Church’s mission in different situations,⁴ particularly in the context of the Gnostic heresy. And second, as a kind of “developed Christology”: divine grace is described and understood on the basis of the insertion and manifestation of the life of Christ in believers, as the direct fruit of the incarnation of the Word, which makes the believer become a son or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>GRACE, SIN, AND GOOD WORKS IN AUGUSTINE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To situate the teaching on grace of Augustine, bishop of Hippo,<italic>Doctor gratiae</italic>, first of all we need to consider the teaching of Pelagius, his principal adversary in the area of Christian spirituality and anthropology. Then we shall consider Augustine’s own theology and finally the influence it had on Church teaching, on the question of semi-Pelagianism, and on that of predestination.⁴</p>
                     <p>Pelagius, a Breton monk who lived between the fourth and fifth centuries, of Stoic formation,⁵ a commentator on Paul, went to Rome in 380 A.D. and dedicated his best energies to spiritual guidance and Church reform. Like many others,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>“CREATED GRACE” IN THE MEDIEVAL PERIOD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three aspects of Augustine’s understanding of the workings of Christian grace may be noted: the priority of divine action (what would later be designated as “uncreated grace”), the human experience of grace (Augustine speaks of the<italic>suavitas amoris</italic>), and human ethical action that derives from grace. According to Augustine, anterior divine action—grace—produces a<italic>delectatio</italic>, a pleasing spiritual inclination in the soul, and divinizes believers<italic>suaviter et fortiter</italic>(gently and firmly), moving them through love to carry out good works. Not only that: it is<italic>grace itself</italic>that carries out the divine actions in humans.</p>
                     <p>The spiritual vigor and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>GRACE AND JUSTIFICATION IN LUTHER AND THE COUNCIL OF TRENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The different ways of understanding grace during the medieval period prepare the way decisively for the radical change in Western Christianity that took place with the Protestant Reformation and the Council of Trent, the fruit of which was the Catholic Counter-Reformation. Let us consider first the doctrine of grace in the most important theologian of the Reformation, Martin Luther, and then in the Council of Trent.</p>
                     <p>Many currents of thought and spirituality prepared the way for Luther’s teaching on grace and anthropology.³ In the first place,<italic>nominalism</italic>. This philosophical vision, briefly explained in the last chapter, was very much present</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>THE MODERN PERIOD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Grace, Freedom, and Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The principal theological issue of the period that immediately followed Luther and Trent involved the relationship between grace and freedom. This is an expression of the tension, already present throughout the Middle Ages, between a transcendent, omnipotent God, on the one hand, and created human beings, who, though fallen, search for their rightful, God-given autonomy, on the other. Three episodes are of particular interest during the period: the<italic>de auxiliis</italic>controversy; the Augustinianism of Michael Baius, a theologian who worked in the years after Trent; and the theology of the seventeenth-century bishop Cornelius O. Jansen. Although in many ways Protestant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>THE HISTORICAL WORKING OUT OF GOD’S PROJECT TO ESTABLISH AN INTIMATE AND PERPETUAL FILIAL COMMUNION OF HUMANS WITH THE TRINITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we read scripture we come to recognize, at the heart of the mystery of God’s relationship with humans, a project of grace, a project of gratuitous and intimate love, which not only calls humans to existence but also invites them to share in the life of the Trinity, in a communion with the divine that is destined to last for ever. The content of this “project of grace” in favor of humans is mysteriously summed up in the person of Christ, the Word of God made man, and is communicated to them through the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>CHILDREN OF GOD IN THE HOLY SPIRIT:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Life of Grace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Grace has God as its origin, as its only source. Grace is simply the life of God in humans. As we saw in the last chapter, grace is present at every stage of human life; it presides over a wide-ranging historical narrative composed of different stages that are, while distinct, inseparable from one another: creation, predestination in Christ, divine call, justification of the person and his gradual purification from sin, and, finally, eschatological communion with the Trinity in glory. We considered them in the previous chapter.</p>
                     <p>Of course Christian grace, which is the result of God’s action, enters into a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>DIVINE LIFE IN HUMANS:</title>
                     <subtitle>God’s “Inhabitation” of Man’s Soul and “Created Grace”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have considered the life of grace from the perspective of its one and only origin, God: the project or plan of divine love that finds its first expression in the work of creation is expressed in terms of predestination and calling, and culminates in justification and glorification. In the previous chapter we considered the fundamental condition of human beings in grace, that is, adopted divine filiation, with its Christological and pneumatological (and therefore Trinitarian) structure.</p>
                     <p>Still, scripture speaks of grace as present and active in humans using a wide variety of expressions, mainly Biblical in origin, that refer openly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>GRACE AND CHRISTIAN LIFE:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Infused Virtues and Gifts of the Holy Spirit</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have just considered what might be called the “objective-metaphysical” side of grace: humans, through the gift of God, are transformed, ontologically elevated, renewed to the depths of their being and faculties by divine grace. On the basis of this elevation we shall now consider the “psychological-moral” side of the life of grace, that is, the renewal that God brings about within the faculties and actions of the human person. In effect, with grace God infuses truly divine powers into the soul, usually called “infused virtues,” powers with which Christians act as God’s children in a truly Christ-like and pneumatological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>GRACE AND HUMAN FREEDOM:</title>
                     <subtitle>Justification, Merit, Experience, and Mediations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding chapters we considered God’s love for us in terms of “uncreated grace” and God as one who gives himself to humans, adopting them as his children in the Holy Spirit. Then we looked into the dynamics of the supernatural organism, fruit of God’s action, which remains stably present and active in believers; this is often referred to as “created grace.” But another important issue still needs to be considered, an articulated and complex one that refers to the relationship between divine grace and free human response, what we have called the personal-existential aspect of the life of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>THE NEED FOR DIVINE GRACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After having spoken of the life of divine grace in humans and their free response, this part of the book shall be concluded by presenting an overview of an issue that, though obvious, is central to this treatise: that of the need for grace to obtain salvation and live in communion with the Trinity. Without God’s gift of grace, humans are simply not justified or saved. God’s grace holds absolute primacy in Christian life, it stands above all the rest.</p>
                     <p>Two complementary perspectives lie behind the affirmation that we stand in need of grace. One is of a more ontological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>THE NATURAL AND THE SUPERNATURAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this fourth and last section of the book we shall consider what it means to be human<italic>in the light of Christian faith</italic>or, more concretely, in the light of saving grace, that is, the life of Christ present in the believer. The previous section dealt with grace in a strict sense and was based simply on Christian revelation. This one will consider a series of issues that are also the object of philosophical and scientific reflection. In chapter 1 they were called “mixed questions.” We shall attempt here to offer a Christian response to the great issues humans</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>THE HUMAN BEING:</title>
                     <subtitle>Union of Body and Soul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>406</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far we have spoken of the human being as a unity, that is, simply, as a person. However, when it comes to describing human nature, all scientific, philosophical, and theological anthropologies speak in a variety of different ways of the different “components” that go to make up the human being, for the most part using terms such as “soul” (or “spirit”) and “body.” More recently it has become common to speak of the “mind” or the “brain.” Humans, we are told, are composed of two fundamental elements or aspects, more or less linked with one another, the body and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>THE GIFT OF GOD AND HUMAN FREEDOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>God made humans in his image and likeness (Gn 1:27). The first consequence of God’s act is the imperative invitation humans receive to exercise dominion over the earth as he blesses them. Under God’s sovereign power, though as his children, they receive the capacity and responsibility of administering the entire material universe.⁶ That is to say, humans live before God as responsible beings in that they respond to what they have received. According to scripture, the task and mission humans receive to exercise dominion over the earth is not of a merely external or transitory kind because they are also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>THE TEMPORALITY AND HISTORICITY OF THE HUMAN BEING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>472</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have spoken frequently in previous chapters of human nature, that is, of those aspects of the human being that are, as it were, stable, fixed, inalterable, what might be called the physical, biological, psychological, and spiritual DNA of humans: their corporeal, intellectual, volitive, social, religious nature, all of which respond to the question “What is the human being?” Common nature is the foundational aspect of human life that makes all sociality and communication possible. In effect, humans are in a position, for better or for worse, to communicate with one another because they share the same nature. And nature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>MAN CREATED IN THE IMAGE OF GOD, A SOCIAL BEING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>495</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That humans are social beings who relate closely to those of their own species is more than obvious. That human sociality has been considered throughout the history of anthropology as something deeply ambivalent, however, is undeniable. In this chapter we shall attempt to describe certain moments of this history of the reality and ambivalence of the social condition. Then we shall consider how the fact of human sociality and its dynamism may be interpreted in the light of faith in order to understand its origin, purpose, and inner meaning. Finally we shall attempt to clarify the notion of human sociality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>HUMANS CREATED IN THE IMAGE OF GOD AS MAN AND WOMAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>514</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most obvious distinctions between persons is the sexual one, between man and woman, between male and female. Sexual difference manifests itself not only physiologically, but also psychologically and with differentiating features in the areas of affectivity and cognition.⁴ In this chapter, however, we cannot consider in depth the complex issues that refer to the psychological, sociological, and human differences between men and women and the corresponding myriad social implications, but rather we shall consider the theological statute of the difference, considering it on the basis of the creation of human persons, of their present action, of their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>HUMANS, MADE IN THE IMAGE OF GOD, AT WORK IN THE WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>537</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Orthodox author Nicholas Berdjaev made the following observation:</p>
                     <p>Labor is the greatest reality of human life in this world, it is a primary reality.… In labor there is both a truth of redemption (“in the sweat of your face shall you gain your bread”) and a truth of the creative and constructive power of men. Both elements are present in labor. Human labor humanizes nature; it bears witness to the great mission of man in nature. But sin and evil have perverted the mission of labor. A reverse process has taken place in the dehumanization of labor, an alienation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>THE HUMAN PERSON:</title>
                     <subtitle>Christianity’s Contribution to Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>552</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Coming to the last chapter of this text, we shall return to the question dealt with in the first chapter: who is the human being? In the light of Christian faith in divine grace through Christ, the reply must be: the human person, Christianity’s foremost contribution to anthropology.</p>
                     <p>In the first place, as we already saw, humans exist and live as beings in relationship, social beings,<italic>ens ab alio</italic>, or, better,<italic>ens</italic>(or<italic>entia</italic>)<italic>ab Alio</italic>. In effect, humans have been created in the image and likeness of God, constituted in complete ontological dependence on the creator, yet are capable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECTED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>569</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF NAMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>571</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GENERAL INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>589</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hrdn0m.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>597</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
