<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B829.5.D55 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophers</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Interviews</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Quiet Powers of the Possible: Interviews in Contemporary French Phenomenology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DIKA</surname>
               <given-names>TAREK R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HACKETT</surname>
               <given-names>W. CHRIS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823264711</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823264759</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19rm9fx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Quiet Powers of the Possible offers an excellent introduction to contemporary French phenomenology through a series of interviews with its most prominent figures. Guided by rigorous questions that push into the most important aspects of the latest phenomenological research, the book gives readers a comprehensive sense of each thinker's intellectual history, motivations, and philosophical commitments. The book introduces readers to debates that have not previously been accessible to the English-speaking world, such as the growing interest in the phenomenological concept of life in its affective and even vital dimensions, the emerging dialogue with the analytic philosophy of mind and language, and reassessments of the so-called theological turn. The diversity of approaches collected here has its origin in a deeper debate about the conceptual and historical foundations of phenomenology itself. In this way the book offers the most accessible and wide-ranging introduction to French phenomenology to have appeared in the English-speaking world to date.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEARNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this work comes from a closing line in Heidegger’s<italic>Being and Time</italic>. He is speaking of the future of phenomenology as a promise of things to come—a sentiment already anticipated in an opening claim of the book: “In phenomenology possibility stands higher than actuality.”¹ For Heidegger this spelled a revolutionary reversal of the old metaphysical paradigm of being as presence, substance, and act and a radical openness to new kinds of questioning.</p>
                     <p>The first generation of French phenomenologists was deeply influenced by this opening. Or, to be more precise, by the momentous legacy of the three</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology and the Concept of Reason</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DIKA</surname>
                           <given-names>TAREK R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HACKETT</surname>
                           <given-names>W. CHRIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The American reception of contemporary French phenomenology, however fecund, has been both selective and cloistered. For many, the “theological turn,” an expression initially coined as an epithet by Dominique Janicaud (and that, like many epithets, has become something of a rallying cry this side of the Atlantic), unquestionably represents what, for better or worse, distinguishes phenomenology from other trends in contemporary philosophy, be they French or Anglo-American. No doubt, French phenomenology has demonstrated a remarkable capacity for describing phenomena hitherto deemed beyond the pale of reason. But according to what (or whose) concept of reason? Whether phenomenology has gone beyond</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>French Phenomenology in Historical Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COURTINE</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-FRANÇOIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>For over twenty years (1987–2009), you were director of the Archives Husserl de Paris at the École normale supérieure, which has historically been an important center of phenomenological research in France. From this position, you have a unique vantage point on the present state of French phenomenology and its future. Are there certain pertinent moments to the story of phenomenology in France that stand out to you over the course of these last three decades?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Archives Husserl de Paris, a research center at the Centre national de la recherche scientifique (CNRS), was in fact “refounded,” so to speak,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Phenomenology of Givenness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARION</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-LUC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Did you begin studying phenomenology (as a student) immediately?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Not at all.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>What brought you to phenomenology?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was studying history, French literature, Latin, Greek, and so on in the<italic>classe préparatoire</italic>for the École normale supérieure’s compulsory admissions exam. At that time, my “major,” so to speak, was, in fact, French literature. So when I was admitted to the École Normale my initial plan was to study literature. And for two years—I was very fortunate but not aware of how fortunate I was—I had Jean Beaufret as my teacher, one of Heidegger’s closest friends. He was very</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Fundamental Concepts of Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROMANO</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAUDE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>In</italic>Au cœur de la raison,<italic>you reconstruct, both historically and systematically, the basic concepts of phenomenology from Husserl to Heidegger to Merleau-Ponty. What developments in contemporary philosophy are you responding to?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>It seems to me that one could diagnose a current crisis in philosophy that echoes Husserl’s statement at the beginning of the last century. On one side, the positivist paradigm that prevailed for a long time in the Anglophone philosophy of language, in the wake of a certain reading of the<italic>Tractatus</italic>and the work of the Vienna Circle, has reached exhaustion: not only the idea of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contextualism, Realism, and the Limits of Intentionality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BENOIST</surname>
                           <given-names>JOCELYN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Who were your teachers? What was the intellectual milieu of the École normale supérieure (ENS) like during your student days, and how did you find your way in and around that milieu? How would you mark the decisive moments in your intellectual development?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Didier Franck was my first philosophy mentor [<italic>maître en philosophie</italic>]. When I entered the École normale supérieure in 1986, his intellectual persona dominated the philosophy department. The context was rather morose. The great teachers of the 1960s or 1970s were dead or at least no longer involved. In a certain sense, what might be said to define</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Material Phenomenology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HENRY</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The following “interview” was compiled specifically for this volume by Jean Leclercq and Grégori Jean of the Fonds Michel Henry (which opened in 2010 at Université catholique de Louvain à Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium) from the body of available interviews conducted over the course of Henry’s life. Below, a preface to the “interview,” written by Leclercq and Jean, offers a brief picture of the basic motivations behind Henry’s work. We translate it here:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Although Michel Henry (1922–2002) attributed more importance to his published books than to other kinds of contributions, the various interviews that he gave, which themselves trace the significant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Phenomenology of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARBARAS</surname>
                           <given-names>RENAUD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>When and with whom did your interest in phenomenology begin?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>My interest in phenomenology was sparked very early on, in secondary school, when a professor had me read Heidegger and Merleau-Ponty. I didn’t understand it all, but I felt that this manner of thinking corresponded to what I was looking for in doing philosophy. Very early, I saw myself working on Merleau-Ponty, but while I was doing my studies at the École normale supérieure de Saint-Cloud (as well as at university), I found myself thrown into a very different atmosphere, one that was essentially hostile toward phenomenology. It was the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Phenomenology and Finitude</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DASTUR</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANÇOISE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>How did you come to phenomenology?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>In postwar France, secondary studies were still reserved for the children of the bourgeoisie. Coming from the working class, I was initially placed in trade school, but I managed—at the age of sixteen—to catch up with the “classic” stream [<italic>filière classique</italic>] and get into a school where one prepared for the<italic>baccalauréat</italic>.¹ I had the good fortune of being introduced to philosophy by Monique Dixsaut,² my high school professor, who is today considered to be the greatest contemporary specialist on Plato in France. It was her first year of teaching, and it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Phenomenology and the Frontier</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LACOSTE</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-YVES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>You have characterized your work as the exploration of the “frontier zone” between philosophy and theology, where the boundaries between them are no longer meaningful. Reflecting on your work as a whole, one might further say that your theoretical task has been to investigate, by means of phenomenology, the reaches of philosophical reflection in light of what you have called the “liturgical possibility.” What kind of possibility does the “liturgical” refer to and how does it relate to the frontier between philosophy and theology?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>“Liturgical” is often poorly understood, as if my ambition were to produce a phenomenology of worship.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Collision of Phenomenology and Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FALQUE</surname>
                           <given-names>EMMANUEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>What, to your mind, distinguishes—historically and philosophically—the various generations of French phenomenology from one another?</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>We may certainly speak of a second generation of French phenomenologists, and perhaps also a third, if we count among the first Emmanuel Lévinas, Michel Henry, and Paul Ricoeur; among the second Jean-Luc Marion, Jean-Yves Lacoste, Jean-Louis Chrétien, and Didier Franck; and among the third Claude Romano, myself, and others. In reality, a difference in context marks the distance between these different generations. The first generation, which developed in the aftermath of World War II, remained closely tied to the works of Husserl</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Attempting to Think Beyond Subjectivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHRÉTIEN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-LOUIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CAMILLE RIQUIER:<italic>Your philosophical formation was first made in the school of phenomenology. Can it be said that phenomenology therefore gives to your path of thinking its unity of inspiration? Is Heidegger your great teacher, even more than Husserl, and perhaps against him?</italic>¹</p>
                     <p>The life of the mind is composed entirely of encounters, of having to report them and to be accountable to them [<italic>d’avoir à y répondre, comme à en répondre</italic>]—up to our very last breath, where only our formation is interrupted, which does not form us for time alone. But for this we need a language or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19rm9fx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
