<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Biblical Knowing</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Scriptural Epistemology of Error</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Johnson</surname>
               <given-names>Dru</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bartholomew</surname>
               <given-names>Craig G.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174388</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902301</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Dru Johnson</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf65j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Christian Scriptures could be theologically described as beginning and ending with an epistemological outlook. The first episode of humanity’s activity centers on the knowledge of good and evil. The final stage of humanity is pictured by Jeremiah as a universally prophetic and knowing society: 'And no longer shall each one teach his neighbor and each his brother, saying, 'Know the Lord', for they shall all know me, from the least of them to the greatest, declares the Lord' (Jer 31:34). What happens to knowledge in between? In this work, Dru Johnson reconsiders epistemology with the tool of biblical theology: an approach to knowledge as developed in Genesis 2 and explored throughout the Tanakh (i.e., the Old Testament) and New Testament. By re-examining the neglected idea that Christian Scripture might be developing robust descriptions of knowing that can direct us today, the ambition of this book is to lay the groundwork for a biblical theology of knowledge - how knowledge is broached, described, and how error is rectified within the texts of the Christian canon. Proper knowing as it occurs in the Scriptures means that there are better and worse ways to know. Even more, the epistemology that is found to be advocated in Scripture is not relegated to religious knowing. Johnson argues that scientific epistemology and biblical epistemology make significant points of contact suggesting that they are fundamentally consistent with each other.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bartholomew</surname>
                           <given-names>Craig G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Runner</surname>
                           <given-names>H. Evan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a privilege to write the foreword to Dru Johnson’s creative and excellent work on<italic>Biblical Knowing</italic>. I had the privilege of being his external examiner for his PhD and am glad to see his work there now gathering further momentum in this impressive book.</p>
                     <p>Recent decades have witnessed a remarkable renaissance in Christian philosophy, a development unimaginable some thirty years ago. This renaissance has yielded a whole new generation of young Christian philosophers who are steadily making their mark. Dru is one of them. Amidst this renaissance a neglected element has been the relationship between Scripture and philosophy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Christian Scriptures could be theologically described as beginning and ending with an epistemological outlook. The first episode of humanity’s activity centers on the knowledge of good and evil. The final stage of humanity is pictured by Jeremiah as a universally prophetic and knowing society: “And no longer shall each one teach his neighbor and each his brother, saying, ‘Know the Lord,’ for they shall all know me, from the least of them to the greatest, declares the Lord” (Jer 31: 34). What happens to knowledge in between? We intend to hash out epistemology with the tool of biblical theology:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>How Should We Conceive of Knowledge and Error?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We walk by faith and not by sight (2 Cor 5:7). What does this mean? Certainly, picturing the Christian life as a walk fits within the collective imagination of the biblical writers. But what are we to do with Paul’s juxtaposition of faith and sight? Regardless of the Apostle Paul’s intended meaning, a common Christian interpretation has pictured something akin to “faith as a blind walk.” Depicting the Christian life as a walk, where Believers grow in knowledge of the Creator and His creation, certainly fits the biblical picture. From ancient Israelite faith to its extension into Christianity, the metaphor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Knowledge in the Garden:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 2</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Take a long look at this X-ray film.¹ In it, the bullet that wounded President Theodore Roosevelt can be seen. Actually, the bullet cannot be seen by just anyone. While anyone can see<italic>something</italic>, we want to know exactly what we are seeing. If it were not for the physician, Dr. Hochreim, trained to read radiographs who also knew the historical context of the X-ray film (i.e., it was to get a look inside Roosevelt’s chest) and marked the film for us, we would only see the bare outline of what we presume to be someone’s chest. Only by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Error in the Garden:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genesis 3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It must be admitted at the outset: Pursuing an abstract idea like knowledge in the Edenic account of the Fall is audacious. A prominent Christian philosopher once warned me that any attempt to derive a philosophical view<italic>from</italic>the Scriptures is a fundamentally asinine attempt. Before we attempt this particular asinine feat from the error in the Garden, let us first consider a direct implication of knowing in the Fall which happened on the top of a mountain: The Transfiguration of Jesus.</p>
                     <p>The Transfiguration accounts that come to us through the Synoptic Gospels are uniform in most of their narrative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Erroneous Knowing in Exodus and Beyond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far, we have attempted to show that the canon is concerned to portray an epistemological process at the very outset of humanity’s history. What does the Tanakh then do with this view of knowing throughout its texts? Stated otherwise, is the epistemological process of Genesis 2–3 unique or normative? We contend below that Scripture recounts Israel’s errors in terms of Genesis 2–3, where knowing is contingent upon which authority is being heeded, and then whether or not the knower participates in the prescribed route to knowledge (e.g., not eating the fruit of prohibition). Proper knowing happens when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Knowing under the Prophet-Messiah:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mark, Luke, and John</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the prior chapters, we have offered a view of knowing as a process that begins with listening to accredited authorities and then enacting their directions in order to see. Submission and praxis are not novel concepts in the history of Judaism or Christianity (or any religion for that matter). However, the idea that accredited authorities, process, and embodied participation form the centerpiece of all proper knowing is a more radical proposition.</p>
                     <p>In the coming chapters, we will argue that the biblical epistemology we are exploring here is fully commensurate with Polanyi’s scientific epistemology. Hence, Scripture’s description of knowing is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Scientific Epistemology, Wisdom, and the Epistles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the next two chapters, we will take a dramatic turn toward recent scholarship in epistemology. We have examined both the historical books of the Tanakh and the Gospel accounts in which an epistemological process is present, relevant, and persistent. Early on, we made the claim that this view should not be reduced to a religious epistemology, but that it covers knowing writ large. In this chapter, we want to argue that there is an extant view of scientific epistemology that provides us with an overlapping model of what we see in the Christian Scriptures. How scientists know, as an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Broad Reality and Contemporary Epistemology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having proffered evidence for a particular epistemological process which the Scriptures are keen to develop, our attention must now turn to engaging the various conversations about epistemology today. Most of these epistemologies can be championed by atheist and theist philosophers alike. But the controlling question for the next two chapters is: What view of epistemology best serves the theological enterprise concerned to reflect these biblical texts?</p>
                     <p>Thus far, we have argued that the epistemological process found in the Scriptures appears to have monolithic features that span across Scripture: authority, authentication, embodiment, participation, and maximic direction in order to know. Of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Analytic Theology and Biblical Scholarship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the prior chapter, we were hesitant about appropriating any of the analytic epistemologies surveyed because they appeared incapable of addressing the broad sense of knowing required to do theology. However, there is a burgeoning group of philosophers and theologians who are advocating that theology might benefit from being more like analytic philosophy, at least, more like the analytic method. This most recent effort to encourage Christian theologians toward the analytic method was captured by the anthology<italic>Analytic Theology</italic>. Yet the question seemingly absent in the philosophy of religion and among analytic theologians has been: What do the sacred texts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Implications for Theologians and the Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the purpose of this text, it is impossible to describe all of the implications of the epistemological process as proposed here. But, in an effort to show the practical matters that have to do with the lives of theologians, philosophers, teachers, pastors, and more, we will briefly consider some reflections and paint pictures of what knowing looks like as a real life process. Further, we will describe some reverberations from thinking about the church’s normal activities as epistemological processes, seeking to enliven our wisdom together in the church.</p>
                     <p>For those familiar with the work of T. F. Torrance, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf65j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
