<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1c84fqp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Dietrich Bonhoeffer and the Ethical Self</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christology, Ethics, and Formation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Elliston</surname>
               <given-names>Clark J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451496260</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451496265</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506418940</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506418945</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c84fqp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s work has persistently challenged Christian consciousness due to both his death at the hands of the Nazis and his provocative prison musings about Christian faithfulness in late modernity. Although understandable given the popularity of both narrative trajectories, such selective focus obscures the depth and fecundity of his overall corpus. Bonhoeffer’s early work, and particularly his Christocentric anthropology, grounds his later expressed commitments to responsibility and faithfulness in a “world come of age." While much debate accompanies claims regarding the continuity of Bonhoeffer’s thought, there are central motifs which pervade his work from his doctoral dissertation to the prison writings. This book suggests that a concern for otherness permeates all of Bonhoeffer’s work. Furthermore, Clark Elliston articulates, drawing on Bonhoeffer, a Christian self-defined by its orientation towards otherness. Taking Bonhoeffer as both the origin and point of return, the text engages Emmanuel Levinas and Simone Weil as dialogue partners who likewise stress the role of the other for self-understanding, albeit in diverse ways. By reading Bonhoeffer “through" their voices, one enhances Bonhoeffer’s already fertile understanding of responsibility.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dietrich Bonhoeffer, in his essay “Ethics as Formation,” describes the precarious position of ethics in his context. He writes,</p>
                     <p>Today we have villains and saints again, in public view.… That evil appears in the form of light, of beneficence, of faithfulness, of renewal, that it appears in the form of historical necessity, of social justice, is for the commonsense observer a clear confirmation of its profound evilness. Ethical theorists, on the other hand, are blinded by it. With their preconceived concepts they cannot grasp what is real, let alone seriously encounter something whose essence and power they don’t even recognize.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Considering Contemporary Selves:</title>
                     <subtitle>Two Approaches</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bonhoeffer’s account of the ethical self has become even more apropos with the onset of “postmodernity.” While this term is perhaps too disputed to be helpful, it heralds increased skepticism regarding the concept of selfhood. Important for the Christian theologian is the question of how God impacts the self. Two texts of particular relevance to this proposed consideration of theological selfhood stand out. They provide tools for considering the concept of an ethically oriented self. Specifically, these texts present the concept of ethical selfhood not as the fruit of reflection on oneself, but as engagement with an “other” who encounters</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Bonhoeffer and the Responsibly Oriented Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although Bonhoeffer only implicitly frames his ethical insights in terms of orientation, his work exhibits an abiding concern for the self–other relation, particularly through his account of human “being for others.” Moreover, this concern for a responsible relation to the other constitutes a theme within most of his main writings. Focusing on and parsing this understanding of human being as structured toward others will guide staged conversations with Emmanuel Levinas and Simone Weil. The first section of the chapter explores Bonhoeffer’s concept of the “self” as the person who exists in the world. This section begins with the human person</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Bound to the Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bonhoeffer and Levinas in Conversation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’s persistent return to otherness, as well as the responsibility this return demands, provides a formidable challenge for both theology and philosophy. Yet, I argue that Bonhoeffer meets this challenge by providing a robustly theological account of otherness. Specifically, Bonhoeffer’s construction of Christ as the mediator of personhood retains genuine otherness.</p>
                     <p>In brief, Bonhoeffer’s invocation of the other as a boundary to the self ensures that the “I,” as a fallen entity prone to possession and to violence toward the other, cannot extend its grasp to the other.¹ Nevertheless, Bonhoeffer safeguards the concrete reality of the other for whom the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Weil’s “Attention” and the Other-Oriented Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous three chapters outline the concept of an ethically oriented self, existing in responsibility for another. That ethically oriented self emerges primarily from discourse between Bonhoeffer and Levinas on the character and limits of responsibility. In this chapter, Weil’s concept of attention adds greater specificity to the self’s existence “for” the other. The first section of this chapter outlines the contours of Weil’s concept of attention, emphasizing the place of attention within Weil’s discussion of the self. Here, the stress is placed not on attention as a metaphysical idea, but as an ethical one.¹ By invoking Weil’s concept of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Adolf Eichmann as Personification of Irresponsibility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Hannah Arendt covered the trial of Nazi war criminal Adolf Eichmann on behalf of<italic>The New Yorker</italic>, her account evoked an enormous public response. Not only did she, in the eyes of her critics, blame Jews for complicity with Nazi authorities, she also cast Eichmann in a sympathetic light. Yet, these concerns partially obscured the philosophical force of her argument. How does someone so average become so evil? This final chapter uses Arendt’s depiction of Eichmann to establish a “negative” of an attentive, responsible self. Specifically, Arendt’s Eichmann personifies an ideal that is the opposite of Weil’s attentive self,¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fqp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
