<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">isis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Isis</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00211753</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456994</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3653207</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/507355</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">ISIS970211005</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
               <subj-group subj-group-type="subheading">
                  <subject>General</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Jan‐Melissa</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Schramm</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>June 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>97</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>isis.2006.97.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>341</fpage>
         <lpage>342</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Stephen </given-names>
               <surname>Kern</surname>
            </string-name>.<source>A Cultural History of Causality: Science, Murder Novels, and Systems of Thought</source>. 437 pp., bibl., index. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press,<year>2004.</year>$29.95 (cloth).</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/507355"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This is a thoughtful, wide‐ranging, and ambitious study by an author well established as an insightful cultural historian. Drawing on close and sensitive readings of a number of nineteenth‐ and twentieth‐century novels of homicide and detection, Stephen Kern charts a paradigmatic shift in the nature of fictional causality. Crime novels were chosen for the insight they might offer the historian into “new ways of rendering the causes and motives for human action,” and Kern traces a movement away from the “clear and strongly deterministic causal factors” (p. 4) favored by nineteenth‐century authors in the explanation of transgression toward greater complication and confusion in modernist representations of causal connection. He argues that a chronological reading of murder novels across his chosen period reveals a “multifaceted shift” in five interrelated ways—“namely, that causal understanding moved in the direction of increasing specificity [as a consequence of developments in forensic science, for example], multiplicity, increasing complexity, probability and uncertainty” (p. 6). In the eight chapters that follow, Kern marshals an enormous amount of evidence to trace these shifts in our understandings of the factors that may influence violent action—our ancestral inheritance, our childhood, the ways in which language or education construct our sense of the real or the actual, our sexuality, our emotions, our intellect, our interaction with society in a wider sense, and our ideological commitments. Kern’s range of reference is impressive, and he moves comfortably from the scientific to the literary, the prosaic to the poetic. He is well acquainted with contemporary developments in the ideas of chance, probability, and determinism, and, in particular, he writes knowledgeably of the consequences for fiction of the emergence of quantum theory in the first half of the twentieth century.</p>
      <p>Kern’s analysis is lucid and his thesis is ultimately persuasive. He argues that “the novel is emphatically historical in capturing a new sense of the complexity and uncertainty of causal understanding” as he traces the “sensitivity” of contemporary authors like Don DeLillo to “the significance of the new technologies of transportation, communication and investigation that transformed causal understanding in modern society” (p. 369). This is an observation with which many literary critics would agree. There are resemblances here to the methodology deployed by Ronald Thomas in his seminal and startlingly successful work<italic>Detective Fiction and the Rise of Forensic Science</italic>(Cambridge, 1999): narrative registers in its very construction the pressures of scientific and epistemological change. Yet a comparison with Thomas’s work reveals perhaps one of the few flaws of Kern’s study. If<italic>A Cultural History of Causality</italic>is directed toward the historian of science, one must question whether novels are ever really adequate source material for the construction of a hypothesis regarding nonfictional understandings of causality and probability. Paul Ricoeur reminds us in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>(Chicago, 1984–1988) that literature has been seen since ancient times as “an ethical laboratory where the artist pursues through the mode of fiction experimentation with values” (Vol. 1, p. 59): fiction is thus both tethered to, yet at the same time distinct from, the world of the actual and the real. Kern acknowledges this to be so, yet his theory of mimesis, of realistic representation, seems to exclude any genuine engagement with tropes of playfulness, indeterminacy, symbolism, and ambiguity that mark literature just as deeply as any desire to replicate the real. Kern notes that he relies “primarily on novels by male authors about male murderers, because [his] method is comparative and requires controlling variables to focus on historical change” (p. 21). This seems to evade a broader question about the extent to which novels can be understood as “evidence” in any sense at all, or whether Kern should be focusing on trial reports rather than their fictionalized representations. This difficulty would be obviated if the focus of the work were an understanding of the impact of developments in scientific theory on narrative form, yet Kern seems reluctant to move fully in this direction. And indeed, if the ideal reader of<italic>A Cultural History of Causality</italic>is in fact a literary critic, he or she may be inclined to probe a number of Kern’s other assumptions as well—he is perhaps a little too inclined to assert that the Victorian novel is artistically “tidy,” that its patterns of closure are always neat and carefully wrought, as an expression of what Thomas Vargish has called “the providential aesthetic” in his study of the same name (Virginia, 1985). Scholars of nineteenth‐century fiction may perhaps feel that Kern’s descriptions of such neat closures sit uncomfortably with their readings of<italic>Bleak House</italic>(which is as much about the loss and destruction of evidence as it is about its recovery and careful explication) or<italic>Our Mutual Friend</italic>or<italic>Daniel Deronda</italic>or<italic>The Brothers Karamazov</italic>(each of which problematizes our sense of a character’s relentless movement toward transgression, judgment, and punishment or acquittal). One is left with a sense that Kern occasionally deploys the term “Victorian” in a rather unsophisticated fashion: as Thomas has shown in<italic>Detective Fiction and the Rise of Forensic Science,</italic>even the most carefully crafted detective story of the nineteenth century can raise for readers and critics crucial questions about individual and national identity and the power of public surveillance. Yet these criticisms should not undermine a reader’s sense of Kern’s achievement in this book: it is a vast, ambitious attempt to effect a synthesis of scientific thought and literary experimentation, and on the whole it succeeds well.</p>
   </body>
</article>
