<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">histpolithou</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013883</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>History of Political Thought</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Imprint Academic</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0143781X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">20512988</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26215878</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>TRUST, PRUDENCE AND HISTORY: JOHN DUNN AND THE TASKS OF POLITICAL THEORY</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>N.J.</given-names>
                  <surname>Rengger</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>1995</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">16</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i26215872</issue-id>
         <fpage>416</fpage>
         <lpage>437</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>copyright: Imprint Academic, 1995</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26215878"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d2900e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e114" publication-type="other">
A rather different version of this paper will appear as part of the introductory chapter of
my Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity: Beyond Enlightenment and Critique
(Oxford, 1994). In its original form the article has benefited from the critical comments of
Terrell Carver and Iain Hampsher-Monk, and from discussions with Judith Squires, Bonnie
Honig, John Charvet, Chris Brown, Ian Forbes, Brian Barry, Chris Bertram and, especially,
Onora O'Neill. A heartfelt thank you to one and all.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e137a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e144" publication-type="other">
See, for example, Brian Barry, ' The Strange Death of Political Philosophy', in Democ-
racy and Power: Essays in Political Theory, 1 (Oxford, 1991); and David Miller, "The
Resurgence of Political Theory', in Political Studies, Vol. XXXVIII, no. 3 (September
1990); and Political Theory Today, ed. David Held (Cambridge, 1991), introduction.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e160a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e167" publication-type="other">
See Barry, "Hie Strange Death of Political Philosophy', p. 18.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e174a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e183" publication-type="other">
The revival of substantive political theory in what is usually called an 'Anglo-American'
mode, is widely held to have been sent into overdrive by the publication of John Rawls' Λ
Theory of Justice (Oxford, 1972) and the launching of the journal Philosophy and Public
Affairs in 1971. As Barry remarks in 'The Strange Death of Political Philosophy', the
rebirth of analytical political theory also benefited from much work in political economy
and economics, especially that in game theory and other forms of formal theory. Recent
representative selections of analytical political theory in this vein would include: Alan
Hamlin and Philip Pettit, The Good Polity: Normative Analysis of the State (Oxford, 1989);
John Broome, Weighing Goods (Oxford, 1992); Will Kymlicka, Liberalism, Community
and Culture (Oxford, 1991); and Brian Barry, Theories of Justice (Vol. 1 of A Treatise of
Social Justice) (Hemel Hempstead, 1989).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e222a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e229" publication-type="other">
Consider, for example, the work in the United States of scholars like Leo Strauss,
Reinhold Niebuhr and Hannah Arendt. In France of Raymond Aron, Alexandre Kojeve,
Louis Althusser and Paul Ricoeur. In Germany, of Adomo and Horkheimer, Habermas and
Gadamer. In Italy of Norberto Bobbio and in the UK of Michael Oakeshott, John Plamenatz
and Isaiah Berlin. It is fair to say, of course, that much of this work was done in the history
of ideas, a point recognized by the likes of Barry and Miller. Their point is precisely that it
was non-historical substantive political theory that was 'dead'. It is also true to say that
'political theory' as it is usually practised in the Anglo-American worlds is slightly
different from cognate activities on mainland Europe. However, most of the above men-
tioned writers (and indeed many others) were certainly not exclusively concerned with the
history of ideas or had a conception of political philosophy that saw the history of ideas as
a crucial component of any substantive theory. This was certainly the view of, for example,
Strauss, Gadamer and Oakeshott, though naturally in different ways. This might be
incorrect; it does not, however, suggest that political philosophy was 'dead'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e277a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e284" publication-type="other">
I shall refer throughout this paper to the kind of political theory that has, allegedly, been
'reborn' as 'Anglo-American' political theory, a common enough terminology these days.
I should emphasize, however, that this term should be taken to refer to a way of doing
political theory and the assumptions associated with it, rather than having any specific
geographical referent. Thus (and for example), Phillipe Van Parijs, who teaches in Bel-
gium, does on my account 'Anglo-American political theory' whereas William Connolly,
who teaches in America, does not.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e310a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e319" publication-type="other">
See, for a (relatively) random sample, Richard J. Bernstein, The New Constellation, The
Restructuring of Social and Political Theory (London, 1976); William Connelly, Identity/
Difference: Democratic Negotiations of Political Paradox (New York, 1991); Richard
Rorty, Contingency, Irony and Solidarity (Cambridge, 1990); Stephen White, Political
Theory and Postmodernism (Cambridge, 1991); Fred Dallmayr, Hegel: Modernity and
Politics (New York, 1993); Bonnie Honig, Political Theory and the Displacement of
Politics (Ithaca, 1993). For a general discussion and critique of these developments see NJ.
Rengger, 'No Time Like The Present? Postmodernism and Political Theory', in Political
Studies (September, 1992) and Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e351a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e358" publication-type="other">
See, for example, Perry Anderson, Lineages of the Absolutist State (London, 1974);
Anthony Giddens, The Nation State and Violence (Cambridge, 1985); Immanuel Waller-
stein, Unthinking Social Science (Cambridge, 1991); Theda Skocpol, States and Social
Revolutions (Cambridge, 1979).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e374a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e381" publication-type="other">
This latter point is the hallmark, of course, of Quentin Skinner and J.G. A. Pocock as well
as Dunn, with whom I shall be principally concerned in this paper. See Meaning and
Context: Quentin Skinner and His Critics, ed. James Tully (Cambridge, 1988). For a good
general survey of competing methods in the history of political thought see The History of
Ideas, ed. Preston King (London, 1983). In addition to the Cambridge school, as the work
of Skinner, Pocock and Dunn has sometimes been characterized, there is some analogous
(though often different) work being done in Europe, especially in Germany. See, for
example, the Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe: Historiches lexikon zur politische- sozialen
Sprache in Deutschland, ed. Otto Bruner, Werner Conze and Reinhart Koselleck (5 vols,
to date: Stuttgart, 1972- ). For a general discussion of the similar yet differing versions of
the 'historical turn' in the history of political thought see Melvin Richter, 'Reconstructing
the History of Political Languages: Pocock, Skinner and the Geschlichtliche Grundbe-
griffe', History and Theory, Vol. XXIX, no. 1 (1990), pp. 38-70.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e426a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e433" publication-type="other">
John Dunn, Modern Revolutions: An Introduction to the Analysis of a Political
Phenomenon (Cambridge, 1972; 2nd edn., 1989) (hereafter MR).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e444a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e451" publication-type="other">
West African States: Failure and Promise, ed. John Dunn (Cambridge, 1978); Contem-
porary West African States, ed, John Dunn, Donal Cruise O'Brien and Richard Rathbone
(Cambridge, 1989).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e464a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e471" publication-type="other">
John Dunn, The Politics of Socialism (Cambridge, 1984).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e478a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e485" publication-type="other">
The Economic Limits to Modern Politics, ed. John Dunn (Cambridge, 1990).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e492a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e499" publication-type="other">
John Dunn, The Political Thought of John Locke (Cambridge, 1969); Political Obliga-
tion in its Historical Context (Cambridge, 1980); Western Political Theory in the Face of
the Future (Cambridge, 1979); Rethinking Modern Political Theory (Cambridge, 1985).
Indeed, one might add comparative/international politics to this list if one looks at his recent
edited collection for the Political Studies Association, "The Crisis of the Nation State'
(Political Studies, Vol. 42 (special issue 1994)).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e522a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e529" publication-type="other">
The most recent being John Dunn, Interpreting Political Responsibility (Cambridge,
1990).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e539a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e546" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 193.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e554a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e561" publication-type="other">
Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e568a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e575" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 195.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e582a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e589" publication-type="other">
See, for a good discussion of these, Iain MacLean, Public Choice (Oxford, 1987).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e596a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e603" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e610a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e617" publication-type="other">
See Ibid, p. 197</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e624a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e631" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Rethinking Modern Political Theory, p. 189.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e639a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e646" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 214.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e653a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e660" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 9, quotation is from Dunn, Political Thought of John Locke, p. x.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e667a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e674" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 9.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e681a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e688" publication-type="other">
This is not the place to go over the many and variegated turns of the realist vs. anti-realist
argument in twentieth-century philosophy. Suffice to say that as opposed to the realist view
which sees fixed, determinate existing objects for social investigations, anti-realism sug-
gests that there are only particular interpretations or assumptions embedded in still further
assumptions, and so on. The assumptions of anti-realist arguments are clearly compatible
with the emphasis on context of Dunn and others of the Cambridge school. There are, of
course, a wide number of possible anti-realist views (as there are realist views) and one
should not assume that Dunn would subscribe to them all.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e717a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e724" publication-type="other">
See, for example, Skinner's views as developed in the essays gathered together by James
Tully in Meaning and Context.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e734a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e741" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 23.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e749a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e756" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 25.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e763a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e770" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 43.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e777a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e784" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 200.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e791a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e798" publication-type="other">
Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e805a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e812" publication-type="other">
Of course, the techniques and assumptions that are used by (amongst others) rational
choice theorists are deployed in a wide variety of ways by different theorists. Here I do not
mean to imply anything other than the fact that Dunn's usage of 'prudence' is very different
from the general sense these theorists would give to the term 'rational', with the instru-
mental sense of which it might be confused.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e831a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e838" publication-type="other">
See, for example, the discussion in Aristotle's Politics, Bk. Ill, 1277a, though of course
'prudence' in our sense does not quite adequately translate the Greek word phronimos, for
which it is usually used.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e852a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e859" publication-type="other">
I refer, of course, to those versions of realism associated with thinkers such as Hans
Morgenthau, Reinold Niebuhr and Raymond Aron rather than the more recent school of
'Neo-Realism' advocated by Kenneth Waltz. For discussions see: Michael Joseph Smith,
Realist Thought from Weber to Kissinger (Baton Rouge, 1986); Joel Rosenthal, Righteous
Realists (Baton Rouge, 1991); and, for Neo Realism, Neo-Realism and Its Critics, ed. R.O.
Keohane (New York, 1984).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e882a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e889" publication-type="other">
See Ken Booth, 'Security in Anarchy: Utopian Realism in Theory and Practice', in
International Affairs, Vol. 67, no. 3 (July 1991). Anthony Giddens, The Consequences of
Modernity (Cambridge, 1990), see especially Ch. 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e902a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e909" publication-type="other">
See for example Giddens, Consequences of Modernity, pp. 114-24; and Booth's empha-
sis on common security.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e919a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e926" publication-type="other">
I take it up in some detail however in Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e933a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e940" publication-type="other">
I am, I know, sidestepping the complex and important question of whether all so-called
postmodern readings of politics actually do this. I accept that some are much better disposed
to Dunn's sort of history than others. In the article on postmodem political theory cited
earlier (Rengger, 'No Time Like The Present?'), and in the book from which both that
article and this are drawn, I drew a distinction between 'hard' sceptical postmodems such
as Jean Baudrillard and soft sceptical postmodems such as William Connolly. In the present
context the latter would be more likely to be sympathetic to Dunn's argument than the
former.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e969a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e976" publication-type="other">
See Quentin Skinner, Ά Reply to my Critics', in Meaning and Context, ed. Tully,
p. 281.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e987a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e994" publication-type="other">
See Dunn, Rethinking Modern Political Theory, p. 1.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1001a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1008" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 209.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1015a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1022" publication-type="other">
See Booth, 'Security in Anarchy', see especially pp. 532 and 535; and Giddens,
Consequences of Modernity, pp. 70-8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1032a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1039" publication-type="other">
The sense in which we can grant these hypotheses is at the heart of my concerns in Ch. 4
of Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1049a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1056" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 178.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1063a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1070" publication-type="other">
Ibid, p. 215.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1078a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1085" publication-type="other">
Ibid, p. 26.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1092a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1099" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 43.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1106a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1113" publication-type="other">
See the works of Dunn cited above (n. 14); David Gauthier, Morals By Agreement
(Oxford, 1986); and Robert Nozick, Anarchy, State and Utopia (Oxford, 1974).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1123a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1132" publication-type="other">
I should emphasize that I do not suggest the state is about to disappear, nor am I
subscribing to any fashionable posthistoire fantasies. I merely assert that the institutions
and processes that we call — in convenient shorthand — the state can hardly expect to
remain unchanged by the rapidity and power of the general pace of global change.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1148a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1155" publication-type="other">
My understanding of this notoriously problematic term can be found in Political Theory,
Modernity and Postmodernity. For conveniance here I simply take it to refer to the set of
problems and issues — intellectual, practical and material — that shape and constrain the
setting of modem politics.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1171a1310">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1178" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Rethinking Modern Political Theory, p. 153.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1186a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1193" publication-type="other">
For a fuller discussion of this argument see Political Theory, Modernity and Post-
modernity, especially Chs. 1 and 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1203a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1210" publication-type="other">
For discussions of liberalism and communitarianism see: Liberalism and its Critics, ed.
Michael Sandel (Oxford, 1989); Stephen Muilhall and Adam Swift, Liberals and Com-
munitarians (Oxford, 1992). I elaborate this argument in Political Theory, Modernity and
Postmodernity, introduction and Ch. 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1226a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1235" publication-type="other">
The four most frequently cited communitarians, of course. See Charles Taylor, Sources
of The Se//(Cambridge, Mass., 1989); Michael Sandel, Liberalism and the Limits of Justice
(Cambridge, 1983); Michael Walzer, Spheres of Justice (New York, 1983); Alisdair
Maclntyre, After Virtue (London, 1981). It is worth pointing out, I think, that linking these
four in this way does grave damage to all of the thinkers concerned. Of the four just
mentioned only two, Walzer and Sandel, seem unworried by the use of the label 'commu-
nitarian' (which is more usually and — in some senses appropriately — applied to writers
such as Amitai Etzioni). Maclntyre has expressly repudiated the idea that he is a commu-
nitarian (see his 'Reply to my Critics', in After Maclntyre, ed. Susan Mendus and John
Horton (Cambridge, 1994)) and Taylor has also expressed his very considerable reserva-
tions (in his 'Cross Purposes: The Liberal-Communitarian debate', in Liberalism and the
Moral Life, ed. Nancy Rosenblum (Cambridge, Mass., 1989)). I discuss this problem in
more detail in Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodemity, especially in the introduc-
tion and Ch. 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1283a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1290" publication-type="other">
See Quentin Skinner, On Justice, The Common Good and Liberty', in Dimensions of
Radical Democracy: Pluralism, Citizenship, Community, ed. Chantai Mouffe (London,
1992). Skinner and Pocock have been especially influential of course in bringing the
republican tradition into greater focus over the last few years. Given the complicated
history of the relations between liberal and republican thought that they so well document,
it is nicely ironic that they seek to attack versions of modern liberalism with weapons taken
from a tradition so deeply, if ambiguously, implicated in its development. It is also worth
pointing out here, however, that 'republicanism' as such has also been 'revived' (if that is
quite the word) by some scholars who hardy share either the methodological or the
normative agenda's of the Cambridge school, to wit some of the friends and allies of Leo
Strauss, especially Harvey Mansfield and Thomas Pangle (see, for example, Mansfield's
Taming the Prince: The Ambivalence of Modern Executive Power (Baltimore, 1989) and
Pangle's The Spirit of Modern Republicanism (Chicago, 1988)). I do not propose to argue
the toss between the Cambridge school and Straussian versions of 'republicanism' here, I
merely point out that this is contested ground.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1341a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1348" publication-type="other">
It is also common to writers connected to the Cambridge school. Richard Tuck, for
example, in his recent and excellent Philosophy and Government 1572-1651 (Cambridge,
1993), provides a slightly different but nonetheless related account of the rise of a particular
set of political assumptions that created at least some aspects of the origins of contemporary
liberalism. Again, however, it is worth noting the similarity (in form, not content) of what
we might call the 'Straussian republicans' Mansfield and Pangle'. Mansfield begins his
account of the rise of the modern executive with Machiavelli, and in doing so explicitly
feels the need to distance his interpretation from that of Skinner and Pocock (see Mansfield,
Taming the Prince, pp. xxiii-xxiv), and the subtitle of Pangle's book is 'The Moral Vision
of the American Founders and the Philosophy of Locke'. As with Dunn and Skinner it is
with interpretations of Machiavelli and Locke that the critique of existing liberalism begins.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1386a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1393" publication-type="other">
See, for example, his argument in 'Practising History and Social Science on "Realist'
Assumptions', in Dunn, Political Obligation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1404a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1411" publication-type="other">
See Dunn, Rethinking Modem Political Theory, Ch. 4, 'Understanding Revolutions'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1418a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1425" publication-type="other">
See Dunn, Political Obligation, Ch. 8, 'Democracy Unretrieved: or the Political Theory
of Professor Macpherson'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1435a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1442" publication-type="other">
A claim associated with Leo Strauss, but one that could with some amendment of
content or temper be applied to analytical theorists also. An entertaining irony, in that
Strauss and the analytical (he would have called them positivistic) theorists were in almost
all other respects diametrically opposed. See, for example, Leo Strauss, What is Political
Philosophy (Chicago, 1954); and Barry 'The Strange Death of Political Philosophy'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1461a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1468" publication-type="other">
By historicism I do not mean the belief in the inevitable laws of history or anything of
this crassly Popperian kind, merely the relativistic point that values and beliefs change
through time; i.e. that there is no independent conception of truth or value that is 'outside'
historically generated norms or assumptions.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1484a1310">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1491" publication-type="other">
Hamlin and Pettit, The Good Polity, p. 1.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1498a1310">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1505" publication-type="other">
Martin Hollis, The Cunning of Reason (Cambridge, 1987), p. 16.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1513a1310">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1520" publication-type="other">
See Rorty, Contingency, Irony and Solidarity, p. 33.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1527a1310">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1534" publication-type="other">
I have tried to lay out the assumptions that he behind it in much greater detail in Political
Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity, Ch. 3.1 also hope to fill in the concept of practical
reason that grows from this in the near future.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1547a1310">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1554" publication-type="other">
For a discussion of these postmodems, and also for some who are perhaps not as
convinced, see Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity, Ch. 2.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1564a1310">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1573" publication-type="other">
The search for better, not wholly instrumental, readings of reason has recently become
more popular, even among analytical theorists, for example Jon Elster. See, amongst many
other works, Jon Elster, The Cement of Society (Cambridge, 1984). Onora O'Neill is
perhaps the philosopher who has done most to explore these issues. See O. O'Neill,
Constructions of Reason: Explorations in Kantian Practical Philosophy (Cambridge,
1989).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1596a1310">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1603" publication-type="other">
Much the same is true of those 'Utopian realists' who, I suggested earlier, in this respect
at least make common cause with Dunn. Giddens, for example, insists that we must
'balance Utopian ideals with realism' given the extremely high-consequence risks of
contemporary social life, echoing Dunn's insistence on the complexity and risk inherent in
modernity, and Booth stresses that his utopianism is not an end-point Utopia but a process
Utopia, agreeing with Dunn's concern that the third task of political theory is to conceive
of realistic ways of getting from where we are to where we might, and should, aim to be.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1629a1310">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1636" publication-type="other">
Dunn, Political Responsibility, p. 214.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1644a1310">
            <label>71</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1651" publication-type="other">
There are, of course, discussions of this sort in a variety of modern moral and political
theories. For example Onora O'Neill has given accounts of this issue from a strongly
Kantian perspective, and the notion of reasonableness and what it leads to plays a central
role in John Finnis's influential rearticulation of Natural Law theory. See Onora O'Neill,
'Vindicating Reason', in The Cambridge Companion to Kant, ed. Paul Guyer (Cambridge,
1992); and John Finnis, Natural Law and Natural Rights (Oxford, 1980). The beginnings
of my own approach to this question can be found in Political Theory, Modernity and
Postmodernity, Chs. 3 and 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1680a1310">
            <label>72</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1687" publication-type="other">
It is partly to avoid such a difficulty, of course, that Habermas (just to give one other
example) develops his theory of communicative action. Unfortunately I am unconvinced
by this argument also, for all its hugely impressive grasp and range. See Jtirgen Habermas,
Théorie des kommunikativen Handelns. Baud 1, Handlungsrationalitat und gesell-
schaftliche Rationalisierung. Baud 2, ΖurKritik derfunktioalistischen Vernunft (Frankfurt,
1981). See also Ch. 2 of Political Theory, Modernity and Postmodernity for a brief
discussion of Habermas. I am currently working on a more thorough treatment of the
reasons for my doubts in a paper: 'Negative Dialectic? Globalization and the Future of
Critical Theory'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2900e1719a1310">
            <label>73</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2900e1726" publication-type="other">
Cited in Maurice Cranston, John Locke: A Biography (Oxford, 1985), p. 244.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
