<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">criticalinquiry</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Critical Inquiry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00931896</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15397858</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4497768</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/526093</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">CI340109</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Books of Critical Interest</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2007</year>
            <string-date>Autumn 2007</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>34</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>526095</issue-id>
         <fpage>225</fpage>
         <lpage>232</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2007 by The University of Chicago.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/526093"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title/>
         <p>Lacoue‐Labarthe, Philippe.<italic>Heidegger and the Politics of Poetry.</italic>Trans. Jeff Fort. Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 2007. 136 pp. $35.00.</p>
         <p>Ladenson, Elisabeth.<italic>Dirt for Art’s Sake: Books on Trial from</italic>Madame Bovary<italic>to</italic>Lolita. Ithaca, New York: Cornell University Press, 2007. 304 pp. $29.95.</p>
         <p>Lambert, Gregg.<italic>Who’s Afraid of Deleuze and Guattari?</italic>London: Continuum, 2006. 180 pp.</p>
         <p>Lau, Estelle T.<italic>Paper Families: Identity, Immigration Administration, and Chinese Exclusion</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 214 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Lazenby, J. Mark.<italic>The Early Wittgenstein on Religion.</italic>London: Continuum, 2006. 126 pp.</p>
         <p>Le Doeuff, Michele.<italic>Hipparchia’s Choice: An Essay Concerning Women, Philosophy, Etc.</italic>Trans. Trista Selous. New York: Columbia University Press, 2007. 416 pp. $24.50 (paper); $69.50 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Lefort, Claude.<italic>Complications: Communism and the Dilemmas of Democracy</italic>. Trans. Julian Bourg. New York: Columbia University Press, 2007. 256 pp. $35.00.</p>
         <p>Leibman, Stuart, ed.<italic>Claude Lanzmann’s</italic>Shoah<italic>: Key Essays.</italic>Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2007. 253 pp. $24.95.</p>
         <p>Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm.<italic>The Shorter Leibniz Texts: A Collection of New Translations.</italic>Ed. Lloyd Strickland. London: Continuum, 2006. 208 pp. $29.95 (paper); $110.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Lesjak, Carolyn.<italic>Working Fictions: A Genealogy of the Victorian Novel</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 270 pp. $22.95 (paper); $79.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Levine, Elana.<italic>Wallowing in Sex: The New Sexual Culture of 1970s American Television.</italic>Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. $22.95 (paper); $79.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Li, Tania Murray.<italic>The Will to Improve: Governmentality, Development, and the Practice of Politics</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 374 pp. $23.95 (paper); $84.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Littau, Karin.<italic>Theories of Reading: Books, Bodies, and Bibliomania</italic>. Cambridge: Polity Press, 2006. 194 pp. $26.95.</p>
         <p>Lock, Margaret and Judith Farquhar, eds.<italic>Beyond the Body Proper: Reading the Anthropology of Material Life.</italic>Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 688 pp. $34.95 (paper); $99.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Lupieri, Edmondo F.<italic>A Commentary on the Apocalypse of John</italic>. Trans. Maria Poggi Johnson and Adam Kamesar. Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 2006. 456 pp. $36.00.</p>
         <p>Maghraoui, Abdeslam M.<italic>Liberalism without Democracy: Nationhood and Citizenship in Egypt, 1922‐1936</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2006. 192 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Mahaffey, Vicki.<italic>Modernist Literature: Challenging Fictions</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, 2007. 242 pp.</p>
         <p>Mailloux, Steven.<italic>Disciplinary Identities: Rhetorical Paths of English, Speech, and Composition</italic>. New York: Modern Language Association, 2006. 165 pp. $19.75 (paper); $37.50 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Manghani, Sunil, Arthur Piper and Jon Simons, eds.<italic>Images: A Reader</italic>. London: SAGE Publications, 2006. 331 pp.</p>
         <p>Mani, B. Venkat.<italic>Cosmopolitical Claims: Turkish‐German Literatures from Nadolny to Pamuk</italic>. Iowa City, Iowa: University of Iowa Press, 2007. 262 pp. $39.95.</p>
         <p>Martin, Nina K.<italic>Sexy Thrills: Undressing the Erotic Thriller.</italic>Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 2007. 206 pp.</p>
         <p>Martin, Randy.<italic>An Empire of Indifference: American War and the Financial Logic of Risk Management.</italic>Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press: 2007. 219 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>May, Larry.<italic>War Crimes and Just War</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 343 pp. $29.99 (paper); $80.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>McAuliffe, Jane Dammen, ed.<italic>The Cambridge Companion to the Qur’an</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2006. 332 pp. $24.99 (paper); $75.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>McDonald, Ronan.<italic>The Cambridge Introduction to Samuel Beckett</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 140 pp. $19.99 (paper); $65.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>McEwan, Colin, Andrew Middleton, Caroline Cartwright, and Rebecca Stacey.<italic>Turquoise Mosaics from Mexico</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 96 pp. $23.95.</p>
         <p>McGirr, Elaine.<italic>Eighteenth‐Century Characters: A Guide to the Literature of the Age</italic>. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007. 207 pp. $30.95 (paper); $93.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Meeker, Natania.<italic>Voluptuous Philosophy: Literary Materialism in the French Enlightenment</italic>. New York: Fordham University Press, 2007. 310 pp. $60.00.</p>
         <p>Megill, Allan.<italic>Historical Knowledge, Historical Error: A Contemporary Guide to Practice</italic>. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 2007. $25.00 (paper); $60.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Melas, Natalie.<italic>All the Difference in the World: Postcoloniality and the Ends of Comparison</italic>. Stanford, California: Stanford University Press, 2006. 278 pp. $21.95.</p>
         <p>Merewether, Charles, and Rika Iezumi Hiro, eds.<italic>Art Ant‐Art Non‐Art: Experiments in the Public Sphere in Postwar Japan 1950‐1970</italic>. Los Angeles: Getty Publications, 2007. 140 pp.</p>
         <p>Metres, Philip.<italic>Behind the Lines: War Resistance Poetry on the American Homefront Since 1941.</italic>Iowa City, Iowa: University of Iowa Press, 2007. 298 pp. $39.95.</p>
         <p>Mishra, Sudesh.<italic>Diaspora Criticism</italic>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2007. 190 pp. $25.00 (paper); $80.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Mishra, Vijay.<italic>The Literature of the Indian Diaspora: Theorizing the Diasporic Imaginary</italic>. London: Routledge, 2007. 286 pp.</p>
         <p>Mitman, Gregg.<italic>Breathing Space: How Allergies Shape Our Lives and Landscapes</italic>. New Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press, 2007. 312 pp.</p>
         <p>Miyao, Daisuke.<italic>Sessue Hayakawa: Silent Cinema and Transnational Stardom</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 379 pp. $23.95 (paper); $84.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Morgan, Michael L.<italic>Discovering Levinas</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 504 pp. $90.00.</p>
         <p>Müller‐Fahrenholz, Geiko.<italic>America’s Battle for God: A European Christian Looks at Civil Religion</italic>. Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 2007.</p>
         <p>Mumford, Lewis and Henry A. Murray.<italic>“In Old Friendship”: The Correspondence of Lewis Mumford and Henry A. Murray, 1928‐1981</italic>. Ed. Frank G. Novak, Jr. Syracuse, New York: Syracuse University Press, 2007. 424 pp. $59.95.</p>
         <p>Nehamas, Alexander.<italic>Only a Promise of Happiness: The Place of Beauty in a World of Art</italic>. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2007. 208 pp. $29.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Needham, Anuradha Dingwaney and Rajeswari Sunder Rajan, eds.<italic>The Crisis of Secularism in India</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 411 pp. $24.95 (paper); $89.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Nguyen, Mimi Thi and Thuy Linh Nguyen Tu, eds.<italic>Alien Encounters: Popular Culture in Asian America</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 365 pp. $23.95 (paper); $84.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Nicholls, David G., ed.<italic>Introduction to Scholarship in Modern Languages and Literatures</italic>. 3rd ed. New York: The Modern Language Association of America, 2007. 370 pp. $22.00 (paper); $40.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Nicolar, Joseph.<italic>The Life and Traditions of the Red Man</italic>. Ed. Annette Kolodny. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press: 2007. 240 pp. $19.95 (paper); $69.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Nuttall, Sarah, ed.<italic>Beautiful/Ugly: African and Diaspora Aesthetics</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2006. 416 pp. $27.95.</p>
         <p>Olcott, Jocelyn, Mary Kay Vaughan, and Gabriela Cano, eds.<italic>Sex in Revolution: Gender, Politics, and Power in Modern Mexico</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 320 pp. $22.95 (paper); $79.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Olsson, Gunnar.<italic>Abysmal: A Critique of Cartographic Reason</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2007. 584 pp. $40.00.</p>
         <p>Olwig, Karen Fog.<italic>Caribbean Journeys: An Ethnography of Migration and Home in Three Family Networks</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 319 pp. $23.95 (paper); $84.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Ortner, Sherry B.<italic>Anthropology and Social Theory: Culture, Power, and the Acting Subject</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 188 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Paradis, Kenneth.<italic>Sex, Paranoia, and Modern Masculinity</italic>. Albany, New York: State University of New York Press, 2007. 228 pp. $65.00.</p>
         <p>Parry, Amie Elizabeth.<italic>Interventions into Modernist Cultures: Poetry from Beyond the Empty Screen</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 188 pp. $22.95 (paper); $79.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Patey, Carolina, Giovanni Cianci, and Francesca Cuojati, eds.<italic>Anglo‐American Modernity and the Mediterranean</italic>. Milan: Cisalpino, 2006. 400 pp. € 32,00.</p>
         <p>Pena, Milagros.<italic>Latina Activists across Borders: Women’s Grassroots Organizing in Mexico and Texas</italic>. Durham: Duke University Press, 2007. 174 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Papanikolas, Zeese.<italic>American Silence</italic>. Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press, 2007. 221 pp. $29.95.</p>
         <p>Perez Jr., Louis A.<italic>To Die in Cuba: Suicide and Society</italic>. Chapel Hill, North Carolina: University of North Carolina Press, 2007. 480 pp. $21.95.</p>
         <p>Pettman, Dominic.<italic>Love and Other Technologies: Retrofitting Eros for the Information Age</italic>. New York: Fordham University Press, 2006. 267 pp. $24.00 (paper); $70.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Petty, Leslie.<italic>Romancing the Vote: Feminist Activism in American Fiction, 1870‐1920</italic>. Athens, Georgia: The University of Georgia Press, 2006. 231 pp. $39.95.</p>
         <p>Pharies, David A.<italic>A Brief History of the Spanish Language</italic>. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 2007. 248 pp. $25.00.</p>
         <p>Purshouse, Luke.<italic>Plato’s</italic>Republic<italic>: A Reader’s Guide</italic>. London: Continuum, 2006. 161 pp. $14.95.</p>
         <p>Pyle, Andrew.<italic>Hume’s</italic>Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion:<italic>Reader’s Guide.</italic>London: Continuum, 2006. 155 pp. $14.95.</p>
         <p>Quintero, Ruben.<italic>A Companion to Satire: Ancient and Modern</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, 2007. 608 pp.</p>
         <p>Rancière, Jacques.<italic>The Future of the Image.</italic>London: Verso, 2007. 147 pp. $26.95.</p>
         <p>Rand, Steven and Heather Kouris, eds.<italic>Cautionary Tales: Critical Curating</italic>. New York: apexart, 2007. 125 pp.</p>
         <p>Ray, Celeste, ed.<italic>Ethnicity</italic>. Chapel Hill, North Carolina: The University of North Carolina Press, 2007. 276 pp.</p>
         <p>Redfield, Marc, ed.<italic>Legacies of Paul de Man</italic>. New York: Fordham University Press, 2007. 226 pp.</p>
         <p>Reinhardt, Mark, Holly Edwards, and Erina Duganne, eds.<italic>Beautiful Suffering: Photography and the Traffic in Pain</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2007.</p>
         <p>Richardson, Riche.<italic>Black Masculinity and the U.S. South: From Uncle Tom to Gangsta</italic>. Athens, Georgia: University of Georgia Press, 2007. 296 pp. $22.95 (paper); $49.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Rickless, Samuel C.<italic>Plato’s Forms in Transition: A Reading of the Parmenides</italic>. Cambridge.: Cambridge University Press, 2007. $90.00. 272 pp.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur, Paul.<italic>On Translation</italic>. Trans. Eileen Brennan. London: Routledge, 2006. 46 pp.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur, Paul.<italic>Reflections on the Just</italic>. Trans. David Pellauer. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 2007. 240 pp. $25.00.</p>
         <p>Riera, Gabriel.<italic>Intrigues: From Being to the Other</italic>. Bronx, New York: Fordham University Press, 2007. 247 pp. $55.00.</p>
         <p>Rivers, Caryl.<italic>Selling Anxiety: How the News Media Scare Women</italic>. Lebanon, New Hampshire: University Press of New England, 2007. 176 pp. $24.95.</p>
         <p>Rofel, Lisa.<italic>Desiring China: Experiments in Neoliberalism, Sexuality, and Public Culture</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 251 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Roy, Srirupa.<italic>Beyond Belief: India and the Politics of Postcolonial Nationalism</italic>. Durham: Duke University Press, 2007. 248 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Ruiz III, Nicholas.<italic>The Metaphysics of Capital</italic>. Intertheory Press. 199 pp. $22.00.</p>
         <p>Rushing, Robert A.<italic>Resisting Arrest: Detective Fiction and Popular Culture</italic>. New York: Other Press, 2007. 210 pp. $29.00.</p>
         <p>Ryan, Michael.<italic>Literary Theory: A Practical Introduction</italic>. 2d ed. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, 2007. 238 pp. $26.95.</p>
         <p>Sa’di, Ahmad H. and Lila Abu‐Lughod, eds.<italic>Nakba: Palestine, 1948, and the Claims of Memory</italic>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2007. 356 pp.</p>
         <p>Sale, Kirkpatrick.<italic>After Eden: The Evolution of Human Domination</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2006. 200 pp. $19.95.</p>
         <p>Sallinen, Sami and Haile Bizen.<italic>Asmara Beloved</italic>. Kĩmaathi Publishing House, 2003. 144 pp. $50.00.</p>
         <p>Saltman, Kenneth J., ed.<italic>Schooling and the Politics of Disaster</italic>. New York: Routledge, 2007. 295 pp.</p>
         <p>Schweber, Libby.<italic>Disciplining Statistics: Demography and Vital Statistics in France and England, 1830‐1885.</italic>Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2006. 277 pp. $74.95 (cloth); $21.95 (paper).</p>
         <p>Schweizer, Peter and Wynton C. Hall, eds.<italic>Landmark Speeches of the American Conservative Movement.</italic>College Station, Texas: Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2007. 169 pp.</p>
         <p>Scofield, Martin.<italic>The Cambridge Introduction to the American Short Story</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 291 pp. $22.99 (paper); $65.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Scott, Bonnie Kime, ed.<italic>Gender in Modernism: New Geographies, Complex Intersections.</italic>Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 2007. 872 pp.</p>
         <p>Serres, Michel.<italic>The Parasite.</italic>Trans. Lawrence R. Schehr. Minneapolis, Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press, 2007. 288 pp. $19.95.</p>
         <p>Sheppard, Eugene R.<italic>Leo Strauss and the Politics of Exile: The Making of a Political Philosopher</italic>. Waltham, Massachusetts: Brandeis University Press, 2006. 210 pp. $24.95.</p>
         <p>Shih, Shu‐mei.<italic>Visuality and Identity: Sinophone Articulations across the Pacific.</italic>Berkeley, California: University of California Press, 2007. 257 pp. $21.95.</p>
         <p>Siedell, Daniel A.<italic>Martinez Celaya: Early Work.</italic>Delray Beach, Florida: Whale and Star, 2006. 390 pp. $69.00.</p>
         <p>Smith, Clarissa.<italic>One for the Girls!: The Pleasures and Practices of Reading Women’s Porn</italic>. Bristol, United Kingdom: Intellect, 2007. 304 pp. $55.00.</p>
         <p>Smith, David Woodruff.<italic>Husserl.</italic>London: Routledge, 2007. 467 pp.</p>
         <p>Stapert, Calvin R.<italic>A New Song for an Old World: Musical Thought in the Early Church</italic>. Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 2007. 246 pp. $18.00.</p>
         <p>Stephen, Lynn.<italic>Transborder Lives: Indigenous Oaxacans in Mexico, California, and Oregon.</italic>Durham: Duke University Press, 2007. 375 pp. $23.95 (paper); $84.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Stewart, Charles, ed.<italic>Creolization: History, Ethnography, Theory</italic>. Walnut Creek, California: Left Coast Press, 2007. 304 pp. $29.95 (paper); $65.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Strauven, Wanda, ed.<italic>The Cinema of Attractions Reloaded</italic>. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 2006. 464 pp. $47.50 (paper); $75.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Suarez, Juan A.<italic>Pop Modernism: Noise and the Reinvention of the Everyday.</italic>Champaign, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 2007. 336 pp. $25.00 (paper); $60.00 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Šukys, Julija.<italic>Silence Is Death: The Life and Work of Tahar Djaout.</italic>Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press, 2007. 197 pp. $26.95.</p>
         <p>Taylor, Michael.<italic>Rembrandt’s Nose: Of Flesh &amp; Spirit in the Master’s Portraits</italic>. New York: Distributed Art Publishers, 2007. 168 pp. $27.50.</p>
         <p>Taylor, Timothy D.<italic>Beyond Exoticism: Western Music and the World</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 328 pp.</p>
         <p>Thomas, Alfred.<italic>The Bohemian Body: Gender and Sexuality in Modern Czech Culture</italic>. Madison. Wisconsin: The University of Wisconsin Press, 2007. 271 pp. $75.00.</p>
         <p>Thompson, Krista A.<italic>An Eye for the Tropics: Tourism, Photography, and Framing the Caribbean Picturesque</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. $24.95 (paper); $89.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Thrailkill, Jane F.<italic>Affecting Fictions: Mind, Body, and Emotion in American Literary Realism.</italic>Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 2007. 312 pp. $45.00.</p>
         <p>Trolander, Paul and Zeynep Tenger.<italic>Sociable Criticism in England, 1625‐1725.</italic>Newark: University of Delaware Press, 2007. 233 pp. $49.50.</p>
         <p>Tucker, Linda G.<italic>Lockstep and Dance: Images of Black Men in Popular Culture</italic>. Jackson, Mississippi: University Press of Mississippi, 2007. 191 pp. $45.00.</p>
         <p>Usandizaga, Aranzazu and Andrew Monnickendam.<italic>Back to Peace: Reconciliation and Retribution in the Postwar Period</italic>. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 2007. 320 pp. $35.00.</p>
         <p>Valberg, J. J.<italic>Dream, Death and the Self</italic>. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2007. 499 pp.</p>
         <p>van den Brink, Bert and David Owen, eds.<italic>Recognition and Power: Axel Honneth and the Tradition of Critical Social Theory</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 399 pp. $85.00.</p>
         <p>Volf, Miroslav.<italic>The End of Memory: Remembering Rightly in a Violent World</italic>. Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 2006. 244 pp.</p>
         <p>Wainwright, Lisa.<italic>Things of Nature and the Nature of Things: John Wilde.</italic>Madison, Wisconsin: The University of Wisconsin Press, 2007. 48 pp. $29.95.</p>
         <p>Wang, David Der‐wei and Carlos Rojas, eds. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 412 pp. $24.95 (paper); $89.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Wang, Eugene Y.<italic>Shaping the Lotus Sutra: Buddhist Visual Culture in Medieval China</italic>. Seattle, Washington: University of Washington Press, 2007. 512 pp.</p>
         <p>Ward, W. R.<italic>Early Evangelicalism: A Global Intellectual History, 1670‐1789</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2006. 220 pp. $80.00.</p>
         <p>Warne, Christopher.<italic>Aristotle’s</italic>Nicomachean Ethics<italic>: Reader’s Guide</italic>. 156 pp. $14.95.</p>
         <p>White, Daniel E.<italic>Early Romanticism and Religious Dissent</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 266 pp. $90.00.</p>
         <p>White, Roger M.<italic>Wittgenstein’s</italic>Tractatus Logico‐Philosophicus<italic>: Reader’s Guide</italic>. London: Continuum, 2006. 163 pp. $14.95.</p>
         <p>Whitworth, Michael H., ed.<italic>Modernsim</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, 2007. 310 pp.</p>
         <p>Wolfson, Susan J. and Marshall Brown, eds.<italic>Reading for Form</italic>. Seattle, Washington: University of Washington Press, 2007. 304 pp. $25.00.</p>
         <p>Woolhouse, Roger.<italic>Locke: A Biography</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007. 548 pp. $39.99.</p>
         <p>Xingjian, Gao.<italic>The Case for Literature</italic>. New Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press, 2007. 192 pp. $25.00.</p>
         <p>Yanni, Carla.<italic>The Architecture of Madness: Insane Asylums in the United States</italic>. Minneapolis, Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press, 2007. 191 pp.</p>
         <p>Zamir, Tzachi.<italic>Double Vision: Moral Philosophy and Shakespearean Drama</italic>. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 2007. 192 pp. $35.00.</p>
         <p>Zhen, Zhang, ed.<italic>The Urban Generation: Chinese Cinema and Society at the Turn of the Twenty‐First Century</italic>. Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 464 pp. $26.95 (paper); $94.95 (cloth).</p>
         <p>Zlomislic, Marko.<italic>Jacques Derrida’s Aporetic Ethics</italic>. Lanham, Maryland: Lexington Books, 2007.</p>
         <p>Zoja, Luigi.<italic>Ethics &amp; Analysis: Philosophical Perspectives and their Application in Therapy.</italic>College Station, Texas: Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2007. 126 pp.</p>
         <p>Zulawski, Ann.<italic>Unequal Cures: Public Health and Political Change in Bolivia, 1900‐1950.</italic>Durham, North Carolina: Duke University Press, 2007. 253 pp. $21.95 (paper); $74.95 (cloth).</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
