<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207409</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/592359</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR841</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Just War, Civic Virtue, and Democratic Social Criticism: Augustinian Reflections<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Richard B.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Miller</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Indiana University</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2009</year>
            <string-date>January 2009</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>89</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>592372</issue-id>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>30</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2009 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/592359"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="epigraph">
         <disp-quote>
            <p>Europe since the outbreak of war has been comparatively quiet, and in consequence indiscriminate hatred has been far less noticeable than it was during the last war. But as the conflict grows more serious, we cannot expect this state of things to last; already there is less moderation in public speeches and private conversation than at the outset. Worse, there is already suppression and distortion of truth “in the interests of the state”; and news has become propaganda and advocacy of a case. One man’s lies are not justified because they contradict another’s.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
      </notes>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>Thanks to Nigel Biggar, Eric Gregory, Aaron Stalnaker, and the editors and reviewers of the<italic>Journal of Religion</italic>for comments and suggestions on a previous draft of this article. An earlier version of this essay was presented at the 2004 annual meeting of the Society of Christian Ethics and at the Theology and Ethics Colloquy at the American Academy of Religion, and I wish to thank interlocutors in those contexts, especially Maria Antonaccio, William J. Buckley, John Carlson, Charles E. Curran, Franklin Gamwell, John Langan, Terence Martin Jr., Douglas Ottati, Jean Porter, William Schweiker, Lisa Sideris, and Charles Wilson for comments and questions. I presented a subsequent version to the Ethics, Philosophy, and Politics Workshop in Religious Studies at Indiana University, and I want to thank Byron Bangert, David Cockerham, Constance Furey, Mark King, Ann Mongoven, and David H. Smith for their critical responses. I’m likewise grateful for informative discussions of memory at the 2006–7 Poynter Center Interdisciplinary Faculty Seminar at Indiana University on “Memory: Ethics, Aesthetics, Politics”: Byron Bangert, John Bodnar, Purnima Bose, Maria Bucur, Patrick Dove, Joseph Hoffmann, Danny James, Ed Linenthal, John Lucaites, Glenda Murray, Melissa Seymour, Lynn Struve, and Mark Wilson.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>G. E. M. Anscombe, “The Justice of the Present War Examined,” in<italic>The Collected Philosophical Papers of G. E. M. Anscombe</italic>, vol. 3,<italic>Ethics, Religion and Politics</italic>(Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1981), 80.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Social Criticism and Political Morality</title>
         <p>One of our beliefs about political morality is that ordinary citizens have a stake in just‐war doctrine during times of war or rumors of war.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>Seen in that way, just‐war doctrine provides a moral framework not only for political leaders and military officials but also for socially responsible citizens in public life. The underlying assumption is that the ethics of war can inform everyday judgments about political and military decisions and that being a responsible citizen means holding oneself and public officials accountable to norms enshrined in the just‐war tradition. Those norms enable citizens to ask about war’s cause, authority, aims, timing, and risks, along with war’s proper and improper methods. For citizens who concern themselves with the morality and prudence of military action, just‐war tenets provide a basis for analysis, criticism, and approval or dissent.</p>
         <p>Of course I am talking about moral and political discourse in democratic societies, where political sovereignty lies in the will of the people. Democracies both presuppose and, ideally, habituate the practice of social criticism, by which I mean the practice of assessing policy, leadership, and customs as these shape the direction of institutions and aspirations of public culture. Democratic societies view such criticism as part of the franchise assigned to the office of citizenship. Just‐war doctrine is significant, in other words, for moral as well as for political reasons. Citizens have a stake in just‐war doctrine insofar as they have a share in popular sovereignty and want to make a difference in the moral quality of the res publica.</p>
         <p>I suspect that this connection between just‐war doctrine and democratic social criticism is self‐evident in political contexts where the ethics of war is a matter of public deliberation and debate. One of my aims in this essay is to indicate why that connection is less obvious than it seems, and how it might be strengthened. The statement by G. E. M. Anscombe above, written at the outbreak of England’s entry into the Second World War, captures some of the issues to which I want to call attention, namely, the cultural effects of war on the dispositions and affections of a nation’s populace. War both relies on and inspires expressions of political allegiance, but it can also tempt citizens toward xenophobic self‐deception and disrespect of others. “There is a widespread tendency,” Anscombe observed of England in 1939, “to make what our country chooses to do, the criterion of what must be done, and to call this patriotism.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>That tendency can impoverish practical reasoning and conscientious self‐analysis, leading Anscombe to instruct her readers that “it is our duty to resist passion and to consider carefully whether all conditions of a just war are satisfied in this present war.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>Further, emotions surrounding war are typically highly charged and, as such, can produce distorted or reified memories that are transmitted to future generations in the formation of political identity. Given that “already men are talking of Germany as a pariah nation” and that Germany must “henceforth be kept down and never allowed to become powerful again,” it seemed inconceivable to Anscombe that anything like a lasting peace would be possible.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>Seen in these terms, war can be an occasion for vice insofar as it can generate passions that weaken a commitment to personal and public justice. Anscombe’s worries about the relation between war and civil society are regrettably rare in the ethics of war, and that fact exposes a gap between just‐war doctrine and its connections to civic virtue, political membership, and democratic social criticism.</p>
         <p>Readers familiar with the just‐war tradition know that the explanation for this gap is genealogical: just‐war doctrine arose in illiberal, undemocratic contexts, in which the idea of popular sovereignty was either inconceivable or anathema to those who conceived it. Yet even if we set aside this problem of political pedigree, a more pressing problem lurks: we (generally) deploy just‐war doctrine chiefly as a morality of statecraft,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>a set of norms according to which political elites and military soldiers should manage the destruction of war, not as a morality for assessing the sentiments and passions of citizens more broadly. As it is currently understood, the connections of just‐war doctrine to the virtues of democratic social criticism remain undertheorized. The tradition’s intellectual and cultural origins are premodern, and its potential role as guide for the individual conscience stands removed from the network of cultural and psychological forces that bear directly on political identity and the civic imagination. While it is true that just‐war criteria can instruct the private citizen’s moral deliberations,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>little work has been done to indicate how and on what terms the ethics of war might inform and guide the powerful longings of patriotism and the existential features of membership in an ongoing political community—cultural forces and desires that press upon the workings of conscience. This connection—or lack thereof—between the ethics of war and the desires that animate a common life is of no small importance given the just‐war tradition’s idea that the good of political community is desirable enough to defend with lethal violence if necessary.</p>
         <p>Another way to put this point is that the ethics of war presumes a psychology and sociology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>Given the powerful emotions that animate a common life, it would seem necessary for just‐war doctrine to function self‐reflexively vis‐à‐vis the shared desires and values to which it is attached. In the moral life generally and during war in particular, it is vital to determine whether our desires are indeed desirable. War excites passion, and passion sometimes undermines practical reason. This means that moral judgment guided by the just‐war tradition is precarious. Moral discourse about war can slip from functioning as a critical, reflective idiom to an idiom of rationalization regarding political decisions and military practices in war. The ethics of war thus requires a kind of moral steadiness in relation to the feelings that enliven the political community and the institutions that serve human needs and aspirations. It must affirm the good of community while resisting the temptation to assign that good absolute value lest it fall prey to political expedience or self‐righteousness, along with their penchant for cost‐benefit analysis and instrumental reason “in the interests of the state.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The need to articulate self‐reflexive features of just‐war doctrine suggests two ideas, the desirability of which I will stipulate here. One stipulation says that the ethics of war ought to inform and build on the habits of civic virtue—that it should provide a framework not only for forming policy and practice but also for forming (or reforming) citizens’ political character over time. With that in mind, I want to develop a connection between just‐war tenets and a corporate, popular “sense of justice,” as John Rawls calls it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>I will thus present an argument about virtues that dispose us toward prophetic social criticism—virtues that draw from and augment the virtue of justice and strengthen moral resolve in the face of political power.</p>
         <p>This concern about character opens up a second idea to which I want to direct attention: the connection between dispositions and the wider culture that shapes them. What is lacking in just‐war discourse is attention to the cultural forces that inform, and often corrode, expressions of courage and a commitment to fairness in times of national duress. On that score, we must attend to how social location affects our perceptions of ourselves and others. Because our affections are shaped by ethos and culture, it behooves us to consider how cultural images and political rhetoric bear upon the imagination, feelings, and “habits of the heart.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>That is to say, given the dynamic relationship between character and culture, moral assessment of the former cannot overlook the quality of the latter.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>We must therefore interrogate how cultures ask their members to imagine themselves and their opponents when they consider putative claims to justice in the recourse to war.</p>
         <p>With these points in mind, I want to make the following argument: as a moral framework for democratic social critics, just‐war doctrine cannot ignore the workings of the imagination, along with its cultural influences, as those bear on the formation of character, the exercise of practical reason, and civic virtue in the polis. The killing, sacrifice, and death involved in war pose deep questions about meaning and loyalty. And for that reason, questions about the stakes of war involve psychological and sociological dimensions that can be easily overlooked when war’s morality is viewed as a matter of political statecraft alone.</p>
         <p>In this essay I want to address connections between just‐war doctrine and civic virtue, the dynamics of culture and character, and the habits of democratic social criticism in four parts. My aim is to take up Anscombe’s concerns about the effects of war on public culture with an eye toward expanding just‐war doctrine’s potential as a practical morality in civil society. To do that, I will first revisit Augustine’s account of the morality of killing in order to reconnect just‐war tradition to a theory of the virtues. Along the way I will correct a widespread misunderstanding about Augustine, namely, that he justifies war as an expression of Christian beneficence to protect innocent persons at risk. Second, I will consider virtue and the emotions to indicate why we cannot omit attention to the dynamic relationship between character and culture, between the private and public formation of the virtues. In passing, I will note why that relationship helps us understand that considerations of war’s morality must subsume not only matters of political statecraft but also the moral character of culture and the responsibility to assess it. Third, I will propose specific civic virtues that should be indexed to just‐war doctrine in the context of modern, liberal democracies. I will propose three such excellences of character: the dispositions of self‐restraint, critical self‐analysis, and openness to deliberate publicly about moral matters in a context of cultural pluralism. I will indicate briefly how these virtues have concrete implications for popular consent, dissent, and decisions about whether to participate in war. I will conclude by noting that just‐war doctrine involves a spiritual exercise—an ascesis—demanding political elites and ordinary citizens to discipline their attitudes, practices, and representations of the Other according to the demands of respect and fairness—including respect for outsiders whose interests may not be one’s own. That point will take us to an odd and controversial idea that harks back to Augustine, namely, that virtue—including political virtue—is grounded in the practice of confession and the habituation of what Paul Ricoeur suggestively calls a “just memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>I will elaborate on that idea as I conclude this essay.</p>
         <p>The outcome of this discussion will be to conceive of just‐war doctrine as a component in a larger theoretical apparatus, namely,<italic>just‐war morality</italic>. Just‐war doctrine is often deontic and criteria driven, providing norms for assessing political policy and military action. The tendency to view the doctrine in these terms is understandable given its account of war as a “rule‐governed activity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>Seen in this way, just‐war tenets function as a supplement (and potential corrective) to legality and, more important, as an apology for morality against the doctrine’s chief rival in social ethics, namely, political realism. Developed with an eye to rules and principles, just‐war doctrine naturally inclines us to consider the dignity of individuals and the rights of states in conflict situations.</p>
         <p>Viewed only in deontic terms, however, just‐war doctrine too easily produces a “checklist” approach to the ethics of war, in which practical reasoning becomes a matter of assessing discrete acts against a set of disembodied criteria. Just‐war morality implies a wider framework according to which we view the application of just‐war criteria as an exercise of civic virtue and properly habituated social criticism. On these terms, we can say that the ethics of war implicates matters of embodied practical reason, desire, and political identity. And for that reason it sharpens our moral attention on the political obligations of ordinary citizens before, during, and after war. Or so I will argue in the interpretive and constructive account that follows.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>By “just‐war doctrine” I refer to the body of reflection in Western theology and ethics regarding the ethics of going to war (<italic>jus ad bellum</italic>) and the conduct of participants in war (<italic>jus in bello</italic>). Contemporary works developing this general body of ideas include Paul Ramsey,<italic>War and the Christian Conscience: How Shall Modern War Be Conducted Justly?</italic>(Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1961), and<italic>The Just War: Force and Moral Responsibility</italic>(New York: Scribner’s, 1968); Michael Walzer,<italic>Just and Unjust Wars: A Moral Argument with Historical Illustrations</italic>, 1st ed. (New York: Basic, 1977), and<italic>Arguing about War</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2004); James Turner Johnson,<italic>Just War Tradition and the Restraint of War: A Moral and Historical Inquiry</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1981); U.S. Catholic Bishops,<italic>The Challenge of Peace: God’s Promise and Our Response</italic>(Washington, DC: National Conference of Catholic Bishops, 1983); James F. Childress,<italic>Moral Responsibility in Conflicts: Essays on Nonviolence, War, and Conscience</italic>(Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1982); Jenny Teichman,<italic>Pacifism and the Just War: A Study in Applied Philosophy</italic>(Oxford: Blackwell, 1986); Ian Clark,<italic>Waging War: A Philosophical Introduction</italic>(Oxford: Clarendon, 1990); Richard B. Miller,<italic>Interpretations of Conflict: Ethics, Pacifism, and the Just‐War Tradition</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991); Lisa Sowle Cahill,<italic>Love Your Enemies: Discipleship, Pacifism, and Just War Theory</italic>(Minneapolis: Fortress, 1994); Terry Nardin, ed.,<italic>The Ethics of War and Peace: Religious and Secular Perspectives</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1996); A. J. Coates,<italic>The Ethics of War</italic>(Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1997); Jean Bethke Elshtain,<italic>Just War against Terror: The Burden of American Power in a Violent World</italic>(New York: Basic, 2003); Oliver O’Donovan,<italic>The Just War Revisited</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003); Brian Orend,<italic>The Morality of War</italic>(Orchard Park, NY: Broadview, 2006).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Anscombe, “The Justice of the Present War Examined,” 81.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Ibid., 72.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Ibid., 81.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>The phrase is from Ramsey,<italic>The Just War</italic>, pt. 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>U.S. Catholic Bishops,<italic>The Challenge of Peace</italic>, pars. 279–329.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>More general ideas connecting moral philosophy and sociology are asserted by Alasdair MacIntyre,<italic>After Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory</italic>, 2nd ed. (Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 1984), 23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>The phrase is lifted from Anscombe, “The Justice of the Present War Examined”; see n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>John Rawls,<italic>A Theory of Justice</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press/Belknap, 1971), 454.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Alexis de Toqueville,<italic>Democracy in America</italic>, trans. George Lawrence, ed. J. P. Mayer (New York: Doubleday/Anchor Books, 1969), 287.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>I discuss this synergism more generally in Richard B. Miller, “On Making a Cultural Turn in Religious Ethics,”<italic>Journal of Religious Ethics</italic>33 (September 2005): 403–39.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey and David Pellauer (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004), 68.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>See Walzer,<italic>Just and Unjust Wars</italic>, 41. Walzer’s approach avoids the charge of disembodiment that I raise in the next paragraph given his use of historical examples and connections to casuistry (xxx).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Augustine on Virtue and Killing</title>
         <p>I want to pursue this more expansive account of just‐war morality by revisiting Augustine’s ethics of desire and killing in self‐defense and war. I do so because the just‐war tradition traces its origins to Augustine and because he so clearly focuses on moral psychology, the affections, and human motivation in his discussion of killing.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>Augustine frames his approach to homicide not in terms of applying moral norms to particular acts but in terms of assessing the effects of killing on the agent who performs it. He reminds us that the morality of actions must consider not only how one’s action affects the well‐being of others but also how one’s action affects oneself. Augustinian morality in this sense is “agent‐referring.”</p>
         <p>Summarizing his views about homicide in a letter written ca. 397, Augustine states: “I do not approve of this, unless one happen[s] to be a soldier or public functionary acting, not for himself, but in defense of others or of the city in which he resides, if he act[s] according to the commission lawfully given him, and in the manner becoming his office.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Here Augustine forbids private individuals from killing in self‐defense but allows public officials to kill in defense of themselves and their community. He clarifies his views later in<italic>City of God</italic>: “When a soldier kills a man in obedience to the legitimate authority under which he served, he is not chargeable with murder by the laws of his country; in fact he is chargeable with insubordination and mutiny if he refuses. But if he did it of his own accord, on his own authority, he would be liable for the charge of homicide. Thus he is punished if he did it without orders for the same reason that he will be punished if he refuses when ordered.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>Note that Augustine’s permission of public killing is not premised on the idea that love requires Christians to assume risks to help others, especially the weak, in need. That idea takes its origins from Augustine’s teacher, Ambrose, and owes its influence today to Paul Ramsey, a follower of Augustine in several respects.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>Love indeed informs Augustine’s ethics of homicide but not as the basis for justifying coercive force as an expression of care or selfless protection of the innocent.</p>
         <p>For Augustine, love is a virtuous desire when it disposes us to order our actions to their proper ends for their own sake.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>We distort Augustinian thinking by confusing the virtue of love with acts of beneficence or by importing the deontic language of agape into a theological eudaemonism structured by the virtue of<italic>caritas</italic>. Augustine focuses not on principles instructing us to protect another from danger but on how our dispositions and attachments are organized in relation to various ends and how we affect ourselves through ordered or disordered activity. “Whatever you injure,” Augustine remarks about acting in hatred, “you injure outwardly; notice what injury you do to yourself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>The evil posed by killing bears on one’s character. That is to say, one key question for Augustine concerns the goods to which one assigns value and which provide the horizon for meaning and identity.</p>
         <p>According to Augustine, those who kill in private self‐defense act for “those things which can be lost against their will, and which they should therefore not love.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>Self‐defensive killing means, among other things, loving ourselves in excess and degrading ourselves in the process. Such killing implicates us in a disordered set of attachments according to which we rank the good of the mortal body above the value of the immortal soul and the value of the neighbor. About life in the body, Augustine writes, “perhaps one might doubt whether life is somehow taken from the soul when the body is slain. But if it can be taken away, it is of little value; and if it cannot, there is nothing to fear.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>According to Augustine, killing in private self‐defense necessarily implies excessive attachment to the transitory good of bodily life.</p>
         <p>Killing in defense of the common good by public officers acting within the parameters of their official responsibilities is different. Augustine writes, “The natural order which seeks the peace of mankind, ordains that the monarch should have the power of undertaking war if he thinks it advisable, and that the soldiers should perform their military duties in behalf of peace and safety of the community.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>He describes acts of justified homicide as “exceptions to the law against killing, made by the authority of God himself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>In Augustine’s mind, especially during the latter part of his career, political life serves real, objective goods that can be defended in ways that allow for proportionate ordering of loves and commitments.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>The public order embodies an image or replication of harmony—less perfect than the ideal, heavenly city but providing a (relatively) good harmony nonetheless. The heavenly city, he writes, “does not hesitate to obey the laws of the earthly city by which those things which are designed for the support of this mortal life are regulated; and the purpose of this obedience is that, since this mortal condition is shared by both cities, a harmony may be preserved between them in things that are relevant to this condition.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>The earthly city serves a relative good, necessary for members of the heavenly city on their pilgrimage to their final destination. Accordingly, persons whose loves are properly ordered may attach relative value to the good that political life is meant to secure. Augustine writes, “[God] has given to mankind certain good things suitable to this life. These are: temporal peace, in proportion to the short span of mortal life—the peace that consists in bodily health and soundness, and in fellowship with one’s kind; and everything necessary to safeguard or recover this peace.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This account of the relative, instrumental good of political life leads Augustine to view its defense by public officials as justifiable. For Augustine, the use of lethal force poses fewer dangers to the ordering of an individual’s attachments when his actions are mediated by role responsibilities and organized toward the protection of the common good. Killing is less intimate for soldiers than for private persons insofar as it is carried out as a duty of public office. For that reason, homicide can be more detached and disinterested—ordered by interests that go beyond a private person’s immediate loves to include the commonweal. Augustine writes, “A soldier who kills the enemy is acting as an agent of the law, so he can easily perform his duty without inordinate desire.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine thus assigns fewer restrictions to public officials using violence in defense of the corporate body than to individuals who use force in defense of the private, individual body. The danger of disordered attachment appears greater to him in the latter case than in the former. That is to say, excessive attachment to bodily, mortal life is a greater temptation for private persons in relation to themselves than it is for public officials who act on behalf of the body politic.</p>
         <p>This is not to suggest that one cannot commit wrongdoing as a public officer. For Augustine, the real evil in war is not injury and death but “love of violence, revengeful cruelty, fierce and implacable enmity, wild resistance, and the lust for power.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>Though justifiable in principle, war is also an occasion for concupiscence and the vice of<italic>libido dominandi</italic>. Soldiers and their commanders might act not in pursuit of justice but from a will‐to‐power. Their actions can become disordered by interests that swing wide from the virtues of fairness, prudence, temperance, and courage. These interests are real temptations, but in Augustine’s view, they can be resisted. And herein lies one key difference in his mind between private and public killing. For the private person, excessive attachment to temporal goods is a<italic>necessary</italic>feature of private self‐defensive violence. For the public official or solider, in contrast, excessive attachment to temporal goods is only a<italic>contingent</italic>feature of violent action.</p>
         <p>Understanding Augustine’s ethics of homicide properly, then, means placing it within a wider framework of moral psychology and social roles, focusing on desire, the order of our attachments, and the temptations that such attachments pose in private and public life. We get nowhere reading Augustine’s theological ethics until we understand that, for him, the good is prior to the right. In his ethics of killing, it is crucial to grasp how homicide raises questions about one’s internal psychic harmony, the ordering of one’s loves. Homicide might derive from a lack of harmony and peace from within. Peace within the soul is the sine qua non of peaceful relationships, relationships that are rightly ordered according to natural purposes and patterns.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Regarding the morality of soldiering, Augustine interprets the love command to apply to the internal dispositions of public officers who are commissioned to defend the common good. Love works to constrain: public officers are not to act out of vengeance or a lust for cruelty, but they are otherwise authorized to use force on behalf of the good of political life. Attention to the duties of public office, individual interiority, and the needs of the commonweal mediate Augustine’s understanding of biblical teaching. This is especially true regarding Jesus’s command to “resist not evil”—a command that would appear to prohibit all uses of violence. That account of the love command, Augustine writes, pertains not to “a bodily action, but an inward disposition. The sacred seat of virtue is the heart.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>The concepts of public responsibility, dispositional morality, and the common good structure Augustine’s account of social responsibility and provide the framework for his interpretation of Jesus’s command. That structure provides rational concepts according to which Augustine translates the teachings of Christian faith into the ethics of killing in private and public life.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Does Augustine authorize the use of force as an expression of neighbor love? This view is widely held among interpreters of Augustine and the just‐war tradition, but it courts confusion. The general idea is that Augustine justifies killing when it aims to protect those who are otherwise helpless; such protection is an expression of Christian charity. Oliver O’Donovan writes along these lines: “Augustine’s famous letter to Boniface treats the obligation of military action as an obligation of love to the neighbor.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>Similarly, the U.S. Catholic bishops state that, according to Augustine, “war arose from disordered ambitions, but it could also be used … to restrain evil and protect the innocent. The classic case which illustrated his view was the use of lethal force to prevent aggression against innocent victims. Faced with the fact of attack on the innocent, the presumption that we do no harm, even to our enemy, yielded to the command to love understood as the need to restrain an enemy who would injure the innocent.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>The same idea finds its way into a letter signed by sixty scholars and public figures, “What We’re Fighting For.” There we read that “the primary moral justification for war is to protect innocent people from certain harm. Augustine … argues (echoing Socrates) that it is better for the Christian as an individual to suffer harm rather than to commit it.” The authors then ask, “But is the morally responsible person also required, or even permitted, to make for<italic>other</italic>innocent persons a commitment to non‐defense? For Augustine, and for the broader just war tradition, the answer is no. If one has compelling evidence that innocent people who are in no position to protect themselves will be grievously harmed unless coercive force is used to stop the aggressor, then the moral principle of love of neighbor calls us to the use of force.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine never articulates his justification of war in these terms. In the letter to Boniface to which O’Donovan refers, Augustine makes no connection between love and the duty to perform military service. He makes the more modest admonition that Boniface “not think that no one who serves as a soldier, using arms for warfare, can be acceptable to God.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>The proper aim of soldiering is not to carry out a duty to the helpless neighbor but to secure peace through war, which must be waged only as a necessity. Indeed, Augustine speaks as if love as an exercise of will lies outside the bounds of war. He writes, “It ought to be necessity, and not your will, that destroys an enemy who is fighting you.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>Claiming that proper recourse to military action arises as an expression of neighbor love goes beyond the plain meaning of Augustine’s text.</p>
         <p>Augustine’s core position is that the use of force is justified in response to a grievance for the sake of civic peace and order when carried out lawfully by proper authorities. (In one letter, to the public official Macedonius, Augustine allows for forceful action by a private citizen to kill in self‐defense, but in that case he is imagining a wayfarer outside the bounds of civic order and public authority—a traveler who kills a robber.)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>Augustine nowhere justifies war as an expression of beneficent love in his various writings and discussions of war, such as<italic>City of God</italic>. Rather, as I indicated above, a just war operates in the service of peace, understood as including rightly ordered relationships between parts and wholes. The just warrior acts to defend or restore peace‐as‐order, not to protect the innocent neighbor selflessly, when carrying out violent acts.</p>
         <p>Stated differently, Augustine justifies killing as a rightly ordered action toward defending the common good by public officials.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>It bears repeating that the key to understanding Augustine’s position is not a moral theory of duty, in which the right is prior to the good, but a broader, teleological ethical theory and moral psychology with a focal concern for psychic and social order. For Augustine, disordered attachments are illusory and dangerous. They are illusory because they mean putting oneself at the center of one’s loyalties and, equally problematic for Augustine, allowing oneself to be the sole arbiter and center of value. Such are the dangers of the sin of pride: ignoring the ontological distinction between eternity and time, Creator and creation. Disordered attachments become dangerous because overstepping the boundary between Creator and creation leads us naturally to violate boundaries that structure our common life. Such internal disharmony leads to the problem the Greeks understood as<italic>pleonexia</italic>—grasping for power and advantage in order to overcome our fear about losing transitory objects of attachment. Confusing the distinction between temporal and eternal goods leads us to ignore the boundaries that properly separate persons from each other and that enable us to grasp our individuality and our differences. Hence the connection between theology, psychology, and morality in Augustine’s discussion of homicide and the moral life more generally. When we privilege ourselves and our temporal needs, we are prone, anxiously and apprehensively, to overreach. For Augustine, boundaries are both metaphysical and moral.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine’s attention to the proper ordering of values and attachments directly informs his practical ethics of war. In that context, one requirement is to avoid killing out of motives that mirror how unjust warriors behave. That is to say, the central danger from an Augustinian standpoint is imitating the wrong paradigm of action, falling prey to what might be called disordered mimesis. Soldiers who kill out of “love of violence, revengeful cruelty, fierce and implacable enmity, wild resistance, and the lust for power” mimic the injustice that they are supposed to remedy and implicate themselves in the prideful evil that they are commissioned to resist. Their character is diminished by the same disordered loyalties that motivate the actions of their (unjust) opponents. Soldiers who obey orders, in contrast, put aside their own judgments and attachments, and act apart from their unmediated interests. Killing that is mediated by obedient submission to authority canalizes the aggressive passions of warriors in combat. Augustine writes, “For the good would even wage war with mercy, were it possible, with the aim of taming unrestrained passions and destroying vices that ought, under a just rule, to be uprooted or suppressed.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>Indeed, Augustine believes that soldiers who obey orders are blameless if they commit wrongdoing at the behest of their superiors.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>
         </p>
         <p>For Augustine, the soldier’s ethic is a virtue ethic—one of psychic restraint, respect for boundaries, and orderly submission in the service of justice. Just war for Augustine operates in part within a penal and restorative paradigm—to punish wrongdoing, reset the balance upset by injustice, and restore a just and peaceable order.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>But about the connections between virtue and other political offices, such as citizenship, Augustine offers us little guidance. As John M. Rist notes, “Augustine’s attitude [toward political activity] is conditioned by the non‐democratic principle that most people have no kind of official status as<italic>de facto</italic>public officials. He leaves little room for the authority and powers of the ordinary individual simply as a citizen, a member of society.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>Perhaps because the empire was crumbling as he was writing the<italic>City of God</italic>, Augustine directed little attention to citizens’ political responsibilities to the res publica. Augustine’s political ethic is thus incomplete, for it ignores the vast space between the private morality of individuals and the public morality of soldiers, princes, and emperors. Attention to “orders of creation” that diversify public life would have to wait until Luther to gain a hearing, and even that hearing provides only a general sketch of the spheres and roles that naturally mediate human freedom and desire in civil society.</p>
         <p>We must therefore expand Augustine’s political morality to subsume a wider range of political responsibilities and practices. For that project, his ideas provide a start. Indeed, as I hope to show, his ideas provide fruitful points of departure for considering the ethical dimensions of, and connections between, death, memory, and the desires that animate public culture. He reminds us that the morality of war is, in part, a morality of desire and love, and that human attachments can be rightly ordered when they stand within a network of differentiated relationships and institutional responsibilities. That fact alone ought to alert us to the importance of the affections and how they are mediated by social processes and cultural norms. For Augustine, the commandment to love is not simple and straightforward; it is structured by our social affiliations and our natural interactions. However distant Augustine’s views of citizen morality might seem, his ideas of moral formation have much to teach. And so let us consider the synergism between culture and the affections as these ideas help shape an understanding of moral formation (and deformation) in the res publica.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>For discussions of Augustine and the just war, see Herbert Deane,<italic>The Political and Social Ideas of St. Augustine</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1963); Richard Shelly Hartigan, “St. Augustine on War and Killing: The Problem of the Innocent,”<italic>Journal of the History of Ideas</italic>27 (April–June 1966): 195–204; Louis J. Swift, “Augustine on War and Killing: Another View,”<italic>Harvard Theological Review</italic>66 (July 1973): 369–83; Frederick H. Russell,<italic>The Just War in the Middle Ages</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975), and “War,” in<italic>Augustine through the Ages: An Encyclopedia</italic>, general ed. Allan D. Fitzgerald, with a foreword by Jaroslav Pelikan (Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1999), 875–76; R. A. Markus, “Saint Augustine’s Views on the ‘Just War,’” in<italic>The Church and War</italic>, ed. W. J. Sheils (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1983), 1–13; John Langan, “The Elements of St. Augustine’s Just War Theory,”<italic>Journal of Religious Ethics</italic>12 (Spring 1984): 19–38; David A. Lenihan, “The Just War Theory in the Work of Saint Augustine,”<italic>Augustinian Studies</italic>19 (1988): 37–70; Robert L. Holmes, “St. Augustine and Just‐War Theory,” in<italic>The Augustinian Tradition</italic>, ed. Gareth B. Matthews (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1999), 323–44; Ramsey,<italic>War and the Christian Conscience</italic>, chap. 2; Johnson,<italic>Just War Tradition and the Restraint of War</italic>, 150–65, 349–51; Cahill,<italic>Love Your Enemies</italic>, 55–80.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Letter 47, to Publicola,” in<italic>A Select Library of Nicene and Post‐Nicene Fathers</italic>, ed. Philip Schaff and Henry Wace, 14 vols. (Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1956), 1:293.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>Concerning the City of God against the Pagans</italic>, trans. Henry Bettenson (New York: Penguin Books, 1972), bk. 1, chap. 26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>The key passage by Ambrose is notably brief: “He who does not keep harm off a friend, if he can, is as much in fault as he who causes it.” See Ambrose, “On the Duties of the Clergy,” in Schaff and Wace,<italic>A Select Library of Nicene and Post‐Nicene Fathers</italic>, vol. 10, bk. 1, chap. 36, par. 179. See also Ramsey,<italic>War and the Christian Conscience</italic>, chap. 2, and<italic>The Just War</italic>, chap. 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>See William S. Babcock, “<italic>Cupiditas and Caritas</italic>: The Early Augustine on Love and Human Fulfillment,” in<italic>The Ethics of St. Augustine</italic>, ed. William S. Babcock (Atlanta: Scholars, 1991), 39–66, at 44; John M. Rist,<italic>Augustine: Ancient Thought Baptized</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994), 174.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>Letter 82.3 in<italic>Works of Saint Augustine: A Translation for the Twenty‐first Century</italic>, Sermons 51–94, ed. John E. Rotelle, trans. Edmund Hill (Brooklyn, NY: New City Press, 1990), pt. 3, 3:370. Rist summarizes Augustine’s position well: “`Private violence’ demoralizes and brutalizes the agent.” See Rist,<italic>Augustine: Ancient Thought Baptized</italic>, 194.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>The comment is from Augustine’s interlocutor, Evodius, but Augustine concurs with the premise in the dialogue. See Augustine,<italic>On Free Choice of the Will</italic>, trans. and with an intro. by Thomas Williams (Indianapolis: Hackett, 1993), 9.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Reply to Faustus the Manichean,” in Schaff and Wace,<italic>A Select Library of Nicene and Post‐Nicene Fathers</italic>, vol. 4, par. 75.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>The City of God</italic>, bk. 1, chap. 21.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>For a discussion of this and related points in the context of Augustine’s developing views of killing and suffering, see Kevin Carnahan, “Perturbations of the Soul and Pains of the Body: Augustine on Evil Suffered and Done in War,”<italic>Journal of Religious Ethics</italic>36 (June 2008): 269–94.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 19, chap. 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Ibid., chap. 13; see also bk. 3, chap. 10, and bk. 19, chaps. 14, 17. Carnahan instructively discusses these passages in “Perturbations of the Soul,” 285.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>On Free Choice of the Will</italic>, 8.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Reply to Faustus the Manichean,” par. 74.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 19, chaps. 12, 13, 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Reply to Faustus the Manichean,” par. 76.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Miller,<italic>Interpretations of Conflict</italic>, 18–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>O’Donovan,<italic>Just War Revisited</italic>, 9. In the letter to Boniface (189) in question, Augustine writes that the obligation to extend mercy to the vanquished in war is an exercise of restorative justice, not that war’s proper aim is to protect the innocent. For a discussion of Augustine and restorative justice, see J. Warren Smith, “Augustine and the Limits of Preemptive and Preventive War,”<italic>Journal of Religious Ethics</italic>35 (March 2007): 141–62.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>U.S. Catholic Bishops,<italic>The Challenge of Peace</italic>, par. 81.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>“What We’re Fighting For,” included as an appendix in Elshtain,<italic>Just War against Terror</italic>, 189; see also Garry Wills, “What Is a Just War?”<italic>New York Review of Books</italic>, November 18, 2004, 33.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Letter 189: Augustine to Boniface (417),” in<italic>Augustine: Political Writings</italic>, ed. E. M. Atkins and R. J. Dodaro (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001), 216.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Ibid., 217.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Letter 153: Augustine to Macedonius (413/414),” in<italic>Augustine: Political Writings</italic>, 81.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>In one context Augustine uses<italic>benevolence</italic>to describe the just warrior’s proper ordering of dispositions toward certain ends. In a letter to Marcellinus, Augustine writes that Christians “should always have perfect benevolence in case we return evil for evil.” Understood in that way, benevolence serves a negative, chastening function. For those who claim that Augustine understands war as an expression of beneficent care for the innocent, it is interesting to note that in this letter he understands acting benevolently to mean that “people are often to be helped, against their will, by being punished with a sort of kind harshness.” The beneficence involved, in other words, targets wrongdoers, not victims. See Augustine, “Letter 138: Augustine to Marcellinus (411/412),” in<italic>Augustine: Political Writings</italic>, 38.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>As William S. Babcock puts it: “It is<italic>cupiditas</italic>, the<italic>amor</italic>for things that can be lost against one’s will (<italic>De lib arb</italic>. 1.4.10), that gives birth to this desperate sense that others constitute a threat to self. Fearing loss, it seeks to secure against loss by removing or dominating others so as to eliminate the threat they represent. … It sets one person against another; and the only answer to it is another love, or rather love for another object that is not vulnerable to loss.” See Babcock, “<italic>Cupiditas and Caritas</italic>,” 47.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Letter 138: Augustine to Marcellinus,” in<italic>Augustine: Political Writings,</italic>38.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Augustine, “Reply to Faustus the Manichean,” par. 75. To the modern reader, these comments and their attention to character say frustratingly little that echoes the idea that war is justified and limited in principled ways. While it is true that Augustine shows little interest in questions such as noncombatant immunity, the<italic>jus in bello</italic>, and the related idea of human rights, I believe it requires little to draw out such ideas from his account. Intentionally killing innocent persons is symptomatic of a deeper set of disordered motives. Such killing is wrong on Augustinian terms because it flows from concupiscent affections. Others’ claim to be left alone is violated by persons who seek to subject them to their avaricious desires. As Babcock suggests, attending to how virtues restrain human impulses enables us to see how Augustine could speak to such modern concerns. Langan’s views on this matter are qualified, but he captures the general point when he observes that Augustine’s warnings against being motivated by revenge “point the way to a limitation of the horrors of war by focusing on the virtues and attitudes of warriors. This does not eliminate the need for a rule of noncombatant immunity, but it is reasonable to think that care to develop a regard for certain moral virtues and values among soldiers would contribute in an important and perhaps decisive way to the preservation of many of the values which the rules of<italic>jus in bello</italic>are designed to protect.” See Hartigan, “St. Augustine on War and Killing: The Problem of the Innocent,” 195–204; Babcock, “<italic>Cupiditas and Caritas</italic>,” 47; Langan, “Elements of St. Augustine’s Just‐War Theory,” 32; Swift, “Augustine on War and Killing,” 369–83.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>I say “in part” so as not to exclude the purpose of defending temporal goods, as I note above.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Rist,<italic>Augustine: Ancient Thought Baptized</italic>, 195.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>War, the Affections, and Civic Virtue</title>
         <p>War typically arouses feelings of indignation and mourning—indignation at the injustices that surround one or both sides in war; mourning for the loss of life and goods associated with forming a common life. Doubtless for that reason Augustine described even a just war as marked by “heartfelt grief.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>Indignation and mourning are more complicated than “unpleasant” or “uncomfortable” sentiments alone; they express esteem for what has been lost or what has been unjustly put at risk: security, friendship, peace, freedom, community, natural habitat. Augustine makes a similar point about the emotions when he poignantly describes his feelings in response to his friend’s death in book 4 of<italic>Confessions</italic>and, later in that same work, when he grieves the death of his mother.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>Augustine’s deep and anxious mourning tells him something about how he orders his loves—about whether they are virtuous or not.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>Underlying that worry is the fact that, in Augustinian moral psychology, emotions are not merely raw feelings. They are moral responses, registering what we value through the passions. Our feelings thus presuppose norms that, properly recognized, prevent us from self‐indulgence or inordinate attachment to worldly objects. Augustine writes, “In general, as a man’s will is attracted to or repelled in accordance with the various character of different objects which are pursued or shunned, so it changes and turns into feelings of various kinds.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>Emotions themselves are not a problem for Augustine; they express an interpretation of an event, the embrace or loss of an objective good. Ideally, indignation or mourning are forms of properly ordered appreciation, for we would not feel a loss were we not previously attached to something genuinely valuable that has now ceased to be.</p>
         <p>Viewing grief and indignation as potentially virtuous seems odd given the tendency to construe virtue in positive terms, as ennobling or self‐enhancing. We typically associate the virtues with a good and genuinely happy life, and surely those positive features characterize the virtues.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>But that fact should not prevent us from seeing how responses to loss and disconnection can also be expressions of moral excellence. Virtue, Aristotle writes, means feeling pleasure and pain in the right way. Schooled in the virtues, we should feel “at the right times, with reference to the right objects, towards the right people, with the right motive, and in the right way,” as he says of strong and noble character.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>Casting similar ideas in Christian terms, Augustine writes, “Citizens of the Holy City of God, as they live by God’s standards in the pilgrimage of this present life, feel fear and desire, pain and gladness in conformity with the holy Scriptures and sound doctrine; and because their love is right, all these feelings are right in them.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine would add that our affections are not merely individualistic; they are intersubjective and attach themselves to political and collective goods (among other shareable values). We “feel together” in ways that led Augustine to be keenly attentive to the moral quality of his friendships as well as to matters that bear on a common life. “The life of a city is inevitably a social life,” he writes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>He expressed these ideas most famously in his account of what constitutes a people. For Augustine, we understand a “people” to be an “association of rational beings united by a common agreement on the objects of their love.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>Unity is experienced dialogically and intersubjectively, for which love and desire provide the social glue. Hence the fact that citizens in the res publica justifiably share a worry about injury to their attachments when injustice occurs: their common goods, cherished traditions, and political values. For Augustine, these goods are legitimate objects of attachment insofar as they furnish essential conditions of creative freedom.</p>
         <p>Grief about the loss of such goods is one way to express a sense of their importance. At the same time, grief’s emotional and practical consequences can be morally precarious. They can produce a thirst for “revengeful cruelty, fierce and implacable enmity, wild resistance, and the lust for power” unless reformed by the virtues. For that reason alone, the experience of collective indignation and mourning should require persons to assess their own society’s conduct, hoping that what is done to others in response to a grievance is not an occasion for further misery. Actions that flow from the emotions should not be the cause of others’ moral indignation. This is one reason to be concerned about justice—justice to ourselves and to others. For Augustine, our sentiments should be constrained by fairness; we should not expect others to endure injustice any more than we do. Pride, “the perverted imitation of God[,] … hates a fellowship of equality under God, and seeks to impose its own dominion on fellow men.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>Without properly ordered love, the conditions necessary for such equality and fellowship are elusive. With that idea in mind, Augustine rebukes the Romans in these terms: “As to the objects of that people’s love—both in the earliest times and in subsequent periods—and the morality of that people as it proceeded to bloody strife of parties and then to the social and civil wars, and corrupted and disrupted that very unity which is, as it were, the health of a people—for all this we have the witness of history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Describing the affections in moral terms takes note of the fact that they are shaped by cultural influences. It is no stretch for Augustine to describe the emotions, as Paul Lauritzen does, as a “kind of cultural artifact.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>Emotions cannot occur outside of a horizon of expectations, a moral world in which our conduct is indexed against a hierarchy of values. The quality of the emotions, says Augustine, lies in “the character of a man’s will. If the will is wrongly directed, the emotions will be wrong; if the will is right, the emotions will not only be blameless, but praiseworthy.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>In this way, emotions are themselves rule‐governed and depend upon a wider system of shared meanings according to which the will directs itself. Emotions are expressions of agency shaped by standards of value, what Charles Taylor calls norms of “strong evaluation.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">58</xref>Such norms articulate goods toward which persons order their commitments and from which they derive their bases for self‐interpretation.</p>
         <p>This account also indicates that the emotions are learned. As culturally mediated, they are transmitted by those who powerfully articulate a society’s standards of value. We gain a sense of how to interpret, respond to, and remember life’s contingencies with the aid of culture’s norms. Because our emotions are shaped by ethos and culture, it behooves us to consider how cultural images and political rhetoric bear upon the imagination. That is to say, given the dynamic relationship between character and culture, moral assessment of the former cannot overlook the quality of the latter. It is therefore necessary to evaluate how cultures ask their members to imagine themselves and their opponents when they consider recourse to war. For these (broad) Augustinian reasons, we can posit an ethics of heterology: cultural representations of the Other should be subject to moral evaluation insofar as they condition, and perhaps corrupt, one’s affective sense of what others are due.</p>
         <p>The good of justice both issues from and helps to discipline the affections, enabling citizens to respond well to war’s moral challenges to individual and collective character. Put differently, the collective experience of the emotions points to the importance of the virtues, especially civic virtue. Virtue refers to rightly ordered habits that incline us to act and feel in certain ways. Equally important, and often overlooked in moral theory, virtues have a political as well as a personal quality; they pertain to public and private life. They thus provide normative terms for informing and disciplining human feelings as we move between our intimate and less personal settings.</p>
         <p>Civic virtue consists of our dispositions toward and loyalty to the commonweal, typically requiring us to subordinate personal goods to civic goods when the two conflict.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">59</xref>The ideal of civic virtue holds great importance in the tradition of civic republicanism that traces its beginnings to Cicero. In that tradition, true excellences are dispositions that incline an agent toward the common good. Augustine’s own attitude toward civic virtue, to be sure, was ambivalent. He believed civic virtue as practiced by the Romans to be a counterfeit excellence. In his estimation, Rome was founded and fueled by a love for glory. About Roman political history, he writes, “It was this greed for praise, this passion for glory, that gave rise to those marvelous achievements, which were, no doubt, praiseworthy and glorious in men’s estimation.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">60</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine’s critique works less to discount civic virtue as a moral ideal than to dispute its goodness in the hands of the Romans. Indeed, his evaluation works on the assumption that civic virtue is a good that was honored in the breach. We should thus view the<italic>City of God</italic>in its entirety as an expression of civic virtue given Augustine’s relentless critique of Roman rule throughout that work.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">61</xref>He avows that Rome was founded on fratricide over envy and the pursuit of glory, recalling the story of Cain and Abel and the founding of the earthly city.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">62</xref>Roman deities “allowed the most terrible and abominable evils to have free play,” not only privately in the mind but publicly in games and the theater.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">63</xref>Augustine cites Roman authorities themselves, including the historian Sallust, to support his view that the Roman republic changed “from the high of excellence to the depths of depravity,” including the permission of such things as the rape of the Sabine women.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">64</xref>Roman gods were clear projections of human desires and the quest for flattery rather than sources of objective sources of “right living.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">65</xref>Recalling these and other facts of Roman history, Augustine writes, “I am sick of recalling the many acts of revolting injustice which have disturbed this city’s history; the powerful classes did their best to subjugate the lower orders, and the lower orders resisted—the leader of each side motivated more by ambition than by any ideas of equity and morality.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">66</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Augustine’s polemics are well known but may lead us wrongly to conclude that civic virtue was only one of the many “splendid vices” of pagan thought and culture. We should rather say that, in Augustine’s hands, civic virtue can function as a critical principle or, more precisely, a disposition to practice social criticism. Political elites and cultural authorities who ask citizens to accept unjust practices corrode a “sense of justice,” the virtue of equity and respect for others that should animate social institutions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">67</xref>As a disposition that infuses a common life and inclines us to think about the moral quality of the commonweal, civic virtue describes a quality of mutual interaction that helps to constitute a collective way of being. Civic virtue thus coordinates and deepens an ensemble of collective desires—our “fellow feelings” toward ourselves as citizens linked by shared purposes of the common good.</p>
         <p>Seen as a feature of civic virtue and the demands of justice, just‐war morality can subsume more than a set of moral norms to assess political policy and military practice. The core claims of justice can also frame how ordinary citizens dispose themselves toward the common good as their leaders respond to political grievances. As a matter of moral and political psychology, we may query whether the popular desires that motivate support for war are desirable. We should thus examine how political authorities describe the stakes in war, how they represent our opponents, and how they attempt to appeal to our sense of fairness for popular support. Without such critical inquiry, our responses to war can too easily curdle into expressions of what Augustine knew as<italic>libido dominandi</italic>, leaving the Other vulnerable to one’s self‐deceiving and dangerous practices.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 19, chap. 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>These two deaths are differently related to the virtue of hope, itself a fruit of Augustine’s conversion. For an instructive discussion of grief, time, hope, and the deaths of Augustine’s friend and mother, see Genevieve Lloyd, “Augustine and the ‘Problem’ of Time,” in<italic>The Augustinian Tradition</italic>, ed. Gareth B. Matthews (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1999), 39–60.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>In the first case, the loss of a friend, Augustine’s grief teaches him that his love is excessive, an expression of inordinate self‐love. See Augustine,<italic>Confessions</italic>, trans. with an introduction by P. S. Pine‐Coffin (New York: Penguin, 1983), bk. 4. Augustine worries about the same problem after the death of his mother, which launches the principal confession of<italic>Confessions</italic>, in bk. 9, chap. 12. Mourning is clearly a response to death for Augustine and has deep connections to his awareness of human finitude and the power of time more generally. Mourning, then, has moral and ontological aspects. In that respect, we must read Augustine’s narrative account of his grief in relation to his theological account of humanity’s being‐in‐time in<italic>Confessions</italic>, bk. 11. As an act of memory, mourning for Augustine would be an act of what Ricoeur calls “being‐in‐the‐face‐of‐death, against‐death.” See Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 369; Lloyd, “Augustine and the ‘Problem' of Time.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 14, chap. 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Augustine argues along such lines in ibid., bk. 19, chap. 3. Augustine adds that even the life of virtue involves struggle (bk. 4).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Aristotle,<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>, trans. W. D. Ross, in<italic>The Basic Works of Aristotle</italic>, ed. Richard McKeon (New York: Random House, 1969), 1106b20–24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 14, chap. 9.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Ibid., bk. 19, chap. 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Ibid., chap. 24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Ibid., chap. 12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>Ibid., chap. 24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>Paul Lauritzen, “Emotions and Religious Ethics,”<italic>Journal of Religious Ethics</italic>16 (Fall 1988): 307–24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 14, chap. 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>Charles Taylor,<italic>Sources of the Self: The Making of the Modern Identity</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1989), chap. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>Richard Dagger,<italic>Civic Virtues: Rights, Citizenship, and Republican Liberalism</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1997), 13–14.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 5, chap. 12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>John Milbank’s interpretation of the<italic>City of God</italic>seems to gesture in this direction, especially when he writes that Augustine achieves an immanent critique “or deconstruction of antique political society.” See John Milbank,<italic>Theology and Social Theory</italic>(London: Basil Blackwell, 1990), 389.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 15, chap. 5. Augustine adds a difference: The quarrel between Remus and Romulus “demonstrated the division of the earthly city against itself; while the conflict between Cain and Abel displayed the conflict between … the City of God and the city of men.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>Ibid., bk. 1, chap. 32.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>Ibid., bk. 2, chaps. 17–19.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>Ibid., chaps. 15, 16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>Ibid., chap. 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>Rawls,<italic>A Theory of Justice</italic>, 454.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Consent and Dissent</title>
         <p>We can view just‐war morality, then, as emerging from an Augustinian attention to virtue and as mediating the desires of citizens toward (and beyond) the commonweal. Seen in those terms, just‐war morality provides a framework that canalizes the affections and provides broad values for assessing how cultural processes structure the passions that underlie popular support for war. As a self‐reflexive idiom for social criticism, just‐war morality provides criteria for both evaluating the decisions of political elites and for disciplining individual and corporate character. And in that way we can strengthen the otherwise tenuous connection between the ethics of war and the responsibilities of democratic social critics.</p>
         <p>This is not to suggest that citizens who are alienated from political and social institutions should co‐opt just‐war morality or that those who protest against authority as their principal expression of political action should adopt just‐war tenets as merely useful rhetoric for venting their views. Just‐war morality provides substance for moral judgment and the expression of democratic consent or dissent.</p>
         <p>When thinking about such judgments and practices of dissent, we do well to distinguish between its<italic>expressive</italic>and<italic>instrumental</italic>forms. Expressive dissenters rebuke public officials as an end in itself, as an intrinsic good, and often find in such dissent a mode of self‐articulation. They reject a priori the idea that government can enjoy the consent of the governed and perhaps find in political criticism an opportunity for ecstatic cathexis, anarchist aesthetics, or the manifestation of a sectarian ethic. But whatever the psychology of such dissent may be, such modes of disaffection undermine the prospect of genuine dialogue, deliberation, and consent as a matter of principle. Expressive dissent rejects the idea that the merits of one or another public policy are open for deliberation, evaluation, and popular approval. Such dissent might draw on nonmainstream political, religious, or cultural traditions, but it is antidemocratic in the context of modern, representative democracies insofar as it categorically rules out the prospect of consent, the very basis of democratic legitimacy.</p>
         <p>Instrumental dissent, on the other hand, is conditional. It is premised on the idea that, in principle, political institutions and policies can pass muster and may be worthy of popular support. Instrumental dissent aims at internal political reform, seeking to establish the proper basis for consent. It presumes that terms exist according to which respect should be assigned to public policy and its formation. Instrumental dissent is essential to, indeed constitutive of, the institution of consent, not a rejection of it. Informed by the idea that such dissent is part of civic virtue in modern, democratic polities, just‐war morality enables citizens to evaluate political leaders’ decisions in order to determine whether those decisions are worthy of approval and allegiance.</p>
         <p>What virtues should be indexed to just‐war morality and the habits it requires for instrumental dissent? I want briefly to identify three such dispositions: self‐restraint, self‐analysis, and the willingness to deliberate publicly. These virtues are implicit in modern democratic theory and augment the habits on which democratic practices rely. They presuppose moral goods that attach to democratic life, goods that redound to cultures in which equality and respect are fundamental principles that organize political roles and institutions. Moreover, they presume that self‐reflection and dialogical deliberation help to constitute a good life. Equally important, they enable us to identify resources for an ethics of heterology that resists the temptations of xenophobia and self‐justification to which Anscombe calls our attention in the comments with which we began.</p>
         <p>Just‐war morality calls forth the virtue of self‐restraint in that it requires citizens, policy makers, and military personnel to situate the use of force within a wider set of moral (and global) goods. The practice of war is not an intrinsic good but should be ordered to the ends of peace and justice in the international arena. As ordained to such ends, war should have peace and justice as goods that are ingredient within its pursuits. For these reasons, just‐war tenets impose a kind of asceticism on public officials, combatants, and ordinary citizens. Self‐restraint is explicitly required by the<italic>ad bellum</italic>criterion of last resort and the<italic>in bello</italic>limits on the conduct of war, and it is implied by the more general fact that war must be pursued in the light of moral ends. That latter idea requires citizens to situate their patriotic allegiances within a wider framework of moral purposes. Patriotic statements about the need to defend one’s homeland, for example, must be chastened by reasonable appeals to moral ends that should inform our conduct and character.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">68</xref>The habits of patriotism and allegiance—important to political motivation, civic identity, and public action—must be disciplined by the attention to a nation’s wider aims, relationships, and responsibilities in the global common good. Just‐war morality thus involves a spiritual exercise, demanding politicians, military planners, and citizens to organize their attitudes and practices according to the demands of fairness—including fairness to Others whose interests may not be one’s own.</p>
         <p>Equally important, war requires a moral justification, an argument that appeals to the public reason of conscientious persons. War is not self‐justifying, and it may not be sought in haste. For this reason, just‐war morality calls forth the civic virtue of critical self‐analysis. As Plato understood in his design of the Republic, the institution of war must be framed by a broader set of parameters, in which self‐reflection and contemplation of the Good mark the highest forms of human activity. Hence Plato’s desire to subordinate the Guardians to the Philosopher‐Kings along with the need to rank warrior‐poetry below philosophy. The purposes that war might serve must stand within a framework that is self‐reflexive and ordered to activities that do not glorify war as an end in itself. In just‐war morality, reality is not organized in conflictual terms according to which martial virtues are goods in themselves.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">69</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The need to produce a justification for war thus calls forth the disposition to deliberate, to place one’s views within a larger dialogical context when assessing the proper terms and course of military action. Deliberation in democratic contexts, Amy Gutmann and Dennis Thompson write, “asks citizens and officials to justify public policy by giving reasons that can be accepted by those who are bound by it.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">70</xref>Just‐war morality serves such deliberative purposes by demanding a public accounting for war, enshrined in part in the<italic>ad bellum</italic>criterion of legitimate authority. That criterion requires those responsible for the common good to declare war and marshal a defense. In democratic contexts, that fact puts the case of war in the public square, requiring policy makers, combatants, and ordinary citizens to weigh reasons for and against the case of war. The grievances to which a just war responds are not always obvious; a case must be made to those whose lives and welfare will be directly affected by its pursuit. Persons who are not disposed to deliberate about the morality of war join cause with those identified by Reinhold Niebuhr as “children of darkness,” viewing war as incorrigible to morality.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">71</xref>They undermine grounds for assessing war as a duty of responsible citizenship.</p>
         <p>Habits of self‐restraint, critical self‐analysis, and the willingness to partake in public moral deliberation echo dispositions valorized in classical Greek moral philosophy; they call to mind the virtues of temperance, wisdom, and courage. Such virtues require us to put political power to critical and moral scrutiny. In these respects attention to virtue requires us to develop the prophetic promise of just‐war morality—its potential to generate social criticism and, when necessary, resistance to political power.</p>
         <p>The virtues to which I have alluded thus possess radical implications for citizens considering the morality of war and, in particular, whether to join a standing army or to agree to conscription in military service. If I am correct about the role of the virtues for just‐war morality, then individual citizens have a duty to settle matters of the<italic>jus ad bellum</italic>during times of conflict or impending conflict. Citizens cannot merely rely on a connection between patriotism and political obedience but should act on the notion that patriotism informed by a sense of justice requires moral reflection about the merits of a polity’s demands on an individual’s conscience. That notion implies higher expectations of moral assessment than has typically been the case in just‐war theorizing and might require citizens to refuse participation or conscription in war. Put differently, citizens who fail to engage in such reflection and who enter into an unjust war may be judged culpably negligent for choosing to be made into soldiers. To be sure, the social, political, economic, legal, and cultural forces that bear on an individual’s decision are complex, making personal agency and moral deliberation in war an extremely complex matter.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">72</xref>But just‐war morality, properly understood, involves dispositions to resist sources of fear and to exercise courage and independence of mind regarding the merits of a polity’s cause.</p>
         <p>Wars that do pass muster on just‐war terms have both moral and political benefits. Put more abstractly, when just‐war morality is expanded to connect with the habits of social criticism, it can contribute to the twin needs of legitimation and justification in democratic contexts. Obviously these points take us beyond Augustine and his vision of a just war. As a product of the premodern era, just‐war doctrine is typically viewed as enabling us to address a war’s moral justification (or lack thereof). But legitimation is different. In modern, democratic settings legitimation turns on the presence of consent (tacit or explicit) to acts authorized by public officials. Its value lies in the democratic commitment to hold authorities accountable to citizens and to provide a firm basis for political representation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">73</xref>Concerns about legitimation are part of a broader theory of justified political coercion: reasons should be provided to persons whose liberties are restricted by a policy. Otherwise such restrictions are tyrannical, imposed heteronomously. Thompson and Gutmann remind us that legitimation is premised on the idea that “the moral authority of collective judgments about policy depends in part on the moral quality of the process by which citizens collectively reach those judgments.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">74</xref>Drawing on the habits of self‐restraint, critical self‐analysis, and willingness to deliberate publicly, the ethics of war can seek the best of both worlds. Just‐war morality can provide moral resources for ensuring that we enter a war that reflects the popular will, one that does not seek to impose its will unjustly on that of others.</p>
         <p>Earlier I stated that just‐war morality involves a spiritual exercise—an ascesis—demanding political elites and ordinary citizens to discipline their attitudes, practices, and representations of the Other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">75</xref>I also said that such an idea suggests a controversial point that harks back to an idea from Augustine, namely, that virtue is grounded in the practice of confession. We are now in a position to see how that is so. Confession for Augustine was not solely or chiefly a matter of privately disclosing personal temptation and wrongdoing, as is often thought. Such personal reports are part of a more general practice of rendering oneself accountable to standards that one does not wishfully create (or project), objective norms by which to measure one’s subjective leanings and desires. Confession, in short, is a matter of making oneself accountable to standards and purposes beyond one’s immediate interests. For Augustine and for those who follow in his path, self‐knowledge quickly slides into excessive self‐love and self‐deception without objective reference points by which to measure oneself. Self‐knowledge, including one’s personal and social memories, must be tested by the principle of reality. Virtue for Augustine thus relies on the willingness to submit oneself to norms by which to evaluate one’s loyalties and commitments. In our self‐reflexive acts, we must ask ourselves whether our self‐interpretation is grounded in reality or fabricated with an eye toward self‐justification.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn69">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>On chastened civic virtue, see Jean Bethke Elshtain,<italic>Women and War</italic>(New York: Basic, 1987), 252. For Elshtain’s reflections on Augustine’s theology, ethics, and politics, see<italic>Augustine and the Limits of Politics</italic>(Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 1995).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
               <label>69</label>
               <p>See also Aristotle,<italic>Politics</italic>, trans. Benjamin Jowett, in<italic>The Basic Works of Aristotle</italic>, ed. Richard McKeon, bk. 7, chap. 2. For a discussion of “militarism,” see Coates,<italic>The Ethics of War</italic>, chap. 2.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
               <label>70</label>
               <p>Amy Gutmann and Dennis Thompson,<italic>Democracy and Disagreement</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1996), 52.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn72">
               <label>71</label>
               <p>Reinhold Niebuhr,<italic>Children of Light and the Children of Darkness</italic>(New York: Scribner’s, 1944).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn73">
               <label>72</label>
               <p>See Walzer,<italic>Just and Unjust Wars</italic>, chaps. 3, 19; David R. Mapel, “Coerced Moral Agents? Individual Responsibility for Military Service,”<italic>Journal of Political Philosophy</italic>6 (1998): 171–89.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn74">
               <label>73</label>
               <p>See Hannah Fenichel Pitkin,<italic>The Concept of Representation</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1967).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn75">
               <label>74</label>
               <p>Gutmann and Thompson,<italic>Democracy and Disagreement</italic>, 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn76">
               <label>75</label>
               <p>For a recent retrieval of the idea of spiritual exercises, see Pierre Hadot,<italic>Philosophy as a Way of Life: Spiritual Exercises from Socrates to Foucault</italic>, ed. with an introduction by Arnold I. Davidson (Oxford: Blackwell, 1995).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Meaning, Memory, and Public History</title>
         <p>Seen in these terms, just‐war morality can mediate civic virtue and, along with it, civic memory and the quest for meaning in the res publica by disposing citizens to evaluate public policy and public sentiment regarding war along with practices according to which war will be recalled in the future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">76</xref>Such assessments are valuable for citizens across generations, bound as they are in political community. We do well to recall that as a political ethic, just‐war morality presupposes the fact that political communities extend over time. They are, as Benedict Anderson famously argued, transgenerational imaginative structures in which past, present, and future members are conceived in solidarity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">77</xref>Just‐war morality thus includes virtues that dispose us to assess not only the sentiments of current citizens but also how public history will teach future generations to remember war in the formation of political identity and public culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">78</xref>Understood as providing a framework for social criticism, just‐war morality provides a set of objective reference points that enable us to ask whether war is memorable for the right reasons and if the desires evoked by war were desirable and worthy of being transmitted to future citizens.</p>
         <p>There is an intimate link, in other words, between collective memory, public history, and the life of a community over time. Collective memory provides what W. James Booth calls the “tectonic plates” on which communities sit—the deep structure according to which collective identities are forged (and conserved) across generations.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">79</xref>In that spirit, we do well to recall George Orwell’s adage that those who control the present control the past. Orwell added to that adage the idea that those who control the past also control the future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">80</xref>Drawing on just‐war doctrine, we (and they) can ask whether war was entered in a timely way, in pursuit of worthy ends, and with limited means. Wars that fall short of those and other expectations leave citizens with less to be proud of, with less of a record to pass along to future generations as representative of a polity’s history and character.</p>
         <p>Augustine helps to shed light on these insights. Note that connections between the ethics of war and memory are intimate indeed, joined at the outset in his discussion of Christianity and political morality in the<italic>City of God</italic>. That work is, among other things, an argument about how to remember the fall of Rome and whether Rome’s decline should be understood as a consequence of embracing Christianity’s putatively pacific virtues. According to Augustine, we must understand that Christianity is not a pacifist creed; it allows for the use of force to defend certain goods. Equally important in Augustine’s mind is the need to remember the true reasons for Rome’s fall: its ongoing pagan sacrifices subsequent to its official conversion to Christian doctrine. This aspect of Augustine’s thought has been universally ignored by theologians and philosophers who have worked in the just‐war tradition. But we should not lose sight of what could be his most striking contribution to the ethics of war and peace. Often overlooked by readers of Augustine is the fact that he is defending the idea of a just war in response to criticisms about the political and cultural effects of accepting Christianity’s moral norms. Thus, he queries at the outset of his magnum opus: “Why do our antagonists bring false accusations against the established Christian order, alleging that catastrophe has come upon the city just because it has left off the worship of its gods?”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">81</xref>With that question in the background, Augustine seeks to absolve Christianity for Rome’s demise. On his account, Rome’s decline should not be remembered as a result of its conversion from Roman religion to Christian beliefs and practices. That argument is part of a larger agenda regarding the civic benefits of the Christian religion along with the core features of its political ethic.</p>
         <p>Augustine’s apology for Christianity and the idea of just war suggests a point that he and his interlocutors presumed as obvious, namely, that there is an ethics of memory—a duty to remember justly for the sake of history, self‐understanding, and narrative recollection. He thus invites us to consider the obligations and virtues of what Ricoeur calls a “just memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">82</xref>Augustine’s ethics is, as I noted above, “agent‐referring”: it attends to the moral effects of an action on the character of the person carrying out that action. He developed his agent‐referring concerns, moreover, not by looking at the morality of individuals as isolated monads but as situated and affected by cultural forces that help shape character over time. The temporal quality of character and culture led him naturally to consider the virtues that surround memory, both individual and collective.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">83</xref>Given the intimate connection between memory and identity, there is an obvious obligation to remember for Augustine, a responsibility to remember truthfully. He thus worried about whether what people remember about themselves is prone to self‐aggrandizement and, with that, self‐deception. For these reasons, we can say that an Augustinian ethics of war is, among other things, an ethics of memory. That Rome’s morality “proceeded to bloody strife of all parties and then to the social and civil wars” is not his own personal judgment; it is, in his words, “the witness of history.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">84</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Viewed in these Augustinian terms, just‐war morality invites one to ask what a war means—how we interpret ourselves and others regarding matters of life and death. Death raises fundamental questions regarding horizons of meaning and desire, and war asks in the starkest terms whether its participants are willing to impose or take on the ultimate sacrifice. In this respect we continue to travel with Augustine despite our distance from him. For surely he would have us ask whether we possess a second‐order framework for determining whether the desires aroused by killing, death, and sacrifice are themselves desirable. That is to say, Augustine would have us ask about the effects of killing on individual and corporate character and how death affects the practices of self‐interpretation and the public history we wish to write about ourselves. War for Augustine was not only a matter of personal virtue and vice; it also raised questions of meaning and memory as these bear upon the formation of civic identity and the construction of desire across generations.</p>
         <p>In modern democracies, the<italic>ars memoriae</italic>have been placed in the hands of the people, dispersed across various roles, ceremonies, institutions, and commemorative practices.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">85</xref>Understood self‐reflexively, just‐war morality can work in such contexts to ensure that war is remembered for the right reasons or, put more accurately, that what is remembered about war is right. In that way citizens can assess war and public history with habits and norms that enable us to resist the twin perils of self‐aggrandizement and self‐deception. That is no small need given how memories of past wars shape how subsequent wars are conceived, authorized, and fought. Viewed as an exercise of ascesis, just‐war morality can discipline passions and actions that risk imposing on fellow citizens and others the ultimate sacrifice. In the process, it enables us to address Anscombe’s anxious premonition: “The death of men, the curtailment of liberty, the destruction of property, the diminution of culture, the obscuring of judgment by passion and interest, the neglect of truth and charity, the decrease in belief and in the practice of religion—all these are the normal accompaniments of a war.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">86</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn77">
               <label>76</label>
               <p>On memory, see Maurice Halbwachs,<italic>On Collective Memory</italic>, ed., trans., with an introduction by Lewis A. Coser (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992); Mary Warnock,<italic>Memory</italic>(London: Faber, 1987); Elie Weisel,<italic>Ethics and Memory</italic>(Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 1997); Edith Wyschogrod,<italic>An Ethics of Remembering: History, Heterology, and the Nameless Others</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998); Edward S. Casey,<italic>Remembering: A Phenomenological Study</italic>, 2nd ed. (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2000); Avishai Margalit,<italic>The Ethics of Memory</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2002); Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>; W. James Booth,<italic>Communities of Memory: On Witness, Identity, and Justice</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 2006).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn78">
               <label>77</label>
               <p>Benedict Anderson,<italic>Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</italic>, 2nd ed. (London: Verso, 1991).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn79">
               <label>78</label>
               <p>By “public history” I mean the recollection of a community’s past in public documents, holidays, ceremonies, and commemorative practices.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn80">
               <label>79</label>
               <p>Booth,<italic>Communities of Memory</italic>, 52.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn81">
               <label>80</label>
               <p>George Orwell,<italic>1984</italic>, with an afterword by Erich Fromm (New York: New American Library, 1977), 37.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn82">
               <label>81</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 1, chap. 15. See also Augustine’s sermon, “The Sacking of the City of Rome,” in<italic>Augustine: Political Writings</italic>, 205–14.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn83">
               <label>82</label>
               <p>Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 68. Memory for Augustine is subject to the power of time, also understood as the power of death. Book 11 of<italic>Confessions</italic>, exploring time as both a condition for and subject of memory, underscores finite humanity’s being‐toward‐death, the fact that time is “the impending state of<italic>not being</italic>.” See<italic>Confessions</italic>, bk. 11, par. 14. Ricoeur engages Heidegger on memory, historicity, and death in<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 357–69. See also n. 48.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn84">
               <label>83</label>
               <p>Augustine’s attention to collective memory is evident in<italic>City of God</italic>; to individual memory in<italic>Confessions</italic>, esp. bks. 10, 11; and Augustine,<italic>On the Trinity: Books 8–15</italic>, ed. Gareth B. Matthews (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002), bks. 12–15. For a discussion of Augustine on individual memory, see Roland Teske, “Augustine’s Philosophy of Memory,” in<italic>The Cambridge Companion to Augustine</italic>, ed. Eleonore Stump and Norman Kretzmann (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001), 148–58.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn85">
               <label>84</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>City of God</italic>, bk. 19, chap. 24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn86">
               <label>85</label>
               <p>On commemorative practices and public history, see John Bodnar,<italic>Remaking America: Public Memory, Commemoration, and Patriotism in the Twentieth Century</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1992); Dominick La Capra,<italic>History and Meaning after Auschwitz</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1998); Jenny Edkins,<italic>Trauma and the Memory of Politics</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003); Edward T. Linenthal,<italic>Sacred Ground: Americans and Their Battlefields</italic>(Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1991), and<italic>The Unfinished Bombing: Oklahoma City in American Memory</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2001); Alison Landsberg,<italic>Prosthetic Memory: The Transformation of American Remembrance in the Age of Mass Culture</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 2004); David Simpson,<italic>9/11: The Culture of Commemoration</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2006); Oren Baruch Stier and J. Shawn Landres, eds.,<italic>Religion, Violence, Memory, and Place</italic>(Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2006); Marita Sturken,<italic>Tangled Memories: The Vietnam War, the AIDS Epidemic, and the Politics of Remembering</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1997); James E. Young,<italic>The Texture of Memory: Holocaust Memorials and Meaning</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1993).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>Anscombe, “The Justice of the Present War Examined,” 81.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
