<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591496</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/431811</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR850403</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Word’s Self‐Portrait in Blood: The Shroud of Turin as Ecstatic Mirror in Emanuele Tesauro’s Baroque<italic>Sacred Paneg</italic>
               <italic>yrics</italic>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Armando</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Maggi</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of Chicago</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>October 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>582</fpage>
         <lpage>608</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2005 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/431811"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>My sincere thanks to Salvatore S. Nigro and John Batzel for their suggestions.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>“The art of writing is so ancient, noble and marvelous,” the Jesuit Emanuele Tesauro states in the opening sentence of the<italic>Commentary</italic>(<italic>Il commentario</italic>), a panegyric on the shroud of Turin that he read in 1627 in the cathedral of Turin before the Savoy family, “that I cannot see who else but God could be the inventor.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>In Tesauro’s words, God allows the soul “to give birth to a highly secret concept [<italic>concetto</italic>] by means of a pen, to suckle it with ink, and to wrap it in the pages of a book like swaddling clothes.” God lets a concept live, grow, and “fly up to the spheres of human eyes.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>For Tesauro’s baroque sensibility, a concept has a visible expression. The page is the sheet or canvas where a “concept” reveals itself. This essay investigates the theological, devotional, visual, and literary connotations of Tesauro’s “concept” by analyzing his two panegyrics on the shroud of Turin,<italic>The Commentary</italic>(1627) and<italic>Sympathy</italic>(1656).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Tesauro explains the formation of a “concept” at the beginning of his vast<italic>The Aristotelian Telescope</italic>(<italic>Il Cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, first ed. 1654), the most important seventeenth‐century analysis of metaphorical expression: “The human intellect, like a pure mirror that is always the same and always different, expresses in itself the images of the objects that present themselves before it [the intellect]. These are what we call thoughts. As our mental discourse is nothing but an ordered context of these inner images, so is the external discourse nothing but an order of sensible<italic>signs</italic>, which are copied from the mental images, like types from their archetypes. But among these external signs, some are eloquent, others are silent, and others composed of silent eloquence and eloquent silence.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>Although he clearly echoes Aristotle’s<italic>De anima</italic>3.4, Tesauro underscores that the intellect “expresses” the images it receives from the external world. Moreover, he identifies these external images with thoughts. An additional, essential detail to consider is Tesauro’s definition of human intellect as “mirror” (<italic>specchio</italic>), a concept that will play a fundamental role in our analysis of his texts on the shroud. Tesauro’s “mirror” elucidates and expands Aristotle’s concept of “writing table” (<italic>De anima</italic>430a1). Tesauro’s “always the same and always different” mirror highlights the mutual relationship between internal and external visibility. For Tesauro, to think means to reflect the infinite multiplicity of the real through an unrelenting production of visual metaphors, verbal and visible alike. For metaphors, Tesauro explicitly states in his<italic>Aristotelian Telescope</italic>, are “the most eloquent and fertile childbirth [<italic>parto</italic>] of human intellect.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Doubling Aristotle’s categorization, Tesauro posits eight forms of basic metaphors with three distinct structures: “simple metaphor,” “propositional metaphor,” and “argumentative metaphor.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>Out of the eight kinds, two metaphors work as the propulsive force of Tesauro’s rhetoric: the metaphor of “similitude” and that of “opposition.” Furthermore, Tesauro underscores that the fundamental goal of every metaphorical expression is the evocation of some form of “marvel” (<italic>meraviglia</italic>), which he defines as follows: “[<italic>Meraviglia</italic>, marvel] is the mind’s attentive contemplation of some new and remarkable object. Ignoring its origin, the soul is suspended and wishes to know it [the object’s origin].”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>Marvel is a form of “brief rapture” (<italic>breve rapimento</italic>) that “alters man in a sensible way.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>Marvel first originates in the intellect and consequently overflows (<italic>ridonda</italic>) into the body. A “sudden ecstasy” (<italic>subita estasi</italic>) possesses the body, which is temporarily “speechless” (<italic>senza favella</italic>). In other words, a successful visual or verbal metaphor produces an “ecstatic” moment of inner suspension. In this internal silence man yearns to understand, to dive into the mystery summoned by marvel.</p>
      <p>How does the shroud relate to the concept of marvel? What kind of silence and subsequent knowledge does the shroud produce in our inner “mirror,” the intellect, whose primary goal is to reflect the real through metaphorical expressions? As I will clarify in this essay, the shroud of Turin embodies the double nature of written and painted surface, but also of divine “mirror” in which the real is reflected. Tesauro’s metaphor speaks of an act of incarnation, in which a nonvisible idea becomes flesh and blood. The shroud has thus clear Eucharistic connotations, although Tesauro makes no direct allusion to the connection between the shroud and the Eucharist. He emphasizes that the shroud is at once the visualization of a concept (the Word’s incarnation) but also the embodiment of such a visualized concept, given that the shroud is “written” with the Word’s own blood. We could say that the shroud is at once name and thing, signifier and signified, metaphor and its exegesis. Moreover, in his second panegyric (<italic>Sympathy</italic>) Tesauro relates the shroud to St. Maurice, whose relics rested in the same cathedral of Turin. The shroud is “symbol,” and the saint’s body is its “agent,” that is, the saint’s relics actualize the shroud. In letting this image create an ecstatic suspension (Tesauro’s “marvel”), we perceive that the shroud is a mirror reflecting a universal biography. Like the relics of St. Maurice, we harbor an inner shroud, a symbolic image of the Word’s suffering and resurrection. The shroud demands that we become its linguistic “agents,” that is, that we mirror and enact its discourse of salvation.</p>
      <p>The first and most influential treatise on the shroud is<italic>Esplicatione del lenzuolo ove fu involto il Signore</italic>(Interpretation of the sheet in which the Lord was enshrouded) by Alfonso Paleotto, Archbishop of Bologna. Paleotto’s seminal text came out in 1598, twenty years after the transfer of the shroud from Chambéry to Turin, the new capital of the state of Savoy. Paleotto’s book is at once a scientific description of the figure imprinted on the cloth and a meditative appropriation of the two images. The section “The Beauty and Measures of the Lord’s Body” (chap. 3) offers a detailed commentary on the two images reproduced at the beginning of his book (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fg1">fig. 1</xref>). Paleotto adds a biblical quotation, “torcular calcavi solus” (I have trodden the wine press alone [Is. 63:3]), as if Christ himself commented on the image of his corpse. According to Paleotto, the Word wished to grant us a remembrance of his handsome face, which in<italic>The Song of Songs</italic>the bride had already contemplated in its powerful splendor.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>If, as session 25 of the Council of Trent confirms, “ordinary” images “created by human art” can be used “to excite our celestial love,” how could we possibly refrain from contemplating the self‐portrait the Word granted us?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>Paleotto’s devotional reading of the shroud could be read as a form of<italic>affetto</italic>(affective response), a key term of Italian seventeenth‐century literature. Based on Ignatius’s<italic>Exercises</italic>,<italic>affetto</italic>indicates a literary text (prose or poetry) that aims at triggering a devotional response in the reader’s mind, a sort of “conversion of the heart,” as the Dominican Ignazio del Nente stresses in his important religious works.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>In “The First Exercise,” Ignatius stresses that, if a meditation is “about something that can be gazed upon,” the imagination must first sketch a “physical space.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>In Paleotto’s text, the shroud is the space of the meditation on Christ’s passion. After the intellect has studied this inner space in greater detail, the will leads us “to deeper affections” [<italic>afectos</italic>].<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>In Paleotto’s<italic>Esplicatione</italic>, the affective response to the shroud has a strong apocalyptic connotation, which will be clarified in a later section of this essay. For Paleotto, the cloth marked with the Word’s blood signifies an interim time between his death and his Second Coming.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>
         <fig-group content-type="figgrp" id="fg1" position="float">
            <label>Fig. 1.<x xml:space="preserve">—</x>
            </label>
            <caption>
               <p>The image of the shroud from Alfonso Paleotto's<italic>Esplicatione</italic>(1598); Regenstein Library, University of Chicago.</p>
            </caption>
            <fig position="float" fig-type="figure">
               <graphic xlink:href="fg1"
                        mimetype="image"
                        position="float"
                        xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </fig-group>
      </p>
      <p>Within this apocalyptic context the house of Savoy comes to play a prominent role. Tesauro’s first panegyric on the shroud (the<italic>Commentary</italic>) is a “praise” that, through the shroud, indirectly regards the Savoy family. The Savoy duchy had acquired the relic in 1453 from Marguerite de la Roche, the last descendent of the Charny family, which had owned the relic since the fourteenth century.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>Tesauro holds that the house of Savoy had been chosen by the Word to preserve the visual memory of his human biography. For the shroud was not only the official relic of a ducal family, it was also its emblem, the visual synthesis of a historical project with openly apocalyptic connotations. Tesauro’s two texts envision the Savoy dynasty as the defender of Catholicism against foreign heretical countries. When Tesauro delivered his first panegyric in 1627, the Savoy duchy was already deeply involved in the Thirty Years War (1618–48), although his text makes no explicit reference to the European conflict.</p>
      <p>The apocalyptic nature of the<italic>Commentary</italic>is detectable in its opening pages. Tesauro writes that from the white sheet of a page like from a field sowed with “venomous seeds,” dead warriors arise to a renewed life.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Thanks to Livy, Horatius Cocles still fights alone against the “immense wave of steel” of the Etruscan army on the bridge over the Tiber.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>The “Latin commentaries” grant a constantly renewed life to Hannibal and the soldiers who died in Cannae, but also to Scipio and the ashes of Carthage.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>History is a series of biographical emblems with a perennial significance. The incarnate Word follows this interpretative model. Like Hannibal or Scipio, the emblem of Christ portrays a royal warrior fighting in an open field against his two main enemies, hell and death.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>According to Tesauro, Christ wears a luminous armor and brandishes the powerful sword of his humanity, an echo of Rev. 9:11–16.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>Christ’s emblem reminds us that his victory was hard earned. His hands are wounded, and his chest is bloody and torn. Hanging from the cross, he seems defeated rather than victorious.</p>
      <p>The opening pages of Tesauro’s<italic>Commentary</italic>evoke a visual hybrid, a double image (Christ at once dying on the cross and fighting as a brave king). Through this paradoxical image, Tesauro defies a facile rational apprehension. The viewer, baffled and surprised by this “marvelous” juxtaposition, feels compelled to follow and embrace Tesauro’s complex exegesis. This emblem of the Word is the object of a “commentary” that the Jesuit Tesauro, like a historian of antiquity, composes to express the silence imposed on the “marveled” mirror of the mind. Tesauro makes clear that “commentary,” a term often indicating biblical exegesis, cannot be applied to the emblem of the Word as a historian would use it to describe his composition of a secular biography. What does “to comment” mean in the context of the Word’s experience of suffering and death?</p>
      <p>For Tesauro, the events registered in the Old Testament foreshadow Christ’s biography. Let us take, Tesauro continues, the story of King Ahasuerus in Esther. Two officers in the king’s office plotted to assassinate Ahasuerus, but the faithful Mordecai heard about this conspiracy and saved him, and the two officers went the gallows.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>Tesauro adds that “the king reported the incident in the Annals.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>This biblical story is both historical event and allegory of Christ’s biography, that is, it is both real and metaphorical. Tesauro compares “King Ahasuerus to the king of heaven, the good Mordecai to his holy humanity, and the two conspirators to the devil and death.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>Moreover, in Esther, King Ahasuerus is at once main character, historian, and commentator. Similarly, the primary transcriber and interpreter of the Word’s emblematic biography is the Word himself.</p>
      <p>The shroud is the Word’s commentary on his human biography. However, unlike the annals of King Ahasuerus, the shroud is also the irreplaceable self‐portrait composed by its author’s body. The image of the Word’s body marked on the cloth is at once text and exegesis. The blood he shed during the crucifixion is the ink he used to compose his text‐portrait. Finally, the letters of his writing create the overall image of his bleeding corpse.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>We can infer that, in Tesauro’s text, the shroud of Turin is first and foremost an emblem. According to Renaissance emblematic theories, an emblem is a communication that blends in verbal and visual components. In “Treatise on Emblems,” the final section of the<italic>Aristotelian Telescope</italic>, Tesauro defines an emblem as a “familiar symbol composed of a figure and words, which through a thesis [<italic>argomento</italic>] manifests a particular statement [<italic>documento</italic>] on human life.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Tesauro also states that an emblem is close to an<italic>impresa</italic>, which is also made of an image plus a motto.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>Unlike an emblem, an<italic>impresa</italic>manifests a “particular and heroic thought” of a single individual.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>An<italic>impresa</italic>is a private communication.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>The most appropriate form of<italic>impresa</italic>is a shield, an artifact that at once reveals and protects someone’s intentions. It is also possible to create an “emblematic<italic>impresa</italic>” by merging the form of an emblem (an understandable image) with the goal of an<italic>impresa</italic>(a private and “heroic” insight).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>For Tesauro, the sceneries (<italic>apparati</italic>) built for saints or deceased princes are “emblematic [<italic>imprese</italic>].” These objects at once regard a unique person and express “a general and virtuous statement [<italic>documento</italic>].”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>“Documento” refers to the mottoes accompanying the image. An explicit epigram may make a figure closer to an emblem, whereas an obscure sentence may signify an<italic>impresa</italic>. However, by “statement” (<italic>documento</italic>) we must also intend what the viewer apprehends as private, invisible nourishment. This<italic>documento</italic>corresponds to the “soul” (<italic>anima</italic>) of an<italic>impresa</italic>.</p>
      <p>To glean a better understanding of this key term, it will be useful to consider the use of the term<italic>documentum</italic>in Christian tradition. In<italic>Benjamin Major</italic>, Richard of St. Victor uses the term<italic>documentum</italic>in his analysis of the two highest forms of contemplation: above reason (fifth form) and beyond reason (sixth form). Recalling Exod. 25:18–20, where God orders Moses to build a sanctuary and, at both sides of the oracle, to place two cherubim facing each other, their faces turned toward the propitiatory, Richard recommends that we “hammer out the form of angelic similitude in ourselves,” since “cherub” stands for “fullness of knowledge.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>Respectful of this divine “pattern” (<italic>documentum</italic>) and “testimony” (<italic>documentum</italic>), we should “spread out the wings of our cherubim” and long “to meet the grace of a showing.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>
         <italic>Documento</italic>is thus both inner nourishment and the ritual leading to that spiritual nourishment (God himself explains how the two cherubim must look at each other but also face toward the propitiatory). Let us remember that the word<italic>documentum</italic>derives from the Latin<italic>docere</italic>(to teach) and<italic>mens</italic>(intellect). As spiritual food,<italic>documento</italic>evokes the Eucharist, as Thomas writes in the hymn<italic>Pange lingua</italic>: “let the old law yield to the new rite” (antiquum documentum novo cedat ritui).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Contradicting most Renaissance theorists who believe that the figure is the “body” (<italic>corpo</italic>) of the<italic>impresa</italic>and the motto is its “soul” (<italic>anima</italic>), Tesauro holds that “the signifying sign is the body” and “the signified concept is the soul.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>For Tesauro, “the [<italic>impresa</italic>] is a miraculous composition whose soul is outside of the body.” If the most common and correct form of<italic>impresa</italic>is the shield, Tesauro concludes that an<italic>impresa</italic>has “its visible signifier in the shield and its intelligible signified in the mind.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>We could thus infer that the shroud is a divine<italic>impresa</italic>, in that it is a visible gesture that produces spiritual nourishment. The “body” of this divine<italic>impresa</italic>is the Eucharist, which is Christ’s body through an act of transubstantiation, and the motto is the shroud of Turin, which is “written” with the Word’s blood. The “soul” is our inner appropriation and response to the Word’s<italic>impresa</italic>.</p>
      <p>In his first panegyric on the shroud, Tesauro stresses that only a “sublime person” is able to write a “sublime commentary” of his own biography, as Julius Caesar did in<italic>The Gallic War</italic>. Tesauro contends that the body inscribed on the shroud is foreshadowed in a passage from the book of Ezekiel, when God sends six men to slaughter the idolaters living in Jerusalem. Among these six mysterious executioners was a man “dressed in linen, with a scribe’s ink‐horn in his belt” (Ezek. 9:2).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>God orders this man clothed in linen to place the mark “Tau” on the foreheads of those who mourn over the abominations committed in Jerusalem (Ezek. 9:4).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>Later, after the killing, the same man dressed in linen scattered burning coals over the city (Ezek. 10:2).</p>
      <p>According to Tesauro, the Son of God, the “sublime” writer of his own commentary, appears to the prophet as a scribe. His writing is first and foremost a sign of judgment and salvation (he marks the foreheads of those who do penance), but also of cleansing (he throws burning coal over the city). The linen cloth covering the body of the divine scribe will later become page and written text. Tesauro writes that, as a new Caesar, the divine scribe competes with himself, since he is at once supreme warrior and supreme historian of his own deeds. But as a written text, the divine scribe finds his literary model in Moses’s Decalogue.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>If the two tablets contained the words that God dictated to Moses, in the two figures marked on both sides of the shroud God later revealed that the body of his Only‐Begotten Son brought his law to its fullness.</p>
      <p>In the shroud, God is “author and autograph, printer and printed text.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>The medium that connects the divine author to his divine manuscript is the Word’s body whose blood is the very ink used to compose God’s visible text of salvation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>Christ’s corpse marked on the linen by his own blood is a hieroglyphic, that is, a symbolic and metaphorical expression made of one and only one figure.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>Aristotle himself, Tesauro continues, holds that a “heroic and distinguished style” necessarily entails “poetic images and metaphorical connections.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>For Tesauro, hieroglyphics and figures of speech are typical components of divine communication. How could the divinity express his royal concepts but through a self‐portrait in human forms? And why is the Son called “Word,” if not to signify that he arises as image from the “Living Principle”? In the beginning, Tesauro holds, was God’s metaphor, the Word, his visible hieroglyphic.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>God created humankind in the image and likeness of his Word, his original “figure of speech.”</p>
      <p>Although Adam and Eve were expelled from the Garden of Eden, the human race still retains a deformed perception of God’s original “metaphor.” “Beatification,” Tesauro explains, is the mind’s “reformation,” that is, man’s transformation from stained glass to clear mirror of God’s “metaphor,” the Word. God’s Only Begotten is the original metaphor who, when he became incarnate, transformed himself into a new “figure,” for he turned into the image and likeness of God. Later, after his resurrection, he returned to the Father as a new “transfigured” image. Augustine may help clarify this point of Tesauro’s reasoning. In<italic>De trinitate</italic>, Augustine offers an exhaustive analysis of his fundamental view of the “reformation” of man’s image‐likeness to the Word as the Father’s “figure.” The mind, Augustine contends, has a trinitarian structure analogous to God’s Trinity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>Consciousness (<italic>memoria</italic>) relates to the Father, knowledge (<italic>intelligentia</italic>) to the Son, and love (<italic>amor</italic>) to the Holy Spirit. Through<italic>memoria</italic>the mind initiates a process of reformation, which can only occur “according to the image of God” (secundum imaginem Dei).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>In Augustine’s view, our mind will perfectly conform to the image of God (it will become its perfect mirror) only at Doomsday.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>One could infer that, according to Augustine, the mind’s process of reformation is an act of listening to the Father’s “figure of speech,” the Word, so that the mind can conform to his discourse.</p>
      <p>In the opening section of the<italic>Telescope</italic>, by the title “Divine Wit,” decades later Tesauro will clarify some of the above concepts on God’s expression. God, Tesauro argues, always addresses men and angels through “heroic [<italic>imprese</italic>], figurative symbols.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>“Divine mythology” is at once literal, tropological, allegorical, and anagogical.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>By “mythology” (<italic>mitologia</italic>), a term he does not explain in detail, Tesauro seems to mean God’s “physical actions,” which later become sacred narratives.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>God’s interventions in the world always express a “heroic,” “marvelous” significance, which men later attempt to fathom through exegetical dissection (the four levels of exegesis).</p>
      <p>The two images impressed on the shroud synthesize God’s “mythic” presence in human history. In the panegyric, Tesauro contends that God alluded to the Word’s dual nature when he said to Moses “You shall not see my face” and “You shall see my back.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>The two‐sided shroud is a literal manifestation of the divine (the frontal side) and human (the back side) nature of Christ.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>In the dynamic rapport between the two parts of the shroud Tesauro identifies the<italic>enargeia</italic>of divine expression. In Tesauro’s words,<italic>enargeia</italic>“expresses human actions as if they presented themselves faithful to the eyes and not to the ears.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>The shroud is the highest exemplar of divine<italic>enargeia</italic>, for this cloth is not a static image but rather (as a mythic representation) a portrait in motion, a figurative discourse that opens itself to infinite forms of apprehension. Let us remember that, for Quintilian, “vividness” (<italic>ornatum</italic>or<italic>enargeia</italic>) “is more than mere perspicuity, since instead of being merely transparent it somehow shows itself off” (se quodam modo ostendit).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>
      </p>
      <p>According to Tesauro, the two parts of the shroud lend themselves to a number of tropological readings. If the back side may represent the Old Testament (a divine figure turning his back to the present), the front side is the New Testament (a divine presence approaching the viewer).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>The source of Tesauro’s comparison could be the Dominican Camillo Balliani’s lengthy<italic>Ragionamenti della Sacra Sindone</italic>(first ed. 1610).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>Tesauro also states that in the shroud we may recognize a figure that falls and one that arises, symbols of Christ’s death and resurrection. Finally, the figure that looks at us and the one that moves away may signify the embrace of those justified by the Word’s grace and the rejection of the sinners.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>If all things came into being through the Word (John 1:3), the shroud is the final disclosure of the Word’s compassion. The shroud “forewarns that last day” when God will open the “divine book of the shroud” and “will force the Enemy of Christ and the damned souls to read their condemnation written in the characters of blood.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>As Paleotto’s<italic>Esplicatione</italic>had already stated, the shroud fore‐signifies the apocalypse. At Doomsday, our bodies will see their eternal condition reflected in the shroud. Like the incarnate Word’s, our lives will acquire the stillness of “emblematic [<italic>imprese</italic>],” at once memorials of a personal past and hieroglyphics of God’s justice.</p>
      <p>As Tesauro will clarify in his second panegyric on this subject (<italic>Sympathy</italic>), the shroud manifests the “sympathy” (<italic>simpatia</italic>) that unites the Word to us. If we let the shroud “marvel” our intellect (our inner “mirror”), we perceive that the shroud is a visual form of self‐recollection in that, by remembering Christ’s human experience, we glean an insight on our own humanity. In Balliani’s<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, Tesauro could find an explicit reference to the shroud as a form of meditation: “If you wish to please Christ, to receive Him correctly, to conform to Him, to bury yourself with Him, and to resuscitate with Him, you must construct a clean shroud within your heart and soul.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">58</xref>As Balliani confirms in his<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, “the shroud helps us form the truthful image and similitude of God’s Son.” It supports us in our attempt to become “the perfect similitude of Christ.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">59</xref>The shroud is thus similar to a “mirror” in which “we contemplate” our progressive resemblance (our reformation) to Christ’s humanity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">60</xref>We could say that the “marvel” of the shroud reminds us that a basic “sympathy” ties the incarnate Word to us.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">61</xref>In other words, the shroud of Turin is a visual narrative concerning both the Word’s and our own biography. The shroud of Turin is indeed a “sympathetic” artifact.</p>
      <p>The sympathy between the incarnate Word and human beings is the theme of Tesauro’s second panegyric on the shroud. With<italic>Sympathy</italic>(1654), written two years after the first edition of the<italic>Aristotelian Telescope</italic>, Tesauro evokes a tenet of Renaissance natural philosophy, which held that “nature consisted of an almost infinite number of processes” linking every physical element to one another.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">62</xref>This natural “process” (sympathy) was essentially an infinite chain of metaphorical connections. For Tesauro, “sympathy” in fact indicates a rhetorical process of associations. “Sympathy,” Tesauro writes at the beginning of this panegyric, is the work of “divine providence, which produces no casual events.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">63</xref>We might say that, as a successful rhetorician shows unexpected connections between seemingly unrelated linguistic signs, so does divine providence speak through “marvelous” affinities that defy the basic categories of time and space.</p>
      <p>Delivering this panegyric in the basilica of Turin, Tesauro poses an audacious “sympathetic” connection between the shroud; the cardinal Maurice of Savoy (1593–1657), who strongly advocated the construction of a new chapel for the shroud; and the legendary martyr St. Maurice. Charles Emmanuel of Savoy had transferred the saint’s sword, his ring, and most of his body from the monastery of Agaunum (St. Moritz) to Turin in 1591.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">64</xref>The subtitle of Tesauro’s panegyric is in fact “On St. Maurice and the Holy shroud.” St. Maurice being of special significance for the Savoy family, Tesauro dedicated a second panegyric to this saint by the title<italic>The Armored Fortress</italic>(Il forte armato), which evokes the “fortress of St Maurice” (Il bastione San Maurizio) built in defense of the city. St. Maurice had acquired a particular prominence in the Savoy family in 1572, when Pope Gregory XIII recognized the new order of the “Chevaliers of Saints Maurice and Lazarus” that Emmanuel Filbert had created to fight the enemies of the Catholic faith.</p>
      <p>Given Tesauro’s insistence on St. Maurice, let us mention only the main points of his life. The crucial document regarding the martyr Maurice and his companions is<italic>Passio Acaunensium martyrum</italic>by the bishop of Lyon Eucherius (450–55).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">65</xref>Maurice’s “blessed passion,” Eucherius writes, took place under the Emperor Maximian (AD 250–310), who “slaughtered and murdered” the followers of the Christian faith in different provinces of the empire.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">66</xref>At that time, Eucherius continues, within the emperor’s army existed a legion called “Theban, made of six‐thousand six‐hundred soldiers.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">67</xref>When this legion arrived in Agaunum (St. Moritz today, in Switzerland), Maurice and his companions refused to engage in pagan sacrifices because they themselves were Christian. The emperor massacred this disloyal legion. The Savoy order of “Maurice and Lazarus” was under the aegis of this model of military allegiance to the true faith. The transfer of parts of Maurice’s body to the Turinese cathedral where the shroud also found its abode was a highly symbolic act, as if the saint’s relics and the Word’s shroud were meant to reside in the same sacred place. The shroud and the relics would enhance each other’s significance, and together they would bless the royal family of Savoy.</p>
      <p>How can he possibly fathom the depth of divine providence that leaves no event to mere chance? Tesauro asks in the opening sentence of<italic>Sympathy</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">68</xref>“Today,” the divinity has formed a “problem” (<italic>problema</italic>) that the human mind cannot easily dismiss or solve. In the “solemn mausoleum” of Turin, divine providence has gathered the “Great Maurice” (Maurice of Savoy) and the holy shroud, but also the body of the martyr Maurice.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">69</xref>If the created world exists under the aegis of divine providence that controls the flight of every bird, the movement of every wave, and the falling of every branch from every tree, this “marvelous” occurrence must harbor a meaning.</p>
      <p>More than any other of Tesauro’s previous discourses, this panegyric will address the “movements and the conjunctions” of what exists, the “blood” (<italic>sangue</italic>) of the created world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">70</xref>With their “apparently casual correspondences,” the stars visible in a clear night sky stage the invisible cohesion of the world. We are unable to fathom their dynamics, although we know that the stars alter seasons, invigorate animals and plants, and secretly affect our “human microcosm.” Similarly, aren’t the martyrs’ bodies the greatest stars in the vault of Mother Church, our heaven on earth?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">71</xref>As the stars influence the creation through their rotations, so did the martyrs’ bodies and the Word’s shroud exert positive effects whenever they were moved from one location to another. “Everything you see in the sky [and] on earth,” Tesauro concludes, “is replete with hatreds and loves, concordances and discordances, sympathies and antipathies.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">72</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Tesauro writes that, as the scriptures and Aristotle confirm, blood (<italic>sangue</italic>) springs from the heart and contains a human being’s “sensitive soul” (the faculty of the sensitive soul present in animals).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">73</xref>Blood is the locus of every natural sympathy and antipathy. Thanks to blood’s inner qualities, two unrelated human beings may show unexpected similarities in their “faces or behaviors.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">74</xref>But blood, being the abode of our sensitive soul, also unites two souls in a love bond. In other words, blood has a physical and spiritual connective power, an infinite metaphorical force. “The sympathy of the blood” (<italic>simpatia del sangue</italic>) causes a certain “boiling in the veins” and a “beaming of the eyes” when two friends meet.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">75</xref>
      </p>
      <p>This form of sympathy that manifests itself in the body is called “natural” (<italic>naturale</italic>) and relates to two other kinds of sympathetic connections: “imaginary” (<italic>fantastica</italic>) and “rational” (<italic>razionale</italic>). In this three‐part concept of sympathy, Tesauro summarizes a rhetorical process in which “human discourse” (<italic>human discorso</italic>) holds the primary position. According to Tesauro, “rational sympathy causes the imaginary [sympathy], and because of its influence on blood the imaginary brings about the natural.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">76</xref>Conversely, a natural sympathy produces internal images, which lead to discourse, “so that a natural love eventually becomes a virtuous habit.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">77</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Blood is thus a substance that harbors a linguistic power. For Tesauro, after the body’s death, blood maintains an expressive energy. Many Renaissance writers hold that, when a murderer approaches his victim’s corpse, blood oozes out of the dead body’s wounds.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">78</xref>How could we possibly deny that blood also possesses a unifying sympathetic power? Even after their death, Tesauro writes, quoting from Gregory the Great, the apostles Peter and Paul could not live distant from each other. Attempts to distance the remains of the two apostles were always accompanied by sinister events.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">79</xref>Their mutual love still echoes in their sympathetic relics.</p>
      <p>But “whose blood was more sympathetic than Christ’s?” Tesauro concludes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">80</xref>When the Word became incarnate, Tesauro states, borrowing from St. Paul, he shared his brothers’ nature so that he would become pure passion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">81</xref>The Word as the embodiment of divine compassion assumed “the gentlest and most benign blood” in order to communicate “a sympathetic and natural compassion” toward all of humanity. The incarnate Word expressed his compassion in a number of occasions by weeping at a human affliction. Since tears are “a limpid distillation coming from the purest blood of the heart,” Christ shared his blood with the Magdalene when he was moved by her cry, when he cried at his friend’s tomb, and when he contemplated the walls of Jerusalem.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">82</xref>As the Word brought out his compassionate blood through his tears, so did his disciples and the crowds that followed him feel physically drawn toward him, toward his blood. Christ’s blood had and still has “a magnetic sympathy.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">83</xref>
      </p>
      <p>We could say that the bloodstains on the shroud signify the conjunction of divine compassion and human history. These stains mark the Word’s openness (his wounds) toward the creation, but they are also our invocation to the divinity. Tesauro draws an astonishing comparison between the shroud and the book of<italic>Leviticus</italic>, where we read that, after shedding the blood of the propitiatory victim in the temple, the High Priest would bring a “particle” (<italic>particella</italic>) of this blood into the tabernacle and would sprinkle it on the veil.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">84</xref>This “mysterious figure” (<italic>misteriosa figura</italic>), “figure” meaning the ritual described in the Old Testament, foreshadows the shroud. If the victim signifies the “crucified humanity,” the temple is a “figure” of the Mount Calvary, and the tabernacle means the sepulcher. Moreover, God’s sanctuary symbolizes the Savior’s body, and the veil of the temple is the shroud. This is why, Tesauro adds, “in the same day, Christ marked the shroud [with his blood] and the veil of the temple was split.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">85</xref>The tearing of the veil is also a figure of the shattering of the figurative correspondence between the Old and the New Testament. When the veil was torn apart, “the mystical sense yielded to the literal sense; the figure [<italic>figura</italic>] yielded to its figured meaning [<italic>figurato</italic>]; the conceptualized object [<italic>ideato</italic>] to its concept [<italic>idea</italic>]; and the copy to its original.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">86</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Following this chain of correspondences, we could infer that the shroud both tears apart the link between figure (image) and its figured meaning (what that means) and reenacts it. The shroud is an “eloquent” book that “speaks with words of blood,” as the scriptures foretell in the story of Abel. “What a marvelous contraposition between Christ and Abel,” Tesauro writes, “between victim and victim, between shedding and shedding, between wounds and wounds, between blood and blood, between sepulcher and sepulcher, between voices and voices.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88">87</xref>
      </p>
      <p>At the beginning of divine revelation lies a profound “marvel.” Abel’s “antipathetic” blood spoke at the beginning of the scriptures whereas Christ utters his “sympathetic” words of blood and compassion at their closure. Although he finds this simile in Balliani’s<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, Tesauro adds that the incarnate Word also introduced new figurative meanings into old figures of speech (murder, wounds, sepulcher, blood, and voice).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89">88</xref>The shroud is both tangible result and figure of this rhetorical renovation. For it is the figure of Christ, but it is also a figure of (his) speech. “Christ is dead and is still speaking,” Tesauro writes, “he is at once dead and alive.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90">89</xref>The shroud is thus both literal and figurative language. Similar to what David Tracy states in regard of the expression “God is Love,” we understand that the shroud exists within the tension between the two levels of signification.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91">90</xref>The impossibility of separating the two rhetorical levels (literal and figurative) is of great importance for Tesauro. He holds that now Christ does not suffer or invoke the Father in an “expressed manner” (<italic>espressamente</italic>), but rather in an interpretative one (<italic>interpretativamente</italic>) because he “continues to represent the vestiges of His mournful passion to the Father.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92">91</xref>
      </p>
      <p>At the beginning of this essay, we saw that, in the opening part of<italic>Commentary</italic>, Tesauro states that “in the beginning” are imageless concepts and not images. Concepts then metamorphose into figures and finally, by “flying up” beyond the “spheres” of the interlocutor’s (or reader’s) mind, return to their original conceptual nature. In the second panegyric<italic>Sympathy</italic>, Tesauro contends that figurative expression is in fact a manifestation of compassion and grief, of emotional participation. Quoting from Seneca’s fortieth epistle to Lucilius and from the book of Wisdom, Tesauro reminds us that images spring from a “distant and impatient longing.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93">92</xref>If Seneca speaks of “pictures of absent friends,” the biblical author foreshadows Christ’s death on the cross and the shroud. The book of Wisdom describes a “tender father who, when death stole his beloved son away, he stole him back from death by forming a very similar simulacrum (<italic>similissimo simulacro</italic>).”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94">93</xref>At the origin of language thus lies the Father’s mournful longing for the Son, as if the sacrifice and death of the Son were the actual core of the divine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95">94</xref>“Who was the inventor of images,” Tesauro asks himself, “but the ingenious love of a tender father” who formed a picture of his son?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96">95</xref>We have seen that, for Tesauro, in the beginning was the Word as metaphor of the Father.</p>
      <p>For Tesauro, the shroud is the figure of a divine disclosure (the divine as mourning of an absence). He states that John 20:12, on the two angels sitting where Christ’s corpse had been, stages this central concept. “[Mary] saw two angels” echoes the two parts of the shroud.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97">96</xref>“In white” corresponds to the color of the cloth. “Sitting” indicates a meditative posture. The two angels (one sitting where the head of Christ had been, the other at his feet) seem to be meditating on an empty space (“where the body of Jesus had been”), as if “they loved to contemplate Christ dead better than resurrected in His glory.” Tesauro holds that the two angels conversing with the Magdalene also figure the “sympathetic” harmony that resulted from Christ’s death. Heaven and earth equally participate in the sympathetic blood shed by the incarnate Word.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98">97</xref>
      </p>
      <p>The blood’s original divine nature is still detectable in the fact that, similar to the Eucharist, it urges us to recall the Word’s sacrifice. However, unlike the Eucharist, this blood does not summon the Word’s presence. We find an analysis of this crucial issue in the Theatine Agaffino Solaro’s<italic>Sindone evangelica</italic>(1627). Contradicting Thomas Aquinas and Francisco Suarez, who believe that no relic can derive from Christ’s body because he resurrected with his entire humanity, Solaro holds that the blood on the shroud does belong to Christ. Christ chose to leave particles of his blood on the shroud in memory of his crucifixion, but this blood has a nonhypostatic nature, because it did not resurrect with the rest of his body.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99">98</xref>If we maintain the comparison to an emblematic structure, we could say that the nonhypostatic blood on the shroud composes the motto of a divine emblem, whose “body” is the Eucharist. The “soul” of this sacred emblem is our dining at the table of the Word’s emblem.</p>
      <p>If the bloodstained shroud echoes the Eucharist, the linen cloth spread on the altar of a church echoes the shroud.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100">99</xref>I have already explained that, faithful to a topos of Italian baroque style, Tesauro founds his writing on two basic metaphors, what he calls “similarity” and “opposition.” Borrowing again from Balliani’s<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, Tesauro posits a direct mirroring between Christ and the linen cloth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101">100</xref>“What is linen,” he asks the reader, “but a plant born in tears?” Describing how linen is produced, Tesauro writes: “It [linen] is pulled away from its native earth, then drowned in water, then torn, lacerated, and beaten.” Later, it is “stretched on the cross of a loom and pierced thousands of times.” As the prophet foresaw (Isa. 43:17), linen is the symbol of martyrdom. Consequently, “what is the shroud but a martyr in cloth? What is a martyr but a shroud in flesh? Or better yet, what is the shroud but the idea [<italic>idea</italic>] of all martyrs?”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102">101</xref>Being the visible sign of martyrdom, Tesauro hypothesizes that the shroud, and not the cross, will become visible at Doomsday. The “the sign of the Son of Man in heaven” that Christ mentions to his disciples (Matt. 24:30) will be the shroud stained with his blood.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103">102</xref>Before sending his angels to gather his elect, the Word will show his own shroud, the supreme “vestige” and emblem of his incarnation. The shroud in Turin will be reflected in the heavens, as a final agreement between earth and sky.</p>
      <p>The relics of St. Maurice were brought to rest next to the shroud in the Turinese cathedral by a complex “sympathetic” movement. First of all, Tesauro contends that the “Theban Legion” is the real “militia of the shroud,” in the sense that it closely recalls the Word’s human experience.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104">103</xref>Given that it originated in Egypt, the Legion of St. Maurice was meant to echo the exile of the baby Jesus from his fatherland.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105">104</xref>St. Maurice as symbol of an entire legion followed the incarnate Word and “copied” his human vicissitudes. According to Tesauro, Maurice recalls both the incarnate Word and the angel Gabriel who witnessed the crucial events of the Word’s human biography. Tesauro underscores that, in his<italic>Passio</italic>of St. Maurice, St. Eucherius calls the Theban martyrs “the angelic legion.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106">105</xref>Since in Greek “angelicus martyr” equals “angelicus testis” (witness), it is easy to identify Maurice as the human reflection of the angelic Gabriel, who was both “custodian and minister of the Savior.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107">106</xref>Tesauro contends that Gabriel, the angel who announced the Savior’s birth to Mary, was also the “Angelus Domini,” who sat alone at the Word’s sepulcher, suggested that the holy family leave for Egypt, and finally comforted Jesus in Gethsemane.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108">107</xref>According to Tesauro, as in the sepulcher Gabriel functioned as “martyr” (in the sense of “witness”), so does now the martyr Maurice serve as the angel custodian of the shroud.</p>
      <p>At the end of this beautifully crafted series of identifications, Maurice “contemplates Christ’s martyrdom in His image and his own martyrdom in Christ’s.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109">108</xref>If the shroud is the visible reminder of an internal shroud that lies dormant within us, the image of the angelic witness Maurice contemplating his own biography in the shroud is a powerful synthesis of this process of self‐enlightenment. In the shroud Maurice recognizes the sense of his martyrdom in the light of the Word’s biography. The image of the shroud is the emblem of our human experience. By visiting the cathedral of Turin, we become “witnesses” of a divine “sympathetic” mirroring between the shroud and its angelic martyr. To meditate on the shroud means to let the reflection between the shroud and the relics of Maurice be reflected on our inner “mirror,” the intellect.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn110">109</xref>
      </p>
      <p>But how does the shroud‐relics reflection operate? What does it mean to participate in a divine mirroring? Tesauro again offers an intrinsically rhetorical interpretation of some tenets of Renaissance hermetic thought.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn111">110</xref>He reminds us that the inner qualities of a given “agent” (<italic>agente</italic>) become apparent when it is connected to its “symbol” (<italic>simbolo</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn112">111</xref>As agent, the relics speak forth the beneficial qualities of the shroud. The shroud, we could say, is here a noun, whereas St. Maurice’s body is its actualization. In other words, the name “shroud” means the relics of the martyr Maurice, and conversely the martyr’s relics are symbolized in the shroud. “Shroud” is the proper name of the relics. The link between an “agent” or object and its name or “symbol” can be in fact seen as a movement from potentiality (<italic>in potenza</italic>) to actuality (<italic>in atto</italic>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn113">112</xref>To explain this crucial point, Tesauro reminds us that Paul, “already destined to martyrdom,” believed that he carried the “stigmata” of the Lord in his body.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn114">113</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Paul had become a perfect mirror of the crucified Christ. For Tesauro, the Word was a sun enlightening the martyr apostle and reflected himself through him. The shroud, Tesauro adds, is the visible echo of Paul’s inner stigmata. But, unlike Paul, we are unable to become pure reflections of this luminous sun. Our contemplation of the sacred cloth in fact beclouds its luminosity. Our intellect is a smudged mirror.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn115">114</xref>In similar terms, writing on 2 Cor. 3:18, in his epistle 147 (<italic>De videndo Deo</italic>) Augustine holds that, after Christ’s resurrection, our faces are mirrors reflecting God’s glory, but those who reject Christ have placed a veil over their faces.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn116">115</xref>We have seen that, in Tesauro’s Catholic view, we still retain a perception of the Word as the Father’s “metaphor.” For Augustine, the Bible as well is a mirror (<italic>speculum</italic>) reflecting our truthful image.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn117">116</xref>In<italic>Anatomia sacra</italic>(Sacred anatomy, 1685), a powerful manual of meditation on the shroud, the Theatine Vittorio Amedeo Barralis dedicates an entire chapter on the image of Christ’s “blindfolded eyes,” in which he opposes Christ’s physical blindness to the sinners’ inner inability to see themselves reflected in the Word’s image.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn118">117</xref>In<italic>Sympathy</italic>, Tesauro contends that the Word has placed the relics of Maurice next to the shroud, because the relics work as “a third and firm mirror that excites that beneficial power of this sun.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn119">118</xref>
      </p>
      <p>As “agent” of the shroud, the body of Maurice is at once “firm mirror” and shield. “Never like now,” Tesauro writes, “we need his [Maurice’s] assistance given the numerous armies and trumpets blaring around us, the numerous ominous appearances of infectious influences close to us.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn120">119</xref>For Tesauro, the Savoy duchy is a new sacred land afflicted by external and internal menaces. Not only do heretical armies threaten this Catholic territory, the air itself seems to be infected with noxious presences. As shield, the martyr Maurice of the Theban Legion is asked to protect the land that Christ has chosen to preserve his sacred cloth. The panegyric concludes with a prayer to the martyr: “Let us implore our Martyr so that he implore [God to grant us] public peace, physical and spiritual health, a more salubrious air [and] a concordance between God, the world, and ourselves.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn121">120</xref>In Tesauro’s words, entering the perfect mirroring between the shroud and the relics, we “implore” the relic “to implore” the shroud.</p>
      <p>We have seen that the shroud is the Word’s “symbol” and the relics are its “agents.” We glean a clearer understanding of this rhetorical and linguistic connection if we read it in the light of Renaissance notions of emblematic expression. In an earlier section of this essay, I explained Tesauro’s innovative theories. I pointed out that Tesauro believes in the existence of visual hybrids, some sorts of emblematic<italic>imprese</italic>, at once “heroic” and personal messages expressed through general visual statements. Contradicting a tenet of the Renaissance concept of emblem, in the<italic>Telescope</italic>Tesauro contends that “the [<italic>impresa</italic>] is a miraculous composition whose soul is outside of the body.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn122">121</xref>For Tesauro, the “miracle” of an<italic>impresa</italic>lies in the fact that its message turns into a personal, nonvisible insight. The “soul” of the shroud‐<italic>impresa</italic>is the marvel brought about in the “mirror” of our intellect.</p>
      <p>Tesauro clarifies further the concordances between the shroud and the martyr Maurice in<italic>Il forte armato</italic>, a brief panegyric entirely dedicated to St. Maurice. Offering a free interpretation of Luke 11:21 (“a strong man fully armed”), Tesauro again portrays Maurice as the “heroic” presence placed at the “entrance of the noble reign of Italy” to protect the peninsula against numerous external dangers, in this case identified with the heresies plaguing the rest of Europe.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn123">122</xref>Serving as custodian and witness (martyr,<italic>testis</italic>), Maurice has also the duty to defend “the canvas of the Savior.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn124">123</xref>If in<italic>Sympathy</italic>he had focused on the blood on the shroud, in<italic>Il forte armato</italic>Tesauro dwells on the blood of the martyrs, which is “the blood of the Church.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn125">124</xref>The martyrs’ blood is an affirmative response, a firm “yes” to the blood of the Word. Like the two‐part shroud, the martyr Maurice and thus his relics have a dynamic nature, for they express at once “stillness and movement, tribulation and peace.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn126">125</xref>If the shroud as “emblematic [<italic>impresa</italic>]” has brought forth a “soul” within the blood of the martyr, so do his relics now possess a similar symbolic nature. The “contamination” from blood to blood, from soul to soul, has no end. This is the redeeming power of the martyr’s relics. Echoing the ending of<italic>Sympathy</italic>, Tesauro insists that the saint’s body safeguards “the air you breathe.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn127">126</xref>
      </p>
      <p>At the end of this avalanche of metaphorical connections, of “marvelous” associations, what final and conclusive role do we assign to the shroud, to the figure marked with the Word’s sympathetic blood? Emanuele Tesauro daringly states that in the beginning was the Father’s Metaphor, the Son, who became figure to share the metaphorical idiom of our “mirror,” the intellect. The dialogue between the divinity and human beings exists as reflecting metaphors. The blood of Christ is the quintessential manifestation of the intrinsically metaphorical nature of the real and of his infinite compassion. If we are mirrors blinded by the marvel constantly disclosed by divine compassion, our exegesis is a maze of hypothetical reflections, of hypothetical metaphorical comparisons. Paul’s words are clear: “Now we see only reflections in a mirror.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn128">127</xref>In allowing the image of the crucified Word, the metaphor of the Father, to reflect its marvel on our beclouded mirror, we are invited to fathom our own metaphorical nature, our being nothing but visible echoes of the Father’s original metaphor. Christ is our biography. Like the martyr Maurice, the shroud’s “agent,” we are reflections of a luminous marvel of salvation.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>See Emanuele Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici sacri</italic>(Venice: Tramontin, 1682), pt. 2, 84. Emanuele Tesauro was born in Turin in 1592 into the noble family of the counts of Salmour. He became a Jesuit in 1611. Some twenty years later (1634), he left the order but remained a secular priest. In 1633, he published the first edition of the<italic>Panegirici sacri</italic>, which was a big success and was dedicated to Christine of France. In 1654, at the age of sixty‐two, Tesauro published the first edition of the<italic>Il Cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>and in 1661 the three tragedies<italic>Ermenegildo</italic>,<italic>Edipo</italic>, and<italic>Ippolito</italic>. Considered a master of the art of preaching, between 1619 and 1670 Tesauro also wrote the vast collection of<italic>Inscriptiones</italic>(first ed., 1666), made of innumerable emblems, mottoes, epigraphs, devices for royal palaces, and all kinds of objects. He died in 1675. For a detailed biography, see Maria Luisa Doglio, “Emanuele Tesauro e la parola che crea: Metafora e potere della scrittura,” in Emanuele Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, facsimile reproduction (Turin: Editrice artistica piemontese, 2000), vii–xvi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” pt. 2, 84.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>See Maria Luisa Doglio, “`Grandezze e meraviglie' della Sindone nella letteratura del Seicento,” in<italic>Il potere e la devozione: La Sindone e la Biblioteca Reale di Torino</italic>, ed. Vera Comoli and Giovanna Giacobello Bernard (Milan: Electa, 2000), 17–28.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 15. Tesauro’s<italic>Aristotelian Telescope</italic>greatly expands the premises and conclusions of Baltasar Gracián’s important<italic>Agudeza y arte de ingenio</italic>(1648). The final edition of Tesauro’s opus (1670) is more than 700 pages long.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 266.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Ibid., 279. The title of the eight kinds of metaphors are metaphor of similitude (<italic>simi</italic>
                  <italic>glian</italic>
                  <italic>za</italic>), of attribution (<italic>attributione</italic>), of ambiguity (<italic>equivoco</italic>), of hypotyposis, of hyperbole (<italic>iperbole</italic>), of laconism (<italic>laconismo</italic>), of opposition (<italic>oppositione</italic>), and of deception (<italic>decettione</italic>, 298). Compare Aristotle,<italic>Poetics</italic>1457b7–9, and<italic>Rhetoric</italic>1411a1. The main difference between Aristotle and Tesauro is that, whereas Aristotle’s definition is based on the logical structure of a metaphorical expression, Tesauro considers the rhetorical results of a given metaphor. This is evident in the titles of Tesauro’s eight basic categories. The secondary literature on Tesauro’s concept of metaphor is vast. See, in particular, Mario Zanardi, “La metafora e la sua dinamica di significazione nel `Cannocchiale aristotelico' di Emanuele Tesauro,”<italic>Giornale storico della letteratura italiana</italic>157 (1980): 321–68; Pierantonio Frare, “Il `Cannocchiale aristotelico': Da retorica della letteratura a letteratura della retorica,”<italic>Studi secenteschi</italic>32 (1991): 33–63; Pierantonio Frare, “Contro la metafora: Antitesi e metafora nella prassi e nella teoria letteraria del Seicento,”<italic>Studi secenteschi</italic>33 (1992): 3–20. Also consider the following important books: Ezio Raimondi,<italic>Letteratura barocca</italic>(Florence: Olschki, 1961), 1–32; Giuseppe Conte,<italic>La metafora barocca: Saggio sulle poetiche del Seicento</italic>(Milan: Mursia, 1972), in particular, on “meraviglia” (123–24), and on the concept of “sign” in the baroque (156–59).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Tesauro offers this important definition in<italic>La filosofia morale</italic>(Venice: Pezzana, 1673), bk. 18 (“On Human Passions”), chap. 4 (“Questions on Human Passions”), 554–55. Compare<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 217. See Raimondi,<italic>Letteratura barocca</italic>, 21–22; Zanardi, “La metafora e la sua dinamica di significazione,” 350–51. Expanding Raimondi’s seminal remarks, Zanardi offers an excellent analysis of the above passage from Tesauro’s<italic>La filosofia morale</italic>. Tesauro’s definition in part echoes Thomas Aquinas’s concept of “admiratio” (<italic>Summa</italic>1, pt. 2, q. 32, art. 8). Thomas writes: “Est autem admiratio desiderium quoddam sciendi, quod in homine contingit ex hoc quod videt effectum et ignorat causam” (Thomae Aquinas,<italic>Summa Theologiae</italic>, ed. Pietro Caramello [Turin: Marietti, 1950], 156–57).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>La filosofia morale</italic>, 554.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Alfonso Paleotto,<italic>Esplicatione del lenzuolo ove fu involto il Signore</italic>(Bologna: Rossi, 1598), 19; Song of Sol. 5:10. It is worth remembering that, according to Clement VII, the antipope of Avignon, who first was compelled to define the nature of this relic, the shroud was only a faithful picture of the actual cloth that touched Christ’s body. On this important subject, see Ulysse Chevalier,<italic>Étude critique sur l’origine du St Suaire de Lirey‐Chambery‐Turin</italic>(Paris: Picard, 1900), in particular 25–26. See also his subsequent<italic>Autour des origines du Suaire de Lirey avec documents inédits</italic>(Paris: Picard, 1903), 11–12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Paleotto,<italic>Esplicatione</italic>, 20–21. See<italic>Concilium tridentinum</italic>, in<italic>Conciliorum oecumenicorum decreta</italic>, ed. Giuseppe Alberigo, 3rd ed. (Bologna: Istituto per le Scienze Religiose, 1973), session 25 (December 3–4, 1563): “De invocatione, veneratione et reliquiis sanctorum, et de sacris imaginibus” (774–76). It is stressed that holy images work as similes of the<italic>prototypa</italic>(originals) they represent (775).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Ignazio del Nente,<italic>Breve modo di fare orazione mentale</italic>(1642; Florence: Onofri, 1677). Del Nente states (4) that “affetto … consiste nell’innamoramento del cuore” (<italic>affetto</italic>is based on the heart falling in love). See also his other treatises:<italic>Solitudini di sacri e pietosi affetti intorno a’ misteri di nostro Signore Giesù Cristo e Maria Vergine</italic>(Florence: Massi &amp; Landi, 1643), and<italic>L’eremo interno del cuore</italic>(Florence: Nestenus &amp; Borghigiani, 1642), in particular “Solitudo montis,” 67–68. On this genre, see Antonio Gentili and Mauro Ragazzoni,<italic>La spi</italic>
                  <italic>ri</italic>
                  <italic>tualità della riforma cattolica</italic>, vol. 5/C (Bologna: Centro Editoriale Dehoniano, 1993); Mario Petrocchi,<italic>La controriforma in Italia</italic>(Rome: Veritas editrice, 1947).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Ignatius of Loyola, “The First Exercise,” in<italic>Spiritual Exercises</italic>, ed. George E. Ganss, SJ (New York: Paulist Press, 1991), 136.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Ibid., 137.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>In this theological context, it is worth mentioning the brief treatise<italic>La Sacra Sindone</italic>by the Theatine Eugenio Quarantotto. After summarizing Paleotto’s disturbing description of the slanted nails in Christ’s hands and feet, Quarantotto remarks that the wound on the side does not look like a scar but is more like a blot of blood (<italic>La Sacra Sindone</italic>[Turin, 1624], 17–18). Since it is located on the left side of the image on the shroud, it means that the Lord must have been pierced on the right side. Thus, many of the paintings portraying Christ on the cross are wrong. To support his conclusion, Quarantotto draws an important and original comparison between the image on the shroud and St. Bonaventure’s description of St. Francis of Assisi’s stigmata: “Dexterum quoque latus, quasi lancea transfixum, rubra cicatrice obductum erat” (<italic>La Sacra Sindone</italic>, 18–19; Bonaventure,<italic>Legenda maior</italic>13.3). The mutual mirroring between Francis and the crucified Christ (Francis wounded by the seraph holding the image of the wounded Christ and conversely the shroud holding the image of the wounded Christ enlightened by the image of the wounded Francis) did not receive a thorough analysis in subsequent treatises on the shroud.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>See Gian Maria Zaccone, “Un percorso storico per la Sindone,” in<italic>Il potere e la devozione</italic>, ed. Vera Comoli and Gainna Giacobello Bernard (Milan: Electa, 2000), 75–88, and<italic>Sulle tracce della Sindone</italic>(Turin: Elle Di Ci, 1997), 5–21.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 84–85.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Livy, bk. 2, chap. 10, 2–3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>On Hannibal and Cannae, see ibid., bk. 22, chaps. 43–52. On Scipio and Carthage, see Valerius Maximus, 4.3.13; Cicero,<italic>De republica</italic>, bk. 6 (<italic>Somnium Scipionis</italic>), 11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 86.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>See Rev. 19:11–15, in<italic>New Jerusalem Bible</italic>, standard ed. (New York: Doubleday, 1998), 1403: “And now I saw heaven open, and a white horse appear; its rider was called Trustworthy and True; in uprightness he judges and makes war … his cloak was soaked in blood. He is known by the name, the Word of God. Behind him, dressed in linen of dazzling white, rode the armies of heaven on white horses. From his mouth came a sharp sword with which to strike the unbelievers.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Esther 2:21–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>The<italic>Vulgata</italic>literally states: “in the presence of the king” (mandatumque est libro annalium coram rege [Esther 2:23]).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 87.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Ibid., 87–88.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 694. For a clear introduction to this complex book, see Yves Hersant,<italic>La métaphore baroque</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 2001), 9–25. Hersant offers the first partial French translation of Tesauro’s treatise.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Between 1622 and 1629, Tesauro wrote a distinct treatise on the nature of<italic>imprese</italic>, which can be seen as an introduction to the subsequent<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>. This short text was published only in 1975: Emanuele Tesauro,<italic>Idea delle perfette imprese</italic>, ed. Maria Luisa Doglio (Florence: Olschki, 1975). In chap. 17, Tesauro stresses that a perfect<italic>impresa</italic>must express a particular thought. An<italic>impresa</italic>can certainly have also a universal meaning, but this general significance must derive from a “individual” mind (94–95).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 684.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>I discuss the differences between<italic>imprese</italic>and emblems in the opening section of “Visual and Verbal Communication in Francesco Pona’s<italic>Cardiomorphoseos</italic>,”<italic>Word and Image</italic>16, no. 2 (2000): 213–26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 706–7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Ibid., 707–8.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>Richard of St. Victor,<italic>The Mystical Ark</italic>, trans. Grover A. Zinn (New York: Paulist Press, 1979), bk. 4, chap. 2, 261.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Ibid., bk. 4, chaps. 12 and 20, 279, 299; Richardi S. Victoris,<italic>Benjamin Major</italic>, in<italic>Patrologia Latina</italic>(<italic>PL</italic>), ed. Jacques‐Paul Migne (Paris: Garnier, 1880), 196:149, 163.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>St. Thomas Aquinas,<italic>Hymnus in die Corporis Christi ad Vesperas</italic>, in<italic>Thesaurus Hymnologicus</italic>, ed. Hermann Adalbert Daniel, (Leipzig: Loeschke, 1862), 1:245.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 641. The most comprehensive treatise on<italic>imprese</italic>is Ercole Tasso’s<italic>Della realtà e perfezione delle imprese</italic>(Bergamo, 1612). Tasso’s book is the summa of sixteenth‐century debate on emblematic expression.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Tesauro,<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 641. The Barnabite Giovan Battista Paggi composes an entire panegyric around the metaphor of the shroud as shield by the title<italic>Lo scudo, panegirico sacro sopra la S. Sindone</italic>(The shield, sacred panegyric on the holy shroud) (Turin: Ferrofino, 1648).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 90;<italic>New Jerusalem Bible</italic>, 976.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Let us remember that, in his second biography of Francis of Assisi, Thomas of Celano reports that brother Pacifico “saw the great sign of the Tau on the forehead of blessed Francis, which displayed its beauty with the multi‐colored circles of a peacock.” Francis drew this sign on walls and signed his name with it. In his mystical insight, brother Pacifico sees that Francis’s body itself is a text marked with the Tau (Thomas of Celano,<italic>The Remembrance of the Desire of a Soul</italic>, in<italic>Francis of Assisi: The Founder</italic>, ed. Regis J. Armstrong, J. A. Wayne Hellman, and William J. Short [New York: New City, 2000], chap. 72, 317).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 91.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Ibid., 92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Ibid., 96.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Ibid., 100–101.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Compare Aristotle,<italic>Poetics</italic>1458a17–24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 104.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>De trinitate</italic>,<italic>PL</italic>42, bk. 15, chap. 3, sec. 5, 1060.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Ibid., bk. 14, 16.22, 1053. In book 1 of the<italic>Institutions</italic>, Calvin openly rejects Augustine’s idea that the soul is a mirror of the Trinity, although he frequently uses the metaphor of the mirror in reference to Christ and the scriptures. I have consulted the following edition: Jean Calvin,<italic>Institution de la religion chretienne</italic>, ed. Jean‐Daniel Benoit, 5 vols. (Paris: Vrin, 1957), vol. 1, bk. 1, chap. 15, 213. On the image of “mirror,” see<italic>Institution de la religion chretienne</italic>, vol. 3, chap. 2, 14. Calvin writes that Christ is the mirror of God’s glory. Later (<italic>Institution</italic>, vol. 3, chap. 25, 476), Calvin stresses that, every time we speak of the resurrection, we must consider the image of Christ. We carry his mortification in our flesh (sa mortification en notre chair). As far the scriptures as mirror are concerned, see<italic>Institution</italic>, vol. 3, chap. 22, 422. Calvin uses the term “mirror” (<italic>miroir</italic>) also to elucidate the thorny issue of free election (<italic>Institution</italic>, vol. 3, chap. 22, 418). On this subject, see the introductory analysis in John Hesselink, “Calvin’s Theology,” in<italic>The Cambridge Companion to John Calvin</italic>, ed. Donald K. McKim (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2004), 74–92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>On this subject, see Gerhart B. Ladner,<italic>The Idea of Reform</italic>(New York: Harper Torchbooks, 1967), 185–203; Etienne Gilson,<italic>Introduction a l’étude de Saint Augustine</italic>(Paris: Vrin, 1943), chap. 4 (“L’image de Dieu”), 286–98. See Cornelius Petrus Maier, OSA,<italic>Die Zeichen in der Geistigen Entwicklung und in der Theologie des Jungen Augustinus</italic>(Würzburg: Augustinus, 1969), 349–60.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Argutezze divine,” in<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 59.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Ibid., 61. Tesauro mentions one eloquent case of divine expression. When in Josh. 10:12 the sun and the moon stood still over Gibeon, the literal meaning corresponds to its historical connotation. The tropological meaning is that the enemies signify the vices against reason and the planets mean the worldly goods. Therefore, man cannot defeat sin unless he uses his goods and is not used by them. The allegorical meaning is that no one can overcome the “enemy” without the beneficial influences of the sun and the moon (Jesus and the Virgin Mary). Finally, the anagogical level becomes evident if we see the enemies as the damned souls, the sun as the divinity, and the moon as the humanity of the blessed souls (ibid., 61–62).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Ibid., 63.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Exod. 33:23. Tesauro could have found this biblical reference in<italic>Dicerie sacre</italic>by Giovan Battista Marino, Italy’s most important baroque poet. Marino’s<italic>Dicerie</italic>(first published in 1614) is a series of three religious discourses. The first, called “On Painting,” focuses on the shroud of Turin. Marino mentions God’s words to Moses toward the end of his text. See Giovan Battista Marino,<italic>Dicerie sacre e la strage degli innocenti</italic>, ed. Giovanni Pozzi (Turin: Einaudi, 1960), “La pittura,” pt. 1, 143.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 107.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Ibid., pt. 2, 110. In the<italic>Telescope</italic>, Tesauro points out that<italic>enargeia</italic>, which “gives strength and stamina to speech,” springs from a “metaphor of movement” (<italic>Il cannocchiale aristotelico</italic>, 332).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Quintilian,<italic>The Orator’s Education</italic>, trans. Donald A. Russell (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2001), bk. 8, chap. 3, sec. 61, 375.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 111.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>See Camillo Balliani,<italic>Ragionamenti della Sacra Sindone</italic>, 2nd ed. (Turin: Pizzamiglio, 1616). Balliani likens the shroud to the two Testaments at least twice, in the “Ragionamento V” (188) and “Ragionamento VIII” (314). The first time he draws this comparison, Balliani adds: “This interpretation is not far‐fetched” (188).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Commentario,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 117–18.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Ibid., 125.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>Balliani, “Ragionamento VIII,” in<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 316–17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>Balliani, “Ragionamento V,” in ibid., 174. Balliani interprets Rom. 8:28: “Praescivit et praedestinavit conformes fieri imaginis filii sui.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>Balliani, “Ragionamento I,” in<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 39–40. A similar concept is treated in “Ragionamento IX” (<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 337), where Balliani reminds us that God ordered Moses to place a vase full of water at the entrance of the tabernacle where the high priests could wash their hands. Moses also put some mirrors in which the priests could check if they had any stains to wash off (Exodus 38). In the powerful “Ode in honor della Sacratissima Sindone” (published at the end of Agaffino Solaro’s<italic>Sindone evangelica, historica, theologica</italic>[Turin: Cavalleris, 1627], n.p.), Guido Casoni expands the metaphor of the shroud as “divine mirror of eternal beauties” (verse 15), in which “the loving soul contemplates and sees / glory in torments and mercy in pain” (verses 31–32). Two short quotations from Casoni’s poem on the shroud had already been published in Quarantotto’s<italic>La Sacra Sindone</italic>, 13, 19. Let us remember that the image of Christ as a mirror reflecting our own humanity is the core of St. Clare of Assisi’s mysticism. In<italic>The Fourth Letter to Agnes of Prague</italic>, Clare suggests that Agnes “look daily into this mirror and continually study [her] face in it” (St. Clare of Assisi, “The Fourth Letter,” in<italic>Franciscan Christology</italic>, trans. Eric Doyle, 37). In “The Third Letter,” Clare speaks of the “mirror of eternity” (<italic>speculo eternitatis</italic>; 33).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>In<italic>Sindone evangelica</italic>, a theological study of the shroud published in 1627 by the Theatine Agaffino Solaro, the “miraculous image” itself was “sketched” at the moment of the Word’s death and “completed” when he resurrected from the dead (40). The shroud itself testifies to a dynamic process of transformation from death to life.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>Alfonso Ingegno, “The New Philosophy of Nature,” in<italic>The Cambridge History of Renaissance Philosophy</italic>, ed. Charles B. Schmitt and Quentin Skinner (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1988), 236–63, quote on 236; William A. Wallace, “Traditional Natural Philosophy,” in ibid., 201–35. See also Ernst Cassirer,<italic>The Individual and the Cosmos in Renaissance Philosophy</italic>, trans. Mario Domandi (Mineola, NY: Dover, 2000), 123–91. For a literary study of these issues, see S. K. Heninger Jr.,<italic>Touches of Sweet Harmony: Pythagorean Cosmology and Renaissance Poetics</italic>(San Marino, CA: Huntington Library, 1974), sec. 3 (“Poetics”), chap. 2 (“Metaphor as Cosmic Correspondence”), 325–63. For an analysis of Tommaso Campanella, the most important seventeenth‐century natural philosopher in Italy, see Germana Ernst,<italic>Religione, ragione e natura: Ricerche su Tommaso Campanella e il tardo Rinascimento</italic>(Milan: Angeli, 1991), and<italic>Tommaso Campanella: Il libro e il corpo della natura</italic>(Rome: Laterza, 2002).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>Compare<italic>Acta Sanctorum</italic>, “Septembris” (1757; reprint, Brusselles: Culture et Civilization, 1970), 6:363, 368. See also entry “San Maurizio,” in<italic>Bibliotheca Sanctorum</italic>(Rome: Istituto Giovanni XXIII, 1961–70), 9:193–205. On Maurice of Savoy, see Luciano Tamburini, “I luoghi della Sindone,” in Comoli and Bernard,<italic>Il potere e la devozione</italic>, 93.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>I have consulted the Latin edition in<italic>Acta Sanctorum</italic>, “Septembris,” 6:342–43.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Acta Sanctorum</italic>, 6:342.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>Ibid., 6:343.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn69">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 3.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn70">
               <label>69</label>
               <p>Ibid., 3–4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn71">
               <label>70</label>
               <p>Ibid., 4.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn72">
               <label>71</label>
               <p>Ibid., 5. Tesauro refers to a homily by Joannis Chrysostomus. See Joannis Chrysostomus, “In Sanctos Maccabaeos. Homilia 1,” in<italic>Opera Omnia</italic>, ed. Beruard de Montfaucon (Paris: Gaume, 1838), 2:743. The image of martyrs as radiant lights is present in the introductory section.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn73">
               <label>72</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn74">
               <label>73</label>
               <p>Ibid., 10–11. The term<italic>sangue</italic>is capitalized in the text. Tesauro reports a slightly modified biblical passage: “anima carnis in sanguine est” (see Gen. 9:4: “carnem cum anima quae est in sanguine”). He also refers to a passage from Aristotle’s<italic>On the Parts of Animals</italic>(bk. 2, 651a13–14): “The character of the blood affects both the temperament and the sensory faculties of animals in many ways.” See<italic>The Complete Works of Aristotle</italic>, ed. Jonathan Barnes, 2 vols. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1995), 1:1013.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn75">
               <label>74</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 13.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn76">
               <label>75</label>
               <p>Ibid., 14.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn77">
               <label>76</label>
               <p>Ibid., 14–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn78">
               <label>77</label>
               <p>Ibid., 15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn79">
               <label>78</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 16–17. Compare Marsilio Ficino,<italic>De vita pro</italic>
                  <italic>du</italic>
                  <italic>cenda sive longa</italic>, in<italic>Opera omnia</italic>, facsimile reproduction (Turin: Bottega d’Erasmo, 1959), vol. 1, pt. 1, bk. 2, chap. 11, 518 (“in sanguine humano virtute [est], qua humanum sanguinem attrah[i]t”); Cornelius Gemma,<italic>De naturae divinis characterismis</italic>(Antwerp: Plantini, 1575); Galeotto Marzio,<italic>De doctrina promiscua</italic>(Leiden: Tornaesium, 1552), chap. 22 (“De spiritibus et quare gaudium aut timor repente occidunt, et cur sanguis occisi coram occisore iterum fluit”), 225–40, 232. Compare Pierre Grégoire,<italic>Syntaxeon artis mirabilis</italic>(Coloniae: Zetnzeri, 1610), bk. 36, chap. 7 (“De magnete”), 444–45; Paracelsus,<italic>Archidoxorum, seu de secretis naturae mysteriis</italic>(Basle: Petrum Pernam, 1582), bk. 6 (“Extractio magisterii ex sanguine”), 105–7. Tesauro concludes this list of authorities with Ioannes Lange (“il Langio”), whose medical theories on blood’s secret qualities are for Tesauro the most accurate. According to Tesauro, Lange stresses the antipathy arising from the imagination. Tesauro probably refers to a passage from Lange’s<italic>Epistolarum Medicinalium</italic>(Hanau: Claudium Marnium, 1605), bk. 1, epistle 24 (“De erotico amore effectu”), 103–4. Lange reports the story of Faustina, daughter of the emperor Antoninus Pius, who had fallen in love with a gladiator. To recover from this disease, some physicians suggested that she swallow some of the man’s warm blood. The gladiator was killed to fulfill this request.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn80">
               <label>79</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 23. Compare Gregorius Magnus,<italic>Registrum epistolarum: IV–VII</italic>, ed. Dag Norberg (Rome: Città nuova editrice, 1996), 4:30, 72–78. Gregory rejects the request of “Constantina augusta” to send the relics of St. Paul to the new church of St. Paul in Constantinople. He contends that to touch the bodies of saints is a sacrilege. Some Christians coming from the East removed the corpses of Peter and Paul right after their martyrdom, because they wished to bring the relics to the saints’ birthplaces. But while they were in a place called “Catacumbas” located only a couple of miles from the city, these people were terrified by a violent thunder and lightening (ibid., 76).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn81">
               <label>80</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 24.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn82">
               <label>81</label>
               <p>Heb. 2:17 (“debuit per omnia fratribus similari ut misericors fieret”).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn83">
               <label>82</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn84">
               <label>83</label>
               <p>Ibid., 27.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn85">
               <label>84</label>
               <p>Ibid., 35; Lev. 4:5–6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn86">
               <label>85</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>On the shroud blending together “figura” and “figurato,” see Balliani’s “Ragionamento VI,” in<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 218–19.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn88">
               <label>87</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 40; Gen. 4:10 (“Vox sanguinis fratris tui clamat ad me de aegro”).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn89">
               <label>88</label>
               <p>Balliani, “Ragionamento VIII,” in<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 310–11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn90">
               <label>89</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 37.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn91">
               <label>90</label>
               <p>David Tracy examines the tension between literal and metaphorical meaning in Christian religious language in “Metaphor and Religion: The Test Case of Christian Texts,” in<italic>On Metaphor</italic>, ed. Sheldon Sacks (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1979), 89–104. Tracy focuses on two basic expressions: “The Kingdom of God is like” and “God is Love.” “The statement ‘God is Love,’” Tracy writes, “does not say literally what God is but<italic>produces</italic>a metaphorical meaning for what God is like” (103). Tracy refers to Paul Ricoeur’s insistence on the concept of tension in<italic>The Rule of Metaphor</italic>(trans. Robert Czerny [Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2000], 247–56). Ricoeur speaks of “the<italic>ecstatic</italic>moment of language,” which is “the moment of<italic>belief</italic>,<italic>of ontological commitment</italic>” (249). Ricoeur summarizes the idea of “tension” within metaphorical truth as follows: “There is no other way to do justice to the notion of metaphorical truth than to include the critical incision of the (literal) ‘is not’ within the ontological vehemence of the metaphorical ‘is’” (255).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn92">
               <label>91</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 37–38.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn93">
               <label>92</label>
               <p>Ibid., 44. Ws 14:15 (“Acerbo enim luctu dolens pater cito sibi rapti filii fecit imaginem”). Tesauro capitalizes “Pater” and “Filii.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn94">
               <label>93</label>
               <p>I consult this Latin‐Italian edition: Seneca,<italic>Lettere morali a Lucilio</italic>, ed. Fernando Solinas (Milan: Mondadori, 1995), vol. 1, bk. 4, letter 4, sec. 1, 192. In the opening sentence of this epistle, Seneca writes that, if the portraits of distant friends are pleasant because they keep us company in our solitude, much more pleasant is a letter that carries the “marks” (<italic>vestigia</italic>) of a friend.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn95">
               <label>94</label>
               <p>Compare Marino,<italic>Dicerie sacre</italic>, “La pittura,” pt. 1, 135. Marino states that the Father painted the image of the shroud before creating the world. At the beginning, God “contemplated Himself within the luminous mirror of His essence” (136).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn96">
               <label>95</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 44. It is interesting to note that, in the<italic>Admonitions</italic>, Francis of Assisi states that God “created and formed” (<italic>creavit et formavit</italic>) man in the image of his beloved Son “according to the body” (<italic>secundum corpus</italic>) and in his likeness “according to the soul” (<italic>secundum spiritum</italic>). See Francis of Assisi,<italic>Admonitiones</italic>, in<italic>Opuscula</italic>, ed. Caietanus Esser (Grottaferrata, Rome: Collegii S. Bonaventurae, 1978), chap. 5, 65–66. Compare Eric Doyle and Damian McElrath, “St. Francis of Assisi and the Christocentric Character of Franciscan Life and Doctrine,” in<italic>Franciscan Christology</italic>, ed. Damian McElrath (St. Bonaventure, NY: Franciscan Institute, 1994), 1–13: “It seems clear that [Francis] is asserting … that the first Adam was created after the image of the second Adam, Jesus Christ. The body of the Incarnate Word … was the blueprint for the bodies of the first human beings” (7).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn97">
               <label>96</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 48.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn98">
               <label>97</label>
               <p>Ibid., 53–54, on Christ’s blood as magnet.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn99">
               <label>98</label>
               <p>Agaffino Solaro,<italic>Sindone evangelica</italic>, 138–39. In the third part of the<italic>Summa</italic>(q. 54, art. 3, 338), broaching the central problem of “The Quality of the Resurrecting Christ,” Thomas had contended that all the blood oozed out of Christ’s body, since it pertained to his human nature and had resurrected with his body. Therefore, Thomas adds, the blood coming out of the relics present in some churches does not derive from Christ’s open side, but rather from images of Christ thanks to some miraculous act (<italic>miraculose</italic>). Solaro disagrees both with Thomas, who had not seen the shroud, and with Francisco Suarez, who in<italic>Commentaria ac disputationes in tertiam partem D. Thomae</italic>(in<italic>Opera Omnia</italic>[Paris: Vivès, 1860], vol. 19, pt. 2, q. 54, art. 4, 826) had contended that the drops of blood present in relics are “accidents of color” and not substance of Christ’s blood.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn100">
               <label>99</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt., 2:61.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn101">
               <label>100</label>
               <p>Compare Balliani, “Ragionamento VIII,” in<italic>Ragionamenti</italic>, 293–94.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn102">
               <label>101</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 62.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn103">
               <label>102</label>
               <p>Ibid., 65. According to Tesauro, Augustine interprets the biblical passage as “parebit triumphale vexillum.” This sentence is not in Augustine. The closest quotation is in Augustine’s<italic>De symbolo</italic>(<italic>PL</italic>, 40, sermo 4, caput 5, 664): “Crux illa fidelibus non est opprobium, sed<italic>triumphus</italic>. Crux illa<italic>vexillum</italic>nostrum est contra adversarium nostrum diabolum” (my emphasis).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn104">
               <label>103</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 68.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn105">
               <label>104</label>
               <p>Ibid., 69.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn106">
               <label>105</label>
               <p>Ibid., 74.<italic>Acta Sanctorum</italic>, “Septembris,” 6:343.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn107">
               <label>106</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 73.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn108">
               <label>107</label>
               <p>Matt. 28:2: “Angelus Domini accedens revoluit lapidem et sedebat super eum”; Matt. 2:13: “Angelus Domini apparuit et dicens, Surge et accipe puerum”; Luke 22:43: “Apparuit illi Angelus de Coelo confortans eum.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn109">
               <label>108</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 74.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn110">
               <label>109</label>
               <p>Compare Marino,<italic>Dicerie sacre</italic>, “La pittura,” pt. 1, 119. Marino compares God to a mirror that reflects the soul’s truthful image. If God withdraws, the soul becomes unable to see itself. The image of mirrors reflecting mirrors is a topos of baroque love poetry. The innumerable sonnets written in seventeenth‐century Italy on this subject aim to create a sense of labyrinthine astonishment, an inner vertigo, the baroque “marvel.” For example, see Giovan Battista Marino,<italic>Rime amorose</italic>, ed. Ottavio Besomi and Alessandro Martini (Ferrara: Edizioni Panini, 1987), sonnets 11–13. This series of poems is entirely dedicated to the topos of the mirror. The most complex and accomplished is the third in which Marino imagines that the mirror reflecting his beloved’s image was made of the tears he had shed and that had become a lucid surface (sonnet 13, verse 2, 61). “The angelic splendor of this goddess” (i.e., his beloved) has turned the mirror into a small heaven, since it reflects the woman’s luminosity (verses 3–4). Love has allowed the metamorphosis of the poet’s tears into mirror, so that his “beautiful sun” (his woman, verse 6) can see what he hides “in the mirror of my heart” (verses 7–8) and detect her beauty in the surface of his visible sorrow. The external mirror is thus a reflection of the poet’s inner mirror in which the luminous woman reflects upon her own image.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn111">
               <label>110</label>
               <p>For a basic introduction to Renaissance hermetic philosophy, see Frances Yates,<italic>Giordano Bruno and the Hermetic Tradition</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991), 169–89.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn112">
               <label>111</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 75.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn113">
               <label>112</label>
               <p>Ibid., 76.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn114">
               <label>113</label>
               <p>Ibid. Gal. 6:17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn115">
               <label>114</label>
               <p>Francisco Suarez speaks at length about the luminosity of Christ’s “glorious body.” The clarity (<italic>claritas</italic>) of the resurrected Christ derives from “the internal light of [his] glorious body” (<italic>Commentaria ac disputationes in tertiam partem D. Thomae</italic>, q. 54, art. 4, 845). As a glass of various colors becomes a luminous prism if exposed to the sun, so does the body of Christ show the transparency of a humanity perfectly permeated by the Father’s light (<italic>Commentaria ac disputationes</italic>, q. 54, art. 3, 812).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn116">
               <label>115</label>
               <p>S. Augustini Episcopi,<italic>De videndo Deo seu Epistola CXLVII</italic>,<italic>PL</italic>33 (Paris: Thibaud, 1865), 620. In Augustine, “speculum” also refers to the scriptures, which reflects our most truthful image.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn117">
               <label>116</label>
               <p>See, e.g.,<italic>Enarratio in psalmum LVI</italic>,<italic>PL</italic>36 (Paris: Thibaud, 1865), 666;<italic>Sermo XLIX</italic>,<italic>PL</italic>38 (Paris: Thibaud, 1865), chap. 5, 322.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn118">
               <label>117</label>
               <p>Vittorio Amedeo Barralis,<italic>Anatomia sacra per la novena della Santa Sindone</italic>(Turin: Gianelli, 1685), 15. Barralis presents two forms of meditation. The first is based on nine parts of Christ’s body. He calls this nine‐part meditation “novena.” The second kind of meditation is what he defines as “rosary” (<italic>rosario</italic>), whose beads are thirty‐three essential moments of Christ’s passion plus five interspersed Hail Marys.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn119">
               <label>118</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “La Simpatia,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 77.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn120">
               <label>119</label>
               <p>Ibid., 78.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn121">
               <label>120</label>
               <p>Ibid., 83. For Tesauro, the metaphor of the saint as shield is of great relevance. If in<italic>Sympathy</italic>Maurice and the shroud are the shields of the Catholic Savoy family, in<italic>Edipo</italic>(Oedipus, 1661), Tesauro’s interpretation of Seneca’s tragedy, Oedipus is the shield that prevents the divinity from exerting his power of purification. In Tesauro’s tragedy, Oedipus holds a long monologue on the “voracious plague” that afflicts the city of Thebes. A praetor replies to the Oedipus that the heavens are merciful because “they oppose your [Oedipus’s] virtue like a shield against their own furor.” See Emanuele Tesauro,<italic>Edipo</italic>, ed. Carlo Ossola (Venice: Marsilio, 1987), 1.1, verse 4, 79, and verses 47–48, 80. We could thus say that, for Tesauro, Maurice is a sort of anti‐Oedipus who has made himself into a lucid mirror of the shroud (the shield reflecting divine will). The saint’s body is a transparent surface reflecting and “actualizing” the “symbol” of the shroud. By contrast, Oedipus’s ignorance of his sins is a darkened, blind shield that prevents the divinity from shining through.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn122">
               <label>121</label>
               <p>See above.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn123">
               <label>122</label>
               <p>Tesauro, “Il Forte Armato,” in<italic>Panegirici</italic>, pt. 2, 130.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn124">
               <label>123</label>
               <p>Ibid., 131. Tesauro speaks of “martyr” as “testis” (149).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn125">
               <label>124</label>
               <p>Ibid., 145.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn126">
               <label>125</label>
               <p>Ibid., 169.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn127">
               <label>126</label>
               <p>Ibid., 175.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn128">
               <label>127</label>
               <p>1 Cor. 13:12.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
