<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         article-type="research-article"
         xml:lang="en"
         dtd-version="1.0">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mexistudestumexi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Mexican Studies/Estudios Mexicanos</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">07429797</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15338320</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">1052158</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/msem.2002.18.2.297</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Research Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="subject">
               <subject>(F) American / Canadian / Latin-Am. History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Tlatelolco 1968: Paz and Poniatowska on Law and Violence</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Sorensen</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2002</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2002</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>18</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>msem.2002.18.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>297</fpage>
         <lpage>321</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Regents of the University of California</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/msem.2002.18.2.297"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Examination of two texts generated by the student massacre at the Plaza de Tlatelolco in 1968:<italic>Postdata</italic>by Octavio Paz, and<italic>La noche de Tlatelolco</italic>by Elena Poniatowska. Paz's totalizing vision interprets the events as providing answers to the questions about the nation posed in<italic>El laberinto de la soledad</italic>, and he insists on the need to rewrite Mexico's history under the aegis of a new genealogy. Poniatowska's book, instead, is ruled by fragmentation and plurality, to convey the often dissonant voices of civil society. The analysis scrutinizes literary form as it is made to represent relations between violence, justice and aesthetics.</p>
            <p>Examen de dos textos generados por la masacre estudiantil de la Plaza de Tlatelolco en 1968:<italic>Postdata</italic>de Octavio Paz y<italic>La noche de Tlatelolco</italic>de Elena Ponioatowska. La visión totalizadora de Paz interpreta el evento como proveedor de respuestas a las cuestiones planteadas acerca de la nación en<italic>El laberinto de la soledad</italic>, e insiste en la necesidad de reescribir la historia de México bajo el eje de una nueva genealogía. El libro de Poniatowska, en cambio, se rige por la fragmentación y la pluralidad, para transmitir las frecuentes voces disonantes de la sociedad civil. El análisis examina los modos en que la forma literaria representa relaciones entre la violencia, la justicia y la estética.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
