<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">JR</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/663737</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR921001</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af1" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Britt</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">Virginia Tech.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>January 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>92</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>662286</issue-id>
         <fpage>123</fpage>
         <lpage>124</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>LaCocque</surname>,<given-names>André</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>The Captivity of Innocence: Babel and the Yahwist</source>. Eugene, OR: Wipf &amp; Stock, 2010. xvi+190 pp. $23.00 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2012 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/663737"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>André LaCocque’s<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>provides close analysis from multiple perspectives on the Tower of Babel episode of Genesis 11. Third in a trilogy of monographs that began with<italic>The Trial of Innocence</italic>(2006, on Gen. 2:4b–4:1) and<italic>Onslaught against Innocence</italic>(2008, on Genesis 4),<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>builds on a portrait of the Yahwist, or J source, as a sixth-century author who integrates ancient Israelite traditions with a rich theology of exile.</p>
      <p>Wide-ranging in approach and intellectual richness,<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>reads like a stimulating seminar that combines close textual analysis with literary, philosophical, and theological reflection. Following a prologue that delineates conventional scholarly approaches and a detailed verse-by-verse exegesis and translation of the text, LaCocque provides thematic analysis under the headings of myth, psychoanalysis, and deconstruction. All three approaches emphasize flexibility of meaning in the canonical text.<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>insightfully argues that Genesis 11 concludes J’s version of ancient history, in which the human search for immortality always fails: “All monuments to human prowess crumble. … A common stupidity smothers them to death” (13).</p>
      <p>Three epigraphs circumscribe the book’s broader themes. The first, from the late philosopher Paul Ricoeur (LaCocque’s friend and collaborator), identifies the role of myth in combining the innocence and guilt of humanity. The second, from Norman Brown’s<italic>Life against Death</italic>, points out how “pyramids and skyscrapers” represent a “flight from death.” The third, from Jacques Derrida, characterizes the Tower of Babel as “an incompletion, the impossibility of finishing, of totalizing” (v). Taken together, these three reflections affirm an understanding of the Babel story as a timeless “symbol of all our constructions and fabrications, with their inexorable outcome: confusion (of our life messages) and scattering (of all the pieces of our projects)” (21). They also provide a model for LaCocque’s own scholarly practice, which is distinctively rigorous yet exploratory at the same time. If, for example, Genesis 11 dates from the exile, it then becomes possible to depict it as a mythic critique of architectural fetishism and political ambition. The “gate of the divine” (Bab-El) thus becomes a dangerous threshold from profane to sacred, one in which the desire to “make a name” reflects an arrogance doomed to confuse all names. As myth, Genesis 11 captures enduring tendencies in human psychology such as infants’ fascination with presence and absence (“fort” and “da”) and the politics of empire.</p>
      <p>The Babel narrative warns against the human desire to stand at the center of things, but with “the ambivalence of the<italic>pharmakon</italic>,” it also provides the basis for a new model of the universe in Gen. 12: the divine-human relationship with Israel (111). With Abraham and his descendents, the true “people of the name” (Gen. 6:4), God’s name will be made great (12:2), and the folly of the tower will be replaced by the covenant.</p>
      <p>This observation reveals some divergence between the biblical answer to Babel and the more universal discussion of LaCocque’s analysis. The critique of Babel’s hubris leads to the covenant of Genesis 12, the “great exception, the miraculous ‘otherness’ that is both judgment and relief for ‘all the families of the earth’” (100). But questions remain. For J, the answer to the loss of innocence in Eden and Babel is the covenant, but in LaCocque’s reading, the text affirms rather the indeterminacy and perennial suspicion of structure more characteristic of postmodern thinkers. In his reading, the tower claims a presence, but “deconstructionism shows the absence of such absolute presence” (154). Such a reading is justified in part by the fact that “authorial intent never exhausts the text’s meanings” (93). While there may be little to regret over the deterioration of Babel’s collapse, the same kind of deconstructive move could be made against the theology of J. The understated theologies of J and LaCocque run suggestively through<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>, but much more could be said about them and how they are related.</p>
      <p>Historical realities, from the ziggurats of Babylon to the sixth-century exile, inform LaCocque’s study, but his real interest lies in the literary ingenuity of J, a “composer” who inherits a wide range of traditions. How these traditions are handed down is always difficult to establish, a point LaCocque makes with understated eloquence: “Literary themes are floating around, ready to be used by anyone” (15). The difficulty is establishing not only how ancient authors came upon these themes, but also how later readers variously interpret them. LaCocque’s own detailed analysis of the text, ranging across the methodological spectrum of biblical and literary studies, makes his readings cogent and compelling.</p>
      <p>
         <italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>successfully concludes an innovative study of primeval myth in J’s Genesis. Its argument about exilic authorship serves as a springboard for a free and erudite exploration of biblical concerns with name, exile, and the paradoxes of divine-human relations. Very few biblical scholars today can compass this range of biblical, literary, and philosophical literature with such finesse. At a time when biblical studies incorporate a wider range of methods than ever, LaCocque, like Roland Barthes (whom he cites), powerfully combines traditional and more contemporary intellectual paradigms. Advanced students and scholars will find in<italic>The Captivity of Innocence</italic>a far-reaching and engaging reading of Genesis 11 by a virtuoso of biblical studies.</p>
   </body>
</article>
