<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">comparatist</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013777</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Comparatist</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01957678</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15590887</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26237234</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>ESSAYS</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>RE-ORIENTALISM: GERMAN INDOLOGY STUDIES BEYOND FOUCAULT AND GADAMER</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Introduction</article-title>
            <subtitle>New Models for Indo-German Scholarship Within the Critical Reappraisal of Orientalism</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>COWAN</surname>
                  <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Kingsborough Community College of the City University of New York</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>MAY 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26237226</issue-id>
         <fpage>47</fpage>
         <lpage>62</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2010 Southern Comparative Literature Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26237234"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy M. The Exotic: A Decadent Quest. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jenkins, Jennifer. “German Orientalism: Introduction,” Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa, and the Middle East 24.2 (2004): 97–100.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchand, Suzanne L. German Orientalism in the Age of Empire: Religion, Race, and Scholarship. German Historical Institute. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pollock, Sheldon. “Deep Orientalism?: Notes on Sanskrit and Power Beyond the Raj.” Orientalism and the Postcolonial Predicament: Perspectives on South Asia. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1993. 76–133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>SELECT BIBLIOGRAPHY OF SCHOLARSHIP ON GERMAN INDOLOGY, 1950–2010</title>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allen, Charles. The Search for the Buddha: The Men Who Discovered India’s Lost Religion. New York: Carroll and Graf, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aronson, Alex. Europe Looks at India: A Study in Cultural Relations. Calcutta: Riddhi-India, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arvidsson, Stefan. Aryan Idols: Indo-European Mythology as Ideology and Science. Trans. Sonia Wichmann. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Behler, Ernst. “Das Indienbild der deutschen Romantik.” Germanisch-Romanische Monatsschrift 1 (1968): 21–37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benes, Tuska. In Babel’s Shadow: Language, Philology, and the Nation in Nineteenth-Century Germany. Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berman, Antoine. L’épreuve de l’étranger: culture et traduction dans l’Allemagne romantique: Herder, Goethe, Schlegel, Novalis, Humboldt, Schleiermacher, Hölderlin. Paris: Gallimard, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berman, Russell A. Enlightenment or Empire: Colonial Discourse in German Culture. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bernal, Martin. Black Athena: The Afroasiatic Roots of Classical Civilization. Volume I: The Fabrication of Ancient Greece, 1785–1985. Newark: Rutgers University Press, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhatawadekar, Sai. “Rewriting Indian Thought: Hegel’s and Schopenhauer’s Interpretations of Indian Philosophy and Religion.” “Mapping Channels between Ganges and Rhine: German-Indian Cross-Cultural Relations.” Interdisciplinary conference. University of Toronto, 25–26 May 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhatawadekar, Sai.. “Three-fold Conceptual Structure of Hegel and Schopenhauer’s Interpretation of Hindu Religious Philosophy.” “Theory, Faith, Culture: An International Interdisciplinary Conference.” Cardiff University. 4–6 July 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhatti, Anil, and Horst Turk, eds. Kulturelle Identität. Deutsch-indische Kulturkontakte in Literatur, Religion und Politik. Berlin: Erich Schmidt Verlag, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhatti, Anil. Reisen, Entdeckungen, Utopien. Jahrbuch für Internationale Germanistik, Reihe A, Kongressberichte, Bd. 48. Bern: Peter Lang, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonfiglio, Thomas Paul. “Toward a Genealogy of Aryan Morality: Nietzsche and Jacolliot.” New Nietzsche Studies. 6.1–2 and 7.1–2 (Fall 2005 and Spring 2006): 170–84.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Breckenridge, Carol A. and Peter van der Veer. Orientalism and the Postcolonial Predicament: Perspectives on South Asia. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bryant, Edwin. The Quest for the Origins of Vedic Culture: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate. New York: Oxford University Press, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bryant, Edwin F. and Laurie L. Patton, eds. The Indo-Aryan Controversy: Evidence and Inference in Indian History. New York: Routledge, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cannon, Garland and Kevin Brine, eds. Objects of Enquiry: Life, Contributions and Influence of Sir William Jones (1746–1794). New York: New York University Press, 1995.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chaudhuri, Nirad. Scholar Extraordinary: The Life of Professor the Rt. Hon. Friedrich Max Muller. London: Chatto and Windus, 1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Childe, V. Gordon. The Aryans: A Study of Indo-European Origins. New York: Dorset, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clarke, J. J. Oriental Enlightenment: The Encounter Between Asian and Western Thought. London: Routledge, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cowan, Robert. “Fear of Infinity: Friedrich Schlegel’s Indictment of Indian Philosophy in Über die Sprache und die Weisheit der Indier.” The German Quarterly 81.3 (Summer 2008): 322–38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cowan, Robert. The Indo-German Identification: Reconciling South Asian Origins and European Destinies, 1765–1885. Rochester: Camden House, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cowan, Robert. “Nietzsche’s Attempted Escape from Schopenhauer’s South Asian Sources in The Birth of Tragedy.” German Studies Review 30.3 (October 2007): 537–56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dahlquist, Allan. Megasthenes and Indian Religion: A Study in Motives and Types. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1962.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dalrymple, William. “The Case for India.” The New York Review of Books 53,3 (2006): 29–30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dalrymple, William. “India: The War Over History.” The New York Review of Books 52.6 (2005): 62–65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dann, Otto. Nation und Nationalismus in Deutschland, 1770–1990. München: C. H. Beck, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Droit, Roger-Pol. Le culte du néant: les philosophes et le Bouddha. Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Erdosy, George, ed. The Indo-Aryans of Ancient South Asia: Language, Material Culture and Ethnicity. Berlin and New York: de Gruyter, 1995.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy Matilda. Aryans, Jews, Brahmins: Theorizing Authority through Myths of Identity. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy Matilda. The Exotic: A Decadent Quest. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy Matilda. Translating the Orient: The Reception of Sakuntala in Nineteenth-Century Europe. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Friedrichsmeyer, Sara, Sara Lennox, and Susanne Zantop, eds. The Imperialist Imagination: German Colonialism and Its Legacy. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gérard, Réne. L’Orient et la pensée romantique allemande. Paris: Marcel Didier, 1963.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germana, Nicholas A. “The Beauty of Enervation: Woman, India, and the Anxiety of System in Hegel’s Philosophy.” German Studies Review, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germana, Nicholas A.. “German Diligence and German Profundity: The Institutionalization of Sanskrit Studies in Prussian Universities, 1818–1830.” Mapping Channels between Ganges and Rhein. Eds. Joerg Esleben, Christina Kraenzle, and Sukanya Kulkarni. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2008. 14–28.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germana, Nicholas A.. “Herder’s India: The ‘Morgenland’ in Mythology and Anthropology.” Anthropology of the Enlightenment. Eds. Larry Wolff and Paul Cipolloni. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2007. 119–37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germana, Nicholas A.. The Orient of Europe: The Mythical Image of India and Competing Images of German National Identity. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glasenapp, Helmut V. Das Indienbild deutscher Denker. Stüttgart: K. F. Koehler, 1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goodrich-Clarke, Nicholas. Hitler’s Priestess: Savitri Devi, the Hindu-Aryan Myth, and Neo-Nazism. New York: New York University Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goodrich-Clarke. The Occult Roots of Nazism: Secret Aryan Cults and Their Influence on Nazi Ideology: The Ariosophists of Austria and Germany, 1890–1935. New York: New York University Press, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Halbfass, Wilhelm. India and Europe: An Essay in Understanding. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Halbfass, Wilhelm. Indien und Europa: Perspektiven ihrer geistigen Begegnung. Basel: Schwabe, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hawley, Daniel S. “L’Inde de Voltaire.” Studies on Voltaire and the Eighteenth Century. Vol. 120. Ed. Theodore Besterman. Oxfordshire: Therpe Mandeville (1974) 139–78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. “Epilinguistic Hypophecy: August Wilhelm Schlegel’s Latin Bhagavadgita.” Epilanguages: Beyond Idioms and Languages. Ed. Pascale Hummel. Paris: Philologicum, forthcoming, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. “The Problem of Action in the Early German Interpretation of the Bhagavadgītā.” Mapping Channels between the Ganges and the Rhine. Eds. Joerg Esleben, Christina Kraenzle, and Sukanya Kulkarni. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2008. 82–106.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. The German Gītā: Hermeneutics and Discipline in the German Reception of Indian Thought, 1778–1831. Studies in Philosophy Series, ed. Robert Bernasconi. New York: Routledge, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hulin, Michel. Hegel et l’Orient. Paris: J. Vrin, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hulin, Michel. “Nietzsche and the Suffering of the Indian Ascetic.” Nietzsche and Asian Thought. Ed. Graham Parkes. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991. 64–75.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inden, Ronald. Imagining India. Cambridge: Oxford University Press, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Irwin, Robert. For Lust of Knowing: The Orientalists and their Enemies. London: Allen Lane, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaiwar, Vasnat and Sucheta Muzumdar, eds. Antinomies of Modernity: Essays on Race, Orient, Nation. Durham: Duke University Press, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Keay, John. India Discovered: The Achievement of the British Raj. New York: Harper Collins, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kirfel, Willibald. “Shiva und Dionysos.” Zeitschrift für Ethnolgie 78 (1953): 83–90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kontje, Todd. German Orientalisms. Ann Arbor: University Michigan Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lefkowitz, Mary R. and Guy MacLean Rogers, eds. Black Athena Revisited. Chapel Hill: University North Carolina Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leifer, Walter. Indien un die Deutschen: 500 Jahr Begegnung und Partnerschaft. Tübingen: Horst Erdmann Verlag, 1969.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lincoln, Bruce. Discourse and the Construction of Society. Oxford: Oxford University Press 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lincoln, Bruce. Theorizing Myth: Narrative, Ideology, and Scholarship. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Macfie, A. L. Orientalism: A Reader. New York: New York University Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maczynska, Magdalena. Die Völkerwanderung: Geschichte einer ruhelosen Epoche im 4. und 5. Jahrhundert. Zurich: Artemis &amp; Winkler, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Manjapra, Kris. M.N. Roy: Marxism and Colonial Cosmopolitanism, New Dehli: Routledge India, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Manjapra, Kris. “The Illusions of Encounter: Muslim ‘Minds’ and Hindu Revolutionaries in First World War Germany and After.” Journal of Global History 1.3 (November 2006): 363–82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchand, Suzanne L. Down from Olympus: Archaeology and Philhellenism in Germany, 1750–1970. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchand, Suzanne L. German Orientalism in the Age of Empire: Race, Religion, and Scholarship.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref70">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">German Historical Institute. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref71">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. Indology, Indomania, Orientalism: Ancient India’s Rebirth in Modern Germany. Madison: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref72">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “‘Into the Centre of Sanskrit Study’: Ancient Indian Studies and German Culture in Berlin and Leipzig in the Nineteenth Century.” Sanskrit and “Orientalism”: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 197–29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref73">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai, eds. Sanskrit and “Orientalism”: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref74">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “Wayward Disciples: Indology and Buddhism in fin-de-siècle Germany.” Sanskrit and “Orientalism”: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 307–36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref75">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “The Whitney-Müller Conflict and Indo-German Connections.” Mapping Channels Between Ganges and Rhein: German-Indian Cross-Cultural Relations. Eds. Jörg Esleben, Christina Kraenzle, and Sukanya Kulkarni. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2008. 29–50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref76">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “Wilting Florists: The Turbulent Early Decades of the Société Asiatique, 1822–1860.” Journal of the History of Ideas 64 (2004): 565–80.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref77">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McKay, Alex. Tibet and the British Raj: The Frontier Cadre, 1904–1947. Surrey: Curzon, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref78">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mishra, Pankaj. “A Cautionary Tale for Americans.” The New York Review of Books 52.9 (26 May 2005): 8–11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref79">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mistry, Freny. Nietzsche and Buddhism: Prolegomena to a Comparative Study. Berlin: De Gruyter, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref80">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mitter, Partha. Much Maligned Monsters: The History of European Reactions to Indian Art. Oxford: Clarendon, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref81">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morrison, Robert G. Nietzsche and Buddhism: A Study in Nihilism and Ironic Affinities. New York: Oxford University Press 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref82">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Murti, Kamakshi P. India: The Seductive and Seduced “Other” of German Orientalism. London: Greenwood, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref83">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Myers, Perry. “Colonial Consciousness: Rudolf Steiner’s Orientalism and German Cultural Identity,” Journal of European Studies 36.4 (2006): 389–417.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref84">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Myers, Perry. “Monistic Visions and Colonial Consciousness: Ernst Haeckel’s Indische Reisebriefe,” Seminar 44.2 (2008): 190–209.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref85">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nicholls, Moira. “The Influences of Eastern Thought on Schopenhauer’s Doctrine of the Thing-in-Itself.” The Cambridge Companion to Schopenhauer. Ed. Christopher Janaway. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999. 171–212.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref86">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nussbaum, Martha C. “Nietzsche, Schopenhauer, and Dionysus.” The Cambridge Companion to Schopenhauer. Ed. Christopher Janaway. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999. 344–74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref87">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Olender, Maurice. The Languages of Paradise: Race, Religion, and Philology in the Nineteenth Century. Arthur Goldhammer, trans. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref88">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oppenberg, Ursula. Quellenstudien zu Friedrich Schlegels Übersetzungen aus dem Sanskrit. Marburg: N. G. Elwert, 1965.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref89">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Orsucci, Andrea. “Ariani, indogermani, stirpi mediterranee: aspetti del dibattito sulle razze europee (1870–1914).” Cromohs 3 (1998): 1–9.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref90">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Park, Peter K. J. “A Catholic Apologist in a Pantheistic World: New Approaches to Friedrich Schlegel.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958 Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and D.R. SarDesai. New Dehli: Manohar, 2004. 83–106.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref91">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Poliakov, Léon. Le mythe aryen: essai sur les sources du racisme et des nationalismes. Paris: Calmann-Lévy, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref92">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pollock, Sheldon. “Deep Orientalism?: Notes on Sanskrit and Power Beyond the Raj.” Orientalism and the Postcolonial Predicament: Perspectives on South Asia. Eds. Carol A. Breckenridge and Peter van der Veer. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1993. 76–133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref93">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Prakash, Gyan “Orienalism Now.” History and Theory 34.3 (Oct. 1995): 199–212. Blackwell for Wesleyan U. http://www.jstor.org/stable/2505621. Accessed 09/05/2008 16:21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref94">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Preisendanz, Karin, ed. Expanding and Merging Horizons: Contributions to South Asian and Cross-Cultural Studies in Commemoration of Wilhelm Halbfass. Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref95">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rajan, Gita and Radhika Mohanram, eds. Postcolonial Discourse and Changing Cultural Contexts. Westport: Greenwood Press, 1995.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref96">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rice, James P. “In the Wake of Orientalism.” Comparative Literature Studies 37.2 (2000): 223–38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref97">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robault-Feuerhahn, Pascale. L’archive des origins: Sanskrit, philologie, anthropologie dans l’Allemagne du XIX siècle. Paris: Éditions du CERF, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref98">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Römer, Ruth. Sprachwissenschaft und Rassenideologie in Deutschland. Munich: Wilhelm Fink Verlag, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref99">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rothermund, Dietman. The German Intellectual Quest for India. New Delhi: Publisher, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref100">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rubiés, Joan-Pau. Travel and Ethnology in the Renaissance: South India through European Eyes, 1250–1625. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref101">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Said, Edward W. Orientalism. New York: Random House, 1978.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref102">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Said, Edward W. The World, the Text, and the Critic. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref103">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sarkar, Sumit. Beyond Nationalist Frames: Postmodernism, Hindu Fundamentalism, History. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref104">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schwab, Raymond. La renaissance orientale. Paris: Payot, 1950.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref105">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schwab, Raymond. The Oriental Renaissance: Europe’s rediscovery of India and the East, 1680–1880. Trans. Gene Patterson-Black and Victor Reinking. Foreword by Edward Said. New York: Columbia University Press, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref106">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sengupta, Indra. From Salon to Discipline: State, University and Indology in Germany, 1821–1914. Heidelberg: Ergon Verlag, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref107">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shapiro, Fred R. “On the Origin of the Term ‘Indo-Germanic.’” Historiographia Linguistica: International Journal for the History of Linguistics 8:1 (1981): 165–70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref108">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, David. “Nietzsche’s Hinduism, Nietzsche’s India.” Journal of Nietzsche Studies 28 (Autumn 2004): 37–56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref109">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty. A Critique of Postcolonial Reason: Toward a History of the Vanishing Present. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref110">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty. The Post-Colonial Critic: Interviews, Strategies, Dialogues. New York: Routledge, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref111">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stambaugh, Joan. Nietzsche’s Thought of the Eternal Return. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref112">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stemmrich-Köhler, Barbara. Zur Funktion der orientalischen Poesie bei Goethe, Herder, Hegel: Exotische Klassik und ästetische Systematik in den »Noten und Abhandlungen zu besserem Verständnis des West-östlichen Divans« Goethes, in Frührschriften Herder und in Hegels Vorlesungen zue Ästetik. Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref113">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Teltscher, Kate. India Inscribed: European and British Writing on India, 1600–1800. New Delhi: Oxford University Press, 1995.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref114">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thapar, Romila. Early India: From the Origins to AD 1300. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref115">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thapar, Romila. History and Beyond. New Dehli, Oxford University Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref116">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thapar, Romila. Sakuntala: Texts, Readings, Histories. New Dehli: Kali for Women, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref117">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thapar, Romila, Jonathan Mark Kenoyer, Madhav M. Deshpande, and Shreen Ratnagar. India: Historical Beginnings and the Concept of the Aryan. New Dehli: National Book Trust, India, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref118">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trautmann, Thomas R. Aryans and British India. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref119">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trautmann, Thomas R. The Aryan Debate. New Dehli: Oxford University Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref120">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tzoref-Ashkenazi, Chen. “India and the Identity of Europe: The Case of Friedrich Schlegel.” Journal of the History of Ideas 67.4 (Oct. 2006): 713–34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref121">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tzoref-Ashkenazi. “The Nationalist Aspect of Friedrich Schlegel’s On the Language and the Wisdom of the Indians.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Dehli: Manohar, 2004. 107–30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref122">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williamson, George S. The Longing for Myth in Germany: Religion and Aesthetic Culture from Romanticism to Nietzsche. Chicago: University Chicago Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref123">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Willson, A. Leslie. A Mythical Image: The Ideal of India in German Romanticism. Durham: Duke University Press, 1964.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref124">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zantop, Susanne. Colonial Fantasies: Conquest, Family, and Nation in Precolonial Germany, 1770–1870. Durham: Duke University Press, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref125">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ziolkowski, Theodore. German Romanticism and Its Institutions. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
