<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">worldpolitics</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100410</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>World Politics</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00438871</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">10863338</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">2010039</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Political Culture and Political Symbolism: Toward a Theoretical Synthesis</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Lowell</given-names>
                  <surname>Dittmer</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>7</month>
            <year>1977</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>29</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>i308701</issue-id>
         <fpage>552</fpage>
         <lpage>583</lpage>
         <page-range>552-583</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1977 Princeton University Press</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2010039"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The concept of political culture embraces some of the most basic, perennially fascinating concerns in behavioral political science; because of certain ambiguities in its theoretical formulation, however, there has been a tendency for the term to grow fuzzy with continued use. Its connection with related concepts, such as political psychology, political structure, and political language, has remained unclear, with the result that political culture has been difficult to isolate as an independent variable. Thus it has come to occupy a position on the periphery of politics, and is usually presumed to reinforce the status quo. This paper re-examines previous formulations of the concept and proposes a theoretical synthesis. The analytical framework is derived from semiological theory, a branch of science specifically designed for the analysis of meanings. The central variable is the political symbol. By analyzing the interactions of political symbols within a comprehensive semiological framework, the traditional concerns of political culture can be accommodated in a more precise and systematic way.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
