<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24709687</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>CHRISTIAN PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY. A REFORMATION PERSPECTIVE</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Gerrit</given-names>
                  <surname>Glas</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2010</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>75</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24709683</issue-id>
         <fpage>141</fpage>
         <lpage>189</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Centre for Reformational Philosophy</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24709687"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1647e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e114" publication-type="other">
This text appeared in Dutch as a chapter in Van Woudenberg (1996). The author thanks
J.N. Kraay for his conscientious translation of the chapter. Although my thoughts — for
instance with respect to the I-self relationship and its importance for both philosophy of mind
and the philosophy of psychiatry and neuroscience — have developed over time, I have made
only few textual improvements and additions compared to the original text. Some newer
literature is added as far as it pertains to the original text.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e137a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e144" publication-type="other">
For the scope and depth of this theme, see Charles Taylor (1989; 1991). For a social
psychological and constructivist account, see Gergen (1991).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e154a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e161" publication-type="other">
This retardation theory, developed by the Dutch biologist Louis Bolk (1866-1930), is now
considered obsolete. Developmental psychologists and neurobiologists do not consider the
baby as passive recipient, but have found that the baby already at birth possesses a refined
motor repertoire and advanced sensory skills. By way of its specific bio-psychical equipment it
models and initiates the mother-child interaction from the start. See for instance Stern (1985).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e180a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e187" publication-type="other">
One of the best introductions still is van Peursen (1956/1966).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e195a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e202" publication-type="other">
See Murphy (1998), (2006) and Murphy and Brown (2007) for a defense of this position
from a Christian point of view.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e212a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e219" publication-type="other">
For clear introductions, see Glover (1988), Cassam (1994), and for the hermeneutic
tradition Ricoeur (1992).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e229a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e236" publication-type="other">
Psychological and philosophical behaviourism has tried to turn the solipsistic need into a
virtue by saying that behaviours and verbal utterances that refer to the inner self are mistakenly
understood to refer to an imperceptible, immaterial reality somewhere within the human
being; there is no ghost in the machine (the body). The entire tradition that bases itself on
introspective data should be transformed into a theory of publicly observable behaviour such as
verbal utterances and motor expressions. We customarily attribute to the inner self something
that in fact is a certain way of organization of behaviour that can be perceived by the senses.
Classic for this approach — in philosophy — is Gilbert Ryle's The concept of mind. (1949). The
phrase 'ghost in the machine' is Ryle's. However, the complete rejection of a subjective, intro-
spectively knowable inner self still betrays dependence on the Cartesian way of questioning:
behaviourism maintains without restriction the Cartesian gap between subject (consciousness)
and object (empirically observable reality). Efforts are made to close the gap by reducing this
subjectivism as much as possible to the intersubjectively (public) and (hence) objectively ob-
servable. It should be noted though that with the rise of cognitive psychology — prepared as it
is to accept mental representations and schemes — hard-core behaviourism is clearly in retreat.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e287a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e294" publication-type="other">
Precisely this transformation of the concrete I into a theoretical I was the reason for philo-
sophers like Kant and Husserl to distinguish, next to the empirical I, a transcendental I. These
thinkers do not consider the 'theorization' of the I as a shortcoming; rather, it expresses some-
thing very essential: the transcendental I (ego) becomes the condition for knowing. The fact
that I (empirical subject) can think thoughts (object) is possible only on the presupposition of
a transcendental I as the necessary condition for the synthesis of the subjective and the
objective moment in (self-)knowledge. This transcendental ego has a purely formal status, no
empirical content at all.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e323a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e330" publication-type="other">
Ouweneel (1986) was the first to write a systematic treatise on man from a reformational
philosophical perspective. After an extensive summary and apology for Dooyeweerd's concep-
tion Ouweneel offers his own elaboration of the process of disclosure in human development
(Chapter 3) and proposes to distinguish a perceptive substructure next to the sensitive substruc-
ture (see below).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e349a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e356" publication-type="other">
This article is referred to as 'Theses' in the main text. The Theses were later published in
students' periodical Sola Fide 1954, 8-18. We will use a translation by John Vander Stelt (with
minor corrections of the translator).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e370a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e377" publication-type="other">
In an interview Dooyeweerd offers as reason for not publishing the second part that the
"traditional-scholastic current... suddenly lost its footing in the theological department at the
Free University [Amsterdam]."(Van Dunné 1976, 54) This may have been one reason why the
third part did not appear either. For his anthropology, too, dualism is Dooyeweerd's major
discussion partner, and this dualism rests on a 'scholastic' arrangement of independent sub-
structures in man. Actually, a typescript of important sections of the third part survived (Ouwe-
neel 1986, 17-20). The author had the opportunity to consult a 160-page translation prepared
by the Dooyeweerd Centre, Ancaster (Canada). The first part deals with philosophy of nature,
and overlaps Dooyeweerd's (1950) article on the concept of substance. The second part,
concerning anthropology, contains extensive confrontation with Gehlen, Scheler, and others,
together with an elaboration of Dooyeweerd's insights regarding the substructures, especially
the act structure. It also contains reflections on the issue of evolution, on the body as form-
totality, on the difference between man and animal, and on the supra-temporal heart.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e422a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e429" publication-type="other">
At issue here is the principle of sphere sovereignty. When Dooyeweerd draws attention to
the relative autonomy of the parts with respect to the whole by saying that the former conform
to their own structural principle, he is trying to do justice to the principle of sphere sovereignty
in the theory of entitary (or thing) structures. Examples of enkapsis are the relation between
living organisms and their environment, and the relation between matrimony and the state.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e448a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e455" publication-type="other">
This addition is important, because meanwhile we know how greatly the regulation of
breathing, heartbeat and transpiration is influenced by learning processes, emotions and
concentrated attention. Research in the 1960s indicated that directing attention inwards
increases the heartbeat, while directing the attention outside oneself results in a lower pulse.
Very well known is Pavlov's experiment at the beginning of the previous century, in which he
succeeded to stimulate salivating in dogs by association of stimuli; after a number of successive
food offerings in combination with an auditory stimulus (a bell), it proved sufficient that the
bell sounded for the dog to salivate. The interlacement of the biotic (salivating) and the
psychical (learning processes) substructures, then, is very strong.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e487a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e494" publication-type="other">
The term 'animal' appears in NC II, 114 (note): Ί have argued that the act-structure of
inner human experience is founded in a lower structure qualified by feeling-drives in which
the psychical aspect has not yet opened its anticipatory spheres.... This animal structure is
bound by the higher act-structure of human experience' (italics mine). Nevertheless, it should
be clear that Dooyeweerd here points to the psychical substructure in the narrower sense, apart
from the typically human disclosure of this structure through anticipating subject-object
relations.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e520a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e527" publication-type="other">
This way of phrasing allows Dooyeweerd (NCII, 113) to distance himself from both beha-
viourism and psychologies that base themselves purely on inner subjective states ('Erlebnisse').</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e537a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e544" publication-type="other">
For an attempt to elaborate upon (and correct) Dooyeweerd's view on emotion, see Glas
(1989).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e555a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e562" publication-type="other">
This is an elaboration of an idea underlying Dooyeweerd's entire theory of individuality
structures, i.e. the idea that many sciences, including biology and psychology, invariably tend
to absolutize their function concept. The modal (functional) perspective is time and again
exchanged for an (ontic) perspective in terms of entities, Dooyeweerd says. Functions are seen
as quasi-entities having a life of their own. The inevitable consequence is that the coherence of
functions becomes a problem. This ultimately results in either dualism (two functions made
independent and placed over against each other) or some kind of monism (reduction of
functions to just one).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e591a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e598" publication-type="other">
For the sake of brevity I pass by the functioning of the brain within the physical
substructure.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e608a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e615" publication-type="other">
The phenomenon of plasticity, currently an item in neuroscience, cannot considered
separate from the fact that in humans the biotic anticipates object functions in higher
lawspheres.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e628a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e635" publication-type="other">
Ouweneel (1986, 202-206) speaks of activated internal object functions of a biotic animal
structure (perceptive), a biotic mamal structure (sensitive), and a biotic human structure
(spiritive). The distinction internal-external concerning object functions has to do with being
part or not being part of the enkaptic structural whole. Activation of the aesthetic object
function of the bird's song does not proceed from the bird itself; it depends on the human
(and is therefore external). In a singing human person this disclosure is internal. The terms
'perceptive' and 'sensitive' point to a distinction in the psychical: Ouweneel holds that elemen-
tary instances of awareness (perceptions) should be distinguished from feelings, tendencies
and desires (the sensitive) (see IV.3.c). Ouweneel's term 'spiritive' points to what Dooyeweerd
calls act structure.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e670a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e677" publication-type="other">
Note that Dooyeweerd introduces still another element in the discussion, namely, that in
human act life the soul (or heart) is operative as well. I leave this for now in order to under-
score again the point at issue, that is, that the brain — and thus actually every organ of the
human body — functions equally in each of the four substructures.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e693a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e700" publication-type="other">
An example may help to illustrate this point. The scientist who investigates the neuro-
hormonal regulation of mood should ask whether this inquiry concerns mostly the area of the
biotic substructure, for example in the case of molecular-biological study of receptor changes;
or whether the inquiry is in the area of the psychical substructure, for example in the case of
various types of mood changes due to (pharmacological) manipulation at receptor level. In the
first case the mood regulation comes into (anticipatory) view as psychical object function
within the biotic substructure. In the second case we are dealing with a biotic subject function
within the psychical substructure (or as biotic object in the psychical modal function). The
problem in this sort of research is that the two perspectives alternate, and so easily lead to a
short-circuit. Mood changes are then causally attributed to neuronal processes. In terms of
Dooyeweerd's system this attribution implies a double short-circuit: modal and in terms of
entities. The principle of (modal) sphere sovereignty does not allow causality between functio-
nal modes (it does allow coherence). The idea of foundational enkapsis allows no causality
between substructures. It does allow coherence and integration within a structural whole. Com-
pare Glas (1991, Chapter 6) and Glas (2001, Chapter 4).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e752a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e759" publication-type="other">
This is not to say that these thought-experiments are complete nonsense. In a humorous
address, published later, Dennett (1981, 310-323) shows that it is possible, unavoidable even, to
raise certain moral and juridical issues in a physicalist framework of thinking.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e772a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e779" publication-type="other">
For a thorough and accurate exposition and defence, see Ouweneel (1986, Chapters 5,
6). For a critique see Steen (1983). In his opposition Steen uses Dooyeweerd's own conceptual
tools to point to traces of the nature-grace motive in Dooyeweerd's thought.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e792a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e799" publication-type="other">
The expression innate impulse' is derived from Dooyeweerd's definition of religion in
NC I, 57: "the innate impulse of human selfhood to direct itself toward the true or toward a
pretended absolute Origin of all temporal diversity of meaning, which it finds focused con-
centrically in itself."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e815a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e822" publication-type="other">
In more contemporary idiom this is the central point in Hart's (1984, 279, 318) reflec-
tion on man as well. The spirit is not something extra, above or outside the body, it is neither
more nor less than the whole of corporeality viewed in terms of origin and destination of man
and world. The unity of the human being is the expression of this dynamism in human
development.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e841a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e848" publication-type="other">
Thesis XVII: "The anima rationalis invariably proves to be the product of a theoretical
abstraction from the full, temporal (hence corporeal) existence of humans, and this abstrac-
tion is subsequently understood as referring to a substance that is essentially independent of
the material body."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e864a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e871" publication-type="other">
Thesis XVI: "Aristotle's definitive conception of the anima rationalis as the 'body in
action' clearly shows that Aristotle must have held thinking and willing to be conscious perfor-
mances on the part of the anima rationalis. He could not consistently develop this important
insight however, because the Greek form-matter theme demanded that at least the general
principle of thinking (as rational form principle) be understood as a substance (ousia) wholly
independent of the 'material body'. Because of this Aristotle could only conceive of the faculty
of receptive human thought (thought as dunamis) as part of the human soul, but not the actual
thinking activity (nous poietikos), understood to be the 'form of the body'." Compare Glas
(1992).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e904a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e913" publication-type="other">
This is why Dooyeweerd calls the heart (in the philosophical sense) an idea. The distinc-
tion between concept and idea derives from Kant. In Kant ideas have a regulative significance.
They have no empirical content, but have a formative effect in the process of acquiring know-
ledge. The ideas direct scientific knowing to that which lies on the other side of the knowing
consciousness: the essentially unknowable reality of the 'Ding-an-sich'. Dooyeweerd gives this
interpretation of the (transcendental) ideas a religious twist, that is, he views the ideas as
necessary religious presuppositions for knowing.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e939a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e946" publication-type="other">
Examples of this are: van der Hoeven (1963); Mekkes (1965), (1971), (1973); Zuidema
(1948; 1972). This latter work contains essays on Kierkegaard, Jaspers, Dewey, Heidegger,
Merleau-Ponty, Blondel, Marcel, Ricoeur, Barth and Bultmann.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e959a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e966" publication-type="other">
For an important (Neo-Thomist) defense of mind-body dualism, see Moreland and Rae
(2000).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e976a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e983" publication-type="other">
The argument counter to these two interpretations (time as comprehensive framework;
time as necessary condition) is that thought would be able to encompass the effective drive of
reality c.q. history. Human thinking cannot however link up in such ways with that which is
outside of reality c.q. history. Both of these are ultimately determined by the triad God-law-
cosmos, that is to say, by the human response to the command of creation, love and respon-
sibility. This response is historical. See Volienhoven (1992a), especially the scheme on page
184; and Vollenhoven (1992b).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1009a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1016" publication-type="other">
At issue here is Dooyeweerd's cosmology as anthropocentric. Apparently, Vollenhoven
accords a less central place to humans in the whole of creation than Dooyeweerd. Actually,
Dooyeweerd, other than Vollenhoven tends to suggest, would not deny that the soul is subject
to law. The supra-temporal sphere as such, too, is subject to law. For Dooyeweerd supra-
temporality is not supra-crealional and eternity is created eternity (aevum). Vollenhoven is correct
however in saying that in Dooyeweerd's thought the entire temporal reality is focused on the
Origin of meaning via the supra-temporal heart.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1042a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1049" publication-type="other">
The term function (al) cloak' is probably derived from Paul's term 'earthly tent' in 2 Cor.
5:1-4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1060a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1067" publication-type="other">
The first 'determination' is the 'such-so' distinction (which is modal), the second
determination' is the 'this-that' distinction (entitary). See Vollenhoven (1967, 22ff, 53ff).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1077a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1084" publication-type="other">
Regarding this struggle and the communications with Janse, see Stellingwerff (1992, 60-
65).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1094a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1103" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd does indeed speak of actual transcending of cosmic time. In the well-known
note in NC I, 31-32, in reaction to the Divergentierapport I' written by Vollenhoven and
circulating among board members of the Association for Calvinistic Philosophy, he writes:
" (...) Some seek the concentration-point of human existence in time and suppose, that this
religious centre must certainly be pre-functional but not supra-temporal. But, at least within
the horizon of cosmic time we have no single experience of something 'pre-functional', i.e.
of anything that would transcend the modal diversity of the aspects. We gain this
experience only in the religious concentration of the radix of our existence upon the
absolute Origin. In this concentration we transcend cosmic time. How could man direct
himself toward eternal things, if eternity were not 'set in his heart'? Even the idolatrous
absolutizing of the temporal cannot be explained from the temporal horizon of human
existence. For the latter nowhere provides a point of contact for an idea of the absolute,
unless it be related apriori to the supra-temporal. This act of concentration presupposes a
supra-temporal starting-point in our consciousness.
This, however, is not to say that the religious centre of human existence is found in a rigid
and static immobility. That is a metaphysical-Greek idea of supra-temporality."
Reading this passage we should realize that Dooyeweerd's notion of time refers to cosmic time,
which is related to modal diversity (and coherence) rather than transience. This is the reason
why Dooyeweerd cannot but say that the unity of existence can only be grasped by
transcending temporal diversity. So, we can conclude that the difference between Dooyeweerd
and Vollenhoven with respect to the supra-temporality of the heart depends on different views
on time and the cosmic time order. Vollenhoven's rejection of the notion of cosmic time order
and his exclusion of numerical and spatial modal qualifications from the notion of time-order
'would even spell a regress in face of the view of Kant' and also in the face of the mathe-
matician Hamilton and of the intuitionist school in mathematics, according to Dooyeweerd
(NC I, 31-32, note 1). For a discussion of the 'Divergentierapport', see Toi and Bril (1992, 107-
11).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1192a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1199" publication-type="other">
See Popma (1963), especially the chapters on illness and sin, and aging and old age, and
Popma (1962, 75ff) on brainwashing.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1209a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1216" publication-type="other">
Popma wrote no less than three books on this topic and in his other writings, too, the
theme often returns (see Popma 1945, 1965, 1972). See also 'Het onaantastbare in ons' in
Popma (1963, 291-311). Popma was a theologian. He wrote in essay style, tending to improvisa-
tion. He often meditated extensively on biblical passages. His writings are characteristically
spirited and refiexively philosophical.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1235a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1242" publication-type="other">
Regarding this Biblical teaching consider for example texts such as "Truly, truly, I say to
you, he who believes has eternal life" (John 6:47), also 6:40 and 6:54, and "And this is eternal
life, that they know thee the only true God..." (John 17:3).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1256a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1263" publication-type="other">
Precision is important here. Popma's formulation is that transcending coincides with
placing oneself 'over against' the creatural, whereby this opposing-oneself-to-the-creatural is
identified with the opposition characteristic of the theoretical attitude of thought. In
Dooyeweerd there is still another link in the chain: religious self-knowledge, c.q. transcending
the cosmic order of time, is not as such theoretical; rather, it is the condition that makes the
'over against' in theorizing possible. Dooyeweerd distinguishes the supra-temporal 'above' (tran-
scendence, religious self-knowledge) and the temporal 'over against' typical of the Gegenstand
relation. In Popma 'above' and 'over against' more or less coincide.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1292a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1299" publication-type="other">
Starting point here is what Jesus tells Martha at the death of Lazarus: 'He who believes in
me, though he die, yet shall he live' (John 11:25). The inviolable of human being is the faith in
this Christ, the Christ who commanded Lazarus to return from death. This faith is inviolable to
the extent that not only illness, decay, violence and betrayal have no power over it; it is
unassailable even in death and at the Last Judgment.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1318a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1327" publication-type="other">
The passage refers to the church, but can easily be applied to human beings. To be
church, Popma seems to say, is never quite attainable in this life. Sin and imperfection make a
caricature of the church as God intended it. The church's being-not-of-this-world is often
unjustifiably identified with its being-in-the-world. However, Popma (1965, 253) says "To the
degree that the congregation lets its 'not-of-this-worldness' be submerged in 'being-in-the
world', to the degree that the church concretely historicizes itself, it exists by grace of a myth...
and lives in a mythical time." The myth, then, consists in this: that the church identifies its
'being-from-heaven' with its historical form. To be sure, the church needs organization, yet it
"must with equal insistence deny its organizational form. Its sole possibility is to exist in
Widerspruch (contradiction)." Whatever one may think of this passage — marked by Popma's
own experience in the ecclesiastical battles of the 1940s and 1960s — we do recognize
something here that is far less prominent in Dooyeweerd and Vollenhoven, namely, a vital
awareness of the discord and brokenness of human existence.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1372a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1379" publication-type="other">
Others who should be mentioned are Schoep (1948) and Van Dijk (1965) concerning
neurosis.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1389a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1396" publication-type="other">
For example, see NC I, 55: "[God] has expressed His image in man by concentrating its
entire temporal existence in the radical religious unity of an ego in which the totality of
meaning of the temporal cosmos was to be focused upon its Origin."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1409a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1416" publication-type="other">
Later, Geertsema (1992, 130) repeated this criticism and on that occasion spoke of an
"unjustified metabasis eis alio genos" that is, an impermissible linkage of biblical teaching and
philosophical problems.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1430a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1437" publication-type="other">
See also the passage in Thesis V: "This revelation concerning the 'soul' of human
existence as integral centre of the whole of corporeality, is entirely correlate with the Self-Revelation
of God as integral Creator of heaven and earth, who has no autonomous power against Him."
This idea of correlation should however be sharply distinguished from the idea of analogia enlis
(analogy between the being of God and the being of creation). Dooyeweerd firmly rejects the
analogia entis.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1460a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1467" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd remained faithful to Abraham Kuyper (1898/1943, 20) here, specifically to
the well-known, almost infamous passage from the Lectures on Calvinism·.
"Hence the first claim demands that such a life system shall find its starting-point in a
special interpretation of our relation to God. This is not accidental, but imperative. If such
an action is to put its stamp upon our entire life, it must start from that point in our
consciousness in which our life is still undivided and lies comprehended in its unity, — not
in the spreading vines but in the root from which the vines spring. This point, of course, lies
in the antithesis between all that is finite in our human life and the infinite that lies beyond
it. Here alone we find the common source from which the different streams of our human
life spring and separate themselves. Personally it is our repeated experience that in the
depths of our hearts, at the point where we disclose ourselves to the Eternal One, all the
rays of our life converge as in one focus, and there alone regain that harmony which we so
often and so painfully lose in the stress of daily duty."
Wiskerke (1978, 75ff.) called this semi-mystical view 'the heart condition' of the philosophy of
the cosmonomic idea (see also the interesting notes on pp. 259ff). Kuyper's statement in the
Stone Lectures is in part based on his interpretation of Ecclesiastes 3:11 ('[God] has put
eternity into man's mind'):
"That age is the world of the Eternal, from which time, and with time all the finite, was
born.... The age that lets you leap over the boundaries of the finite and envelops you in the
ocean of the heavenly and Divine... that awakens your faith as a wholly other, wholly
independent faculty of thought and reveals you to yourself as a wholly other, far richer and
brilliant being than the world ever allowed you to see in its mirror." (De Héraut 1781, 18-2-
1912; cited in Dutch by Wiskerke 1978, 79).
Wiskerke suggests that this semi-mysticism evinces some affinity with thinkers such as Clemens
of Alexandria, Origines and particularly Gregory of Nyssa. According to Gregory, through
relinquishing the passions and by displaying some of the divine model and ultimately through
self-concentration, the soul attains a kind of ex lasts in which a human being 'in itself possesses
God. Wiskerke admits that, to be sure, Kuyper was a world conqueror rather than a hermit.
The parallel goes halfway only; Kuyper's is a.«mi-mysticism. "The inner-core experience, then,
is starting-point rather than conclusion; it urges clarification in reflection and application in
practice" (Wiskerke 1978,84).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1569a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1576" publication-type="other">
The background of this is the dilemma between substantialism (starting out from the
primacy of substance over relation) versus funnlionalism (where function or relation is primary
over substance). According to Dooyeweerd there is a third, Berkouwer says, namely that "the
relation does not in the least threaten, dim or dissolve reality; rather, it makes it possible to
understand the nature of this reality in its relatedness to God." In other words, if some hold
that a relational view of man does not adequately portray the 'reality', i.e., the ontic status of
being-human, they betray that they are still enslaved to a view in which substances are too
much seen as self-sufficient. But if relations and substances should not be played out over
against each other, the implication is that the supra-temporal heart, too, exists in a 'relational-
ontic' sense. It is not surprising therefore that Blosser interprets Berkouwer's comment as a
plea for a mitigated substance-thinking, in other words, as a thinking that admits the existence
of substances, though without ascribing self-sufficiency to them. See Blosser (1993, 205-08) and
Evans (1993).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1621a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1628" publication-type="other">
See Bruggeman-Kruijff (1981, 156): the broken versus the one and undivided. Also Van
Woudenberg (1992, 171-176).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1638a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1645" publication-type="other">
In the pertinent passage Dooyeweerd's view of the I as a transcendental concentration
point is contrasted with Kierkegaard's comment on the I (or self). Kierkegaard calls the self "a
relation which relates to itself, and in relating to itself relates to something else." This 'some-
thing else' is a power, namely: God. See Kierkegaard (1849, 43) and Glas (1995a, 74-76).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1661a1310">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1668" publication-type="other">
Cooper does not stand alone, as is clear from a statement by Alvin Plantinga in an inter-
view in Beweging 59 (1995), 11. Plantinga states that he has two objections to Dooyeweerd's
philosophy: the rejection of the body-soul dualism and the transcendental framework of his
philosophy. For a dualistic approach see also Swinburne (1987).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1685a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1692" publication-type="other">
One also could apply the rejection of the notion of extinction to the body. Paul calls the
body a seed sown in the field to be raised on the First Day (I Cor. 15: 35-49). As I see it, this
Scriptural thought has been insufficiently reckoned with in Christian anthropology. Actually,
rejection of the notion of extinction can no longer be used to argue for a dualism of body and
soul.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1711a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1718" publication-type="other">
One could ask whether the soul's being subject to death does not imply an element of
discontinuity as well. Cooper stresses the continued, personal existence of the soul. The Bible
however speaks of death as a mortification of sin and that, surely, implies a profound change.
In death personal identity remains, 1 stay my-self, yet become wholly different from what I was
prior to my death.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1737a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1746" publication-type="other">
Cooper (1989, 221) also comments on indications in Scripture that persons continue life
after death with a visible form of corporeality: the appearances of Samuel, Moses and Elijah.
With great reservation Cooper tends towards the view that these were visible manifestations of
energy, probably comparable to the ether-body in spiritism (and anthroposophy). Popma, who
also places great emphasis on the soul's continued temporal life after death, is more cautious
but he does refer to a continuation of the temporal function-cloak in some other, unknown
form. For Cooper this thought is an argument in favour of dualism (in view of the difference
between this energy-body and the ordinary earthly body). In Popma the idea of the
continuation of the function-cloak is meant as anti-dualistic argument.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1778a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1785" publication-type="other">
Especially in connection with this 'before and after death' questions can be raised. Does
the soul emerge from the process of dying unchanged? I suggested that, considering the no-
longer-in-sin after death, this is unlikely. There is continuity and discontinuity. The question is
whether the discontinuity is so great that it threatens the identity of the soul as non-material
substance. Cooper would not go this far, because he seems to identify personal identity with the
existence of the soul. Such identification is questionable however, not only because in this way
the personal character of corporeality becomes a problem (the personification of the body is
then secondary since it is achieved only in the joining of the corporeal and the spiritual), it is
also questionable because human personhood ultimately is and remains a secret — a mysteiy
that permits no identification with whatever substance.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1820a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1827" publication-type="other">
In the passage at issue Cooper quotes Dooyeweerd via the English translation of Ber-
kouwer (1957). Berkouwer in turn quoted Dooyeweerd's (1940, 181) article on the problem of
time, which does contain the passage about the human soul which "naar het getuigenis van de
Schrift door den tijdelijlten dood niet getroffen wordt, maar ook na de aflegging van het
"lichaam", d.i. van heel den tijdelijken in individualiteits-structuur besloten beslaansvorm, blijft
voortbestaan." But the translation is incorrect! The translators of Berkouwer's book rendered
the passage as follows: "The soul. Scripture shows, is not affected by temporal death, but after
the end of the body (i.e. of all the temporal aspects of man), it continues as a form of existence
with an individuality structure" (Cooper 1989, 251). The Dutch text, Berkouwer (1957, 285,
note 148), quotes Dooyeweerd correctly. In Dooyeweerd the term 'individuality structure'
refers to the body; the translators related it, wrongly, to the soul. It is likely that this has
occasioned Cooper's misunderstanding. The passage should read: "As Scripture testifies, [the
human soul] is not touched by temporal death, but continues to exist even after the shedding
of the 'body', i.e. [the shedding] of the entire temporal, individuality-structure-enclosed form of
existence."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1878a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1885" publication-type="other">
In Cooper's interpretation of Dooyeweerd two further errors are present. Cooper (1989,
250) says that Dooyeweerd's "notion of the ego allows the supranatural to shape the temporal
but not the reverse." Dooyeweerd however speaks of both divergence and concentration.
Cooper also states that in Dooyeweerd the basic directions of thinking, imagining and willing
are rooted in the heart, not in the temporal act structure. The passage at issue deals with the
functioning of the soul after death. Cooper holds that such rootedness of the basic directions
in the heart allows us to argue that the basic directions can also function outside the earthly
(i.e. temporal) modes. Apart from the fact that for Dooyeweerd the supra-temporal belongs to
the creatural (earthly) order, Cooper neglects that Dooyeweerd strongly denied the idea of an
incorporeal personal centre: acts and basic directions are inconceivable without involvement of
the temporal function cloak, c.q. the act structure.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1924a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1931" publication-type="other">
This question was posed by Bruggeman-Kruijff (1981) as well.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1938a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1945" publication-type="other">
Wiskerke (1978) pointed at this in the chapter on the semimystical heart conception of
Kuyper; see also Wiskerke (1963, 224).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1955a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1962" publication-type="other">
The contributions to the congress were published in Philosophia Reformata 1992 and 1993.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1969a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1976" publication-type="other">
Stafleu (1991, 130) says: "It would be utterly wrong to relate the religious character of
humanity exclusively to questions of destiny, unity and origin." The religious nature of human
beings is given with their place in the cosmos, in the normative position relative to the realms
of the plants and the animals, and relative to the history of culture.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e1992a1310">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e1999" publication-type="other">
Stafleu adds two substructures: a spatial and a kinematic substructure. Arguments in sup-
port of this are found in Stafleu (1985), (1989, Chapters 3-5). Moreover, he amends Dooye-
weerd in connection with the interlacement of substructures through additional distinctions
between possible founding functions. The kinematic substructure splits into two, a substruc-
ture with a numerical founding function and a substructure with a spatial founding function;
the physical substructure thus consists in three substructures, the biotic in four and the
psychical in five. Together with the single spatial structure this means a total of fifteen sub-
structures. Stafleu here neglects the figure of the founding enkapsis·. in Dooyeweerd the under-
lying substructure as individuality structure, rather than the foundational modality, is the
foundation for higher substructures, see NC III, 653-661 and Ouweneel (1986, 191).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2034a1310">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2041" publication-type="other">
'Emergence' is meant in the sense that in the course of evolution structures sponta-
neously developed that, compared to existing structures, are conceptually or ontically of a
qualitatively different order. Within the continuity of the evolution process, then, something
new emerges. Stafleu is no evolutionist in the sense that evolution theory is his worldview; he
does adhere to the theory of evolution. As he sees it, systematic reformational philosophy has
concerned itself far too little with the issue of evolution. Stafleu holds that evolution is often
mistakenly taken to mean that the emergence of new structures, biotic structures for example,
can be explained via the laws for existing structures, in other words, by physical-chemical laws.
Approached in this way, the irreducibility of the modal aspects is at issue (the classical
objection from the side of reformational philosophy). The problem however dissolves entirely
as long as law and that which is subjected to it are not mixed. The laws for new structures are
not themselves a product of evolution; they become operational once the situation is ready for
them.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2087a1310">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2094" publication-type="other">
A well-known example of this is one of the paradoxes of Zeno, who argued that Achilles
can never overtake the turtle if the latter is allowed to start out first. When Achilles has covered
the distance that the turtle had at point a the turtle has moved on, and when Achilles has
covered that distance as well, the turtle has moved up too, etc. The paradox dissolves as soon as
it is recognized that the spatial analysis (distances) is not enough to study the phenomenon of
speed. Speed is a kinematic category. When the spatial aspect is not related to time (as in the
kinematic aspect) speed difference is a phenomenon that cannot be grasped.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2120a1310">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2127" publication-type="other">
In human beings in a vegetative condition the cerebral cortex and important parts of the
limbic system are switched off. The brainstem (and basic nuclei) however are intact. These
patients are in permanent coma, and are unconscious, although they can as a rule breathe and
swallow without mechanical help. In other words, these coma patients have an intact 'reptilian
brain', but do not function in the perceptive sense.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2146a1310">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2153" publication-type="other">
Over the past decades it has been established that the so-called orientation reaction is
strongly influenced by these 'sensitively' determined processes. Contra Ouweneel (1986, 108-
109).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2166a1310">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2173" publication-type="other">
In the theory of the enkaptic structural whole Dengerink sees too many remnants of the
old Aristotelian hierarchv of functions.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1647e2183a1310">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1647e2190" publication-type="other">
Because they escape precise modal qualification, Troost suggests that insight into disposi-
tions can only be gained in an idea-ruled (idee-matig) understanding, in an idea-regulated 'on
the way' in the transcendental direction of time. For reformational philosophy this raises an
old and prima facie purely theoretical problem: Do the modalities 'continue' right into the
heart? One could paraphrase Troost's view for example such that for him the heart should
primarily be sought 'below' or 'behind' the act structure, and that the dispositions — relative
to this vertical axis — constitute a horizontal layer in which the lower substructures are
interwoven with the act structure. In that case the integration of the lower structures in the act
structure would take place via the dispositions rather than through a direct relationship with
the heart. This notion — for which hints can be found in Dooyeweerd — would in any case
lead to an appreciably more nuanced picture of the 'binding' and 'releasing' of substructures.
If I understand Troost correctly, he would allow this interpretation for the substructures,
though not for the modalities. His caution concerning the 'continuing' of the modalities 'into
the' heart is epistemological: the cosmological concentration of the modal functions in the
heart is a transcendental idea; at best we see dots (the idea-regulated 'on the way' in the
transcendental direction of time), but we should not turn them into lines.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d1647e2253a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2257" publication-type="other">
Berkouwer, G.C. (1957), De mens het beeld Gods, Kampen: Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2264a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2268" publication-type="other">
Blosser, P. (1993), 'Reconnoitering Dooyeweerd's theory of man', Phibsophb
Reformata58,192-209.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2278a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2282" publication-type="other">
Brtiggeman-Kruijff, A.Th. (1981), 'Tijd als omsluiting, tijd als ontsluiting',
Phibsophia Reformata 46, 119-163.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2296" publication-type="other">
Buller, D.J. (2006), Adapting minds. Evolutbnary psychology and the persistent quest
for human nature, Cambridge, MA/London: MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2307a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2311" publication-type="other">
Carew, T.J., Walters, E.T. and Kandel, E.R. (1981), 'Associative learning in
Aplysia: Cellular correlates supporting a conditioned fear hypothesis',
Science 211, 501-504.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2324a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2328" publication-type="other">
Cassam, Q. (Ed.) (1994), Self-knowledge [Oxford Readings in Philosophy],
Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2338a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2342" publication-type="other">
Cooper, J.W. (1982), 'Dualism and the biblical view of human beings I &amp; II',
Reformedfoumal, September, 13-16; October, 16-18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2352a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2356" publication-type="other">
Cooper, W. (1989), Body, Soul, and Life Everlasting. Biblical Anthropobgy and the
Monism-Dualism Debate, Grand Rapids: W.B. Eerdmans Publishing
Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2369a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2373" publication-type="other">
Dengerink, J.D. (1986), De ζ in van de werkelijkheid. Een wijsgerige benadenng,
Amsterdam: VU-Uitgeverij.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2383a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2387" publication-type="other">
Dennett, D.C. (1981), Brainstorms. Phibsophical Essays on Mind and Psychobgy,
Brighton (Sussex) : Harvester Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2398a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2402" publication-type="other">
Dennett, D.C. (1991), ConscwusnessExpbined, Boston: Litde, Brown &amp; Comp.,</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2413" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1940), 'Het tijdsprobleem in de wijsbegeerte der wetsidee',
Phibsophia Reformata, 5, 160-182, 193-234.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2423a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2427" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1942), 'De leer van de mens in de wijsbegeerte der wetsidee',
Correspondentiebladen van de Vereniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte 7, 134-44.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2437a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2441" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1950), 'Het substantiebegrip in de moderne natuurfilosofie
en de theorie van het enkaptisch structuurgeheel', Phibsophb Reformata 15,
66-139.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2454a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2458" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1953-1958), A New Critique of Theoretical Thought (NQ, Volume
I-IV, Amsterdam:Paris / Philadelphia: Presbyterian and Reformed
Publishing Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2471a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2475" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1960a), 'Van Peursen's critische vragen bij Ά New Critique
of Theoretical Thought", Phibsophia Reformata 25, 97-150.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2486a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2490" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1960b), In the Twilight of Western Thought, Philadelphia:
Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2500a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2504" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1961) 'De taak ener wijsgerige anthropologie en de
doodlopende wegen tot wijsgerige zelfkennis', Phibsophb Reformata 26, 35-
58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2517a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2521" publication-type="other">
Evans, C.S. (1993), 'Human persons as substantial achievers', Phibsophb
Reformab 58, 100-112.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2531a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2535" publication-type="other">
Geertsema, H.G. (1970), 'Transcendentale openheid', Phibsophia Reformata 35,
25-56 and 132-155.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2545a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2549" publication-type="other">
Geertsema, H.G. (1992), Het menselijk karakter van cms kennen, Amsterdam:
Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2559a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2563" publication-type="other">
Gehlen, Α. (1988), Man. His nature and place in the world, New York: Columbia
University Press (translation of Der Mensch: seine Natur und seine Stellung in
der Welt, Bonn: Athenâum-Verlag, 4' verbesserte Auflage, 1950).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2577a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2581" publication-type="other">
Gergen, K. (1991), The saturated self. Dilemmas of identity in contemporary life, New
York: Basic Book.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2591a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2595" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1989), 'Emotie als struktuur-probleem. Een onderzoek aan de hand
van Dooyeweerds leer van het enkaptisch struktuurgeheel', Philosophia
Reformata 54, 29-43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2608a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2612" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1991), Concepten van angst en angststoornissen. Een psychiatrische en
vakfilosofische studie, Lisse/Amsterdam: Swets &amp; Zeidinger.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2622a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2626" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1992), 'Hierarchy and dualism in Aristotelian psychology', Philosophia
Reformata 57, 95-116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2636a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2640" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1993), Ontheemd-zijn, contingentie en zin. Over de mogelijkheid de oorsprongs-
loosheid te den ken, Leiden: Rijksuniversiteit Leiden [inaugural address].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2650a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2654" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1995a), 'Ego, self, and the body', in Christian philosophy at the close of the
twentieth century; Assessment and perspective, edited by S. Griffioen and B.M.
Balk, Kampen: Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2668a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2672" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1995b), 'Lichaam, lichaamsbeeld en lichaamsideaal', Bezveging59, 80-
83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2682a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2686" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (2001), Angst - beleving structuur, macht, Amsterdam: Boom.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2693a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2697" publication-type="other">
Glover, J. (1988), The Philosophy and Psychology of Personal Identity, London:
Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2707a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2711" publication-type="other">
Hart, H. (1984), Understanding our world. An integral ontology, Lanham/New
York/ London: University of America Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2721a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2725" publication-type="other">
Heschel, A.J. (1966), Who is man?, Stanford: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2732a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2736" publication-type="other">
Hofstadter, D.R. and Dennett, D.C. (Eds.) (1981), The mind's I: Fantasies and
Reflections on Mind and Soul, New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2747a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2751" publication-type="other">
Hume, D. (1739-1740), A Treatise of Human Nature, London: Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2758a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2762" publication-type="other">
Janse, A. (1938), Van idolen en schepselen, Kampen: Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2769a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2773" publication-type="other">
Kandel, E.R. (1983), 'From metapsychology to molecular biology: Explorations
into the nature of anxiety', American Journal of Psychiatry 140, 1277-1293</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2783a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2787" publication-type="other">
Kandel, E.R. and Hawkins. R.D. (1992), 'The biological basis of learning and
individuality', Scientific American 267(3), 79-86.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2797a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2801" publication-type="other">
Kierkegaard, S. (1849/1989), The sickness unto death. A Christian psychological
exposition for edification and awakening [translated with an introduction and
notes by A. Hannay], London: Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2814a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2818" publication-type="other">
Kim, J. (1993), Supervenience and Mind. Selected Philosophical Essays, Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2829a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2833" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, J. (1987), 'Reformational philosophy on the boundary between the
past and the future', Philosophia Reformata 52, 101-134.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2843a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2847" publication-type="other">
Kok, J.H. (1992), Vollenhoven. His early development, Sioux Center: Dordt College
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2857a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2861" publication-type="other">
Kristeva, J. (1991), Strangers to ourselves [translation by Leon Roudiez], New
York: Columbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2871a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2875" publication-type="other">
Kuyper, Α., Lectures on Calvinism - The Stone Lectures of 1898, Grand Rapids:
Eerdmans Publishing Company 1943 [also available at the website of the
Kuyper Foundation; see www.kuyper.org].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2888a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2892" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, J.P.A. (1965), Teken en motief der creatuur, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp;
Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2902a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2906" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, J.P.A. (1971), Radix, tijd en kennen, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp;
Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2917a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2921" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, J.P.A. (1973), Tijd der beginning, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2928a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2932" publication-type="other">
Moreland J.P. and Rae S.B. (2000), Body and soul. Human nature and the crisis in
ethics, Downers Grove, Illinois: InterVarsity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2942a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2946" publication-type="other">
Murphy, N. (1998), "Non-reductive physicalism: Philosophical issues", in
Whatever happened to the soul? Sdentific and theological portraits of human nature,
edited by W.S. Brown, N. Murphy and H.N. Malony, Minneapolis: Fortress
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2962a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2966" publication-type="other">
Murphy, N. (2006), Bodies and Souls, or spirited bodies? Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2976a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2980" publication-type="other">
Murphy, N. and W.S. Brown (2007), Made my neurons make me do it? Philosophical
and neurobiological perspectives on moral responsibility and free will, Oxford:
Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e2993a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e2997" publication-type="other">
Ouweneel, W.J. (1986), De leer van de mens. Proeve van een christelijk-wijsgerige
antropologie, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3008a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3012" publication-type="other">
Parfit, D. (1984), Reasons and persons, Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3019a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3023" publication-type="other">
Pinker, S. (2002), The blank slate. The modern denial of human nature, London &amp;
New York: Viking/Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3033a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3037" publication-type="other">
Popma, K.J. (1945), Calvinistischegeschiedenisbeschouwing Franeker: Wever.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3044a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3048" publication-type="other">
Popma, K.J. (1962), Levensbeschouwing. Opmerkingen naar aanleiding van de
Heidelbergse Catechismus, Deel V, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3058a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3062" publication-type="other">
Popma, K.J. (1963), Wijsbegeerte en anthropologe, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipper-
heijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3072a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3076" publication-type="other">
Popma, K.J. (1965), Nadenken over de tijd, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3084a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3088" publication-type="other">
Popma, K.J. (1972), Evangelic en geschiedenis, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp;
Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3098a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3102" publication-type="other">
Popper, K.R. and Eccles,J.C. (1977), The self and its brain, Berlin: Springer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3109a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3113" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. (1992), Oneself as another, Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3120a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3124" publication-type="other">
Rorty, R. (1980), Philosophy and the mirror of nature, Princeton: Princeton
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3134a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3138" publication-type="other">
Ryle, G. (1949), The concept of mind, London: Hutchinson.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3145a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3149" publication-type="other">
Sartre, J.-P. (1966/1936), Transcendence of the ego: an existentialist theory of
consciousness, New York: Noonday Press [translation of La transcendance de
l'ego, Paris: Gallimard].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3163a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3167" publication-type="other">
Schilder, Κ. (1947), Heidelbergsche Catechismus, Deel I, Goes: Oosterbaan &amp; Le
Cointre.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3177a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3181" publication-type="other">
Schoep, G.K. (1948), 'Neurose en religie', Philosophia Reformata 13, 168-186.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3188a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3192" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M.D. (1985), 'Spatial things and kinematic events', Philosophia
Reformata 50, 9-20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3202a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3206" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M.D. (1986), 'Some problems of time - some facts of life', Phihsophia
Reformata 51, 67-82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3216a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3220" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M.D. (1989), De verborgen structuur, Amsterdam: Buijten &amp;
Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3230a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3234" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M.D. (1991), 'On being human in the cosmos', Philosophia Reformata
56,101-131.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3245a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3249" publication-type="other">
Steen, P.J. (1983), The structure of Dooyeweerd's thought, Toronto: Wedge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3260" publication-type="other">
Stellingwerff, J. (1992), D.H.Th. Vollenhoven (1892-1978). Reformater der
wijsbegeerte, Baarn: Ten Have.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3274" publication-type="other">
Stern, D. (1985), The interpersonal life of the infant, New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3281a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3285" publication-type="other">
Swinburne, R. (1987), The evolution of the soul, Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3296" publication-type="other">
Taylor, C. (1989), Sources of the self; The making of the modern identity, Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3306a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3310" publication-type="other">
Taylor, C. (1991), The ethics of authenticity, Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3318a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3322" publication-type="other">
Toi, A. and Bril, K.A (Eds.) (1992), Vollenhoven als wijsgeer. Inleidingen en teksten,
Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3332a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3336" publication-type="other">
Troost, A. (1983), The Christian ethos - A philosophical survey, Bloemfontein:
Patmos.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3346a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3350" publication-type="other">
Troost, A. (1993), 'Disposities. Moment uit een reformatorisch-
antropologische karakterleer en deugdentheorie', Philosophia Reformata 58,
221-236.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3363a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3367" publication-type="other">
Van der Hoeven, J.H. (1963), Kritische ondervraging van de fenomenologische rede,
Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3377a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3381" publication-type="other">
Van Dijk, W.K. (1965), 'Neurosis and religion' in Philosophy and Christianity.
Philosophical essays dedicated to Professor Dr. Herman Dooyeweerd,
Kampen/Amsterdam: J.H. Kok/North-Holland Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3394a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3398" publication-type="other">
Van Dunné, J.M. et al (Eds.) (1976), Acht àvilisten in burger, Zwolle: Tjeenk
Willink.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3413" publication-type="other">
Van Peursen, C.A. (1966), Body, soul, spirit: A survey of the body-mind problem
[translation of Lichaam, ziel, geest. Utrecht: Bijleveld, 1956], Oxford: Oxford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3426a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3430" publication-type="other">
Van Woudenberg, R. (1992), Gelovend denken. Inleiding tot een christelijke filosofie,
Amsterdam/Kampen: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn/Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3440a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3444" publication-type="other">
Van Woudenberg, R. (Ed.) (1996), Kennis en werkelijkheid. Tweede inleiding tot een
christelijke filosofie, Amsterdam/Kampen: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn/Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3454a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3458" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, D.H.Th. (1967), Isagoogè Philosophiae, Amsterdam: Filosofisch
Instituut, Vrije Universiteit.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3468a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3472" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, D.H.Th. (1992a), 'Problemen rondom de tijd' in Vollenhoven als
wijsgeer. Inleidingen en teksten edited by A. Toi and K.A Bril, Amsterdam:
Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3485a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3489" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, D.H.Th. (1992b), 'Problemen van de tijd in onze kring' in Vollen-
hoven als wijsgeer. Inleidingen en teksten, edited by A. Toi and K.A Bril, Amster-
dam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3503a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3507" publication-type="other">
Wilson, E.O. (1975), Sociobiology. A new synthesis, Cambridge, MA: Belknap
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3517a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3521" publication-type="other">
Wiskerke, J.R. (1963), Leven tussen sterven en opstanding Goes: Oosterbaan &amp; Le
Cointre.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3531a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3535" publication-type="other">
Wiskerke, J.R. (1978), De strijd om de sleutel der kennis. Een bundel opstellen over
théologie en filosofie, Groningen: De Vuurbaak.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3545a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3549" publication-type="other">
Zuidema, S.U. (1948), Nacht zonder dageraad. Naar aanleiding van het atheistisch en
nihilistisch existentalisme van Jean-Paul Sartre, Franeker: Wever [inaugural
address].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1647e3562a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1647e3566" publication-type="other">
Zuidema S.U. (1972), Communication and confrontation. A philosophical appraisal
and cntique of modern society and contemporary thought, Assen/Kampen: Van
Gorcum/ Kok.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
