<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.28.3.0315</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.28.3.0315</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Is a Hermeneutic Phenomenology Wide Enough? A Ricoeurian Reply to Janicaud's<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open”</italic>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Davidson</surname>
                  <given-names>Scott</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Oklahoma City University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>7</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">28</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.28.3.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>315</fpage>
         <lpage>326</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.28.3.0315"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>More than fifteen years have now passed since the publication of Dominique Janicaud's book<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open”</italic>; however, many of its central claims still remain unexamined. This article initiates a critical reflection on Janicaud's notion of a minimal phenomenology by way of a contrast with Paul Ricoeur's hermeneutic phenomenology. The article demonstrates that Janicaud's attempt to decouple phenomenology from hermeneutics fails due to his underestimation of their deeper connection. The notion of a minimal phenomenology remains valuable, nonetheless, for opening up some new directions for hermeneutic phenomenology, particularly an engagement with certain insights to be drawn from Deleuze.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>phenomenology</kwd>
            <kwd>hermeneutics</kwd>
            <kwd>Ricoeur</kwd>
            <kwd>Janicaud</kwd>
            <kwd>Deleuze</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>More than fifteen years have now passed since the publication of Dominique Janicaud's book<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open”</italic>(<italic>Phénomenologie Eclatée</italic>)—the sequel to his controversial essay published in<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn.”</italic>
         <xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>1</sup>
         </xref>There, as is widely known, Janicaud raised the question of whether the phenomenological enterprises of figures such as Emmanuel Levinas, Michel Henry, and Jean-Luc Marion were marked by a “theological turn” and, if so, whether such a turn was phenomenologically warranted. At this point, a voluminous literature over this debate exists, much of it defending the accused against those charges.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>Perhaps as an indirect result of that focus, there has been relatively little discussion of Janicaud's later development of a “minimal phenomenology.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>To correct this state of affairs, the broad aim of this article is to redirect attention to Janicaud's minimal phenomenology and to show how it opens up new possibilities for phenomenological reflection today.</p>
      <p>In<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open,”</italic>Janicaud gets his starting point by noting two competing tendencies within Husserlian phenomenology: first, there is Husserl's “metaphysical” effort to establish phenomenology as a first philosophy; second, there are his patient descriptions leading to the development of various regional ontologies. The former tendency—or what might be called a maximal phenomenology—is the one that inspires the proponents of the theological turn who regard phenomenology as the only conceivable path for metaphysics today. Janicaud, by contrast, develops his notion of a minimal phenomenology in line with the other tendency in Husserl's work. This marks a twofold shift of approach. Terminologically, it means eschewing the pretenses to reach the absolute, to be scientific, and to become a foundation of the new metaphysics. A minimal phenomenology speaks more modestly in terms of testing hypotheses within a larger project, seeking out the morphology of a set of appearances, or dealing with something in its uniqueness. Methodologically, minimal phenomenology follows the lead of Merleau-Ponty and goes directly to the phenomena without a detour through the phenomenological reduction, which is part and parcel of phenomenology's foundational impulses.</p>
      <p>Janicaud, to be sure, is not the first to question the metaphysical ambitions of Husserlian phenomenology. Such criticisms, in fact, have a lineage that goes all the way back to the early reception of Husserl by hermeneutically minded thinkers such as Heidegger and Ricoeur.<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>This naturally prompts a question concerning the relation between Janicaud's minimal phenomenology and hermeneutic phenomenology. Put simply, is a minimal phenomenology hermeneutical, and conversely, is a hermeneutic phenomenology “wide open” enough for a minimal phenomenology?<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>5</sup>
         </xref>This article will take up this question in the context of chapter 4 of Janicaud's book—entitled “Articulations/Disarticulations”—where he sets out to distance himself from hermeneutic phenomenology. Though this purported distinction will be shown to fail, at the same time this article suggests that Janicaud's project opens up some new and important pathways for future research in phenomenology and hermeneutics.</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>Articulations/Disarticulations</title>
         <p>In chapter 4 of<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open,”</italic>Janicaud sets out to examine the delicate balance to be maintained between phenomenology and hermeneutics “in the junctions and disjunctions, the crossings and divergences between them.”<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>Hermeneutic phenomenology, on his view, establishes this balance all too smoothly, and so, by way of contrast, he seeks to emphasize the ways in which they are “disjointed rather than jointed.” He observes that the two discourses, for instance, develop out of very different historical origins—the former from German idealism and the latter from questions of biblical interpretation—and they have very different aims.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>Phenomenology seeks a return to the things themselves as they are given in intuition, while hermeneutics (at least in its traditional construal) is directed toward written words that are encoded in texts. On the basis of these and other disjunctions, Janicaud suspects that the establishment of a hermeneutical phenomenology is much more problematic and perilous than is commonly acknowledged.</p>
         <p>In support of this conjecture, Janicaud takes up Ricoeur's image of the “grafting” of hermeneutics onto phenomenology. This image suggests that their connection is like a patch of skin that covers over a wound that has opened up on the body. By analogy, it would seem that phenomenology opens onto certain limit experiences that stand beyond the limits of what is given in intuition. It is at that point that hermeneutics enters the scene and takes up the task of covering over this opening. But what motivates this desire to graft these two separate discourses together in the first place? Why should one try to form them into a cohesive, unified whole? Janicaud suspects that this is the result of a subtle attempt to reinscribe the ontotheological structure of traditional (think Kantian) metaphysics. On such a view, phenomenology would take the place traditionally held by ontology, while hermeneutics would take over the traditional role of theology.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>The fundamental problem here, for Janicaud, is that this paints an all too hierarchical, neat, and unified picture of the relation between these two projects—a picture that is based on deep assumptions about a unified meaning that would undergird them.<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>It is plain to see that, in making this move, Janicaud is trying to align hermeneutic phenomenology with the theological turn of phenomenology whose ontotheological underpinnings were identified in his earlier work. But the question remains: Is this critique of hermeneutic phenomenology truly accurate? It is indeed the case that Ricoeur employs the image of the “graft” to characterize the relation between phenomenology and hermeneutics, but this only provides a partial account of his understanding of their relation. To be precise, it suggests that they only have a “thin” connection, so to speak, in which one is merely a supplement to the other. Yet, by turning to Ricoeur's essay “Phenomenology and Hermeneutics,” it becomes clear that their connection turns out to be more “thick” than Janicaud ever suspects.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>10</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Ricoeur, like Janicaud, criticizes the Idealistic or “maximal” tendencies of Husserlian phenomenology. He characterizes Husserl's Idealism in terms of the following five theses: (1) It understands its task in foundational terms, as the search for beginnings or first principles; (2) its ultimate principles are established through intuition; (3) its source of full evidence is the immanence of subjectivity; (4) it severs the transcendental subject from the material reality of the empirical ego; (5) it defines the self in terms of autonomy, as a wholly self-responsible ego. Instead of examining each of these targets of Ricoeur's hermeneutical critique, I will briefly highlight the key elements of this critique that anticipate Janicaud's critique of “maximal phenomenology” and then turn to Ricoeur's own hermeneutic appropriation of phenomenology.<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>11</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>First, hermeneutics rejects the scientific ideal of phenomenology. Husserl conceives phenomenology in foundational terms as a first philosophy whose role is to provide a metaphysical grounding or an Archimedean point for scientific knowledge. But hermeneutics challenges the foundational enterprise altogether.<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>12</sup>
            </xref>The search for foundations, on this view, is forgetful of its own origins within a more encompassing context of relations. Thought can never establish itself at the beginning or end point; instead it is always situated in medias res, that is, in the midst of a conversation or dialogue that has already begun.</p>
         <p>Hermeneutics, moreover, challenges the central role that Husserl ascribes to intuition, especially in his early works. The call to return to the things themselves is heeded by a return to what is given in intuition. But, as Ricoeur puts it, “the Husserlian demand for the return to intuition is countered by the necessity for all understanding to be mediated by an interpretation.”<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>13</sup>
            </xref>In support of this claim, Ricoeur draws inspiration from Heidegger's conception of the as-structure of being, which maintains that being is always revealed in a partial manner, as this or as that.<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>14</sup>
            </xref>This as-structure suggests that nothing is ever directly or fully given, and for this reason, what is given always calls for a process of interpretation enabling it to be seen as this or that. If it is the case that all givenness is perspectival and partial, Ricoeur contends that phenomenology “cannot constitute itself without a<italic>hermeneutical presupposition</italic>. The hermeneutical condition of phenomenology is linked to the role of<italic>Auslegung</italic>in the fulfillment of its philosophical project.”<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>15</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>This suggestion about the vital role of interpretation in phenomenology, as Ricoeur notes, is not foreign to Husserl's own work, either. For Husserl himself employs a method of explication (<italic>Auslegung</italic>) of what is given to intuition in order to elucidate its deeper or hidden meanings.<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>16</sup>
            </xref>This indicates that hermeneutics is not simply a separate entity that is grafted onto phenomenology and takes up where phenomenology leaves off; instead it is already operative within the phenomenological constitution of meaning. Moreover, their connection is pushed even further when Ricoeur goes on to show later in the same essay that phenomenology, in turn, remains the “unsurpassable presupposition of hermeneutics.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>17</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Although this latter aspect of Ricoeur's argument stands outside the scope of this article, the overall point is already abundantly clear: phenomenology and hermeneutics are not two separate discourses that simply happen to overlap at some point of juncture; instead the two discourses share a deep connection to the extent that each mutually presupposes the other. The mutual implication of phenomenology and hermeneutics, as I will return to later, makes hermeneutic phenomenology a much more natural fit for Janicaud's minimal phenomenology than he ever acknowledges.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>Against the Despot and the Priest: The Deleuzian Opening</title>
         <p>Janicaud's most thought-provoking suggestions arise out of his attempt to challenge hermeneutic phenomenology from the outside and to show that it imposes an illegitimate narrowing of the scope of phenomenological appearing. Here, Janicaud calls on the assistance of Gilles Deleuze, who famously denounces phenomenology and hermeneutics as “the two diseases of the earth, the pair of the despot and priest.”<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>18</sup>
            </xref>Deleuze links phenomenology, on the one hand, to the figure of the despot, in light of its effort to establish the transcendental ego as the source and master of all meaning. Hermeneutics, on the other hand, is linked to the figure of the priest, inasmuch as its search for hidden meanings is suspected to carry the residue of its biblical lineage, with its pursuit of the divine. These two discourses, though separate, suffer in fact from the same underlying disease: the choice for meaning. This choice, for Deleuze, imposes a restriction on their scope, which implies that they are only able to address the aftereffects or residues of a pre-subjective and pre-objective life that they ignore.</p>
         <p>Janicaud readily admits that it would be ridiculous to strive to annex Deleuze to phenomenology “like we add an extension to the family table on Sundays.”<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>19</sup>
            </xref>Nonetheless, he does suggest that some parts of Deleuze's work might be construed, if not as an escape from phenomenology, at least as a move away from its well-worn paths.</p>
         <p>A full inquiry into this topic, to be sure, would exceed the bounds of this project, inasmuch as it would potentially involve a whole series of analyses that would weave Deleuze's insights—into the logic of sense, of sensation, of conscious life, of the body, and so on—together with Husserl's own analyses of related themes. So, even if the question that Janicaud has opened is quite important, here I can provide only the briefest indication of the direction of such analyses, taking the Deleuzian notion of “the aspect” as one example.</p>
         <p>The account of the aspect in Husserlian phenomenology is well known. With his theory of adumbrations, Husserl described how the perceived object is given in a one-sided, partial manner. The perception of its actual profile or aspect is given against the horizon of a set of potential perceptions of its other sides. Together these actual and potential perceptions are unified to form the sense of the thing that is perceived. For Deleuze, though, Husserl's account operates on the level of aftereffects because it does not ever consider the genesis or coming into being of the aspect itself. It is this event—the genesis of the aspect as such—that Deleuze's work brings to the fore. The Deleuzian aspect is separated from every figure and context. Think of it as being like the smile of the Cheshire Cat, which wanders away from the cat's body. This is not simply an imaginary or hallucinatory appearance; instead it indicates the genesis of a sensation prior to the work of figuration or its placement within a context. Every figure or form is a secondary coagulation or solidification of this primary sensation. To the extent that the aspect disarticulates itself from every position or background field, it can rightly be called an in-visible. This is how a minimal phenomenology approaches the invisible. That is, it approaches this minimal threshold of sense—the threshold that gives rise to sensation and conscious experience.</p>
         <p>This example, albeit brief, already provides an important clue about the locus of the connection between Deleuze and phenomenology. For the above contrast could equally be characterized in terms of the difference between a static and a genetic phenomenology. Deleuze's transcendental empiricism, in other words, bears some resemblance to Husserl's description of the passive syntheses (temporality, habit, etc.) that precede and condition the active syntheses performed by intentional acts of consciousness. From this perspective, we can see both thinkers as inquiring into what precedes and gives rise to the meaning-formations established within a static analysis of intentional consciousness. By all accounts, Deleuze was unaware of Husserl's genetic phenomenology. But if he were, one could easily imagine that he would have been more receptive to phenomenology. And likewise, when Husserlians become aware of the new directions developed in Janicaud's minimal phenomenology, my sense is that they too will come to embrace Deleuzian insights as possible extensions of genetic phenomenology.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>The Ricoeurian Reply</title>
         <p>It seems to me that, at this point, Janicaud's argument still remains incomplete. He has suggested that phenomenology can and should be transformed in order to accommodate Deleuzian insights. But why wouldn't hermeneutics be the discourse by which this passage from Deleuze to phenomenology is made? If the worry has to do with Deleuze's suspicions of its priestly residues, why couldn't one perform a transformation of the hermeneutical project similar to Janicaud's transformation of the phenomenological project?<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>20</sup>
            </xref>In light of these questions, I want to construct what I would imagine to be, if not Ricoeur's own view, at least a Ricoeurian reply whose aim is to show that hermeneutics provides the resources needed for carrying out Janicaud's minimal phenomenology.</p>
         <p>First of all, it might come as some surprise—not only for Janicaud but equally for Ricoeur scholars—to note that in a 2003 interview, Ricoeur mentions Deleuze as one of “the two thinkers” whom he “most admired.”<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>21</sup>
            </xref>There is little evidence in Ricoeur's writings that would actually support this claim, since Deleuze is hardly even mentioned by him and is never engaged in any sustained manner. Nonetheless, Ricoeur's remark does suggest that he would embrace the endeavor to bring Deleuze's work into dialogue with phenomenology, though I do not think that he would believe that such a dialogue could take place without the work of hermeneutics.</p>
         <p>A good model for envisioning how a hermeneutic phenomenology would engage Deleuze can be developed by drawing from resources established elsewhere in Ricoeur's thought. What I have in mind, specifically, is his reading of Freud in the book<italic>Freud and Philosophy</italic>.<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>22</sup>
            </xref>There Ricoeur reads Freud's work as “a mixed or even ambiguous discourse, which at times states conflicts of force subject to an energetics, at times relations of meaning subject to a hermeneutics.”<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>23</sup>
            </xref>Freud's energetics, on the one hand, offers a naturalistic account of desire in which it is understood in terms of a cathexis—the placement and displacement of energy. And yet, psychoanalysis continually points back to the work of interpretation in which the psychoanalyst is dealing with conscious representations. The coexistence of these two discourses gives rise to an aporia, which Ricoeur formulates in the following way: “What is the status of representation or ideas in relation to the notions of instinct, aim of instinct and affect? How can an interpretation of meaning through meaning be integrated with an economics of cathexis, withdrawal of cathexis, anticathexis?”<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>24</sup>
            </xref>To solve this aporia, Ricoeur goes on to show that these two discourses in Freud's work are not actually opposed. Instead, as he puts it, “the energetics implies a hermeneutics and the hermeneutics discloses an energetics.”<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>25</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>It seems to me that this provides the basis for a good answer to the question that was posed at the outset of this article, that is: “Is a hermeneutic phenomenology ‘wide open’ enough for a minimal phenomenology?” This is indeed the case. For, just as Freud's mixed discourse means that each discourse points to a discourse outside itself, the same could be said of the relation between Deleuze and phenomenology.<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>26</sup>
            </xref>The key here is to recognize that the nonsignifying or the impersonal is on the way to meaning and on the way to consciousness. And at the same time, phenomenological discourse necessarily points back to a nonsignifying or impersonal reality that precedes and gives rise to it. The role of a hermeneutic phenomenology is to mediate between these two discourses by traveling along this path back and forth between meaning and its becoming, following its composition and decomposition in the movement from sense to non-sense, from the impersonal to the personal, from the formless to form—and back again.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>Conclusions</title>
         <p>There are two results of this discussion to which I want to draw specific attention. First, this article suggests that commentators on Janicaud's minimal phenomenology, though few, have largely misunderstood the significance of this development. They have taken it to diminish the prestige of phenomenology, to the point of turning it into a trivial enterprise that describes banal phenomena.<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>27</sup>
            </xref>This can be traced back to the fact that they set up the issue in terms of a contrast between an ambitious maximal phenomenology that tests the limits of the visible and a minimal phenomenology that roots itself firmly within its boundaries. But Janicaud himself already dispels that contrast: his call for a minimal phenomenology does not advocate for a less ambitious or more restrained vision of phenomenology, as if its motto were to “keep costs down, do as little as possible, take no risks.”<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>28</sup>
            </xref>The alternative is not, as commentators have suggested, between either a phenomenology of the invisible or a phenomenology of the visible; instead it concerns two different possible approaches to a phenomenology of the invisible: one that pushes the limits of the visible through a maximal threshold of excess (Marion, Levinas, Henry) and another that pursues those limits through a minimal threshold of sense (Merleau-Ponty, Deleuze). That is the choice that Janicaud bequeaths to phenomenology today.</p>
         <p>The second result of this article, as I see it, is more speculative in nature, to the extent that it goes a little further than anything that either Ricoeur or Janicaud has explicitly said. Janicaud gives up the metaphysical ambitions of phenomenology to establish itself as a first philosophy, which leads the phenomenologist to be characterized rightly as a despot, or if taking a theological turn, a priest. But if a minimal phenomenology leads in a new direction, then what transformation of the phenomenologist's role would follow? What figure, in other words, would come to characterize the work of the minimal phenomenologist? Drawing from work that I have developed elsewhere, I can think of no better answer to this question than the figure of the translator, or to be even more precise, the code-switcher.<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>29</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>For, if phenomenology renounces its search for the absolute and for foundations, then it must give up seeing itself as a single and self-contained discourse. The minimal phenomenologist renounces monolinguism and is no longer the master of only one discourse. Instead, he or she must practice a mixed discourse. To do this is to practice diglossia, to become a code-switcher. In its ordinary sense, the practice of code-switching refers to the passage from one language or dialect to another one in the course of a single conversation, for instance, when the conversation moves from an informal to a formal setting or when it moves from one topic to another. But in the phenomenological context, this would involve the ability to shift from a phenomenological discourse to its “others,” whether they might be Freudian energetics, Deleuzian aspects, Badiouan events, and so on. This practice of translation or code-switching has perhaps always been the role of the phenomenologist, if it is accepted that phenomenological reflection does not begin from itself but is nourished by a life that precedes it and gives rise to it.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Dominique Janicaud,<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open”: After the French Debate</italic>, trans. Charles N. Cabral (New York: Fordham, 2005). Dominique Janicaud, Jean-François Courtine, Jean-Louis Chrétien, Michel Henry, Jean-Luc Marion, and Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn”: The French Debate</italic>, trans. Bernard G. Prusak (New York: Fordham, 2001).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>This defense begins with essays by the accused that are included in the same book under the heading “Phenomenology and Theology” and continues with countless secondary articles that ensued.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The few examples are Dan Zahavi, “Michel Henry and the Phenomenology of the Invisible,”<italic>Philosophical Review</italic>32 (1999): 232–40; and Brian Harding, “What Is a Minimalist Phenomenology?”<italic>Alea</italic>6 (2008): 10–27; as well as François-David Sebbah,<italic>Testing the Limits</italic>, trans. Stephen Barker (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2012).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See my “Husserl Heretics: Levinas, Ricoeur, and the French Reception of Husserlian Phenomenology,”<italic>Studia Phaenomenologica</italic>13 (2013): 209–30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Note that I have framed this question in keeping with the English translation of the title. However, the question could also be raised over the<italic>éclatement</italic>or shattering of phenomenology, but the conclusion would likely lead in the same direction.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Janicaud,<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open,”</italic>47–48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 48ff.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur's essay, which Domenico Jervolino considers to be about “the very possibility of philosophy to exist today,” is the focus of detailed discussion in chapter 2 of Jervolino's book<italic>The Cogito and Hermeneutics: The Question of the Subject in Ricoeur</italic>, trans. Gordon Poole (Dordrecht: Kluwer, 1990), 87.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For early discussions of Ricoeur's notion of hermeneutic phenomenology, see Don Ihde,<italic>Hermeneutic Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur</italic>(Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1971); David Klemm,<italic>The Hermeneutical Theory of Paul Ricoeur</italic>(Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press, 1983), chap. 3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>To get a sense of what a nonfoundational phenomenology might entail, see James R. Mensch,<italic>Postfoundational Phenomenology: Husserlian Reflections on Presence and Embodiment</italic>(University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press, 2001).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>From Text to Action</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey and John B. Thompson (Evanston: Northwestern University Press, 1991), 31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Martin Heidegger,<italic>Being and Time</italic>, trans. John MacQuarrie and Edward Robinson (New York: Harper, 1962), 188.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r015">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur,<italic>From Text to Action</italic>, 26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r016">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>It is worth noting that Ricoeur establishes this point through studies of Husserl's<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>and later in his<italic>Cartesian Meditations</italic>. However, the more compelling connection might be with Husserl's genetic phenomenology, which includes a greater emphasis on the temporal, developmental, and historical aspects of conscious life. There the break from intuition and turn to an interpretive method are much more decisive.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r017">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur,<italic>From Text to Action</italic>, 26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r018">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gilles Deleuze and Claire Parnet,<italic>Dialogues</italic>, trans. Hugh Tomlinson and Barbara Habberjam (New York: Columbia University Press, 1977), 47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r019">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Janicaud,<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open,”</italic>59.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r020">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Time permitting, here we would need to explore another side of this project that would pass through the deconstructive critique of hermeneutics. This would not leave the task of hermeneutics untouched and might point it in the direction of a lateral (rather than depth) hermeneutics.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r021">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur, “La conviction et la critique,” an interview with Nathalie Crom, Bruno Frappat, and Robert Migliorini, in<italic>Cahier Ricœur</italic>, ed. François Azouvi and Myriam Revault d'Allonnes (Paris: Editions de l'Herne, 2004), 15–18, at 17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r022">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Incidentally, it should be noted that Deleuze and Guattari do refer to Ricoeur's book on Freud in their own writings on psychoanalysis, including Gilles Deleuze and Félix Guattari,<italic>Anti-Oedipus</italic>(Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1983), as well as their discussion of the<italic>cogito</italic>in Gilles Deleuze,<italic>Difference and Repetition</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1995).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r023">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Freud and Philosophy: An Essay of Interpretation</italic>, trans. Denis Savage (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1977), 65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r024">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 66.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r025">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r026">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Along a phenomenological register, one could also point to Claude Romano's hermeneutics of events as a further indication of this direction. His hermeneutic of events stands between two extreme poles of the event: between thinkers such as Badiou, Deleuze, and Rancière, on the one hand, and the phenomenology of the event developed by Jean-Luc Marion, on the other hand. The former group conceptualizes the event as an exception—something that is totally heterogeneous to everything prior—whereas the latter—Marion—considers it to be something that is entirely banal, to the extent that it is contained within every appeal. Romano's hermeneutic approach, in the simplest of terms, tries to span this gap by seeing this as a range of possibilities for the event.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r027">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Here I am referring in particular to Zahavi, “Michel Henry and the Phenomenology of the Invisible”; and Harding, “What Is a Minimalist Phenomenology?”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r028">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Janicaud,<italic>Phenomenology “Wide Open,”</italic>66.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r029">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For instance, see my “Ricoeur's Later Thought: From Hermeneutics to Translation and Back Again,”<italic>Philosophy Today</italic>57, no. 1 (2013): 61–72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
