<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">historytheory</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100176</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>History and Theory</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00182656</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14682303</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24542850</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>REPRESENTATION AS A COGNITIVE INSTRUMENT</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>FRANK</given-names>
                  <surname>ANKERSMIT</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>52</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24542833</issue-id>
         <fpage>171</fpage>
         <lpage>193</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>©2013 Wesleyan University</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24542850"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This essay discusses the role of the notions of reference, truth, and meaning in historical representation. Four major claims will be argued. First, conditional for all meaningful discussion of historical representation is that one radically discards from one's mind the paradigm of the true statement and all the epistemological and ontological problems occasioned by it. Second, representation is not a two-place, but a three-place operator: in representation a represented reality (1) is represented by a representation (2) focusing on certain aspects of represented reality (3). Third, applying the notions of reference, truth, and meaning to historical representations compels us to give them a content basically different from the ones they have in contemporary philosophy of language and science. Fourth, it will be shown that in (historical) representation, meaning precedes truth—and not the other way around as in most of contemporary philosophy of language.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d3195e114a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e121" publication-type="other">
But as we shall find in section VII, this does not in the least imply that no content could be
given to the notion of "representational meaning." In fact, the notion of representational meaning is
conditional for all understanding of (historical) representation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e134a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e141" publication-type="other">
Arthur C. Danto, The Transfiguration of the Commonplace: A Philosophy of Art (Cambridge,
MA: Harvard University Press, 1983), 167.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e151a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e158" publication-type="other">
Max Black, "Metaphor," in Black, Models and Metaphors (Ithaca, NY, and London: Cornell
University Press, 1962), 40; his italics.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e168a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e175" publication-type="other">
This is where historical metaphor differs from all that has been said about metaphor since Black
by, among others, philosophers such as Hesse, Davidson, Rorty, Derrida, or Lakoff and Johnson.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e186a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e193" publication-type="other">
1 deliberately refrain here from saying "the neutrinos as investigated by the physicist." To move
automatically from the former to the latter is the origin of the penchant for idealism in much of con-
temporary history and philosophy of science, for the "as" lifts the neutrino from the level of reality
to that of the scientist's language.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e209a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e216" publication-type="other">
Keith Donnellan, "Proper Names and Identifying Descriptions," in Semantics of Natural Lan-
guage, ed. Donald Davidson and Gilbert Harman (Dordrecht: Reidel 1972), 356-380.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e226a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e233" publication-type="other">
W. V. O. Quine, From a Logical Point of View (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
1961),41.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e243a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e250" publication-type="other">
For a brilliant synopsis of the relevant part of the recent history of philosophy of science, see
John Zammito, A Nice Derangement ofEpistemes: Post-positivism in the Study of Science from Quine
to Latour (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004), 15-52.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e263a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e270" publication-type="other">
As is demanded by the resemblance theory of representation whose history goes back to Plato's
Cratylus.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e280a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e287" publication-type="other">
That is to say, the form of the true statement "x is c|&gt;" invites us to embrace the metaphysical
doctrine that reality is built up of individual objects all having certain properties. Hence, it is a form
of metaphysics drawing its inspiration from what our language happens to look like.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e301a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e308" publication-type="other">
Martin Heidegger, Sein und Zeit (Tübingen: Niemeyer, 2006), 218, 219. "Die Aussage ist
wahr, bedeutet: sie endeckt das Seiende an ihm selbst. Sie sagt aus, sie zeigt auf, sie "lässt sehen"
(ajr£Kf&gt;aoiq) das Seiende in seiner Entdecktheit. Wahrsein (Wahrheit) der Aussage muss verstanden
werden als entdeckend-sein. Wahrheit hat also gar nicht die Struktur einer Übereinstimmung zwi-
schen Erkennen und Gegenstand im Sinne einer Angleichung eines Seienden (Subjekt) an ein anderes
(Objekt)."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e331a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e338" publication-type="other">
Ibid., 218.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e345a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e352" publication-type="other">
The component "-X.f)0éia" is derived from the Greek verb "M|0a&gt;" meaning "being hidden" or
"escape." Heidegger's etymology of the word "aM|0eia" has been disputed. See for this J. D. Caputo,
Demythologizing Heidegger (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1993), 22ff.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e365a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e372" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, Sein und Zeit, 219. "Die Übersetzung [von "aX.f|0eia"] durch das Wort "Wah-
rheit" und erst recht die theoretische Begriffsbestimmungen dieses Ausdrucks verdecken den Sinn
dessen, was die Griechen als vor-philosophisches Verständnis dem terminologischen Gebrauch von
"aW)0£ia "selbstverständlich zugrunde legten."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e388a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e395" publication-type="other">
Quoted in M. H. Abrams, The Mirror and the Lamp: Romantic Theory and the Critical Tra-
dition (New York: Oxford University Press, 1953), 60. No less illustrative is the quote from Yeats
that Abrams chose as his book's epigraph: "it must go further still: that soul must become its own
betrayer, its own deliverer, the one activity, the mirror tum lamp." It is to be regretted that Richard
Rorty—the author of Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature—never pronounced about the preference
of Romanticists for the metaphor of the lamp to that of the mirror, for quite a lot depends on this.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e418a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e425" publication-type="other">
R. W. Southern, "The Historical Experience," Times Literary Supplement (June 2, 1977),
771-774.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e436a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e445" publication-type="other">
Hans-Georg Gadamer, Wahrheit und Methode (Tübingen: Max Niemeyers Verlag, 1972), 259.
"[Die] Romantik... mißt nicht mehr die Vergangenheit mit den Maßstäben der Gegenwart wie an
einem Absoluten, sie spricht vergangene Zeiten einen eigenen Wert zu.... Die großen Leistungen
der Romantik, die Erweckung der Zeitenfrühe, das Vernehmen der Stimme der Völker in Liedern, die
Sammlung der Märchen und der Sagen, die Pflege des alten Brauchtums, die Entdeckung der Spra-
chen als Weltanschauungen, das Studium der "Religion und Weisheit der Inder"—sie alle haben his-
torische Forschung ausgelöst, die langsam, Schritt für Schritt in ahnungsreiche Wiedererweckung in
abständige historische Erkenntnis verwandelte. Der Anschluss der historischen Schule an die Roman-
tik bestätigt damit, daß die romantische Wiederholung des Ursprünglichen selber auf dem Boden
der Aufklärung steht. Die historische Wissenschaft des 19. Jahrhunderts ist ihre stolzeste Frucht und
versteht sich geradezu als die Vollendung der Aufklärung, als den letzen Schritt in der Befreiung des
Geistes von dogmatischer Befangenheit, der Schritt zur objektieven Erkenntnis der geschichtlichen
Welt, die der Erkenntnis der Natur durch die moderne Wissenschaft ebenbürtig zur Seite tritt."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e490a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e497" publication-type="other">
Michael Dummett, Frege: Philosophy of Language (London: Duckworth and Cambridge, MA:
Harvard University Press, 1981). 84.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e507a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e514" publication-type="other">
Ferdinand de Saussure, Course in General Linguistics, transi, and annotated by Roy Harris
(London: Duckworth, 1983), 114.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e524a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e531" publication-type="other">
For a further elucidation and for how the argument in question can be related to Leibniz's
monadology, see my Narrative Logic (The Hague/Boston: Martinus Nijhoff, 1983), 239-241.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e541a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e548" publication-type="other">
Roy Harris, Language, Saussure, and Wirtgenstein: How to Play Games With Words (London
and New York: Routledge, 1988), 23. Observe that in the last sentence of this quote Harris's sug-
gestion is that syntagmatic ordering is a specific case of associative ordering. If this interpretation is
correct, Saussure's model of the two axes should be replaced by that of a set and a subset of that set.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e564a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e571" publication-type="other">
As far as I can see, the only exceptions to this rule are phenomenologists (Paul Ricoeur and
David Carr) and dialecticians (Fredric Jameson). However, what they say about the historical text as
a whole emasculates the text's cognitive powers by tacitly (Ricoeur) or explicitly (Carr, Jameson)
subscribing to Mink's notion of "Universal History" to be discussed in a moment.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e588a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e595" publication-type="other">
Mink's argument about "Universal History" has never been challenged—as far as I know—and
yet I'm convinced that most historians and philosophers of history still believe in it. At least, they
argue as if they do.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e608a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e615" publication-type="other">
"Yet the idea that the past itself is an untold story has retreated from the arena of conscious
belief and controversy to habituate itself as a presupposition in that area of our apriori conceptual
framework which resists explicit statement and examination." See Louis O. Mink, Historical Under-
standing, ed. Brian Fay, Eugene O. Golob, and Richard T. Vann (Ithaca, NY, and London: Cornell
University Press, 1987), 194.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d3195e634a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3195e641" publication-type="other">
What I have described elsewhere as "the Magritte conception of history." See Ankersmit,
Meaning, Truth, and Reference in Historical Representation (Ithaca, NY, and London: Cornell Uni-
versity Press, 2012), 192-196.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
