<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">intelitestud</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Interdisciplinary Literary Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">15248429</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">2161427X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">intelitestud.16.2.0282</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/intelitestud.16.2.0282</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Open Wounds of Being:</article-title>
            <subtitle>The Poetics of Testimony in the Works of Patricia Jabbeh Wesley</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Eze</surname>
                  <given-names>Chielozona</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Northeastern Illinois University</aff>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <bold>
                     <sc>chielozona eze</sc>
                  </bold>studied philosophy and literature at Purdue University. He is associate professor of Anglophone African literature at Northeastern Illinois University, Chicago. He is currently working on a book on African feminism.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>9</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">16</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">intelitestud.16.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>282</fpage>
         <lpage>306</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/intelitestud.16.2.0282"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The poet Patricia Jabbeh Wesley acknowledged in an interview that her primary goal in poetry is to immortalize the suffering of her people. What exactly does she mean by that? What are the implications of remembering suffering, of keeping sorrows alive, especially in narratives? This article explores these questions in light of Primo Levi's envisaged moral obligation to bear testimony to the victims of the Jewish holocaust, as well as Giorgio Agamben's thoughts on that episode. I argue that ethics is central to Jabbeh Wesley's poetics. The poet has a calling: the moral responsibility to bear testimony to the dead and the dispossessed. I will discuss Jabbeh Wesley's poems as both a tribute to the dead and as an appeal to the living to change their lives. To situate my discussions of Jabbeh Wesley and Levi, I will revisit the ethical implications of Aristotle's definition of tragedy.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>literature and ethics</kwd>
            <kwd>poetry and testimony</kwd>
            <kwd>African literature</kwd>
            <kwd>postcolonial discourse</kwd>
            <kwd>empathy</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <disp-quote content-type="epi">
         <p>It is the function of poetry in its narrative and dramatic form, to propose to the imagination and to its mediation various figures that constitute so many thought experiments by which we learn to link together the ethical aspects of human conduct and happiness and misfortune. By means of poetry we learn how reversals and fortune result from this or that conduct, as this is constructed by the plot in the narrative.</p>
         <attrib>—<sc>paul ricoeur</sc>
         </attrib>
      </disp-quote>
      <p>Patricia Jabbeh Wesley is one of the most prolific African poets of the twenty-first century. With four collections of poetry spanning over fifteen years, and having won prestigious awards and garnered rave reviews, she is the most renowned of African women poets. While she is known to many students of African literature, it is a shame that she has not yet attracted as much scholarly attention as she deserves, especially given the depth of her poetics and the thematic relevance of her works. To my knowledge, the only scholarly article on her works is that of Carol Blessing titled “Exile and Maternal Loss in the Poems of Patricia Jabbeh Wesley.” Jabbeh Wesley occupies a metonymic position in writings about Africa, a continent that has experienced brutal historic traumas, but one that has an abundant will to heal, to live, and to flourish. What is said of Jabbeh Wesley applies in some respects to her native country, Liberia, whose former head of state Charles Taylor was convicted of war crimes in 2012 by a special court in The Hague.</p>
      <p>Liberia was born of the efforts of the American Colonization Society, founded in 1816, to resettle freed black slaves. The resettlement took place on a strip of coastal land in Mesurado. The colony was initially called Christopolis but was later rechristened Monrovia, after the American president James Monroe (Wilson, 25–30). The colony expanded to what would later be known as Liberia, a place of freedom. For John-Peter Pham, social divisions “have characterized the complex tapestry of Liberian society from the very beginning” (52). Yekutiel Gershoni states that Liberia's ruling elites, comprising exclusively the descendants of free slaves, “chose to adopt attitudes and tactics … which were borrowed from the colonial administrators of white powers” toward the “indigenous Africans” (xi). The Americo-Liberians, as they were called, were largely “perceived by the Africans as foreign rulers in every sense” (95). George Klay Kieh Jr. rightly argues that while the ethno-cultural antagonisms between and among the various ethnic groups were not what led to the eventual political and social collapse of the country, they surely did not create political cohesion (25–29).</p>
      <p>When Jabbeh Wesley was asked about her reference to the conflict between the Americo-Liberians and the indigenous population as “a metaphor for Liberia,” she did not deny the conflict. She acknowledged that the descendants of freed American slaves “actually did some enslaving of indigenous people—who were my ancestors—similar to what they had suffered in the American South” (Beattie-Moss).</p>
      <p>Although Jabbeh Wesley has addressed the conflict between the Americo-Liberians and the indigenous populations, it is not her intention to revive old identity-based encounters or conflicts; the major goal in her poetry is to bring to discourse the Liberian people's human condition. She understands that literature involves the experiences of people. “It doesn't exist in isolation of the experiences of a specific group of people” (Beattie-Moss). More specifically, “poetry is an outlet for my grief and a way to immortalize some of the suffering that we've endured, my family, my people, Liberia” (Herring). To immortalize people's suffering in narratives is to bear testimony to people's struggles, to give voice to the voiceless. Her specific intention is to bring about healing by demonstrating that the pain of one is the pain of all.</p>
      <p>Yet we have to ask if narratives can actually bring about healing. One way to approach this question is from the perspective of Primo Levi, who, having survived Auschwitz, began to give voice to the imperative to not keep silent, to speak. So why do we tell stories of human tragedies?</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>WE TELL STORIES TO BE HUMAN</title>
         <p>Aristotle teaches us in his<italic>Poetics</italic>the importance of narrative in the human life and suggests that the need for stories is anthropological; it is born of the need to imitate:<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>“Imitation comes naturally to human beings from childhood (and in this they differ from other animals, i.e., in having a strong propensity to imitation and in learning their earliest lessons through imitation); so does the universal pleasure in imitation” (6).</p>
         <p>Contrary to Aristotle's belief, other animals do imitate, and that contributes to their learning process. In Aristotle's understanding, though, humans raise imitation to the level of culture, to a thing that can be made (<italic>poesis</italic>), and that can be orchestrated for leisure and educational purposes. Humans are storytelling animals; the difference in human and animal imitation lies in our ability to re-create actions that can be imitated over and over and performed in multiple forms for our pleasure. This is where Aristotle places tragedy, which he defines as “an imitation of an action that is admirable, complete and possesses magnitude; in language made pleasurable, each of its species separated in different parts, performed by actors, not through narration; effecting through pity and fear the purification of such emotions” (10).</p>
         <p>We imitate actions, not characters. Of course characters/agents are needed to carry forth or to dramatize or perform those actions. Their performances follow an arc or plot that ultimately reveals how these agents fare and why we should relate to them. The plot that allows us to understand a story has to be complete; it must have “a beginning, a middle and an end” (13). Only in this constellation can it effect an ethical change in humans. As W. Hamilton Fyfe argues in<italic>Aristotle's Art of Poetry: A Greek View of Poetry and Drama</italic>, “The aim of a tragedy is to give the audience a peculiar form of pleasure such as no other art can give, and its success or failure must therefore be judged by reference to that aim. How does the tragedian achieve it? He arouses the emotions of his audience by re-presenting life to them. And this he does by staging a story. In any story there must be people, and they, as human beings, must have moral and intellectual qualities” (xx).</p>
         <p>Paul A. Taylor states that “usually when we feel we have learned something from a novel or play, it is the story itself that strikes us as illuminating, and in a direct way that needs no help from an outside authority” (265). Simply stated, narrative involves individuals (characters) to whom we relate. It is also correct to argue, as Aristotle does, that ethics, to the degree that we are wired to relate to others, is anthropological. This idea has been advanced by the renowned primatologist Frans De Waal in<italic>The Age of Empathy: Nature's Lessons for a Kinder Society</italic>. Empathy, he argues, is based on anthropology, contrary to what some philosophers believe (66–71, 208–9). Humans and primates share the instinct to empathy, but humans tell stories, among other reasons, to enhance their innate propensity to relate to others.</p>
         <p>It is also correct that Aristotle did not envisage tragedy as a mere strategy designed to engender fear and trembling just for the sake of horror. Indeed, he explicitly condemns such ploys. Rather he is interested in realistic actions that might have unpleasant consequences for the agent, on the one hand, or pleasant outcomes that we can admire, on the other. Thus he rejects the intervention of gods in the actions of humans. It is in this regard that Aristotle argues that every well-told story has something to teach, and it does so by revealing universal aspects of the human condition in individual agents. In this respect, poetry is more philosophical than history.</p>
         <p>We imitate characters that are better than we are, characters whom Aristotle calls “heroes.” This does not mean that the characters or agents are without flaws; it means that there is something in the protagonists that makes them stand out so as to attract the sustained attention of the audience or the reader, something that makes them worthy of emulation. There is a risk in trying to understand Aristotle reductively in this regard. He does not anticipate a one-to-one identification with the characters of the narrative. In fact, he has a place for the imitation of characters who are inferior to us, that is to say, characters with only human flaws. This is the reserve of comedy, which is “an imitation of inferior people—not, however, with respect to every kind of defect: the laughable is a species of what is disgraceful” (9). He also recognizes that even our “heroes” have flaws. But even with these flaws, they are still noble; their actions can be judged only within the parameters of the human condition; they are better than we are. To judge their flaws as truly human, Aristotle insists, “there should be nothing irrational in the events themselves; or, failing that, such events should be outside the play, as for example in Sophocles'<italic>Oedipus</italic>” (25).</p>
         <p>The effect of the imitation of action in tragedy is that the audience experiences an immediate emotional thrill in the form of “pity and fear” through which the whole experience is purified in catharsis. Gerald Else argues in<italic>Aristotle's Poetics</italic>that catharsis “belongs to Aristotle's defense of the emotional side of poetry against Plato. The arousing of pity and fear is an integral part of the work of tragedy, at least, and something about that production is such that those feelings are, or can be made, beneficent rather than hurtful” (6–7).</p>
         <p>I am interested here in the beneficent aspect of the imitation of the actions of agents within the framework of tragedy, and I interpret this aspect as a question of ethics because it concerns our relation to others. Humphrey House contends, in<italic>Aristotle's Poetics: A Course of Eight Lectures</italic>, that “both pity and fear are derived from the self-regarding instinct, and pity springs from the feeling that a similar suffering might happen to ourselves. The objects of pity therefore should be like ourselves…. This is the basis of the very possibility of sympathy—of the ‘feeling with’ somebody else” (101–2).</p>
         <p>In the same line of argument as House's, Stephen Halliwell states in<italic>Aristotle's Poetics</italic>that pity and fear refer specifically to the “capacity to sympathize with the sufferer.” He emphasizes that “Aristotle does not derive this sympathy from an undifferentiated sense of humanity: instead, he takes it to be rooted in a felt or perceived affinity between the subject and the object of the emotion.” In that regard, tragic characters “have to be within the reach of an audience's compassion” (175–79). When we see actors perform on stage, we become direct witnesses to their fate. In narratives, the poet/novelist achieves the same effects by providing us with realistic details that bring the characters to life so that we can begin to know them. In B. L. Ullman's understanding, “pitiful and fearful situations are better produced by the structure of the story than by actual scenes on the stage. But those, who through such scenes produce not fear but mere sensationalism, have nothing to do with tragedy” (26). Stories become relevant to readers or audiences in the totality of their elements, through which the story reflects plausible events to the readers themselves. Paul Ricoeur's understanding of the function of poetry, as indicated in the epigraph, goes to the core of the relation of narrative and ethics. Poetry enables the imagination to piece together, in ways acceptable to human flourishing, bits of human conduct, the elements of our happiness and misfortune. He explains in “Life in Quest of Narrative,” that by “means of poetry we learn how reversals and fortune result from this or that conduct, as this is constructed by the plot in the narrative” (23). Ricoeur differentiates between phronetic (prudential), and theoretical/scientific understanding of human nature. Narratives provide the former, while science provides the latter. In line with Ricoeur, Richard Kearney states in “Narrative and Ethics” that “what is peculiar to the ethical quality of narrative understanding, especially in literary works, is that it gives priority to the perception of particular people and situations over abstract rules” (31). The situations described in the narrative force us to engage the individual not in abstract or universalistic terms but in our own terms or in terms that our pain or humiliation has dictated, and this requires prudence.</p>
         <p>Martha Nussbaum furthers the understanding of our connection with the suffering hero in her discussion of empathy as the “imaginative reconstruction of the experience of the sufferer.” Empathy “involves a participatory enactment of the situation of the sufferer, but always combined with the awareness that one is not oneself the sufferer” (327). To be sure, people do not always empathize with others who are in pain. Empathy can be blocked, for example, by the kinds of conditioning that Germans were subjected to during the Nazi regime. However, it is also true that to be human is to reach out in gestures of empathy to others. People can even derive pleasure in feeling the pain of others, as Susan L. Feagin argues in “The Pleasure of Tragedy.” Pleasure from tragedy is a meta-response; and it is gratifying to know that there is “a unity of feeling among members of humanity, that we are not alone, and that these feelings are at the heart of morality itself” (103).</p>
         <p>In Aristotle's understanding, therefore, the writer who imitates people's actions in tragedy bears witness to humanity's experience of pain. In provoking pity and fear in us when we witness the pain of others in narratives, the writer indirectly seeks to put a stop to the source of that pain. This, in my understanding, is where Aristotle, Primo Levi, and Jabbeh Wesley's understanding of narrative merge. When Patricia Jabbeh Wesley states that she writes as a way of keeping her people's suffering alive or that writing provides a way for her to grieve, she touches at the heart of Aristotle's idea of tragedy as illuminating ethics by initiating some form of purification in people. She crafts her poems as testimonies in pursuit of life in its fullness. Testimony is also at the core of Primo Levi's poems and memoirs of survival in the German concentration camps.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>THE ETHICS OF TESTIMONY AND THE MORAL CHALLENGES OF LIVING</title>
         <p>The Jewish Holocaust is, no doubt, the most fully documented horror of the twentieth century, excepting, of course, the two world wars themselves. Geoffrey Hartman argues that “no other man-made catastrophe has been so voluminously recorded and publicized as the Shoah” (249). Accounts of holocaust survival are also veritable templates for survival of all large-scale ethnic or racial traumas. Simon Wiesenthal, Eli Wiesel, Viktor Frankl, and Primo Levi provide some of the best examples of testimonies about the evils of the Holocaust and the healing power and moral obligations of testimonies.</p>
         <p>In the concluding chapter of his memoir<italic>The Drowned and the Saved</italic>, Primo Levi offers a rationale for speaking about his experience in the concentration camp: “We see it as a duty and, at the same time, as a risk: the risk of appearing anachronistic, of not being listened to. We must be listened to: above and beyond our personal experiences, we have collectively witnessed a fundamental, unexpected event, fundamental precisely because unexpected, not foreseen by anyone. It took place in the teeth of all forecasts; it happened in Europe” (199).</p>
         <p>Levi's assertion that “we must be listened to” underscores his belief in the fundamental insight of Aristotle's understanding of tragedy. Levi believes that the survivors of the Shoah have stories that are capable of provoking “pity and fear,” stories that ultimately lead to a more ethically conscious life. There is, therefore, a moral urgency to inform the living of what happened to the dead. He issues an urgent warning: “It happened, therefore it can happen again: this is the core of what we have to say” (199). The moral obligation of all survivors of horror is to prevent it from happening again, and this, of course, presupposes that all have been moved to pity and fear by the narrative of what happened.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Survival in Auschwitz</italic>, Levi makes his most robust ethical case for revealing the horrors of the camps. He notes that the book was written to satisfy certain needs, primarily that of “an interior liberation” (9). He confronts his audience with an ethical responsibility. He does this in a short, epigraphic poem, “If This Is a Man,” in which the speaker addresses the reader directly, thus situating him or her in the center of Levi's moral imagination:<disp-quote>
               <p>You who live safe</p>
               <p>In your warm houses,</p>
               <p>You who find on returning in the evening,</p>
               <p>Hot food and friendly faces</p>
            </disp-quote>Now that readers feel directly addressed, Levi reveals, in the second stanza, the core moral issues to be faced when he paints the pictures of inmates of the camps: a man who “works in the mud” and who “fights for a scrap of bread”; a “woman without hair … her eyes empty.”</p>
         <p>The concrete details of the man and woman who have been humiliated by their fellow humans should trouble every person who lives safely in their warm houses. Levi, however, urges these individuals further to<disp-quote>
               <p>Meditate that this came about:</p>
               <p>I commend these words to you,</p>
               <p>Carve them in your hearts</p>
               <p>At home, in the streets,</p>
               <p>Going to bed, rising;</p>
               <p>Repeat them to your children. (9)</p>
            </disp-quote>As Nicholas Patruno argues in<italic>Understanding Primo Levi</italic>, this epigraphic poem, written in January 1946, is a “loosely paraphrased interpretation of one of the most often invoked Hebrew prayers, the Shema” (9). The imperative not to forget is a well-known component of Jewish history and culture. Remembrance is the holy grail of survival. Conversely, to forget is to subject oneself to extinction. For Patruno, the title of the poem is intended to raise a “rhetorical question of conscience whose impact is so powerful that any reply would be superfluous” (10). Jonathan Druker contends in “Ethics and Ontology in Primo Levi's ‘Survival in Auschwitz’: A Levinasian Reading,” that the ethical import of Primo Levi's memoir is highlighted by the poem, which “commands the ‘safe’ reader, surrounded by ‘friendly faces,’ to reflect on whether the dehumanized victim, unable to assert his or her own subjectivity, is yet a human being for whom the reader is responsible” (533). Druker, alluding to Emmanuel Levinas, further points out that “the human face is the focal point of the poem's gaze as the ‘friendly faces’ (<italic>visi amici</italic>) of the first stanza give way to the dehumanized victim's blank stare ‘her eyes empty’; (<italic>vuoti gli occhi</italic>)” (534).</p>
         <p>By inviting the reader to look closely at the faces of the camp inmates, Levi asks the reader indirectly: What would you do? Do you still feel comfortable among your friendly faces? Do you not recognize the humanity of that other human who has been forced to waste away? Would you still keep silent? Levi knows the destructive force of silence, for, as he notes, the silence of the majority of the German population, their failure to let the secrets about the concentration camps be known, is a moral failure. This failure, Levi argues in<italic>The Drowned and the Saved</italic>, “represents one of the major collective crimes of the German people and the most obvious demonstration of the cowardice to which Hitlerian terror had reduced them: a cowardice which became an integral part of mores and so profound as to prevent husbands from telling their wives, parents their children” (15).</p>
         <p>To keep silent when one should have spoken out is to refuse to acknowledge the humanity of others, of those in pain. Perhaps the many genocides that took place after the horrors of Auschwitz bear him out. The 1994 genocide in Rwanda and those in Bosnia and Herzegovina between 1992 and 1995 come readily to mind.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>JABBEH WESLEY'S POETICS OF ATTENTION</title>
         <p>My discussion of Jabbeh Wesley's poetics is based on poems that, in my view, best demonstrate what I have already identified as the ethical thrust of her writing. Jabbeh Wesley writes in the tradition of Aristotle's understanding of tragedy discussed above. In her faithful rendition of the observed world, she imitates people's action in pleasurable language with the ultimate goal of affecting the reader. Avoiding flashy, contrived strategies, her poems operate within what Donald Revell calls the poetry of attention. They trust “the opened eye to see” (13). For Revell the “poetry of attention proceeds not by acquisition but, rather, by plain accumulation. It doesn't add up; it goes. I see the light, but seeing doesn't make it mine” (18).</p>
         <p>The title of Jabbeh Wesley's fourth collection of poetry,<italic>Where the Road Turns</italic>, is a subtle allusion to Wole Soyinka's<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">1965</xref>play,<italic>The Road</italic>, and Ben Okri's<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>Booker Prize–winning novel,<italic>The Famished Road</italic>. These two books explore the riches of Yoruba mythology in order to shed light on the African condition. The characters in Soyinka's play live on the road and make their living from what the road has to offer. Critics have pointed out the absurdist elements in Soyinka's conception of the road as a metaphor for Africa's instability, especially in the play's parallel with Samuel Beckett's<italic>Waiting for Godot</italic>. What is said of<italic>The Road</italic>applies to Jabbeh Wesley's<italic>Where the Road Turns</italic>. Aided by the picture of the winding dirt road on the cover and at the beginning of each of the book's four sections, Jabbeh Wesley reminds us of the twisting road of Africa's existential journeys. The eponymous poem itself is representative of the poetry of attention:<disp-quote>
               <p>I'm right here on the road, in the open</p>
               <p>You will find me waiting where Gbarnga's</p>
               <p>hills curve into zigzags, and cars slow down</p>
               <p>because potholes have taken over the road,</p>
               <p>because potholes have taken over my life.</p>
            </disp-quote>The detailed description of the place where a lonely speaker waits enables us to see what the speaker sees: a crumbling world. We are even more troubled by the fact that the speaker sees a parallel between him or her and the road: “Potholes have taken over my life” just as they have taken over the road. This self-identification with the road is to be understood as a lamentation for the conditions of the speaker's life and not as romanticizing the rural life of Africa. But little romanticizing is possible given that the speaker waits in the manner that reminds one of Samuel Beckett's remarkable characters, Pozzo and Lucky, in<italic>Waiting for Godot</italic>.<disp-quote>
               <p>I still wait here,</p>
               <p>in the corner of the road, cutting, weeding,</p>
               <p>watering already-sun-burnt plants, waiting</p>
               <p>because someone told me that if I could</p>
               <p>wait long enough, just long enough, things</p>
               <p>will change; the government will change;</p>
               <p>food will come for us refugees;</p>
               <p>something will happen for my good.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The road in an unnamed country in Africa is representative of the condition of the entire continent; the speaker stands for its dispossessed people. Unlike Beckett's Pozzo and Lucky, the speaker does not just wait; he or she is engaged in meaningful activities, the result of which is nothing short of Pozzo and Lucky's absurd world. According to Mark Doty, the National Book Award–winning poet and critic, “Every achieved poem inscribes a perceptual signature in the world” (21). “Where the Road Turns” achieves just that. We are confronted with an environment that persists in our inner vision. For Doty, “What descriptions—or good ones, anyway—actually describe then is consciousness, the mind playing over the world of matter, finding there a glass various and lustrous enough to reflect back the complexities of the self that's doing the looking” (33).</p>
         <p>In the achieved poem, therefore, we are made to confront not only the world of the speaker but also his consciousness, and ultimately that of the poet. By presenting this decayed part of the African world, the poet wants us to be troubled the way she is. Indeed, the first poem in the collection, “Cheede, My Bride: A Grebo Man Laments—1985,” appears to have set the consciousness-raising tone for the rest of the poems.</p>
         <disp-quote>
            <p>While we sleep, jumbo trucks haul timber</p>
            <p>to build needle houses and monkey bridges</p>
            <p>across the skies in some city far away.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <p>One day my wife, Cheede, will run away</p>
            <p>to Monrovia, that swallows its victims whole</p>
            <p>down boa-constrictor bellies.</p>
         </disp-quote>
         <p>We meet a mind grappling with a world that is being ruthlessly exploited. The exploitation of the world plays itself out in the lives of the people, as the second stanza reveals. One is reminded of Africa's struggles with neoimperialism. Africa's natural resources are being used for the development of other parts of the world. Such exploitation contributes to the implosion of different units of African life: the family, the village, the county, the city, and the country. What this and other poems aim to achieve, therefore, is to raise our consciousness of the precariousness of the African world as seen from Liberia. This is the most that poets or tragedians can do, and they do so in the knowledge or the hope that the audience or the reader will be moved to relate to that world, as Aristotle might have anticipated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>THE SILENCE THE DEAD REFUSE TO TAKE</title>
         <p>Though Jabbeh Wesley is not as demanding of her readers as Levi is of his, her testimonies are no less morally urgent. She too understands the importance of defeating the tyranny of silence. In the poem “Requiem for Auntie,” from the collection<italic>Becoming Ebony</italic>, she takes us through a maze of relationships between the dead and the living. The poem is spoken from the perspective of a little girl observing the body of her aunt. The first stanza begins with a general observation but then quickly narrows to a particular person's experience, to the girl's perspective:<disp-quote>
               <p>When the dead first arrive in death, their eyes stand</p>
               <p>naked and wide and bare to the bone. This gaze</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>numbed my girl eyes the day they brought my Auntie</p>
               <p>home.</p>
            </disp-quote>The reference to nakedness suggests the closure in the dead person's existence; at the same time, it recalls its parallel opposite: the fact that the living still have opportunities. The dead person's gaze constitutes a direct challenge to the girl, who is literally shocked into the realization of her own good fortune at being alive and of the possibilities open to her. In this short, powerful moment, there is an unspoken dialogue between the deceased and the bereaved, between an aunt and her niece; there is a simultaneous negotiation between nakedness and the urgent moral call to clothe that nakedness. The affinity between the dead aunt and her living niece is as much a moment of feminine solidarity as it is a universal experience of sympathy with the weak or with people in pain, as Susan Feagin suggested above. By the end of the poem, the speaker, the little girl, has grown into a woman with a profound sense of responsibility, and she meditates on the mysteries of the world based on, or, inspired by, her original experience as a child:<disp-quote>
               <p>The mysteries of this world are not in the living.</p>
               <p>The mysteries of this world are in the dead cold of</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>death, in the weathered things of this world, in</p>
               <p>the silence that the dead refuse to take along.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>In her musings, the niece reveals that her aunt had left something with her: the silence she refused to take along to the grave. That silence, like all silence about human suffering, is oppressive, and it urges the niece to do something. The niece therefore has the obligation to end the tyranny of silence and her aunt's helplessness by bearing testimony, by telling us about her aunt. In her requiem, her aunt, now standing for all the dead, speaks through her niece. The panorama that Jabbeh Wesley paints here calls to mind Giorgio Agamben's analysis of Primo Levi's memoirs, cited above.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Survival in Auschwitz</italic>, Levi recounts how the inmates of the camps used the word “Muselmann” to designate those so debilitated by hunger and sickness that they resembled the living dead more than human beings.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>Giorgio Agamben describes them as the body “of the overcomatose person and the neomort attached to life-support systems today” (156). The existence of nearly every so-called Muselmann ended in the gas chamber. For Agamben, even though those who were eventually led to the gas chambers were the perfect witnesses of the evils of the Holocaust, they cannot bear witness because they took their experience to the grave. Nevertheless, Agamben argues that a life that had become “bare, unassignable and unwitnessable” is not necessarily condemned to silence (156–57). However, the only way it can speak is through the survivor, through the witness, whose authority “consists in his capacity to speak solely in the name of an incapacity to speak—that is, in his or her being a subject” (158). In light of Agamben's explanation, we understand that Primo Levi, who barely survived extermination, speaks not just for himself but also on behalf of all who did not survive. Testimony consists of any action taken by the survivor of violence to ensure that the Muselmann is not forgotten. Agamben argues that “it is because there is testimony only where there is an impossibility of speaking, because there is a witness only where there has been desubjectification, that the<italic>Muselmann</italic>is the complete witness and that the survivor and the<italic>Muselmann</italic>cannot be split apart” (158).</p>
         <p>I am interested in the idea that the survivor and the Muselmann cannot be split apart. This fusion attests to the moral power of witnessing by binding the dead with the living, the privileged with the underprivileged. In speaking for those incapable of speaking, the survivor becomes one with the victim. The same can be said of the little girl in “Requiem for Auntie.” In the speaker's being drawn into her aunt's world, in speaking about her aunt, the speaker's life can no longer be separated from that of her aunt. In the same way, the survivors of the Liberian war can no longer be separated from the dead. They are bound by a common fate, by the open wound of being, a wound that the poet, in line with Aristotelian thinking, seeks to heal.</p>
         <p>Jabbeh Wesley is to Liberia what Primo Levi is to the survivors of the Holocaust. She speaks through her characters, one of whom is the girl in “Requiem for Auntie,” and lets us know that the survivor who turns his or her back on the dead will eventually be confronted with the moral vacuity of his or her existence. This awareness is enhanced by the experience of the speaker in “Coming Home to Iyeeh” from<italic>Becoming Ebony</italic>. The speaker is the “child that wanders [and who] comes home only to graves.” The poem reveals a tone of regret in the speaker, who has been away from his homeland for a long time, and who never cared to know what became of the dead. But it is now time for mourning, for paying respect to the dead:<disp-quote>
               <p>Every teardrop falling, every dirge sung, every wail or moan</p>
               <p>or sigh … all the drumming and praise songs must be hers.</p>
               <p>
                  <italic>Iyeeh</italic>, Mother,<italic>Khadi Wheh</italic>,<italic>Wahnjeh</italic>, we praise you—</p>
               <p>it is your children who now praise you … your wandering</p>
               <p>stranger-children now coming home.</p>
               <p>Where there are trumpets, they will sound.</p>
               <p>We do not pour libation with ancestral hands or gourds.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>The River Is Rising</italic>is, among Jabbeh Wesley's four collections, the one most directly occupied with the memories of the dead by making an urgent moral plea. The poet provides specific details of the Liberian wars, incidents, and even names that ultimately confer humanity on places and incidents and therefore bring them closer to the reader's axis of empathy. In the title poem, “The River Is Rising,” the image of a river stands for the ebb and flow of memory. The speaker announces to us that the river is “swelling with the incoming tide,” and people, the speaker included, “stand at the banks” as witnesses to what the rising river will bring. Of course the rising river brings with it crabs and clams and shrimps, but there is much more than these natural inhabitants of the river that the speaker calls the “river's creatures.”</p>
         <p>The refrain “The river is rising, but this is not a flood” is designed to calm those who stand by the river waiting for what would be washed up. The rising river will not sweep them away. Rather they should watch for what the rivers have to show them besides the river's creatures:<disp-quote>
               <p>Do not let your eye wander away from this scene</p>
               <p>Yes, all bones below the Mesurado or the St. Paul</p>
               <p>or Sinoe or the Loffa River will be brought up</p>
               <p>to land so all the overwhelming questions</p>
               <p>can once more overwhelm us.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>We do not have answers to the overwhelming questions that the washed-up remains will raise, nor are the questions revealed to the readers. They are left to the imagination, which at this stage has probably already been shocked into pity and fear. Being overwhelmed by questions about life implies experiencing an Aristotelian catharsis after which their lives could hardly return to what they had always been. But it would be a testimony to the humanity of the bystanders if they are overwhelmed by what they will see, because the remains are not part of the “river's creatures”; human bones are not supposed to be washed up by the rivers. This human wreckage could only have been the product of atrocities, and the tide of the river bears witness to them. The history of Liberia is rife with instances of atrocities against innocent people. We recall the British- and American-sponsored colonization of the nineteenth century as well as the brutal regimes and wars of Samuel Doe and Charles Taylor. The Mesurado, the Loffa, and other rivers must have born witness to those crimes. All the victims we can imagine come together in the person of “a lost sister” washed up by the rivers and who stands at the bank “waving at those / who in refusing to die, simply refuse to die.” The redundancy in the phrase is designed to underscore the stubbornness of the dead. The dead refuse to die. They are the ones who literally set the rivers moving; with the help of the rivers, they make their way to the feet of the living. The rivers are their vehicles. By being washed up into the memory of the living, they become one with the survivors—those who, in their own way, also refused to die.</p>
         <p>In a generous communal spirit, the speaker reminds us that the song is not for “Ellen alone.” It is also a song “for Mapue and Tenneh and all the Ellens there are.” It is also a song for Kimah and Musu and Massa and the many others. The poet, in having her speaker invoke names belonging to many ethnic groups, makes a gesture of inclusion; she casts the net of her community wide and reminds all Liberians that the healing duty of memory is for all. Healing cannot be partial.</p>
         <p>The last stanza, “Let no man stand between us / and the river again” hints at the necessity for all to confront the devastating evidence that raised overwhelming questions. No one should stand between people and what is remembered; if people lose sight of what is remembered, they will no longer grieve for the dead, and the failure to grieve, as can be implied in Primo Levi's testimonies, derides the living and makes the recurrence of war atrocities possible. Little surprise therefore that Jabbeh Wesley declared in her interview that poetry was an outlet for her grief.</p>
         <p>Remembering is a function of the meaning-making process after the emptiness of loss. Spelder and Strickland suggest that “grief is the emotional response to bereavement, to the event of loss” (as qtd. in DuBose, 368). The theologian Todd J. DuBose explains that “grief gazes at an ever-receding present as it moves further and further into the past. The immediate reaction often involves bargaining for a reversal of the loss, denial, anger, shock, anguish, distress, sadness” (368). These reactions are the body's means of trying to make sense of the world in the wake of the emptiness created by bereavement. Interpreting Drew Leder and Maurice Merleau-Ponty's notion of chiasmic structure of the body, DuBose explains that the body realizes its existence only in relation to other bodies. It touches because it is being touched. Other bodies make ours perceptible. The disappearance of these other bodies in death is, in tune with the chiasmic structure of bodily existence, the disappearance of our own bodies. We experience that disappearance as pain, grief, sorrow. These manifestations of pain are, indeed, the ways our bodies adjust to vacuum and fill it with meaning. For DuBose, “meaning-making processes, which<italic>appear</italic>to be immaterial processes, are embodied phenomena. Reflection, perception, feeling, language, even logic make sense only through the influx of the body's ‘reading’ of space, time, action, and sensation” (370).</p>
         <p>The body invents some immaterial entities or gestures to take the place of the material loss; they include consolation, hope, and love, sometimes even hallucinations and fantasies. The memory of the departed keeps alive the grief of their loss and so confers the present with meaning. For Jabbeh Wesley, therefore, to write poetry is to make sense of the dysfunctional world of Liberia. The grief in her works comes with memory, sauntering like ghosts. Indeed, the persistence of ghosts is a metaphor for the persistence of the memory of the dead and for the attendant grief. This is particularly true in the poem “Ghosts Don't Go Away Just Like That,” from<italic>Where the Road Turns</italic>.</p>
         <p>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>Sometimes they lurk in hallways where they have lost</p>
               <p>the other side of them. They may hover over new wars</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>like the wars that carried them away from their bodies,</p>
               <p>causing them to lose their world and us in the rush.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>Ghosts don't go away just like that, you know;</p>
               <p>they may come in that same huge crowd that was</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>massacred together with them, and since that massacre</p>
               <p>may have happened at school, in a bar or at church, they</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>may be found, kneeling at the pulpit, singing and taking</p>
               <p>communion again and again, with everyone else.</p>
            </disp-quote>In her writing, Jabbeh Wesley thus performs rituals that acknowledge the existence of these ghosts in ways that bring peace not only to them but also to the living.</p>
         <p>No other poem expresses the violence in Liberia as does “An Elegy for the St. Peter's Church Massacred,” from<italic>The River Is Rising</italic>. It is a poem that details the massacre of six hundred men, women, and children at St. Peter's Church, a horrible act that made international news (Reuters). Over two hundred soldiers from the Armed Forces of Liberia (AFL) forced their way into the church and shot the people who had taken refuge there. For the speaker, the survival of such tragedies is more painful than death, and that is why he believes he is in a worse situation than the victims:<disp-quote>
               <p>I envy those who were massacred.</p>
               <p>Those who never saw their killers approach</p>
               <p>with heavy bootsteps that made no sound</p>
               <p>in the dark morning hours.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>He also envies those people who died in the dark, who did not have to “see the faces of their murderers.” Perhaps the advantage of the dead's not glimpsing the faces of their murderers is that the deceased would never realize the horror of the depravity of their fellow humans. It is this truth of human existence that the speaker, the survivor of the whole horror, has had to live with: “It is a sad story when one survives.” The speaker is perhaps guilty of having survived the horrors that consumed others. One of the ways to assuage that guilt is to defy the silence that surrounds the horror. Through him the poet seems to put the survivors to shame and guilt.</p>
         <p>Against the background of rampant violence, the most dramatic aspect of which was the massacre of those six hundred unarmed civilians, we begin to understand the agony of a person searching for the members of his family in the poem “Finding My Family,” from<italic>Before the Palm Could Bloom</italic>. The speaker is a man who set out in search of his children, his “big boy, Nyema,” and “the small one, Doeteh.” He asks a stranger if he saw “a mother walking by their side.” The speaker's having lost hope of finding them alive, his tone changes from desperation to one of mourning:<disp-quote>
               <p>Good friend, were they hungry</p>
               <p>when they met their end?</p>
               <p>Oh, good friend, I will follow</p>
               <p>to wrap up their bones.</p>
               <p>Thank you, good friend.</p>
               <p>But how will I know their bones?</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Are we in the position to provide him with answers to his bewildering questions? Do we know where his wife and children are? These questions are designed to put us on the spot and to embarrass us. In our helplessness, we might be tempted to point fingers. We know that the major culprits in the war are the warlords who may have conscripted his boys and killed his wife. But knowing the names of the warlords is not enough. That is not even what the speaker or the poet demands of us. The search, the questions addressed to an unnamed passerby, one whom the speaker calls friend, is an open invitation to the reader to take the place of this distraught questioner. It is an ethical call to empathize in the manner that Primo Levi urged in the epigraphic poem above. By switching perspectives, which is exactly what empathy achieves, by putting ourselves in the position of the sufferer, or, in this case, the grieving person, we begin to understand the devastation so completely as to be compelled to prevent its recurrence. This, to me, is at the core of Jabbeh Wesley's poetics of testimony. She foresees that anyone capable of fully experiencing another's pain will not likely stand by and allow that pain to be inflicted on others. It is true that the human tendency toward aggression offers no assurance that such shifts of perspective will prevent anyone from inflicting more pain on others. Yet the writer hopes that much can be achieved by keeping the consciousness of the human condition alive.</p>
         <p>In “Child Soldier,” from<italic>Before the Palm Could Bloom</italic>, the speaker erects a spiritual monument for the “war children / who follow men who have lost all reason” (19). Each of the poem's six stanzas begins with, or is constructed around, a different name. These names—Saye, Ghapu, Kahieh, Nimley, Kortu, Wlemunga—are drawn from the different tribes and ethnicities in Liberia. Ghapu is a Bassa name meaning “light skinned” or “white man.” Nimley means “victor” or “I have survived.” Kortu means “end the war.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Of particular importance for Jabbeh Wesley's ethical attitude toward Liberia and the world is not only the universal, cosmopolitan spirit that guided the poet's choice of names but also the fact that some of the names that might belong to one ethnic group were hybrids created from at least two languages and ethnicities. One such name is Nimley, which is both Grebo and Kru. Grebo and Kru, along with Bassa, are from the Kwa or Klao family of languages. These languages have common roots and are so intermeshed as to defy any search for linguistic purity. By choosing names from these language cultures, the poet raises the specter of wars of brothers against brothers. Given that these were child soldiers, the poet calls Africa's attention not only to senseless fratricidal murder but also to the smothering of the future of Africa itself. The poet thus insinuates a question: Why bring children into a world where they will turn against their parents like Frankenstein's creature? The idea of children turning against their parents is particularly demonstrated by the existence of Dekuah, a spirit child, whose symbolic relevance we shall discuss more fully later.</p>
         <p>In the poem “In the Ruined City: A Poem for Monrovia,” from<italic>The River Is Rising</italic>, the speaker laments the dearth of aesthetics and leisure:<disp-quote>
               <p>There are no more trumpets or drums.</p>
               <p>The Dorklor dancer who lost his legs</p>
               <p>in the war now sits by the roadside, waiting.</p>
               <p>It is something to lose your legs to a war,</p>
               <p>they say, to Charles Taylor's ugly war,</p>
               <p>where the fighter cannot recall why he still fights.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The senselessness of Charles Taylor's war is demonstrated in a particularly painful way through the suggestion that the soldiers no longer know why they fight. But our attention remains with the dancer who has now lost the means for his art, for that which gave meaning to his life. And he sits by the roadside waiting. What exactly is the dancer waiting for? Does this dancer wait in the same way that the speaker in “Where the Road Turns” does? In the dancer's waiting, the poet leaves a hole in our hearts, a great longing symbolized by his missing limbs. Perhaps the question of what the dancer is waiting for is better left unanswered. It is, in the manner of Levi's “If This Is a Man,” designed to raise questions that any answer would diminish.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s05">
         <title>THE DESIRE TO LIVE</title>
         <p>Jabbeh Wesley leaves us with more than pictures of desolation in her poetics of testimony. Even as she explores the traumas of the war, she steers the reader's attention to the Liberian people's passion for life. In “I am Not Dekuah,” from<italic>Before the Palm Could Bloom</italic>, the speaker addresses his clansmen:<disp-quote>
               <p>Dieh, I come knocking</p>
               <p>Clansmen, I come calling.</p>
               <p>I come crawling at your doors.</p>
               <p>There is a matter</p>
               <p>from my heart.</p>
               <p>Gather your sons from afar</p>
               <p>at<italic>Tuwa Kai</italic>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <italic>Kwee</italic>must come to town today.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>The picture painted is that of a guest asking for accommodation. But we learn that the speaker is a child, and therefore his plea is existential; he wants to live and to thrive. The speaker's clan is representative of the larger world. He pleads with the world for a chance to grow. “I am not Dekuah; let me live” (9). “I am not Dekuah” appears five times in the seven stanzas of the poem, underscoring the speaker's resolve to live. This anaphora draws attention to the precariousness of the situation that children, and, indeed everyone else, was facing at that time. People were making peace with the fact that children were not surviving childhood. As child soldiers, even some of the children had turned against their parents. It is in this context that the speaker announced that he is not Dekuah.</p>
         <p>Dekuah is a spirit child whose goal is to punish its birthing family, as it is bound to slip into the birthing mother's womb again, only to die again after birth. It is to be assumed that Dekuah is a gratuitously malignant spirit that delights in the pain of the persons who gave it life. Some children, according to this mythology, succeed in being born up to three times. There is an obvious influence of Wole Soyinka's poem “Abiku” on Jabbeh Wesley's uses of Dekuah in her poetry. In “Abiku,” the spirit child boasts in the first stanza that there is nothing his birthing family can do to keep him in the land of the living:<disp-quote>
               <p>In vain your bangles cast</p>
               <p>Charmed circles at my feet</p>
               <p>I am Abiku, calling for the first</p>
               <p>And repeated time</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Abiku children are given marks on their faces or other visible parts of the body so that when they are born again, those marks will reveal them for who they are: deceivers, spirit children. Some of the children, now having been discovered and shamed, decide to stay in the land of the living. Some, nevertheless still return to the “spirit world” because of their stronger binding pacts with other children there (Maduka, 18). The Grebo (Jabbeh Wesley's ethnicity), believe, as do most West African cultures, that such spirit children exist. In these cultures, children are given similar names. Dekuah in Grebo can be broken down as De “come,” Kuah, “to die.” A child who has come to die. Other names associated with the Dekuah (Abiku) phenomenon are Mudi, “Go Back”; Sejlah, “We Don't Want You”; Kude, “The Devil's Mother,” and so on.</p>
         <p>If Dekuah signifies the unwillingness to live, or reminds us of the Frankenstein syndrome, as suggested above, it is no surprise that the child in the poem immediately announces that he is not Dekuah; he has not come to die. Emphasizing the singularity of his existence, his will to live, he says, “I've never been born before,” and then goes on to announce what he is and what he desires. “My name is Nehklon / Let me live.” Of particular relevance is the shift from the negative declaration “I am not” to a positive one, “I am.” In this linguistic switch, the poet signals a deeper moral and existential consequence. In this shift from a reactionary attitude to life to one that is proactive, Jabbeh Wesley brings the challenges of life affirmation to the consciousness of her readers. Through Nehklon, she enables us to imagine people taking charge of their lives, as Primo Levi does in his “If This Is a Man.” It is therefore not only Nehklon who pleads; all Liberians plead for a chance to live, for a fair share in life's bounty. There is nothing to be happy about in the remembrance of the war's violence; there is no happy ending for the narrative other than the hope that people might be allowed to live and to thrive. People are not Dekuahs; they have not come to die.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s06">
         <title>CONCLUSION</title>
         <p>Patricia Jabbeh Wesley is among the new generation of African writers who have turned their back on the typical Achebean write-back to the center of the empire. She is not interested in the anti-imperialist rhetoric and attitudes that have hitherto controlled African postcolonial discourses. By ignoring the gaze of the empire, so to speak, she redirects the African gaze onto herself. She writes back to self.</p>
         <p>In an interview with Melissa Beattie-Moss, Jabbeh Wesley lamented the virtual nonexistence of significant literary figures in Liberia, writers who could be compared with those in Nigeria, Kenya, or other regions of Africa. But even those African writers understandably wrote about their own experiences, which were based on their confrontations with colonialism. Those who could be identified as her literary forebears in Liberia were mostly Americo-Liberians whose writing was a kind “settler d of literature, with American images, written in isolation of the environment and culture of Africa.” Sadly, her people, “the so-called elite, educated ones—frowned on anything African for a long time,” so in effect, she had no established literary figure to look up to (Beattie-Moss). Jabbeh Wesley has reluctantly accepted the honor of being the first truly Liberian literary figure—at least, one with an international profile.<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>I am in no way making Jabbeh Wesley the Chinua Achebe of Liberian literature, nor does she claim to be. She acknowledges that she has benefited considerably from the many griots and oral narrators of her culture. But she is a pioneer; her four poetry collections address themes of war, love, globalization, feminism, African renaissance, diaspora identity, and much more.</p>
         <p>Carol Blessing rightly observes that Jabbeh Wesley's poetry “shifts between critical, bemused, revelatory, celebratory, and mournful, as she discusses both her American and Liberian lives” (78–79). Her style is generally narrative, predominantly free verse that lives primarily through her deft evocation of powerful images. Adhering closely to formal stanzas often arranged in couplets, tercets, and quatrains, but dispensing with strict meters and rhymes, she delves into conversational rhythms that invoke a familial atmosphere. Her narrative is often folklorist—as if the narrator were among friends, telling stories around the kitchen table. The moment of epiphany, though, comes when mournful tones sneak into the words of the speaker. For example, “Strange Lovers,” from the collection<italic>Before the Palm Could Bloom</italic>, begins:<disp-quote>
               <p>So it is the moon that sends the Mesurado</p>
               <p>running to visit the Atlantic</p>
               <p>with its millions of troops?</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Here, Jabbeh Wesley plays with elements that the listeners are very familiar with and that they can easily visualize. The personification of the Mesurado River achieves comic relief even in the midst of tragedy. Throughout the poem, a voice induces a dialogue between the river and the millions of troops—its fishes—and, taking the position of the fishes, goes on with questions, now directed at some other forces. One can imagine children chuckling at the narrative, and adults grinning, while they are all seated around the family hearth listening. The last three stanzas begin a change in tone, preparing the reader for a shocking realization. The fish, and the voice that had taken their perspective, are tired of being sent on rendezvous. One of these days the voice/fishes would be gone:<disp-quote>
               <p>Like a frog that cried and cried for the rain,</p>
               <p>and before the rains, withers beside the dried</p>
               <p>banks of the stream.</p>
               <p>I'll be gone, Mesurado, do you hear me?</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Even in her familial tone, and perhaps because of it, Jabbeh Wesley never forgets that the healing and meaning-making function of grief and mourning, as painful as grief and mourning are, is not to be avoided. Rather, as DuBose argues, based on the painful experience of his wife's miscarriage, as “‘child’ and ‘parent’ disappeared, our bodies and our society<italic>dys</italic>-appeared, and our connections and hopes re-appeared” (374). Jabbeh Wesley attaches the reappearance of the hopes for the healing and reconstruction of her Liberian world to people's ability and willingness to truly experience the painful process of grief and, perhaps informed by that cathartic experience, allow compassion and empathy to guide their relationship to others.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I use<italic>narrative</italic>as a term that embraces the crafting processes of poetry, fiction, and drama. They call into being not necessarily a factual world but a realistically probable one that calls on the receivers to apply their imagination to bring about the completion of the work in question. It is also in this respect that we understand Aristotle's uses of tragedy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“Muselmann” is German for “Muslim.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I am grateful to Patricia Jabbeh Wesley for translating these names and guiding me through Liberian cultures and languages.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a list of important names in contemporary Liberian literature, see<italic>Sea Breeze Journal</italic>,<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.liberiaseabreeze.com">www.liberiaseabreeze.com</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="works_cited">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Agamben, Giorgio</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Remnants of Auschwitz: The Witness and the Archive</italic>
               </source>. Translated by<string-name>Daniel Heller-Roazen</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Zone Books</publisher-name>,<year>1999</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Aristotle</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Poetics</italic>
               </source>. Translated by<string-name>Malcolm Heath</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Penguin Books</publisher-name>,<year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Beattie-Moss, Melissa</string-name>.<article-title>“Word of Mouth. The Painful, Joyful Heart: A Conversation with Patricia Jabbeh Wesley.”</article-title>Penn State News, September 5,<year>2005</year>.<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.rps.psu.edu/jabbeh/index.html">http://www.rps.psu.edu/jabbeh/index.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Blessing, Carol</string-name>.<article-title>“Exile and Maternal Loss in the Poems of Patricia Jabbeth [<italic>sic</italic>] Wesley.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Exile and the Narrative/Poetic Imagination</italic>
               </source>, edited by<string-name>Agnieszka Gutthy</string-name>,<fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Cambridge Scholars</publisher-name>,<year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>De Waal, Frans</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Age of Empathy: Nature's Lessons for a Kinder Society</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harmony Books</publisher-name>,<year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Doty, Mark</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Art of Description: World into Word</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Graywolf Press</publisher-name>,<year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Druker, Jonathan</string-name>.<article-title>“Ethics and Ontology in Primo Levi's ‘Survival in Auschwitz’: A Levinasian Reading.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Italica</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>83</volume>, no.<issue>3/4</issue>(<year>2006</year>):<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>DuBose, J. Todd</string-name>.<article-title>“The Phenomenology of Bereavement, Grief, and Mourning.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Journal of Religion and Health</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>36</volume>, no.<issue>4</issue>(<year>1997</year>):<fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Else, Gerald F.</string-name>, trans.<source>
                  <italic>Aristotle's Poetics</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>,<year>1967</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Feagin, Susan L.</string-name>
               <article-title>“The Pleasure of Tragedy.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>American Philosophical Quarterly</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>20</volume>, no.<issue>1</issue>(<year>1983</year>):<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Fyfe, W. Hamilton</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Aristotle's Art of Poetry: A Greek View of Poetry and Drama</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>,<year>1940</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gershoni, Yekutiel</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Black Colonialism: The Americo-Liberian Scramble for the Hinterland</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Westview Press</publisher-name>,<year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r13">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Halliwell, Stephen</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Aristotle's Poetics</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>,<year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r14">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Hartman, Geoffrey</string-name>.<article-title>“The Humanities of Testimonies: An Introduction,”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Poetics Today</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>27</volume>, no.<issue>2</issue>:<fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r15">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Herring, Hal</string-name>.<article-title>“Dreaming of Home: A Conversation with Liberian Poet Patricia Jabbeh Wesley.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Bloomsbury Review</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>23</volume>, no.<issue>5</issue>(<year>2003</year>). Unpaginated.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r16">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>House, Humphrey</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Aristotle's Poetics: A Course of Eight Lectures</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Rupert Hart-Davis</publisher-name>,<year>1967</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r17">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Jabbeh Wesley, Patricia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Becoming Ebony</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Southern Illinois University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2003</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r18">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Jabbeh Wesley, Patricia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Before the Palm Could Bloom: Poems of Africa</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>New Issues Press</publisher-name>,<year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r19">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Jabbeh Wesley, Patricia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The River Is Rising</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Autumn House Press</publisher-name>,<year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r20">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Jabbeh Wesley, Patricia</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Where the Road Turns</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Autumn House Press</publisher-name>,<year>2010</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r21">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kearney, Richard</string-name>.<article-title>“Narrative and Ethics.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Proceedings of the Aristotelian Society</italic>
               </source>, supplementary volumes,<volume>70</volume>(<year>1996</year>):<fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r22">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kieh, George Klay</string-name>, Jr.<source>
                  <italic>The First Liberian Civil War: The Crises of Underdevelopment</italic>
               </source>. Society and Politics in Africa, vol.<volume>17</volume>.:<publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r23">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Levi, Primo</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Drowned and the Saved</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>,<year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r24">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Levi, Primo</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Survival in Auschwitz: The Nazi Assault on Humanity</italic>
               </source>. Translated by<string-name>Stuart Woolf</string-name>.:<publisher-name>A Touchstone Book</publisher-name>,<year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r25">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Maduka, Chidi T.</string-name>
               <article-title>“African Religious Beliefs in Literary Imagination: Ogbanje and Abiku in Chinua Achebe, J. P. Clark, and Wole Soyinka.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Journal of Commonwealth Literature</italic>
               </source>.<volume>22</volume>, no.<italic>1</italic>(<year>1987</year>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r26">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Nussbaum, Martha</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Upheavals of Though: The Intelligence of Emotions</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r27">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Okri, Ben</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Famished Road</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Jonathan Cape</publisher-name>,<year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r28">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Patruno, Nicholas</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Understanding Primo Levi</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of South Carolina Press</publisher-name>,<year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r29">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Pham, John-Peter</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Liberia: Portraits of a Failed State</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Reed</publisher-name>,<year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r30">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Reuters</string-name>.<article-title>“Liberia Troops Accused of Massacre in Church.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>New York Times</italic>
               </source>, July 31,<year>1990</year>.<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/1990/07/31/world/liberia-troops-accused-of-massacre-in-church.html">http://www.nytimes.com/1990/07/31/world/liberia-troops-accused-of-massacre-in-church.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r31">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Revell, Donald</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>The Art of Attention: A Poet's Eye</italic>
               </source>. Minneapolis, Minn. Graywolf Press,<year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r32">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<article-title>“Life in Quest of Narrative.”</article-title>In<source>
                  <italic>On Paul Ricoeur: Narrative and Interpretation</italic>
               </source>, edited by<string-name>David Wood</string-name>,<fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r33">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Soyinka, Wole</string-name>.<article-title>“Abiku.”</article-title>
               <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.cafeafrikana.com/poetry.html">www.cafeafrikana.com/poetry.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r34">
            <mixed-citation>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Road</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>,<year>1965</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r35">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Taylor, Paul A.</string-name>
               <article-title>“Sympathy and Insight in Aristotle's Poetics.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>66</volume>, no.<italic>3</italic>(<year>2008</year>):<fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r36">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ullman, B. L.</string-name>
               <article-title>“History and Tragedy.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>73</volume>(<year>1942</year>):<fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r37">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Wilson, Charles Morrow</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Black Africa in Microcosm</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harper and Row</publisher-name>,<year>1971</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
