<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">jroyaanthinst</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100913</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>The Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">13590987</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14679655</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23011571</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Words and things in Yucatán: poststructuralism and the everyday life of Mayan multiculturalism</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
                  <surname>Armstrong-Fumero</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>17</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23011305</issue-id>
         <fpage>63</fpage>
         <lpage>81</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2011 Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain &amp; Ireland</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:role="external-fulltext-any"
                   xlink:title="an external site"
                   xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9655.2010.01669.x"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article draws on ethnographic examples to examine how rural Maya-speakers in the Mexican state of Yucatán ground the experience of identity politics in quotidian engagements with pre-Hispanic objects and utterances in the Maya language. My argument is intended as a revision of models of critical scholarship that have been influenced by poststructuralism and that place an overwhelming emphasis on discourse as a modality through which politically viable identities are created and performed. Specific examples show how vernacular multiculturalism is shaped by the agency of forms of language use and physical objects that have been a part of local life-worlds long before the popularization of Mayan identity politics. This offers some potentials for collaborative work that have not been fully explored in poststructural critiques of representation. L'auteur s'appuie sur des exemples ethnographiques pour étudier la manière dont les locuteurs du maya vivant dans les zones rurales de l'état mexicain du Yucatán fondent leur expérience de la politique identitaire sur une interaction quotidienne avec les objets et énoncés préhispaniques de la langue maya. Son argumentation se veut une remise en cause des modèles universitaires critiques influencés par le poststructuralisme, qui mettent lourdement l'accent sur le discours en tant que modalité permettant de créer et de réaliser des identités politiquement viables. Des exemples concrets montrent comme un multiculturalisme vernaculaire se constitue par l'action des formes d'usage du langage et des objets matériels qui faisaient partie de la vie locale longtemps avant que la politique identitaire maya se popularise. Cette approche offre un potentiel de travail en collaboration qui n'a pas été complètement exploré par les critiques poststructuralistes de la représentation.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="d6378e116a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e123" publication-type="other">
Words and things (2005 [1959])</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="d6378e139a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e143" publication-type="other">
Abu el-Haj, N. 1998. Translating truths: nationalism, the practice of archaeology, and the remaking of the
past and present in contemporary Jerusalem. American Ethnologist 25,166-88.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e153a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e157" publication-type="other">
Ahmad, A. 1991. Between Orientalism and historicism: anthropological knowledge of India. Studies in
History 7,135-63.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e167a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e171" publication-type="other">
Amaro Gamboa, J. 1999. Vocabulario del uayeismo en la cultura de Yucatdn. Merida: UADY.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e178a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e182" publication-type="other">
Arias, A. (ed.) 2001. The Rigoberta Menchti controversy. Minneapolis: Univeristy of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e190a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e194" publication-type="other">
Armstrong-Fumero, F. 2009a. A heritage of ambiguity: the historical substrate of vernacular multicultur-
alism in Yucatdn, Mexico. American Ethnologist 36, 299-316.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e204a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e208" publication-type="other">
—2009b. Old jokes and new multiculturalisms. American Anthropologist 111,360-72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e215a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e219" publication-type="other">
Bartra, R. 2002. Blood, ink, and culture: miseries and splendors of the post-Mexican condition. Durham, N.C.:
Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e229a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e233" publication-type="other">
Bauman, R. &amp; C.L. Briggs 2003. Voices of modernity: language ideologies and the politics of inequality.
Cambridge: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e243a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e247" publication-type="other">
Berkley, A. 1998. Revitalization and remembrance: the archive of pure Maya. Ph.D. dissertation, Department
of Anthropology, University of Chicago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e257a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e261" publication-type="other">
Beverley, J. &amp; J. Oviedo 1995. Introduction. In The postmodernism debate in Latin America (eds) J. Beverley,
J. Oviedo &amp; M. Aronna, 1-18. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e272a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e276" publication-type="other">
Breglia, L. 2006. Monumental ambivalence: the politics of heritage. Austin: Univeristy of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e283a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e287" publication-type="other">
Brunhouse, R. 1971. Sylvanus G. Morley and the world of the ancient Mayas. Norman: Oklahoma University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e297a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e301" publication-type="other">
Burns, A. 1983. An epoch of miracles: oral literature of the Yucatec Maya. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e308a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e312" publication-type="other">
Carrillo y Ancona, C. 1863. Arqueologia de las ruinas de Yucatan. Repertorio Pintoresco 1:1,129-33,300-2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e319a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e323" publication-type="other">
Castaneda, Q. 1996. In the museum of Maya culture: touring Chichen Itza. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e333a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e337" publication-type="other">
—2003. New and old social movements: measuring Piste, from the 'mouth of the well' to the 107th
Municipio of Yucatdn. Ethnohistory 50, 611-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e348a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e352" publication-type="other">
—2004. Art-writing in the modern Maya art world of Chichen Itzd: transcultural ethnography and
experimental fieldwork. American Ethnologist 31, 21-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e362a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e366" publication-type="other">
—&amp; C. Matthews (eds) 2008. Ethnographic archaeologies: reflections on stakeholders and archaeological
practices. Lanham, Md: AltaMira.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e376a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e380" publication-type="other">
Castillo Cocom, J. 2005. 'It was simply their word': Yucatec Maya PRInces in YucaPAN and the politics of
respect. Critique of Anthropology 25:131,132-55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e390a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e394" publication-type="other">
Cifuentes, B. 2002. Lenguas para un pasado, huellas de una nacidn: los estudios sobre las lenguas indigenas de
Mixico en el siglo XIX. M&amp;cico: CONACULTA-INAH.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e404a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e408" publication-type="other">
Collier, G. &amp; E. Quaratiello 2005. Basta! Land and the Zapatista Rebellion. Oakland: Food First Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e415a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e419" publication-type="other">
Domanska, E. 2006. The material presence of the past. History and Theory 45, 337-48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e427a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e431" publication-type="other">
England, N. 2003. Mayan language revival and revitalization politics: linguists and linguistic ideologies.
American Anthropologist 105, 733-43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e441a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e445" publication-type="other">
Fischer, T. 1999. Cultural logic and Maya identity: rethinking constructivism and essentialism. Current
Anthropology 40, 473-99.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e455a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e459" publication-type="other">
—&amp; R.M. Brown (eds) 1996. Maya cultural activism in Guatemala. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e466a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e470" publication-type="other">
Foucault, M. 1980 [1976]. Two lectures. In Power/knowledge: selected interviews and other writings, 1972-1977
(ed.) C. Gordon, 78-108. New York: Pantheon.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e480a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e484" publication-type="other">
—1994 [1970]. The order of things. New York: Vintage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e491a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e495" publication-type="other">
Gabbert, W. 2004. Becoming Maya: ethnicity and social inequality in Yucatan since 1300. Tucson: University
of Arizona Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e506a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e510" publication-type="other">
Gell, A. 1998. Art and agency: an anthropological theory. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e517a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e521" publication-type="other">
Gellner, E. 2005 [1959]. Words and things: an examination of, and an attack on, linguistic philosophy. New
York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e531a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e535" publication-type="other">
Genette, G. 1983. Narrative discourse: an essay in method. Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e542a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e546" publication-type="other">
Gobierno del Estado de Yucatan 2004. Programa estatal de desarrollo del pueblo Maya 2001-2007
(available on-line: http://www.indemaya.gob.mx/descargas/archivos/plan-desarrollo-puehlo-maya.pdf,
accessed 26 October 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e559a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e563" publication-type="other">
Graham, I. 2002. Alfred Maudslay and the Maya. London: The British Museum Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e570a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e574" publication-type="other">
Hale, C. 1999. Travel warning: elite appropriations of hybridity, mestizaje, antiracism, equality and other
progressive-sounding discourses in Highland Guatemala. Journal of American Folklore 112: 445, 297-315.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e585a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e589" publication-type="other">
Hervik, P. 1999. Mayan people within and beyond boundaries: social categories and lived identity in Yucatan.
Amsterdam: Harwood Academic.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e599a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e603" publication-type="other">
-&amp; H.E. Kahn 2006. Scholarly surrealism: the persistence of Mayanness. Critique of Anthropology 26:
9, 209-32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e617" publication-type="other">
Hodder, I. 2003. Sustainable time travel: toward a global politics of the past. In Politics of archaeology and
identity in a global context (ed.) S. Kane, 139-47. Boston: Archaeological Institute of America.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e627a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e631" publication-type="other">
Jameson, E 1972. The prison house of language: a critical account of structuralism and Russian formalism.
Princeton: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e641a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e645" publication-type="other">
Latour, B. 1999. Pandora's hope: essays on the reality of science studies. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e655a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e659" publication-type="other">
Marcus, G. &amp; J. Fischer 1986. Anthropology as cultural critique. Chicago: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e667a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e671" publication-type="other">
Maxwell, J. 1996. Prescriptive grammar and Kaqchikel revitalization. In Maya cultural activism in Guate-
mala (eds) E. Fischer &amp; R.M. Brown, 178-94. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e681a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e685" publication-type="other">
May, T. 1997. Reconsidering difference: Nancy, Derrida, Levinas, and Deleuze. College Park: Pennsylvania State
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e695a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e699" publication-type="other">
Megill, A. 1985. Prophets of extremity: Nietzsche, Heidegger, Foucault, Derrida. Berkeley: University of Cali-
fornia Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e709a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e713" publication-type="other">
Miller, D. 2005. Materiality: an introduction. In Materiality (ed.) D. Miller, 1-50. Durham, N.C.: Duke
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e723a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e727" publication-type="other">
Montejo, V. 2005. Maya intellectual renaissance: identity, representation and leadership. Austin: University of
Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e737a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e741" publication-type="other">
Nelson, D. 1999. A finger in the wound: body politics in quincentennial Guatemala. Berkeley: Univeristy of
California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e752a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e756" publication-type="other">
Pendergast, D. 2005. Engineering problems in ancient Maya architecture: past, present and future. Envi-
ronmental Geology 16, 67-73</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e766a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e770" publication-type="other">
Pfeiler, B. &amp; L. Zamisia 2006. Bilingual education: strategy for language maintenance or language shift of
Yucatec Maya? In Mexican indigenous languages at the dawn of the twenty-first century (ed.) M. Hidalgo,
281-300. Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e783a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e787" publication-type="other">
Povinelli, E. 2002. The cunning of recognition: indigenous alterities and the making of Australian multicul-
turalism. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e797a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e801" publication-type="other">
Redfield, R. 1932. Maya archaeology as the Mayas see it. Sociologus: Zeitschrift filr Volker-psychologie und
Soziologie 8, 299-309.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e811a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e815" publication-type="other">
-&amp; S. Tax 1952. General characteristics of present-day Mesoamerican Indian society. In Heritage of
conquest: the ethnology of Middle America (ed.) S. Tax &amp; the Members of the Viking Fund Seminar on
Middle American Ethnology, 29-40. Glencoe, 111.: Free Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e828a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e832" publication-type="other">
-&amp; A. Villa Rojas 1934. Chan Kom: a Maya village. Washington, D.C.: The Carnegie Institute.
Restall, M. 1997a. Heirs to the hieroglyphs: indigenous writing in colonial Mesoamerica. The Americas 54,
239-67-</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e846a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e850" publication-type="other">
-1997b- The Maya world: Yucatec culture and society 1550-1850. Stanford: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e857a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e861" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. 1994. One's self as another. Chicago: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e868a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e872" publication-type="other">
-2006. On translation (thinking in action). New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e879a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e883" publication-type="other">
Rorty, R. 1998. Achieving our country: leftist thought in twentieth-century America. Cambridge, Mass.:
Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e893a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e897" publication-type="other">
Roys, R.L. 1943. The Indian background of colonial Yucatan. Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institute of
Washington.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e907a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e911" publication-type="other">
Schieffelin, B. 2000. Introducing Kaluli literacy: a chronology of influences. In Regimes of language (ed.) P.
Kroskrity, 293-328. Santa Fe: School of American Research.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e922a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e926" publication-type="other">
-&amp; R.C. Doucet 1994. The 'real' Haitian Creole: ideology, metalinguistics and orthographic choice.
American Ethnologist 21,176-200.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e936a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e940" publication-type="other">
Spivak, G. 1987. In other words: essays in cultural politics. New York: Methuen.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e947a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e951" publication-type="other">
Stoll, D. 1999. Rigoberta Menchu and the story of all poor Guatemalans. Boulder, Colo.: Westview.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e958a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e962" publication-type="other">
Tax, S. &amp; the Members of the Viking Fund Seminar on Middle American Ethnology (eds) 1952.
Heritage of conquest: the ethnology of Middle America. Glencoe, 111.: Free Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e972a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e976" publication-type="other">
Thompson, J.E. 1970. Maya history and religion. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e983a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e987" publication-type="other">
Tyler, S. 1986. Post-modern ethnography: from document of the occult to occult document. In Writing
culture (eds) J. Clifford &amp; G. Marcus, 122-30. Berkeley: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e998a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1002" publication-type="other">
Urry, J. 1990. The tourist gaze: leisure and travel in contemporary societies. London: Sage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e1009a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1013" publication-type="other">
Voloshinov, V.N., L. Matejka &amp; I.R. Titunik 1973. Marxism and the philosophy of language. New York:
Seminar Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e1023a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1027" publication-type="other">
Warren, K. 1998. Indigenous movements and their critics: Pan-Maya activism in Guatemala. Princeton:
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e1037a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1041" publication-type="other">
White, H. 1987. The content of form: narrative discourse and historical representation. Baltimore: Johns
Hopkins University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e1051a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1055" publication-type="other">
Williams, R. 1977. Marxism and literature. Oxford: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d6378e1062a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d6378e1066" publication-type="other">
Yashar, D. 2005. Contesting citizenship in Latin America: the rise of indigenous movements and the postliheral
challenge. Cambridge: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
