<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">comparatist</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013777</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Comparatist</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01957678</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15590887</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26237235</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>ESSAYS</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>RE-ORIENTALISM: GERMAN INDOLOGY STUDIES BEYOND FOUCAULT AND GADAMER</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>“Either a Hermeneutical Consciousness or a Critical Consciousness”</article-title>
            <subtitle>Renegotiating Theories of the Germany-India Encounter</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>HERLIGN</surname>
                  <given-names>BRADLEY L.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Marymount Manhattan College</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>MAY 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26237226</issue-id>
         <fpage>63</fpage>
         <lpage>79</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2010 Southern Comparative Literature Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26237235"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benes, Tuska. In Babel’s Shadow: Language, Philology, and the Nation in Nineteenth-Century Germany. Detriot: Wayne State University Press, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy M. Aryans, Jews, Brahmins: Theorizing Authority through Myths of Identity. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy M.. The Exotic: A Decadent Quest. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fleck, Ludwik. Genesis and Development of a Scientific Fact. Trans. Fred Bradley and Thaddeus J. Trenn. Eds. Thaddeus Trenn and Robert K. Merton. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Foucault, Michel. Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison. New York: Routledge, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gadamer, Hans-Georg. Truth and Method. 2nd ed. Trans. Joel Weinsheimer and Donald G. Marshall. New York: Continuum, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germana, Nicholas. The Orient of Europe: The Mythical Image of India and Competing Images of German National Identity. Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Halbfass, Wihelm. India and Europe: An Essay in Philosophical Understanding. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herder, Johann Gottfried. God: Some Conversations. Trans. Frederick H. Burkhardt. New York: Veritas Press, 1940.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. “Epilinguistic Hypophecy: August Wilhelm Schlegel’s Latin Bhagavadgītā.” Epilanguages: Beyond Idioms and Languages. Ed. Pascale Catharine Hummel. Paris: Philologicum, 2009. 95–122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. The German Gītā: Hermeneutics and Discipline in the German Reception of Indian Thought, 1778–1831. London: Routledge, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. “The Problem of Action in the Early German Interpretation of the Bhagavadgītā.” Mapping Channels between the Ganges and the Rhein. Eds. Joerg Esleben, Christina Kraenzle, and Sukanya Kulkarni. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2008. 82–106.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Humboldt, Wilhelm von. “Ueber die unter dem Namen Bhagavad-Gîtâ bekannte Episode des Mahâ-Bhârata [I and II].” Gesammelte Schriften. Vol. 5. 1906; reprint, Berlin: Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co., 1968. 190–232, 325–44.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inden, Ronald. Imagining India. Bloomington and Indianapolis: Indiana University Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">King, Richard. Orientalism and Religion: Postcolonial Theory, India and ‘The Mystic East.’ London: Routledge, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kontje, Todd. German Orientalisms. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lincoln, Bruce. Theorizing Myth: Narrative, Ideology, and Scholarship. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchand, Suzanne L. German Orientalism in the Age of Empire: Religion, Race, and Scholarship. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchignoli, Saverio. “Canonizing an Indian Text? A.W. Schlegel, W. von Humboldt, Hegel, and the Bhagavadgītā.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K.J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 245–70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, Paul. Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on Interpretation. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, Paul. “Hermeneutics and the Critique of Ideology.” Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences. Ed. and trans. John B. Thompson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993. 63–100.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Said, Edward. Orientalism. New York: Vintage Books, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schlegel, August Wilhelm von, trans. Bhagavad-Gītā, id est Thespesion Melos sive Almi Krishnae et Arjunae Colloquium de Rebus Divinis, Bharatae Episodium. Bonn: Edward Weber, 1823.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schlegel, Friedrich. “Gespräch über Poesie.” Kritische Friedrich-Schlegel-Ausgabe. Vol. 2. Ed. Ernst Behler. Paderborn: Schöningh, 1967. 284–98.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schlegel, Friedrich. Über die Sprache und Weisheit der Indier. Kritische Friedrich-Schlegel-Ausgabe. Vol. 8. Eds. Ernst Behler and Ursula Struc-Oppenberg. Paderborn: Schöningh, 1975. 105–433.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schlegel, Friedrich. “On the Language and Wisdom of the Indians.” The Aesthetic and Miscellaneous Works of Frederick von Schlegel. Trans. E.J. Millington. London: Henry G. Bohn, 1849. 425–526.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Weigle, G.H. Preface to “Essay on the Episode of the Mahabharat, Known by the Name of Bhagvat-Geeta; by Baron William de Humboldt.” The Bhagvat-Geeta, Dialogues of Krishna and Arjoon; in Eighteen Lectures. Ed. J. Garrett. Bangalore: The Wesleyan Mission Press, 1849. 121.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wilkins, Charles, trans. The Bhagvat-Geeta. 1785. Reprint, Delmar, N.Y.: Scholars’ Facsimiles &amp; Reprints, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williamson, George S. The Longing for Myth in Germany: Religion and Aesthetic Culture from Romanticism to Nietzsche. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Willson, A. Leslie. A Mythical Image: The Ideal of India in German Romanticism. Durham: Duke University Press, 1964.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
