<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591495</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/431810</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR850402</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Interreligious Dialogue as a Politics of Recognition: A Postcolonial Rereading of Hegel for Interreligious Solidarity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Hyo‐Dong</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Lee</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Hobart and William Smith Colleges</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>October 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>555</fpage>
         <lpage>581</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2005 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/431810"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Interreligious Dialogue and Its Critics</title>
         <p>The idea of interreligious dialogue has in the last decade or so been brought under some serious questioning in Christian theology, especially in regard to the efforts made by the proponents of religious pluralism to find on either theoretical or practical grounds a common base and starting point for interreligious dialogue. The postliberal and neotraditionalist critics of pluralism have objected to such an attempt on the basis of the alleged incommensurability and nonconvergence of religions and the need for each religion to confess itself in all its particularity in order to resist the imperial and universalist agenda of secular liberal modernity. Thus, if these opponents of pluralism do not reject the idea of interreligious dialogue altogether, they regard it at best as occasional, ad hoc apologetics or the work of evangelization and witness in another form.</p>
         <p>In this essay I intend to defend the idea of interreligious dialogue, while moving the discussion forward in light of its critics, by making a case for reconfiguring it as a practice of political theology with the help of the Hegelian notion of “mutual recognition.” I will begin by arguing, against postliberalism and neotraditionalism, for the necessity of reconceiving the idea of interreligious dialogue as a form of “politics of recognition” within today’s postcolonial‐neocolonial global context. I will show that the Hegelian notion of mutual recognition, especially when qualified by Frantz Fanon’s postcolonial rereading of it, can be the key for such a reconception insofar as it provides a model of interreligious relationship within a common polity that rejects relations of domination and exclusion while nurturing a sense of solidarity among religious communities. I will then further develop this model in the direction of a “dialectic” of theology of religions and comparative theology with an eye to avoiding the pitfall of spurious recognition present in the discourses of multiculturalism and identity politics. With the help of cultural studies and postcolonial criticism, I will bring the essay to conclusion by further reconfiguring the dialectic in a manner that guards against the falsely homogenizing discourse of religious “identity” while helping to construct a politically unifying narrative of resistance that is interreligiously hybrid in nature.</p>
         <p>For the last two decades or so, Christian theological advocates of religious pluralism have argued for a paradigm shift that would enable Christians finally to move away from their millennia‐long insistence on the superiority and finality of their way, whether in its exclusivist or inclusivist version, and to recognize the equal and independent validity of other religions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>Such a paradigm shift, the pluralists have claimed, is to be made on the basis of theoretical explications of some reality or mystery underlying all religions or some commonly exhibited historical traits among them or else on the basis of the strength of some shared practical concerns that all religions have in face of the commonly experienced reality of injustice and suffering in the world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>The critics of pluralism have objected to the notion of interreligious dialogue as championed by the pluralists precisely because it is seen to presuppose such a paradigm shift as its necessary precondition. There is a great variety of angles from which these critics of pluralism speak, but they can more or less be called “confessional pluralists,” in the sense that their overarching concern is that the raw and often galling confessional differences found among the actual beliefs and practices of different religions be preserved to ensure each religion's fidelity to its tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The critics of pluralism who approach the question of religious difference from a cultural‐linguistic or “postliberal” perspective, notably George Lindbeck, Paul Griffiths, and J. A. DiNoia, claim that, just as each language constitutes a semiotic “world” not reducible to another, religious traditions form culturally and linguistically distinct communities of discourse and practice that are mutually incommensurable.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>Religious scriptures and doctrines, they contend, function both as the rules shaping and governing the communal life of each religious community and as the “lens” through which everything is interpreted and reinscribed “intratextually” within its semiotic world. Such a grammatical and interpretive function of scriptures and doctrines, they argue, confers the characteristics of centrality and comprehensiveness upon the truth claims made by religious communities—the characteristics that render those truth claims very difficult, if not impossible, to reconcile with one another.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The postliberal emphasis upon the cultural‐linguistic and communal nature of religious traditions resonates with the neotraditionalist critics of pluralism, notably John Milbank and Stanley Hauerwas, who situate the issue of religious plurality within the sociopolitical context of Western modernity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>Western modernity, they argue, consists in the Enlightenment project of universalizing reason by means of domestication of tradition, a project in which religious traditions and their truth claims are summoned to the court of the allegedly universal reason and reduced to matters of culturally relative and subjective tastes. Thus shorn of any objective reality and public truth value and thereby deprived of any staying power to challenge the rule of universal reason in the form of alternative cultural visions and social projects, diverse religious traditions are now given equal status by the secular liberal nation‐state as private affairs of its individual citizens. Pluralism, these critics contend, is founded upon this “repressive tolerance” of Western modernity, as can be seen, for example, in the way that the rules of interreligious dialogue proposed by the advocates of pluralism either try to bar from the outset any claim of uniqueness, superiority, and finality or demand that the participants of the dialogue first submit to a universal ethical imperative, such as the notion of justice allegedly shared by all religions, which in the view of the critics is very much a product of the modern Western culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>As a strategy of resistance to this liberal imperialism, neotraditionalism together with postliberalism call for Christianity’s aggressive confession of itself in all its particularity, including its traditional claim to superiority and finality and its faithful ecclesial practice of its central narratives and texts, in order to retain its distinct identity and alternative social space against the encroachment of secular liberal modernity.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>The exclusivist version is the claim that salvation requires an explicit faith in Jesus Christ and that other religions are therefore of little or no value, and the inclusivist version is the position that other religions have salvific significance but only by virtue of the hidden and unrecognized redemptive work of Christ in them, requiring their fulfillment in Christianity. The typology of exclusivism, inclusivism, and pluralism was introduced by Alan Race in<italic>Christians and Religious Pluralism: Patterns in the Christian Theology of Religions</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1982), 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>As suggested by the programmatic volume<italic>The Myth of Christian Uniqueness</italic>, which is a kind of pluralist “manifesto.” John Hick and Paul F. Knitter, eds.,<italic>The Myth of Christian Uniqueness: Toward a Pluralistic Theology of Religions</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1987).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>The term “confessional pluralists” comes from Anselm Min’s very helpful alternative typology of pluralism, which classifies pluralism into five categories and includes the critics of pluralism. See Anselm Kyongsuk Min, “Dialectical Pluralism and Solidarity of Others: Towards a New Paradigm,”<italic>Journal of the American Academy of Religion</italic>65, no. 3 (1997): 587–88.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>“Postliberal” is the term used by George A. Lindbeck in his<italic>The Nature of Doctrine: Religion and Theology in a Postliberal Age</italic>(Philadelphia: Westminster, 1984), 113, 135 n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Ibid., 30–45; J. A. DiNoia, “Pluralist Theology of Religions: Pluralistic or Non‐Pluralistic?” in<italic>Christian Uniqueness Reconsidered: The Myth of a Pluralistic Theology of Religions</italic>, ed. Gavin D’Costa (Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1990), 122–28; Paul J. Griffiths, “The Uniqueness of Christian Doctrine Defended,” in ibid., 157–73, and<italic>Problems of Religious Diversity</italic>(Oxford and Malden, MA: Blackwell, 2001).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>“Neotraditionalism” comes from Jeffrey Stout’s term “new traditionalism” in his<italic>Democracy and Tradition</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2004), 2. For the neotraditionalist critique of secular liberalism and pluralism, see John Milbank,<italic>Theology and Social Theory: Beyond Secular Reason</italic>(Oxford and Cambridge, MA: Blackwell, 1990), and “The End of Dialogue,” in D'Costa, ed.,<italic>Christian Uniqueness Reconsidered</italic>, 174–91; William T. Cavanaugh,<italic>Theopolitical Imagination</italic>(London: T&amp;T Clark, 2002); Leslie Newbigin,<italic>The Gospel in a Pluralist Society</italic>(Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans; Geneva: WCC Publications, 1989), and “Religion for the Marketplace,” in D'Costa, ed.,<italic>Christian Uniqueness Reconsidered</italic>, 135–48; Stanley Hauerwas,<italic>A Better Hope: Resources for a Church Confronting Capitalism, Democracy, and Postmodernity</italic>(Grand Rapids, MI: Brazos, 2000), and<italic>After Christendom? How the Church Is to Behave if Freedom, Justice, and a Christian Nation Are Bad Ideas</italic>(Nashville: Abingdon, 1991).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Concerning the “repressive tolerance” of Western modernity, see Stanley Hauerwas and William H. Willimon,<italic>Resident Aliens: A Provocative Christian Assessment of Culture and Ministry for People Who Know That Something Is Wrong</italic>(Nashville: Abingdon, 1989), 41. For the “ground rules” of interreligious dialogue, see Leonard Swidler, “Interreligious and Interideological Dialogue: The Matrix for All Systematic Reflection Today,” in<italic>Toward a Universal Theology of Religion</italic>, ed. Leonard Swidler (Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1987), 13–16. For the critique of the pluralist criteria of justice, see Milbank, “End of Dialogue,” 185–88; Newbigin, “Religion,” 146–47. See also S. Mark Heim,<italic>Salvations: Truth and Difference in Religion</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1995), 91–98.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>The Postcolonial‐Neocolonial Context Needs Solidary Pluralism<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>
         </title>
         <p>Whether or not the picture of liberalism and pluralism that these critics paint is entirely fair and accurate, it must be admitted that their emphasis on the nature of religions as radically different communal‐social practices is certainly a welcome reality check for any overenthusiastic and premature envisioning of the harmony of all religions and even their convergence.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>Furthermore, their—especially the neotraditionalists'—exposure of the political concerns of the modern West underlying the pluralist discourse is perhaps their most significant contribution to the subject of interreligious dialogue. Yet if their untiring emphasis on the particularity of each religious community does not make them reject interreligious dialogue altogether, it leads them to regard the latter at best either as ad hoc apologetics necessitated by the merely occasional and tangential encounters of the largely isolated cultural‐linguistic enclaves that are religions or as the work of evangelization and conversion in another garb that follows the innate logic of the universalizing horizon of Christianity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>As analyses of and positive proposals for interreligious relationships rather than interreligious differences, however, these positions overall fail to take adequately into account the postcolonial or neocolonial character of the concrete economic, political, and cultural context of today’s religious plurality. The so‐called global village and the culturally and religiously plural nation‐states of today are largely products of a colonial and postcolonial history in which the centuries‐long imposition of relations of economic, political, and cultural dominance and subservience has closely interwoven the fate of different communities and brought them into a common space of living. The birth of new ethnically and religiously plural nation‐states along the arbitrarily drawn boundaries of the colonial governing units, the forces of neocolonial global economy and the increasing economic, political, and cultural subservience of the two‐thirds world to the first world, the mass displacement and migration of people from the peripheries of the former colonial empires to the metropolitan centers, the explosion of mass media and information technologies—all these have conspired, since the end of the World War II and the beginning of political decolonization, to bring the religions of the world as they are actually lived and practiced into the very neighborhoods and doorsteps of one another.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>To an unprecedented degree, different religious communities across the world are pushed by the forces of postcolonial history to inhabit not merely neighboring spaces but a common economic, political, and cultural space and in so doing to become constituents of a larger, more encompassing human community.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>
         </p>
         <p>What the critics of interreligious dialogue seem to gloss over is the fact that, even if the secular liberal nation‐state or the international order of global capitalism is exposed as no truly universal community under whose umbrella religious communities are to stand merely as intermediate associations, the latter as cultural‐linguistic enclaves and alternative social spaces still find themselves today having already become constituents of a wider, more encompassing common space of living seared by the violent legacy of recent colonial history and its postcolonial‐neocolonial aftermath. For example, in their eagerness to resist what they see as the present colonization of this common space by the secular nation‐state and global capitalism, the neotraditionalist critics suggest a picture of interreligious relations that appears to call for an alternative colonization of that same space by the universal church. John Milbank, notably, argues for substituting the idea of interreligious dialogue with what he calls “conversation,” which he defines as the work of conversion carried out in a spirit of mutual suspicion and with the aim of subverting the essentially violent discourses of other religions—such as Hinduism—by baptizing whatever peaceable discourse found in them as anomalous typological anticipations of the essentially nonviolent Christian Logos.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>The rhetorical violence of this contention, made in the context of Great Britain, whose colonial and postcolonial history has brought millions of Hindus, Sikhs, and Muslims to live in London, Leicester, Birmingham, and so on, makes one wonder what kind of alternative social space he envisions the church to be for the former colonial subjects if the capitalist, liberal, and pluralist nation‐state is ever forced to relinquish its alleged monopoly on social space.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>The picture of interreligious relations drawn by Leslie Newbigin and Stanley Hauerwas is not very different in the sense that for them interreligious relations consists essentially in the work of witnessing by the church with the express aim of universalizing its alternative social space and turning it into a universal Christian dominion, that is, a new Christendom minus the kind of violence that plagued its previous incarnation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>But however much Milbank and Hauerwas claim the new Christendom to be an intrinsically nonviolent order or a “complex space” respectful of differences, the “alternative economies and authorities” allowed to flourish in that space must be ones that acknowledge the peaceable lordship of Christ and participate in the triune life of God as members of the Body of Christ.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>Those that do not do so would be either excluded from that space or at best allowed to inhabit it as subalterns, since—with the possible exception of Platonic and Jewish discourses, as Milbank claims—they constitute essentially violent, “pagan” economies of the “world” fundamentally at odds with the nonviolent economy of the church.</p>
         <p>The unreservedly militant rhetoric of these critics of pluralism reveals that, in their preoccupation with countering what they view as the totalizing and falsely universalizing agenda of the secular liberal nation‐state and global capitalism, they make the mistake of treating the present plight of the church as that of just another oppressed tribe standing alongside others, such as the Cherokee or the Maya. What they seem to fail to acknowledge is that the universal church is made up of different communities living different histories along geopolitical boundaries, including the European and Euro‐American Christian communities that historically have played and still play the dominant role within it, and that therefore the universal church cannot so easily and so soon be exonerated from the history of its complicity with Western imperialism and colonialism in which it availed itself of the power of the colonizing empires to spread its hegemony and influence across the globe.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>Less than half a century after formal decolonization and in face of the ongoing neocolonial hegemony of the former colonizing nation‐states with which the church has colluded, such a claim of universal dominion and “self‐congratulatory competitiveness” on the part of the church today cannot help being a rhetorical exercise of violence, stirring up the scarring and still threatening memory of its recent universalizing violence.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>Any call made by the church today for a thorough disestablishment and de‐Constantinization of itself must therefore first be accompanied by an earnest gesture of “owning up” to its past and redressing this historical wrong.</p>
         <p>Insofar as interreligious relations are concerned, then, what is demanded of Christian communities first and foremost by the exigencies of inhabiting the common postcolonial/neocolonial space of living is neither an alternative colonization of that space by the supposedly peaceable Christian dominion nor a mere pursuit of self‐identity on the part of Christian communities as cultural‐linguistic enclaves but rather an effort made by Christian communities to inhabit the common space in such a way that their presence would not only be nonthreatening to other religious communities but also be conducive to forging a sense of solidarity among all the coinhabitants of that space. In other words, the task laid before the de‐Constantinizing church is that of making its own small contribution to the solidarity of different religious communities with the goal of organizing that common space into an order free of domination and exclusion in opposition to the “new world order.” In order for this to be possible, then, it is imperative that religious communities reach some kind of consensus on the conditions of peaceful coexistence and coflourishing, on the one hand, and solidary action, on the other. But if the communities are to reach such a consensus, they must first be able to practice genuine dialogue, that is, authentic communication free of relations of domination and exclusion, so that the consensus reached may not be a product of the hegemonic and falsely universalizing agenda of those communities with more resources and power.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>For this term, I am indebted to Min’s notion of “solidarity of others,” which refers to the kind of solidarity in which “no group is a privileged center, where all of us are ‘other’ to one another in religion, culture, language, and ethnic origin.” Min, “Dialectical Pluralism,” 589.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>For a defense of liberalism and pluralism, see, among others, Stout,<italic>Democracy and Tradition</italic>; Christopher J. Insole, “Against Radical Orthodoxy: The Dangers of Overcoming Political Liberalism,”<italic>Modern Theology</italic>20, no. 2 (2004): 213–41.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>The term “ad hoc apologetics,” originally coined by Hans Frei, is taken from Lindbeck,<italic>Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 129. Paul J. Griffiths develops this notion to argue that every interreligious dialogue should be in the form of occasional (nonsystematic) and nonfoundational interreligious apologetics in the sense of defense and formal justification of one’s doctrines. See Griffiths,<italic>An Apology for Apologetics: A Study in the Logic of Interreligious Dialogue</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1991), 1–18. For the confessional‐pluralist recasting of interreligious dialogue in terms of conversion or giving witness, see Milbank, “End of Dialogue,” 189–90; Newbigin,<italic>Gospel</italic>, 181–82.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>This is especially true in what used to be the heartland of Christianity, namely, Europe and North America, where the religious landscape in recent decades has been palpably changed by the migration of people from Asia and Africa. See Shireen Hunter, ed.,<italic>Islam, Europe’s Second Religion: The New Social, Cultural, and Political Landscape</italic>(Westport, CN: Praeger, 2002); Diana L. Eck,<italic>A New Religious America: How a “Christian Country” Has Now Become the World’s Most Religiously Diverse Nation</italic>(San Francisco: HarperSanFrancisco, 2001). For the postcolonial character of the migration, see Peter Kivisto,<italic>Multiculturalism in a Global Society</italic>(Oxford and Malden, MA: Blackwell, 2002), 1–6; D. George Boyce,<italic>Decolonisation and the British Empire, 1775–1997</italic>( London: MacMillan; New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1999), 246–55; Terence Ranger, Yunas Samad, and Ossie Stuart, eds.,<italic>Culture, Identity and Politics: Ethnic Minorities in Britain</italic>(Aldershot: Avebury, 1996); Alec G. Hargreaves and Mark McKinney, “Introduction: The Post‐colonial Problematic in France,” in<italic>Post‐colonial Cultures in France</italic>, ed. Alec G. Hargreaves and Mark McKinney (London and New York: Routledge, 1997), 3–25.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>I am using the word “community” somewhat loosely for the larger human community or the international community, that is, without implying the communitarian notion of community formed around a definite notion of common good. The common economic, political, and cultural space, be it local or transnational, refers in that sense to a much more tangible, physical reality of togetherness, i.e., a common geopolitical space. In addition to the formerly colonizing Western nation‐states, instances of religiously and ethnically plural nations born in the aftermath of decolonization are numerous—India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Sudan, South Africa, Northern Ireland, to name just a few—of which some have been secular (such as India and Indonesia) and some have not (such as Sudan). On the transnational level, there is a kind of global culture and institutions emerging from the gradually forming consensus in the international community on what constitutes the minimum conditions of human well‐being, such as the global culture of human rights undergirded by the International Criminal Court or the mandate for environmental stewardship stipulated by various global accords and treaties, all goaded on and further challenged by a global coalitional politics of various nongovernmental organizations and social movements against the neocolonial, labor‐exploitive, and environmentally destructive forces of global capitalism. For the emergence of the global culture of human rights and the challenges made against it in the name of religious and cultural identity, see Michael Singer, “Relativism, Culture, Religion, and Identity,” in<italic>Religious Fundamentalisms and the Human Rights of Women</italic>, ed. Courtney W. Howland (New York: Palgrave, 2001), 45–54; Radhika Coomaraswamy, “Different but Free: Cultural Relativism and Women's Rights as Human Rights” in ibid.,79–90.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Milbank, “End of Dialogue,” 189–90. Milbank not only contrasts his idealized reading of Christianity with what he considers the intrinsic violence and nihilism of Western modernity but also lumps non‐Christian religions—with the possible exception of Platonic and Jewish discourses—together as violent metanarratives (Milbank, “End of Dialogue,” 185–90). His sweeping and little substantiated characterization of “the East” as inherently violent, which is based merely on his reading of Georges Dumézil’s controversial interpretation of Hinduism, refuses to acknowledge the presence in it of peaceful analogs to Christianity, such as Buddhism, as anything other than “‘typological’ anticipations of the Christian<italic>Logos</italic>” inconsistent with and anomalous to the fundamentally violent character of “the East” (basically arguing that Buddhism has to be actually Greek, Jewish, and Christian in spirit).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>Milbank would object that the church does not claim any territory and therefore cannot colonize any social space. Based on his idealized reading of Christianity as the only peaceful social project more postmodern than any other metanarrative, he claims that the church is a “nomad city” with no territory of its own, having rejected the violence of establishing itself territorially. See John Milbank, “‘Postmodern Critical Augustinianism’: A Short<italic>Summa</italic>in Forty‐Two Responses to Unasked Questions,”<italic>Modern Theology</italic>7, no. 3 (1991): 225–37. But insofar as he maintains that the church is a separate society, I do not see how it can be without a physical and social space to inhabit—as a society the church must have its own institutions of economic production and distribution, education, health service, etc., and that requires establishing itself in a space of living. See, on this note, Kathryn Tanner,<italic>Theory of Culture: A New Agenda for Theology</italic>(Minneapolis: Fortress, 1997), 93–119.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Hauerwas,<italic>A Better Hope</italic>, 44–45, where he endorses Gerald Schlabach’s characterization of his position as a vision of nonviolent Christendom. See also Hauerwas,<italic>After Christendom?</italic>151–52. For Newbigin, see his<italic>Gospel</italic>, 181–82.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>For the notion of “complex space,” see John Milbank,<italic>The Word Made Strange: Theology, Language, Culture</italic>(Oxford and Cambridge, MA: Blackwell, 1997), 274–92. The phrase “alternative economies and authorities” is taken from William T. Cavanaugh, “Killing for the Telephone Company: Why the Nation‐State Is Not the Keeper of the Common Good,” in<italic>Modern Theology</italic>20, no. 2 (2004): 267.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>For the pivotal role played by the missionary propagation of the Bible, namely, the Authorized Version, in the colonial project of “civilizing” and educating the natives in English ways, see R. S. Sugirtharajah,<italic>Postcolonial Criticism and Biblical Interpretation</italic>(Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2002), 145–50. In addition to European and Euro‐American Christian communities, the Euro‐Canadian and Euro‐Australian Christian communities also share this complicity in varying degrees, although the colonial and postcolonial construction of “Europeanness” is quite complex, as the case of the French‐Canadians, who were colonizers subjugated and oppressed by another group of colonizers, well illustrates. See Sneja Gunew,<italic>Haunted Nations: The Colonial Dimensions of Multiculturalisms</italic>(London and New York: Routledge, 2004), 33–50.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>For the neocolonial or imperial character of the postcolonial world order, see James Petras and Henry Veltmeyer, “World Development: Globalization or Imperialism?” in<italic>Globalization and Antiglobalization: Dynamics of Change in the New World Order</italic>(Aldershot and Burlington, VT: Ashgate, 2004), 11–24; Ray Kiely, “The Crisis of Global Development,” in<italic>Globalisation and the Third World</italic>, ed. Ray Kiely and Phil Marfleet (London and New York: Routledge, 1998), 23–43, and “Transnational Companies, Global Capital and the Third World,” in ibid., 45–66. The phrase “self‐congratulatory competitiveness” is Andrew Shank’s designation of Milbank’s confessionalism in Shank,<italic>God and Modernity: A New and Better Way to Do Theology</italic>(London and New York: Routledge, 2000), 101.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Hegel, Mutual Recognition, and the Freedom to Participate</title>
         <p>The relevance of Hegel’s idea of mutual recognition in this context lies in its claim that the establishment of a free community devoid of relations of domination and exclusion hinges on the mutual recognition of its constituents, freely acknowledging one another as free agents whose participation or nonparticipation—or manner of participation—in the life of the community is not coerced. In the<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>and his ethical and political writings, Hegel provides the crucial insights that my freedom is not constituted in an atomistic fashion by an individual fiat but always in and through being recognized and “let go” by others as a free agent and that, in order for the others’ recognition of me to be genuine, they must also be constituted and affirmed as free agents by my recognition and releasement of them.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>According to Hegel, my freedom cannot come into being through a sheer assertion of my sovereign independence, because such an assertion fails to demonstrate that I have freed myself from my self‐centeredness, that is, my enthrallment to the purely particular interests of my own at odds with the interests and ends of others, which brings me into conflict with others and proves my claim of freedom to be a self‐serving illusion. Consequently, in order for me to be certain of my freedom, the other must willingly subordinate rather than oppose his or her own desires, interests, and goals to mine and, by doing so, affirm my will as the universal will and recognize me as the one who is truly free. Yet an interhuman relation defined by unidirectional subordination and recognition, as in the case of a master‐slave relation, cannot be a site of genuine freedom, since the certainty of the master’s freedom rests precariously on the dubious recognition given by the slave, whose will has been suppressed and made dependent on the master’s. The only viable way of securing freedom, then, lies in a relationship of reciprocal subordination and mutual recognition—the relationship in which two individuals knowingly and willingly submit their freedom to each other and, precisely in doing so, gain it back from each other with a certainty of one’s liberation from self‐centeredness. This essentially relational constitution of ethical or participatory freedom implies that, in order for freedom to exist at all in a community, everyone in that community must be free and that a partially free community, that is, a community in which some are free and the rest are not, is a self‐contradiction. Furthermore, in order for there to be such a community in which everyone is free, it must be built up of and completely permeated by interhuman and social relations of bidirectional recognition and reciprocal releasement.</p>
         <p>Although Hegel’s explicit formulation of the process of mutual recognition seems to refer primarily to the relations among individuals within a single community, it can be applied also to the relations among communities or nations, as Hegel’s own view of international relations indicates.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>Any community, people, or nation that arrogates to itself freedom to pursue universalistic values, aspirations, and claims by means of dominating and silencing other communities or certain groups of people within itself (women, ethnic, racial or sexual minorities, the poor, the lower caste, etc.) would end up calling in question its own claim to free agency, insofar as its stance of domination exposes its captivity to the model of master‐slave relation according to which one group of human beings, in an idolatry of its parochial self‐interest, coerces and disciplines another group to recognize its ends and interests as universal. As constituents of a larger, more encompassing human community inhabiting a common space of living, either religious communities can face one another in a posture of nonrecognition, domination, and exclusion and, in doing so, give the lie to their universalistic aspirations and claims or they can establish both intercommunal and intracommunal relations of mutual recognition that would enable them to communicate with one another as free and equal subjects and, by reciprocally subordinating to one another their freedom to pursue their interests and goals, possibly come to an uncoerced consensus on some conditions of coexistence and solidary action.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>Especially in situations where there is a gross inequality of power among religious communities and within each of them, mutual recognition of free agency would have to involve recognition of the need for some degree of intercommunal and intracommunal redistribution of resources on the one hand and institutional measures against the tyranny of majority on the other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>My reading of Hegel is based on his “mature” work starting from<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>. His explicit thematization and formulation of mutual recognition is found in the first part of the chapter on “Self‐Consciousness” in<italic>Phenomenology</italic>, especially his famous section on “Lordship and Bondage,” and in the “Phenomenology” chapter of his<italic>Encyclopedia</italic>. G. W. F. Hegel,<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>, trans. A. V. Miller (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1977), 104– 19, and<italic>Hegel’s Philosophy of Subjective Spirit</italic>, ed. and trans. M. J. Petry, vol. 3,<italic>Phenomenology and Psychology</italic>(Dordrecht: D. Reidel, 1979), §§424–36. Although not as thematized as in the above two works, Hegel’s notion of mutual recognition is present ubiquitously in his<italic>Philosophy of Right</italic>as an “operative concept.” See Robert R. Williams,<italic>Hegel’s Ethics of Recognition</italic>(Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London: University of California Press, 1997).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>While the phenomenological description of mutual recognition found in the<italic>Encyclopedia</italic>belongs to the philosophy of subjective spirit and is therefore about individuals within a community, the account in the<italic>Phenomenology</italic>could be read as referring to either singular subjectivity or universal subjectivity. Also, as Hegel argues in his<italic>Philosophy of Right</italic>, the sovereignty of a nation‐state as an individual becomes actual only in being recognized by other nation‐states (<italic>Elements of the Philosophy of Right</italic>, ed. Allen W. Wood, trans. H. B. Nisbet [Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1991], §§331–36). But unlike interpersonal recognition, international recognition is predicated not on the mere existence of nation‐states but on the level of internal sovereignty and freedom they have attained, as reflected in their constitutions (or “internal principles of legitimacy,” to quote Williams [<italic>Hegel's Ethics</italic>, 350]). Nation‐states with constitutions based on “natural” forms of ethical life, such as those that have patriarchal social structures, practice slavery, and regard their social order as sanctioned by nature or some arbitrary divine power, have not attained the internal level of freedom and autonomy necessary for them to be recognized as free individuals. In other words, international recognition for Hegel presupposes comparable levels of cultural development and convergence of values, especially freedom, as R. R. Williams points out (349–54). This gives rise to the problem of cross‐cultural recognition, especially one between peoples with fundamentally different convictions concerning freedom. What if a culture or nation subordinates freedom to “natural” or divinely ordained inequalities, i.e., to master‐slave relations, both in its internal organization and in its external relations? According to Williams, Hegel adopts a historical approach to mediate the differences between cultures via a concept of developmental stages in the consciousness of freedom, which enables an indirect historical—and asymmetrical—recognition of the intrinsic potential of each culture to achieve freedom (<italic>Hegel's Ethics</italic>, 355–56). Certainly, insofar as Hegel’s Eurocentrism means a developmental scheme at the apex of which Western Europe stands (a supercessionist position), it must be rejected, although fairly persuasive cases have been made—mainly based on his<italic>Lectures on the Philosophy of Religion</italic>—for the existence of a latent typological scheme of cultural differences in Hegel’s system in spite of his unsuccessful effort to create a developmental, supercessionist narrative (Walter Jaeschke,<italic>Reason in Religion: The Foundations of Hegel’s Philosophy of Religion</italic>, trans. J. Michael Stewart and Peter C. Hodgson [Berkeley, Los Angeles, and Oxford: University of California Press, 1990]; Peter C. Hodgson, “Logic, History, and Alternative Paradigms in Hegel’s Interpretation of the Religions,”<italic>Journal of Religion</italic>68, no. 1 [1988]: 1–20). What is, however, of enduring significance in Hegel independent of his failed developmental narrative, I think, is his central insight that a state of conflict and war will continue to be the order of the day unless different nations and cultures come to share an affirmation of some kind of nonviolent and noncoercive relation, predicated on a mutual recognition of free agency, as the key value and organizing principle around which they must structure their internal lives and external relations to one another. By his own criteria, Hegel’s Eurocentric developmental scheme for the consciousness of freedom can be judged wrong precisely because Europe in its colonial domination of other peoples has exposed its own continuing captivity to the model of master‐slave relation in which one group of human beings, in an idolatry of its parochial self‐interest, tries to force another group to recognize its ends and interests as universal.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>The minimum conditions of coexistence, coflourishing, and solidary action can be spelled out from some “primary goods,” i.e., universal needs all human beings share regardless of their gender, class, race, ethnicity, culture, and religion, such as security of life; basic freedom from violence, coercion, and exploitation (such as slavery and genocide); and basic fairness in the distribution and exercise of political and economic power. See Amy Gutmann, introduction to<italic>Multiculturalism: Examining the Politics of Recognition</italic>, ed. Amy Gutmann (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1994), 4; Min, “Dialectical Pluralism,” 600.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Anselm Min draws our attention to the fact that the ideal condition of dialogical reason is dependent on and either fostered or obstructed by material and sociohistorical conditions, such as inequalities in political and economic power (Min, “Dialectical Pluralism,” 598–99). I agree in the sense that the ideal condition of dialogue presupposes free agency, and, as the inclusion of economic rights in addition to civil and political rights in the human rights discourse shows, free agency is either nurtured or hampered by the amount of material and cultural resources to which one has access, such as the level of income and education. Nancy Fraser makes a similar observation about the objective conditions of participatory parity. Nancy Fraser, “Recognition without Ethics?” in<italic>Recognition and Difference</italic>, ed. Scott Lash and Mike Featherstone (London: SAGE, 2002), 29.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Fanon and the Specter of Spurious Recognition</title>
         <p>Yet while mutual recognition of free agency ensuring equal participation—recognition of “participatory parity,” to borrow Nancy Fraser’s term—is a necessary and indispensable precondition of there being a polity free of overt institutional domination and exclusion, it in and of itself is not sufficient to bring that polity into being as a genuine community animated by a spirit of solidaristic acceptance of one another, as Axel Honneth argues.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>My recognition and letting go of the other as a free agent, when reciprocated by the other, may lead to an uncoerced consensus on the conditions of peaceful coexistence, but that by itself does not guarantee that the consensus reached would be anything other than merely expedient and self‐interested compromises grudgingly agreed to by either or both of the parties involved. What can be missing here is a genuine recognition of the worth of the other, without which what could prevail in the relationship between the two is the suspicion that the other’s act of recognizing my free agency is mere “tolerance” that is actually a thinly veiled contempt of who and what I am.</p>
         <p>A classic diagnosis of this phenomenon of recognition in bad faith is found in Fanon’s famous reading of Hegel’s “master‐slave dialectic,” where he points out the essential separability of the master’s manumission of the slave from his heartfelt recognition of the slave as an equal.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>The master, argues Fanon, may free the slave out of fear of rebellion and in doing so recognize the slave’s free and self‐determining agency, yet at the same time he can still regard the slave as quite inferior to himself. Such a condescending recognition of free agency is precisely what Fanon finds prevalent in the postcolonial situation, in which the colonizers who have recognized and let go of the colonized as free beings still refuse to acknowledge the latter, including their culture and way of life, as on a par with themselves and their own values. The spurious and dissembling recognition thus given by the former colonizers, Fanon claims, can drive the formerly colonized into what in Hegel’s terms could be called “unhappy consciousness,” that is, a state of consciousness in which one feels split and alienated from one’s own essential self, here identified with the former colonizers whose values and goals the formerly colonized had come to internalize in the course of the long years of the colonial rule.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>The other side of the coin in this situation is that, unable to gain recognition from the former masters by means of emulating them, the formerly colonized may come to reject the values of the colonizing culture and to posit their own indigenous traditions as the source of their true identity and the means by which they now demand recognition from their former masters.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>The discourses of multiculturalism and politics of identity (or difference) widely practiced today especially in the metropole of the global order, such as the demand made by the minority communities in the United States that their indigenous tradition and history be included in the curriculums of public education, derive their persuasive power precisely from this need for recognition present in the postcolonial‐neocolonial context of nonrecognition of worth or spurious recognition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>Not content merely to be tolerated and left alone to practice their own ways of life, the groups, communities, and peoples hitherto oppressed and marginalized have come to demand that the inherent worth of their values and practices be recognized and publicly validated for the sake of redressing the long years of invisibility that they have suffered.</p>
         <p>It appears, then, that, in addition to mutual recognition of free participatory agency as its necessary precondition, a solidary interreligious relationship within the postcolonial‐neocolonial context also requires mutual recognition of identity or worth. The damage to self‐esteem inflicted upon a community and its members and the consequent festering of resentment in the wake of a recognition of worth withheld could be destructive to any efforts made to establish the conditions of coexistence and solidary action necessary for creating a peaceable polity—however loosely it may be meant—in opposition to the violence of today’s global order. Nevertheless, in spite of its historical‐contextual justification and exigency, there is something self‐contradictory about the notion of recognition on demand, that is, recognition given to certain values and practices solely on account of their uniqueness and difference. Recognition, as re‐cognition, implies the seeing, remembering, and rediscovering of oneself in another and therefore involves by definition some assessment and evaluation of another from one’s existing perspective and criteria, for both individuals and communities. Charles Taylor’s pioneering essay on the politics of recognition shows how a suppression of this fact actually results in nonrecognition. If one's recognition of another is produced purely by the force of will following a sense of moral imperative to respect difference as such, it is patronizing if not downright condescending: I do not know why or on what grounds I should recognize you, but I will grant you recognition anyway because you need it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>Furthermore, as long as one cannot do away with one’s perspective and criteria of evaluation, such a patronizing recognition degenerates into hypocrisy in case the object of recognition does not meet the criteria: “I know deep down in my heart that you do not really deserve it, but …” Indeed the specter of recognition in bad faith returns here with a vengeance.</p>
         <p>In order to recognize another's worth bona fide, one has to make an assessment in light of some standard of evaluation, and, in the absence of a genuinely global culture with a horizon or perspective more comprehensive than and inclusive of the perspectives of the individual communities, one cannot help having recourse to one’s parochial point of view and treating it as somehow universally relevant and applicable. The inevitability of a particular perspective in recognition of worth is all the more the case for religious communities that make universalistic and ultimate truth claims, such as the Christian assertion of the centrality and universality of the salvation achieved by God in and through Jesus Christ. For Christian communities their recognition of other ways of life cannot avoid being given—or not given—in reference to the divine will and practice which they believe have been disclosed for all people in Jesus’s life, death, and resurrection.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Fraser’s notion of participatory parity claims that what requires recognition is not group‐specific identity but rather the status of group members as full partners in social interaction (Fraser, “Recognition,” 24). In her words, it means recognizing that “everyone has an equal right to pursue social esteem under fair conditions of equal opportunity” (28). In my reading, Hegel’s master‐slave dialectic is primarily about equal recognition of self‐determining rational agents and less about equal recognition of cultural identity or worth, as my discussion of Fanon makes clear. I agree with Axel Honneth that in order for there to be a sense of social solidarity, social esteem conferred by recognition of worth (of one another’s abilities, skills, and ways of life) is necessary. Axel Honneth, “Recognition or Redistribution? Changing Perspectives on the Moral Order of Society,” in Lash and Featherstone, eds.,<italic>Recognition and Difference</italic>, 49–50.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>For the following analysis, see Fanon’s essay “The Negro and Recognition,” in his<italic>Frantz Fanon, Black Skin, White Masks</italic>, trans. Charles Lam Markmann (New York: Grove Press, 1967), 210–22. I have been helped in my reading of Fanon by Alfred J. López, although in my view he does not show clearly that what is at stake for Fanon is recognition of identity and worth. Alfred J. López,<italic>Posts and Pasts: A Theory of Postcolonialism</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 2001), 121–42.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>For a postcolonial reading of the Hegelian notion of “unhappy consciousness,” see López, 128–29, 135–36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>See Fanon’s essay “The Fact of Blackness,” in Fanon,<italic>Black Skin, White Masks</italic>, 109–40, for this penetrating analysis of the dialectical movement of the psyche of the colonized. See also “On National Culture,” in Frantz Fanon,<italic>The Wretched of the Earth</italic>, trans. Constance Farrington (New York: Grove Press, 1963), 206–48.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>For the multiculturalism debate around the curriculum of public education, see Paul Berman, ed.,<italic>Debating P.C.: The Controversy over Political Correctness on College Campuses</italic>(New York: Dell, 1992). See also Ward Churchill, “White Studies: The Intellectual Imperialism of US Higher Education,” in<italic>Theorizing Multiculturalism: A Guide to the Current Debate</italic>, ed. Cynthia Willet (Oxford and Malden, MA: Blackwell, 1998), 334–56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Charles Taylor, “The Politics of Recognition,” in Gutmann, ed.,<italic>Multiculturalism</italic>, 63–73.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Recognition as Uncoerced Self‐Transformation</title>
         <p>Given the absence of comprehensively universal standards of evaluation for recognition of worth, then, religious communities seem to be caught between the horns of a dilemma: the need for their mutual recognition of worth for the sake of greater solidarity within the present postcolonial‐neocolonial context, on the one hand, and the necessity of evaluation from their parochial yet inescapably universalized points of view, on the other. Yet this dilemma may not be an irresolvable contradiction. First of all, the notion of recognition on demand is incompatible with the practice of mutual recognition as such insofar as there are cultural practices that do not honor mutuality and reciprocity. In other words, mutual recognition of free participatory agency itself provides a minimum universal standard for mutual recognition of worth in the sense that the former by definition precludes recognizing the worth of a community’s particular practices that seek to dominate, marginalize, and exclude from participation other communities as well as some of its own members. Nancy Fraser’s thesis that the standard of recognition must be the norm of participatory parity is helpful in explicating this point: a community claiming recognition of worth for its religious or cultural practices must show that these practices neither impede the free and equal participation of other communities and their members in the common space of living nor bar some of its own members from being free participants in its internal life with the power to define and represent it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>Any communal practice that upholds the master‐slave relation as a key value and organizing principle around which the community attempts to structure its internal life and external relations must be denied recognition of worth by virtue of its own rejection of the values of reciprocity and participatory freedom intrinsic to the practice of mutual recognition.</p>
         <p>Certainly this sounds like an imperial imposition of a modern European political idea on religious communities that may not share the same cultural horizon—the very thing on account of which the postliberals and neotraditionalists reject the idea of interreligious dialogue. But the Hegelian notion of mutual recognition of free participatory agency is but one among many possible theoretical enunciations of the kind of political practice that must absolutely take place if different religious communities are to live in peace and solidarity. Although the trailblazing efforts made to implement that practice and give it theoretical articulations in the historical experiences of the modern European peoples have all too often been marred by patriarchal, racist, ethnocentric, and class‐based forms of master‐slave relation, that fact does not by itself cancel out the need for a solidary political practice of mutuality and free participation today in order to meet the challenges of the postcolonial‐neocolonial global order. Each religious community would need to go to its scriptures, narratives, myths, symbolisms, rituals, and practices to find motivations and reasons of its own to engage in such a political practice and possibly give its own theoretical account of why it recognizes practices of mutuality and free participation while denying the value of dominating and coercively marginalizing practices.</p>
         <p>While mutual recognition of free participatory agency thus provides a minimum universal standard for mutual recognition of worth and precludes recognition on demand, the question remains whether that minimum condition can become more encompassing of the values and practices of individual religious communities—encompassing to the extent that there will emerge some kind of unifying narrative of identity constructing a cultural space within which a genuinely solidaristic acceptance of one another in friendship could blossom and an interreligiously coalitional politics of resistance could unfold. A positive answer to this question is not impossible, for the parochial yet universalized evaluative horizon of a religious community can become open to an increasing degree of convergence of a sort with that of another via self‐transformation and not necessarily devolve into an idolatry of the particular that is forgetful of the sociohistorical conditions of its own production. Although it may be the case, as postliberals claim, that religious communities constitute semiotic “worlds” irreducible to one another, that does not mean that their criteria of interpretation and evaluation are immune to change or that the boundaries of their horizons do not shift. Religions, like cultures, are not monolithic, fixed, and sui generis entities existing by themselves but rather thoroughly relational “concrete totalities” whose respective boundaries and internal configurations are constantly changing in accordance with alterations in their sociohistorical conditions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>Religious identity is not a stable and static set of commonly held beliefs, ideas, symbolic forms, and texts deposited in tradition and acting unilaterally as regulative grammar but a site of both regularity and contestation in which people as embodied carriers of tradition generate the sense of who they are religiously by skillfully negotiating and contesting various social and cultural identities coursing through the site and inscribed in their gendered, racialized, and laboring bodies, as Kathryn Tanner and Mary McClintock Fulkerson have convincingly shown.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>If religious identity is a sociohistorically concrete site of cultural contestation and negotiation, then a religious community’s evaluative horizon and criteria of recognition cannot avoid being something constantly emergent, negotiated, hybridized, and subject to permutations as the configuration of the site and its milieu undergo social and historical changes. The present historical context, in which religious communities have been driven to inhabit a common space of living, brings the sites of cultural contestation and negotiation that are religious identities into closer proximity to one another than ever, and this forces any one site of religious identity to be a field in which multiple religious identities are negotiated and contested, insofar as they have become part of the general sociocultural discourses—an “ocean of heteroglossia,” to use Mikhail Bakhtin’s term—inscribed in the bodily habitus of the people on that site.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>Cross‐fertilization and hybridization via unreflective borrowings and mimetic appropriations are inevitable features of the daily negotiation of one’s religious identity in such a historical context.</p>
         <p>It is important here, however, to make a distinction similar to the key distinction drawn by Bakhtin between two forms of linguistic hybridity: unconscious, “organic” hybridity that is characteristic of the historical evolution of all languages and in most cases not radically disruptive of the sense of order and continuity and conscious, intentional hybridity that builds upon the historical foundation of organic hybridity to shock, challenge, and revitalize by means of deliberate and internally dialogical fusions of disparate social languages, ideas, and images.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>While the negotiated and contested character of religious identity discussed above largely belongs to the historical process of unreflective, organic hybridization, the kind of unifying narrative of identity sought for the sake of fostering an interreligiously solidary politics of resistance cannot be anything but a product of conscious, intentional hybridization rooted in the existing historical process of organic hybridization and enabled by the latter to push forward to a strategically produced identity of interreligiously hybrid nature. The question, then, is what concrete form the self‐transformation of one’s always emergent and contested horizon of religious recognition and its convergence with another horizon can take within the interreligiously negotiated site of reflective, intentional hybridization.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Fraser, “Recognition without Ethics?” 34–35.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>I borrow Min’s helpful definition of religion as “concrete totalities”: “a system of symbols that comprises beliefs, rituals, and practices that embody the collective self‐understanding of its adherents within a ‘plausibility structure’ (Peter Berger), i.e., those objective socio‐historical conditions that render such self‐understanding plausible” (Min, “Dialectical Pluralism,” 590). For the dynamic models of culture that stress the indeterminate, hybrid, conflictual, and contested character of cultural identity formation predicated on sociohistorical processes and an understanding of religion in accordance with those models of culture, see Tanner,<italic>Theory of Culture</italic>, 38–58.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>See Tanner,<italic>Theory of Culture</italic>; and Mary McClintock Fulkerson, “`We don’t see color here': A Case Study in Ecclesial‐Cultural Invention,” in<italic>Converging on Culture: Theologians in Dialogue with Cultural Analysis and Criticism</italic>, ed. Delwin Brown, Sheila Greeve Davaney, and Kathryn Tanner (Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2001), 140–57.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Mikhail M. Bakhtin,<italic>The Dialogic Imagination</italic>, ed. Michael Holquist, trans. Caryl Emerson and Michael Holquist (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1981), 368. I am indebted to Fulkerson for the notion of religious identity as bodily habitus. See Fulkerson, “`We don't see color here,'” 147–48.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Bakhtin,<italic>Dialogic Imagination</italic>, 358–61. In this reading of Bakhtin, I have been helped by Pnina Werbner, “Introduction: The Dialectics of Cultural Hybridity,” in<italic>Debating Hybridity: Multi‐Cultural Identities and the Politics of Anti‐racism</italic>, ed. Pnina Werbner and Tariq Modood (London and Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Zed Books, 1997), 4–6.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc6">
         <title>Dialectic of Comparative Theology and Theology of Religions</title>
         <p>Within the rubric of his objectively idealistic conceptualities, Hegel himself has provided a model for the self‐transformation of recognitive horizon in the introduction to the<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>. Read in the Gadamerian language of “horizons” that I have been using, his point is that, although the recognitive process starts out initially as an assessment of the other against the totalizing horizon of my existing standard, that initial assessment soon encounters a disclosure of the other that, as the voice of the infinite, questions the finite and provisional nature of my totalizing horizon and exposes the other as understood in my initial recognition or nonrecognition of it as “my”—domiciled, normalized, and nondisturbing—other, not the other as such.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>The noncorrespondence here between my initial concept of the other formed against the horizon of my existing standard, on the one hand, and the subsequent disclosure of the other that exceeds and overflows the content of that initial concept, on the other, leads to the demise of the initial standard and its transformation into a new standard with an expanded horizon to account for the other’s disclosed difference. In other words, my recognition or nonrecognition of the other is not something given to the other once and for all but something always “on the move,” so to speak, constantly being amended and revised as my broadening and deepening encounter with the other transforms the configuration and horizon of my own identity—my standard of evaluation—which I seek to see, remember, and re‐cognize in the other.</p>
         <p>When this Hegelian journey of self‐transformative<italic>Erfahrung</italic>is envisaged more concretely as a project of strategically intentional interreligious hybridization, two concomitant prongs of interreligious engagement take shape as its necessary moments. First, in order for an interreligious engagement to involve one’s self‐transformative encounter with the other’s self‐disclosure, it must embody some form of learning about the other in an undistorted way by means of dialogue and immersion in the other’s ideas and practices within a context of mutuality and equal participation. From the perspective of Christian theology, the newly emerging discipline of comparative theology, pioneered by Francis Clooney and others, here offers a model.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>Comparative theology demands that I acquire as the proper context of my theological practice both an in‐depth understanding of the texts, symbolisms, rituals, and practices of other religious traditions and a stance of openness and vulnerability to the transformative power of their truth claims, so that my reading of my own Christian tradition may be carried out as an act of self‐critical and nonidolatrous commitment to its distinct claim to truth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Yet, just as a bona fide recognition of others’ worth cannot be produced by a mere moral injunction to esteem difference, a genuine openness to being transformed by others cannot follow from a sheer demand to be open and vulnerable to their truth claims. In order to have a truly self‐transformative encounter with another, a provisional presumption of the other's worth and the accompanying open‐mindedness toward listening to the other are requisite. From a Christian theological perspective, this means that a Christian confessional standpoint that makes such a presumption, namely, some kind of working theology of religions that is favorably disposed to the value of other religious traditions, is necessary. Given that exclusivism refuses to recognize the value of other traditions as a matter of principle, such a working theology of religions would have to be some form of inclusivism or confessional pluralism whose unreserved confession of the uniqueness, centrality, and comprehensiveness of its own parochial way has at the same time a measure of a priori recognition of others built into it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The model of interreligious engagement here proposed for Christian theology as a way of creating a politically unifying narrative of identity via intentional hybridization, then, is some kind of dialectical relationship between a comparative‐theological undertaking and an inclusivist or confessional‐pluralist theology of religions taking place on the basis of mutual recognition of free participatory agency. Under this model, the demand of another religious tradition for recognition of worth, possibly for the sake of redressing a historical injustice, is first met by my initial theological assessment and recognition of it as attractive and appealing. Having been drawn and opened up to the appeal of another tradition by my initial recognition of its worth, I then descend to the “depth of its riches” by means of the comparative‐theological undertaking of dialogue and immersion.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>Such an unreserved encounter with another tradition in a posture of openness and vulnerability eventually leads me to revise my original assessment of it and the theological presuppositions on the basis of which that initial recognition was given. In philosophical terms this process could be called a dialectic of infinity and relative totality, in which one’s totalizing recognitive horizon is challenged and relativized by its encounter with the infinite voice of the Other that breaks into and overflows it, leading to a reconfiguration of the totalizing horizon internally and of its assessment of the other externally.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref>When interreligious engagement is envisaged thus as a dialectic of theology of religions (which represents the comprehensive and totalizing horizon) and comparative theology (which introduces the voice of the infinite Other), what can be expected as the end product of this process is a new and expanded theological horizon that can either recognize the other’s worth in a more informed manner or withdraw the initial recognition in light of a new disclosure of the other’s radical difference. In and through the act of enriching and transforming its moments in a to‐and‐fro movement, the dialectic spirals forward into either the discovery of a terrain of irreconcilable religious differences—a “negative dialectic” (Theodor Adorno)—or the coalescence of a pattern of mutual compatibility and complementarity enabling a far‐reaching interreligious consensus on the criteria of mutual recognition of worth upon which a politically solidary narrative of interreligiously hybrid identity could be constructed.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>See Hegel,<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>, 46–57. My reading is Gadamerian in the sense that I substitute cultural and linguistic “horizon” for the idealistic notion of “form of consciousness.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>The literature of comparative theology is enormous, but, for a programmatic overview of comparative theology as a theological movement and method, see James L. Fredericks, “A Universal Religious Experience? Comparative Theology as an Alternative to a Theology of Religions,”<italic>Horizons</italic>22, no. 1 (1995): 68–75; James L. Fredericks,<italic>Faith among Faiths: Christian Theology and Non‐Christian Religions</italic>(New York and Mahwah, NJ: Paulist Press, 1999); Stephen J. Duffy, “A Theology of Religions and/or a Comparative Theology?<italic>Horizons</italic>26, no. 1 (1999):105–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Francis X. Clooney,<italic>Hindu God, Christian God: How Reason Helps Break Down the Boundaries between Religions</italic>(Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2001), 26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Clooney acknowledges that comparative theology presupposes an initial theological understanding of other religious traditions that helps one be favorably disposed toward them and elicits a search for whatever goodness, virtue, and spiritual appeal—all at first understood in Christian terms—that can be found in those traditions. In his view, an inclusivist position is better suited for this purpose than an exclusivist or pluralist position. Francis X. Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedanta: An Experiment in Comparative Theology</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 1993), 194–95. Arguing against comparative theologians who demand a moratorium on theology of religions, Paul Knitter makes a similar point in<italic>Introducing Theologies of Religions</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 2002), 235–37.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>The phrase “depth of its riches” is taken from the title of S. Mark Heim’s<italic>The Depth of the Riches: A Trinitarian Theology of Religious Ends</italic>(Cambridge and Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans, 2001).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>I am indebted to Anselm Min for this notion, although his formulation more precisely speaks of a “triple dialectic” of relative totality, infinity, and solidarity. See Anselm Kyongsuk Min, “Toward a Dialectic of Totality and Infinity: Reflections on Emmanuel Levinas,”<italic>Journal of Religion</italic>78, no. 4 (1998): 592.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>The idea of mutual complementarity and convergence of religions has been advanced by Jacques Dupuis and Aloysius Pieris. Jacques Dupuis, “Christianity and Religions,” in<italic>Many Mansions? Multiple Religious Belonging and Christian Identity</italic>, ed. Catherine Cornille (Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 2002), 65–69; Aloysius Pieris, “The Buddha and the Christ,” in Hick and Knitter, eds.,<italic>Myth of Christian Uniqueness</italic>, 162–77.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc7">
         <title>Toward an Interreligiously Solidary Narrative of Subaltern Others</title>
         <p>Yet while a dialectic of theology of religions and comparative theology can thus provide the most basic modus operandi of solidary interreligious engagement for Christians, the formulation given it so far has been based on a Gadamerian reading of Hegel’s dialectically formulated recognitive process in terms of “fusion of horizons” that is also informed by a Levinasian critique of Hegel in the name of the self’s asymmetrical relation to the infinity of the other’s voice.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref>When left as it is, however, such a reading does not do full justice to the sociopolitically inscribed nature of the recognitive process, insofar as each religious horizon of recognition and evaluation refers to an emergent religious identity that is a site of negotiation and contestation for various social, cultural, and religious identities. Thus, the question here put to the idea of “fusion of horizons” is: which horizons? Similarly, the challenge presented to the notion of the rupture of one’s totalizing horizon by the always emergent, negotiated, and contested voice of a religious other is: which other? The language of “horizon” or “other” must first be given back its sociopolitically concrete and internally heterogeneous meaning if the unifying narrative of identity sought by means of politically intentional hybridization is not to turn out as an instrument of domination suppressing the multiplicity of heterogeneous voices—social, cultural, and religious identities—within each site of religious identity that clamors for recognition.</p>
         <p>Taking my cue from Homi Bhabha’s twofold thesis that the colonial and postcolonial history has been characterized by the colonizers’ construction of a binary opposition between pure, homogeneous, and culturally superior Europe and the equally homogeneous but inferior and decadent other of Europe and that the traditionalist, nativist, and nationalist movements of anticolonial resistance have all more or less bought into that binary scheme repressive of hybridity and internal heterogeneity, I suggest the following sociopolitically concrete reformulation of the dialectic.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref>First of all, any claim of pure and homogeneous religious identity made today must initially be put within its proper postcolonial‐neocolonial context via a hermeneutic of suspicion and examined in regard to the degree to which it may or may not be stained with the enduring impact of the centuries‐long imposition of economic, political, and cultural master‐slave relations. For example, when today a European or Euro‐American Christian community calls for a return to the “pure,” “orthodox” tradition in total opposition to modernity—variously called “the world,” “the liberal nation‐state,” “the secular humanistic culture,” and so forth—and castigates feminist and other liberationist voices of resistance springing up both within itself and outside for having been contaminated by modernity, it is apropos to ask if that gesture of repudiation and return is an attempt to maintain an originary myth of pure and homogeneous identity in another package after modernity’s totalizing binary opposition of Europe and Other has been discredited and condemned. Especially, if that community today asserts once more the long‐standing Christian view that Christianity is the only true way, one is all the more drawn to wonder whether that assertion now camouflages a lingering residue of and an effort to perpetuate by other means the sense of culturally superior identity it enjoyed for so long, being at the center of the colonizing empires and serving as the latter’s mouthpiece and “civilizing” servant, however much it repudiates that role now. By the same token, when Hindu communities in India and the diaspora today advocate an idealized and monolithic representation of Hinduism devoid of internal complexity and diversity, put an undue emphasis on the sacred texts and their translation for missionary purposes, and construct the other—usually Islam—to explain the past and present ills of Hinduism, one needs to question whether all these constitute a postcolonial nativist reaction to a history of humiliation and nonrecognition rather than an uninterrupted extension and expression of whatever nativists claim to be their traditional and “pure” identity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>The Islamists’ angry rejection of the “Western” and “Christian” discourses of women’s rights and pluralistic democracy in the name of the past golden age of a pure form of Islam could be understood in a similar vein, as a nativist oppositional politics that merely tries to turn the essentializing binary scheme of hierarchical evaluation around on Europe and America and in the course of doing so squelch the heterogeneous discourses welling up within itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">44</xref>
         </p>
         <p>When totalizing representations of religious identity are thus scrutinized through the lens of a hermeneutic of suspicion, the first step is taken toward recovering the sociopolitically concrete meaning of religious “identity,” “horizon,” or “other” and envisaging the dialectic of theology of religions and comparative theology in a manner that counters forceful discursive closures that produce the fixed binary opposition of the hegemonic Self and the hegemonic Other. First, the comparative‐theological undertaking of dialogue with and immersion in the texts, symbolisms, rituals, and practices of a religious other needs initially to be a political act of both intra‐ and interreligious solidarity that attempts to free the suppressed subaltern voices of difference—women, ethnic, racial, or sexual minorities, the poor, the outcast—both within one’s own tradition and within the religious other being compared. In other words, comparative theology must first be a politically liberating praxis of restoring and enabling the subaltern representations—in the sense of both portraiture (<italic>Darstellung</italic>) and political representation (<italic>Vertretung</italic>)—of the religious traditions being compared, so that the minimum condition of mutual recognition of identity or worth, that is, mutual recognition of free participatory agency, can be established as political reality rather than merely postulated as ideal dialogical condition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref>For this to be possible, furthermore, an inclusivist or confessional‐pluralist theology of religions from which the comparative‐theological undertaking starts must be one that perpetually guards against the sociopolitically privileged epistemic positioning of its rules of recognition in terms of gender, race, class, nationality, and/or the like and one whose totalizing metaphysical desire has enough apophatic sensibility built into it to accept the loss of its positional privilege as epistemic gain.</p>
         <p>Once the dialectic of theology of religions and comparative theology is reconfigured strategically as a politically liberating praxis of restoring and enabling the subaltern representations of religious identities with the goal of establishing participatory parity as political reality, the question of the self‐transformation and possible convergence of religious horizons of recognition needs to be restated in terms of the possible coalescence of the subaltern representations into a politically solidary narrative of interreligiously hybrid nature.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">46</xref>Can subaltern religious narratives of resistance recognize one another enough to be able to weave themselves into a grand narrative that unites across the permeable boundaries of religious identities that are all other to one another—that is, decentered others—for the sake of countering the hegemonic Selves of the present global order? Can, for instance, the German peasants’ millenarian appeal to the Holy Spirit, to whose articulation Thomas Müntzer lent his voice, coalesce in our social imagination with the antifeudal and anticolonial insurgency of the Tonghaks in the name of Hanŭnim or the Heaven who is in every human being?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">47</xref>Will it be possible for poor African Christian women and poor Asian Muslim women likewise to weave their stories together into a unifying narrative of interreligiously hybrid identity that indicts and counters the overwhelming economic, political, cultural, and religious forces arrayed against them to “put them in their place”? When possible, such a solidary act of grand‐narrative construction would amount to what Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak has called “strategic essentialism,” namely, the construction of a unified oppositional agency of “others” for the sake of resisting and undermining the very structures and forces that have worked to create those others as other of today’s Caesars.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">48</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Liberated from its epistemic imprisonment in the closed economy of an intellectual transaction between the hegemonic Self and the hegemonic Other and reconfigured as a politically liberating praxis of restoring and enabling the representational agency of the subaltern for the sake of a coalitional construction of subversive social imagery, the dialectic of theology of religions and comparative theology becomes a political‐theological practice of interreligious dialogue, that is, a “politics of recognition” aimed at fostering a mutual and solidaristic acceptance of decentered others who are all other to one another. At a time when the global human community needs the resources of every culture and religion to nurture just and solidary values and institutions for the sake of a truly postcolonial globalization in opposition to today’s neocolonial globalization, interreligious dialogue reconfigured as such a liberating and solidary praxis cannot be deemed a merely extraneous option or a luxury.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>See Hans‐Georg Gadamer,<italic>Truth and Method</italic>, trans. Joel Weinsheimer and Donald G. Marshall, 2nd ed. and 2nd rev. ed. (New York: Crossroad, 1989; Continuum, 1998); Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Totality and Infinity: An Essay on Exteriority</italic>, trans. Alphonso Lingis (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, 1969), 33–52. Levinas argues that dialogue is founded upon the asymmetrical relationship between the self and the infinite Other (“Dialogue … is a thinking of the<italic>unequal</italic>, a thought thinking<italic>beyond</italic>the given” [Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>God Who Comes to Mind</italic>, trans. Bettina Bergo (Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 1998), 151]) and in that sense not a method of uncovering truth but a call to (self‐) transcendence, i.e., to ethics (ibid., 143–51). Levinas’s purely asymmetrical ethical understanding of the self‐other relation, in which the practice of dialogue is reduced to the infinite Other’s “breaking in” and rupturing of the totalizing horizon of my world, is meant as a critique of Hegel’s more symmetrical, interdependent, and holistic understanding of the self‐other relation in terms of mutual recognition. But this criticism is predicated on what in my view is an unconvincing identification of holism, which is an internally differentiated harmony, with totality, which is devoid of internal differentiation whatsoever. I follow Paul Ricoeur’s more Hegelian, dialectical understanding of the self‐other relation (that is at the same time informed by the Levinasian critique), in which the horizon of my world is driven by its own logic to a universalizability test via the sieve of the other’s scrutiny and is transformed in the process. Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey (Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 1992), 169–296.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>See Homi K. Bhabha,<italic>Location of Culture</italic>(London and New York: Routledge, 1994). Following in Fanon’s footsteps, he provides a pertinent analysis of how the identity‐shaping recognitive process within the concrete historical conditions of colonialism and its postcolonial aftermath has worked to suppress the play of difference within each cultural identity. Part of the strategy of colonial rule and ideological justification for the European colonizers, he points out, was always to construct rules and standards of recognition around the notions of “modernity,” “rationality,” and “progress” and to produce a totalizing and hierarchically structured binary opposition between the colonizers and the colonized by recognizing the full presence of modernity and rationality in the former while assigning to the latter their complete absence or merely partial presence. The colonizing Europe accomplished this by disavowing the presence of heterogeneity within itself, such as the feminine and the irrational, and symbolically constructing and representing the colonized cultures as the essentialized Other of its now homogeneous rational self (and civilized, muscular Christianity)—e.g., the bestially sexual Africans, the duplicitous Chinese, and the effeminate and degenerate Hindus. But the artificial construction of such a binary opposition is inherently unstable, Bhabha argues, as can be seen for instance from the self‐contradictory nature of the colonizers’ attempt to convert the subject population to Christianity and to create a class of colonial elites educated in the ways of Europe, which was tantamount to an implicit recognition of the capacity of the colonized for rationality and self‐government, while at the same time deprecating and deriding that recognized presence of the “civilized” qualities in them as mere mimicry or even mockery of the authentic European, Christian identity. According to Bhabha, it is precisely the practice of mimicry on the part of the colonized—i.e., the imperial production of hybrid cultures and identities or of what he calls “the Third Space” (Bhabha,<italic>Location</italic>, 36)—which has appropriated, throughout colonial and postcolonial history, the discourses of the colonizers in order to challenge and subvert the originary myth of a pure, homogeneous, and superior cultural identity, be it that of the European colonizers or one espoused by the oppositional politics of the traditionalist, nativist anticolonial resistance movements.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>See Sharada Sugirtharajah,<italic>Imagining Hinduism: A Postcolonial Perspective</italic>(London and New York: Routledge, 2003), 133–43.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Mahnaz Afkhami points out the similarity between the Western Orientalists’ reports of traditional Islamic societies and contemporary Islamist descriptions of the supposedly homogeneous and harmonious Muslim societies before Western corruption that are used to bolster their claims of legitimacy. Mahnaz Afkhami, “Gender Apartheid and the Discourse of Relativity of Rights in Muslim Societies,” in Howland, ed.,<italic>Religious Fundamentalisms</italic>, 70.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>For the distinction between<italic>Darstellung</italic>and<italic>Vertretung</italic>, see Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak,<italic>A Critique of Postcolonial Reason: Toward a History of the Vanishing Present</italic>(London and Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1999), 257–64. For Spivak the pure subaltern cannot speak and represent themselves in both senses of the term, since the moment particular subalterns emerge as spokespersons for their communities—organic intellectuals in Antonio Gramsci’s sense—they cease to be subaltern (“Subaltern Talk: Interview with the Editors,” in<italic>The Spivak Reader: Selected Works of Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak</italic>, ed. Donna Landry and Gerald MacLean [New York and London: Routledge, 1996], 287–92). My argument for restoring and enabling the subaltern representations of religious traditions refers to the “nonpure” subalterns who through an enormous effort have come to speak for their purely subaltern communities—such as Rigoberta Menchú for the Mayans—but whose representations, if to be heard, require a solidary political praxis of resisting the attempts to silence them and whose already silenced and forgotten testimonials call for a similar praxis of rediscovery and restoration.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>I say “reconfigured strategically” to avoid the impression that my attempt to reconfigure the dialectic of comparative theology and theology of religions as a politically liberating praxis excludes the more elite discourses of the religious traditions involved (such as those of India’s Brahmins and China’s Confucian elites), which are in many cases both hegemonic (within a particular cultural framework) and marginalized (within a larger or global context). The solidary praxis of restoring and enabling subaltern religious representations is aimed at establishing participatory parity as a political reality in which both subaltern and elite representations could take part as decentered centers that are all other to one another and no longer as subaltern or elite in terms of sociopolitical and cultural hegemony. To bring into being such a politically level playing field, in which the more elite discourses find themselves also liberated and with a new voice, I think it is strategically necessary to emphasize first an act of solidarity with the oppressed. I thank the anonymous reviewer of my essay for raising the question of my thesis’s possible exclusion of elite religious discourses.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>One can find such a coalescence of subaltern religious representations and creation of a politically solidary narrative via intentional hybridization in the works of the Korean<italic>minjung</italic>poet Kim Chi Ha (1941– ). Kim’s poetry weaves Catholic liberation theology with the antifeudal and anticolonial social vision of the Tonghak religion, which rose as an indigenous religious movement of peasants for democratic revolution in Korea at the turn of the nineteenth century and played a prominent role in the 3.1 Independence Movement of 1919. The Tonghak religion itself was the product of a coalescence of elements of Confucianism, Buddhism, Taoism, Christianity, and indigenous beliefs in the subaltern religious and social imagination of the Korean peasantry. In the unfinished talk poem (ballad)<italic>The World of Chang Il Tam</italic>, one of the works for which he was imprisoned, tortured, and sentenced to life imprisonment by the dictatorial South Korean regime of Park Chung Hee in 1976, Kim merges the symbols of the Eucharist—the mystical body of the deity that is eaten—with the Tonghak teaching of “human being is heaven [<italic>in nae chʾǒn</italic>]”: “Food is heaven / As we eat / God enters us / Food is heaven. / Oh, food / Should be shared and eaten by all.” See Kim Chi Ha,<italic>The Gold‐Crowned Jesus and Other Writings</italic>, ed. Chong Sun Kim and Shelly Killen (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis, 1978), 13–39. See also his<italic>Saengmyǒng</italic>(Seoul: Sol, 1992), 132–49. Kim’s religiously hybrid poetic vision has been one of the mainsprings of inspiration for South Korea’s<italic>minjung</italic>theology. See Suh Nam Dong, “Du Iyagi ŭi Hamryu” [The merging of two stories], in<italic>Minjung gwa Hanguk Sinhak</italic>[Minjung and Korean theology], ed. NCC Sinhak Yǒngu Wiwǒnhoe [Committee of Theological Study, National Council of Churches] (Seoul: Hanguk Sinhak Yǒnguso [Korea Theological Study Institute], 1982), 237–76.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>For the notion of strategic essentialism, see Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak, “Subaltern Studies: Deconstructing Historiography,” in her<italic>The Spivak Reader</italic>, 214–21. Serene Jones has drawn attention to the fact that the poststructuralist theoretical assumptions about the always oppressive nature of binarisms do not necessarily hold up under the pressures of concrete political struggles and that, in order to strengthen the bond of solidarity for a coalition of diverse social and cultural identities, what is called for is some kind of grand narrative that clearly defines the powers to be resisted and dismantled. I think this applies to a coalition of different religious identities as well. Serene Jones, “Cultural Labor and Theological Critique,” in Brown, Davaney, and Tanner, eds.,<italic>Converging on Culture</italic>, 166–68.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
