<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">afrdevafrdev</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50014718</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Africa Development / Afrique et Développement</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>CODESRIA</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08503907</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24484686</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Negotiating Nation-building and Citizenship through the Truth and Reconciliation Committee's 'Dramatic' Spheres: A Reading of Two Post-apartheid Plays</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Busuyi</given-names>
                  <surname>Mekusi</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2010</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">35</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">1/2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24482948</issue-id>
         <fpage>71</fpage>
         <lpage>94</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Council for the Development of Social Science Research in Africa, 2010</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24484686"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Having a voice, either at the level of the individual or the community, has been one of the atavistic ways of defining or asserting humanity. This allows for the inscription of the twin-capped hegemony of successes or victories and frustrations at both the private locus and the public sphere. The disruptions of this possibility by rifts between natives in pre-colonial South Africa were aggravated in the heat of the colonial suppression it suffered, and was compounded by the operation of apartheid rule. By reason of this misrule, voices were suppressed, with a few cacophonies of dissention breaking forth. The culmination of these disenchantments into the demise of apartheid significantly presaged the need for reconstruction and redefinition of citizenship and cohabitation, and hence the necessity for establishing a public sphere, or put alternatively, a public domain in the form of the Archbishop Desmond Tutu's Truth and Reconciliation Commission. This paper, therefore, seeks to interrogate the dramatic world(s) created using the material properties of the TRC in John Kani's Nothing but the Truth and Zakes Mda's The Bells of Amersfoort. The paper argues that the domination and manipulation of this public realm by the state at the expense of the individual is not only counterproductive, but constitutes a denial of the relevance of such spheres. The paper, going by indices in the plays, therefore, concludes that every individual should not only be: given a voice, and be heard, but be allowed equal unbiased participation. Otherwise, the public sphere would not just be impotent, but the idea of nation-building and desirable citizenship would be a mere ruse. Avoir une voix, que ce soit au niveau individuel ou communautaire, a été l'un des moyens ataviques de définition et d'affirmation de l'humanité. Cela tient compte de l'inscription de l'hégémonie à double face des succés ou victoires et des frustrations tant au niveau de l'espace privé que de la sphère publique. Les parturbations de cette possibilité par des clivages entre les autochtones en Afrique du Sud précoloniale ont empiré sous le feu de la répression coloniale que ce pays a subie et ont été aggravées par le régime d'apartheid. En raison de cette mauvaise administration, des voix ont été réprimées, avec quelques cacophonies de dissension. Le paroxysme de ces désenchantements vers la fin de l'apartheid présageait significativement la nécessité de la reconstruction et la redéfinition de la citoyenneté et de la cohabitation, et donc la nécessité d'établir une sphère publique, ou sinon établir un domaine public, sous la forme de la Commission vérité et réconciliation de l'archevêque Desmond Tutu. Cet article vise donc à examiner le (s) monde (s) dramatique (s) créé (s) à l'aide des propriétés matérielles du TRC dans Nothing but the Truth de John Kani et The Bells of Amersfoort de Zakes Mda. L'article soutient que la domination et la manipulation de ce domaine public par l'État au détriment de l'individu n'est pas seulement nuisible, mais constitue un rejet de la pertinence de telles sphères. Cet article, en parcourant les indexes de ces pièces, conclut donc que tout individu doit non seulement avoir une voix et être entendu, mais aussi jouir de son droit à une participation égale impartiale. Sinon, la sphère publique ne serait impuissante et l'idée de construction de la nation et de la citoyenneté souhaitable ne serait rien d'autre qu'un simple stratagème.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="d111030e116a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e123" publication-type="other">
Gary Bridge (2004:61 a)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e130a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e137" publication-type="other">
Charles T. Goodsell (2003:362)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e144a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e151" publication-type="other">
Wolfgang Natter and John Paul Jones III ( 1997:151 ).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e158a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e165" publication-type="other">
Benno Werlen ( 1993:174)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e173a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e180" publication-type="other">
Ruston Bharucha 2002:362</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e186" publication-type="other">
Jay A. Vora and Erika Vora (2004:303)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e192" publication-type="other">
Charles Manga
Fombad 2004:196</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e202a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e209" publication-type="other">
Jay A. Vora and Erika Vora (2004:305).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e216a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e223" publication-type="other">
TBA, 150</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e230a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e237" publication-type="other">
Jay A. Vora and Erika Vora (2004:309)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e243" publication-type="other">
Charles Manga Fombad (2004:198)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e249" publication-type="other">
Jay A. Vora and Erika Vora (2004:319)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e256a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e263" publication-type="other">
NBT, 49</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e270a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e277" publication-type="other">
NBT, 29</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e285a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e292" publication-type="other">
Mark Sanders (2007:25)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d111030e308a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e312" publication-type="other">
Achebe, C., 1975, Morning Yet on Creation Day, New York: Anchor Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e319a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e323" publication-type="other">
Ainley, R., ed., 1998, 'Introduction', New Frontiers of Space, Bodies and Gender,
London: Routledge, pp. xiii-xvii.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e333a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e337" publication-type="other">
Asmal,K. etal., 1996, Reconciliation Through Truth: a Reckoning of Apartheid's
Criminal Governance, Cape Town: David Philip Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e347a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e351" publication-type="other">
Baddeley, A., 1989, 'The Psychology of Remembering and Forgetting', Memory,
History, Culture and the Mind, ed., Thomas Butler, New York: Basil Blackwell
Ltd, pp. 33-60.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e365a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e369" publication-type="other">
Ben Achour, Y., 2002, 'The Order of Truth and the Order of Society', Experiments
with Truth: Transitional Justice and the Process of Truth and Reconciliation,
Document 1 l_Platform 2, Okwui Enwezor et al., eds., Ostfildern-Ruit: Hatje
Cantz Publishers, pp. 123-134.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e385a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e389" publication-type="other">
Bester, R., 2002, 'Trauma and Truth', Experiments with Truth: Transitional Justice
and the Process of Truth and Reconciliation, Document 11_ Platform 2, Okwui
Enwezor et al., eds., Ostfildern-Ruit: Hatje Cantz Publishers, pp. 155-173.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e402a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e406" publication-type="other">
Bharucha, R., 2002, 'Between Truth and Reconciliation: Experiments in Theater
and Public Culture', Experiments with Truth: Transitional Justice and the
Process of Truth and Reconciliation, Document 1 l_Platform 2, Okwui Enwezor
et al., eds., Ostfildern-Ruit: Hatje Cantz Publishers, pp. 361-388.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e422a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e426" publication-type="other">
Bozzoli, B., 2004, Theatre of Struggle and the End of Apartheid, Johannesburg:
Wits University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e436a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e440" publication-type="other">
Bridge, G., 2004, 'Pierre Bourdieu', Key Thinkers on Space and Place, eds., Phil
Hubbard, Rob Kitchin and Gill Valentine, London: SAGE Publications Inc., pp.
59-64.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e453a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e457" publication-type="other">
Clarke, D. and Doel, M., 2004, 'Zygmunt Bauman', Key Thinkers on Space and
Place, eds., Phil Hubbard, Rob Kitchin and Gill Valentine, London: SAGE
Publications Inc., pp. 33-39.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e471a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e475" publication-type="other">
Cole, C.M., 2004, 'Theatres of Truth, Acts of Reconciliation: the TRC in South
Africa', African Drama and Performance, eds., John Conteh-Morgan and
Tejumola Olaniyan, Bloomington: Indiana University Press, pp. 219-226.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e488a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e492" publication-type="other">
Enwezor, O., 2002, 'Introduction', Experiments with Truth: Transitional Justice
and the Process of Truth and Reconciliation, Document 1 l_Platform 2, Okwui
Enwezor et al., eds., Ostfildern-Ruit: Hatje Cantz Publishers, pp. 13-17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e505a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e509" publication-type="other">
Fombad, C.M., 2004, 'Prospects for Peace Building through Truth Commissions
in Africa', The Quest for Peace in Africa: Transformations, Democracy and
Public Policy, ed., Alfred G. Nhema, Utrecht: International Books, pp. 189-219.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e522a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e526" publication-type="other">
Goode, L., 2005, Jürgen Habermas: Democracy and the Public Sphere, London:
Pluto Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e536a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e540" publication-type="other">
Goodsell, C.T., 2003, 'The Concept of Public Space and Its Democratic
Manifestations', American Review of Public Administration, Vol. 33, No. 4,
pp. 361-383.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e553a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e557" publication-type="other">
Kani, J., 2002, Nothing But the Truth, Johannesburg: Witwatersrand University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e568a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e572" publication-type="other">
Kok, de I., 1998, 'Cracked Heirlooms: Memory on Exhibition', Negotiating the
Past: the Making of Memory in South Africa, eds., Sarrah Nuttall and Carli
Coetzee, Cape Town: Oxford University Press, pp. 57-71.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e585a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e589" publication-type="other">
Mamdani, M., 2000, 'The Truth According to the TRC', The Politics of Memory:
Truth, Healing and Social Justice, eds., Ifi Amadiume and Abdullahi An-
Na'im, London: Zed Books, pp. 176-182.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e602a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e606" publication-type="other">
Massey, D., 2005, For Space, London: SAGE Publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e617" publication-type="other">
McCorkle, J., 2001, 'Gender, Text and Space in J.M. Coetzee's Fiction', Spaces and
Crossings: Essays on Literature and Culture in Africa and Beyond, eds., Rita
Wilson and Carlotta von Maltzan, New York: Peter Lang, pp. 107-123.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e630a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e634" publication-type="other">
McGuigan, J., 1998, 'What Price the Public Sphere?', Electronic Empires: Global
Media and Local Resistance, ed., Daya Kishan Thussu, London: Arnold, pp.
91-107.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e647a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e651" publication-type="other">
Mda, Z., 2002, Fools, Bells, and the Habit of Eating (Three satires), Johannesburg:
Witwatersrand University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e662a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e666" publication-type="other">
Natter, W. and J.P. Jones, 1997, 'Identity, Space, and Other Uncertainties', Georges
Benko and Ulf Strohmayer, eds., Space and Social Theory, Oxford: Blackwell
Publishers Ltd, pp. 141-161.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e679a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e683" publication-type="other">
Nuttall, S., 1998, 'Telling "Free" Stories? Memory and Democracy in SouthAffican
Autobiography Since 1994', Negotiating the Past: the Making of Memory in
South Africa, Sarah Nuttall and Carli Coetzee, eds., Cape Town: Oxford
University Press, pp. 76-88.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e699a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e703" publication-type="other">
Olukoshi, A., 2008, 'Bringing the Public Sphere into African Democratic Theory',
Paper presented during the First Plenary Session of the CODESRIA 12th General
Assembly, at Yaoundé, Cameroon, on 8th December.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e716a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e720" publication-type="other">
Philo, C., 2004, 'Michel Foucault', Key Thinkers on Space and Place, eds., Phil
Hubbard, Rob Kitchin and Gill Valentine, London: SAGE Publications Inc., pp.
121-128.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e733a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e737" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P., 2004, Memory, History, Forgetting, Translated by Kathleen Blarney
and David Pellaver, Chicago: The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e747a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e751" publication-type="other">
Sachs, A., 2002, 'Different Kinds of Truth: The South African Truth and
Reconciliation Commission', Experiments with Truth: Transitional Justice
and the Process of Truth and Reconciliation, Document 1 l_Platform 2, Okwui
Enwezor et al., eds., Ostfildern-Ruit: Hatje Cantz Publishers, pp. 43-60.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e768a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e772" publication-type="other">
Sanders, M., 2007, Ambiguities of Witnessing: Law and Literature in the Time of
a Truth Commission, Johannesburg, Wits University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e782a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e786" publication-type="other">
Shafir, M., 2004, 'The Politics of Public Space and the Legacy of the Holocaust in
Postcommunist Hungary', An abridged version of the Paper 'Hungarian
Politics and the Legacy of the Holocaust Since 1989', presented at the 16-18
March 2004 Symposium 'The Holocaust in Hungary: Sixty Years Later',
Washington, D. C., The United State Holocaust Memorial Museum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e805a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e809" publication-type="other">
Sharp, J., 2007, 'The Life and Death of Public Spaces: Public Art and Community
Regeneration in Glasgow', Cultural Geographies, pp. 274-292.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e819a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e823" publication-type="other">
Shields, R., 1997, 'Spatial Stress and Resistance: Social Meanings of Spatialization',
Georges Benko and Ulf Strohmayer, eds., Space and Social Theory, Oxford:
Blackwell Publishers Ltd, pp. 186-202.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e836a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e840" publication-type="other">
Soyinka, W., 2000, 'Memory, Truth and Healing', The Politics of Memory: Truth,
Healing and Social Justice, eds., Ifi Amadiume and Abdullahi An-Na'im,
London: Zed Books, pp. 20-37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e853a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e857" publication-type="other">
Sparks, C, 1998, 'Is there a Public Sphere?', in Electronic Empires: Global Media
and Local Resistance, ed., Daya Kishan Thussu, London: Arnold, pp. 108-
124.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e871a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e875" publication-type="other">
Tierney, T., 2007, Abstract Space: The Beneath the Media Surface, Oxon: Taylor
&amp; Francis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e885a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e889" publication-type="other">
Vora, J.A. and Vora, E., 2004, 'The Effectiveness of South Africa's Truth and
Reconciliation Commission: Perceptions of Xhosa, Afrikaner, and English South
Africa', Journal of Black Studies, Vol. 34, No 3, pp. 301-322.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d111030e902a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d111030e906" publication-type="other">
Werlen, B., 1993, Society, Action and Space: An Alternative Human Geography,
London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
