<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">riviintesciesoci</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50004310</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Rivista Internazionale di Scienze Sociali</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Societa Cattolica Italiana per gli Studi Scientifici</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0035676X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">18277918</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41623852</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>LA RAGIONE DELLE REGOLE TRA CONTRATTO E "LEVIATHAN"</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>ANDREA</given-names>
                  <surname>VILLANI</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>7</month>
            <year>1994</year>
      
            <day>1</day>
            <month>9</month>
            <year>1994</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>102</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40077267</issue-id>
         <fpage>589</fpage>
         <lpage>630</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 1994 Vita e Pensiero / Pubblicazioni dell'Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41623852"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>A community, in the same way as an individual, can follow as a normal way of behaviour — or as a wanted criteria for behaviour — for all future circumstances to decide discretionally, «case by case», or to define in a moment in time the rule (or a set of rules) that must be valid for the future. To define rules in a community has been indicated by some authors (Geoffrey Brennan and James M. Buchanan particularly) as a way to exit from a situation of a war of every man against every other man, as in the Hobbesian jungle, on one side, and from a situation dominated by a Leviathan on the other. This in a perspective where rules of a common living have been set through a social contract. The rules established through this contract would also form the criteria for a just conduct, in the end therefore for criteria of justice. The essay analyzes the situations and the conditions in which constraining oneself can be rational, even as it is not definible that in all circumstances constraining is more rational than not constraining oneself, that it is more desirable to have rules rather than discretionary decisions, the definition of ways of behaviour rather than the pre-definition of outcomes. As for what concerns the problem of justice, it is indicated how through a contractarian and constitutional procedure rules can be put by unanimous consent, but the problem of the foundation of the same rules remains unresolved. Rules do not seek truth, but only express values accepted by the counterparts in a certain moment in time, and have individuals as sources of these values.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>ita</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>BIBLIOGRAFIA</title>
         <ref id="d16140e126a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e130" publication-type="other">
A.B. Atkinson, James M. Buchanan's Contributions to Economics, in «Scandinavian Journal of
Economics», LXXXIX, 1, 1987, pp. 5-15.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e140a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e144" publication-type="other">
R. Axelrod, The Emergence of Cooperation among Egoists, in «American Political Science
Review», LXXV, 1981, pp. 306-318.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e154a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e158" publication-type="other">
N.P. Barry, Unanimity, Agreement, and Liberalism - A Critique of James Buchanan ys Social
Philosophy, in «Political Theory», XII, 4, novembre 1984, pp. 579-596.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e168a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e172" publication-type="other">
G. Becker, The Economic Approach to Human Behavior, The University of Chicago Press,
Chicago 1976.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e183a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e187" publication-type="other">
P. Bernholz, The Limits of Liberty Between Anarchy and Leviathan. A Critical Appraisal, in
Autori Vari, Pioneering Economics: International Essays in Honor of Professor Demaria,
CEDAM, Padova 1978, pp. 87-107.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e200a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e204" publication-type="other">
C. Bicchieri, Norms of Cooperation, in «Ethics», C, 4, luglio 1990, pp. 838-861.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e211a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e215" publication-type="other">
N. Bobbio, Contratto e contrattualismo nel dibattito attuale, in II futuro della democrazia,
Einaudi, Torino 1984, pp. 125-147.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e225a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e229" publication-type="other">
M. Bovero (a cura di), Ricerche politiche due. Identità, interessi e scelte collettive, Il Saggiatore,
Milano 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e239a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e243" publication-type="other">
D. Braybrooke, No Rules without Virtues: No Virtues without Rules, «Social Theory and
Practice», XXVII, 2, estate 1991, pp. 139-156.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e253a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e257" publication-type="other">
G. Brennan, The Limits and the Logic of Constitutional Restrictions, COUPE Conference
Proceedings, Philadelphia, ottobre 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e268a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e272" publication-type="other">
G. Brennan, Large Numbers, Small Costs: the Uneasy Foundations of Democratic Rule, in G.
Brennan - L.E. Lomasky (eds.), Politics and Process: New Essays in Democratic Theory,
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e285a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e289" publication-type="other">
G. Brennan - J.M. Buchanan, The Reason of Rules. Constitutional Political Economy (1985),
trad. it. a cura di A. Villani, La ragione delle regole, F. Angeli, Milano 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e299a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e303" publication-type="other">
G. Brennan - L.E. Lomasky (eds.), Politics and Process - New Essays in Democratic Thought,
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e313a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e317" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, Limits of Liberty - Between Anarchy and Leviathan (1975), trad. it. parziale, a
cura di D. da Empoli, I limiti della libertà, «Quaderni di Biblioteca della Libertà», Torino 1978.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e327a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e331" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, Freedom in Constitutional Contract (1977), trad. it. a cura di P. Martelli,
Libertà nel contratto costituzionale, Il Saggiatore, Milano 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e341a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e345" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, Liberty, Market and State - Political Economy in the 1980s (1986), trad. it. a
cura di D. da Empoli, Stato, mercato e libertà, Il Mulino, Bologna 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e356a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e360" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, Peut-on apprivoiser la démocratiel, in «Commentaire», XXXVI, inverno 1986,
pp. 673-676.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e370a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e374" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, The Constitution of Economic Policy, in «The American Economic Review»,
LXXVII, 1987, pp. 243-250.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e384a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e388" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, Constitutional Economics, in J. Eatwell - M. Milgate - P. Newman (eds.),
The Invisible Hand, W.W. Norton, New York 1989, pp. 79-87</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e398a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e402" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan, The Domain of Constitutional Economics, in «Constitutional Political
Economy», I, 1, inverno 1989, pp. 1-18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e412a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e416" publication-type="other">
J.M. Buchanan - G. Tullock, The Calculus of Consent: Logical Foundations of Constitutional
Democracy, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (Mich.) 1962.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e426a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e430" publication-type="other">
S. Carubba - D. da Empoli, (a cura di), Scelte pubbliche. Costi della politica e controllo
democratico, Le Monnier, Firenze 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e441a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e445" publication-type="other">
J.L. Coleman, Market Contractarianism and the Unanimity Rule, in «Social Philosophy &amp;
Policy», 2, 1985, pp. 69-114.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e455a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e459" publication-type="other">
J.L. Coleman, Norms as Social Capital, in G. Radnitzcy - P. Bernholz (eds.), Economic
Imperialism - The Economic Approach Applied Outside the Field of Economics, Paragon House
Publishers, New York 1987, pp. 133-155.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e472a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e476" publication-type="other">
D. da Empoli, La libertà programmata, in «Biblioteca della Libertà», aprile-settembre 1977, pp.
175-1182.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e486a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e490" publication-type="other">
D. da Empoli, Libertà e costituzione: da Hayek a Buchanan, in «Il Mulino», 1986, pp. 697-702.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e497a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e501" publication-type="other">
D. da Empoli, Introduzione, in J.M. Buchanan, Stato, mercato e libertà, Il Mulino, Bologna
1989, pp.7-33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e511a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e515" publication-type="other">
D. da Empoli, Beni pubblici e democrazia, in B. Jossa (a cura di), Teoria dei sistemi economici,
UTET, Torino 1989, pp. 77-93.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e526a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e530" publication-type="other">
J. Elster, The Multiple Self(1985), trad. it. L'io multiplo, Feltrinelli, Milano 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e537a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e541" publication-type="other">
J. Elster, Social Norms and Economic Theory, in «The Journal of Economic Perspectives», III, 4,
1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e551a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e555" publication-type="other">
F. Forte, La costituzione fiscale e monetaria e la democrazia competitiva razionale: un approccio
contrattuale, in «Quaderni di Politeia», 1, luglio 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e565a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e569" publication-type="other">
F. Forte, Principi di economia finanziaria, Giuffrè, Milano 1988 (partie. Parte I, vol. I).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e576a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e580" publication-type="other">
F. Forte - E. Granaglia (a cura di), La nuova economia politica americana, Sugarco, Milano
1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e590a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e594" publication-type="other">
F. Forte - G. Mossetto (a cura di), Economia del benessere e democrazia, F. Angeli, Milano
1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e605a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e609" publication-type="other">
B. Frey, From Paradoxes to Social Rules, Or: How Economics Repeats Itself in «Constitutional
Political Economy», I, 2, primavera-estate 1990, pp. 27-34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e619a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e623" publication-type="other">
G. Galeotti, La metafora contrattuale di James Buchanan tra apologo e paradosso, in «Note
economiche», 1, 1982, pp. 21-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e633a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e637" publication-type="other">
G. Galeotti, Dal calcolo del consenso alla costituzione economica. I problemi della democrazia
nell'analisi economica da Buchanan a Schumpeter, Università di Perugia, Perugia 1988 (mimeo).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e647a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e651" publication-type="other">
G. Galeotti, Consenso e costituzione: i problemi della democrazia nell'analisi economica di
James Buchanan, in «Stato e Mercato», 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e661a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e665" publication-type="other">
D. Gauthier, Morals by Agreement, Oxford University Press, Oxford 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e672a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e676" publication-type="other">
A. Glbbard, Norms, Discussions, and Ritual: Evolutionary Puzzles, in «Ethics», C, 4, luglio
1990, pp. 787-802</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e687a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e691" publication-type="other">
R. Hardin, Morality within the Limits of Reason, University of Chicago Press, Chicago 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e698a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e702" publication-type="other">
R. Hardin, Constitutional Political Economy - Agreement on Rules, in «British Journal of
Political Science», XVIII, ottobre 1988, pp. 513-530.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e712a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e716" publication-type="other">
R. Hardin, Contractarianism: Wistful Thinking, in «Constitutional Political Economy», I, 2,
primavera-estate 1990, pp. 35-52.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e726a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e730" publication-type="other">
F.A. Hayek, Law, Legislation and Liberty, I: Rules and Order, Routledge and Kegan Paul,
London 1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e740a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e744" publication-type="other">
R.A. Heiner, Rule-Governed Behavior in Evolution and Human Society, in «Constitutional
Political Economy», I, 1, inverno 1990, pp. 19-46.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e754a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e758" publication-type="other">
T. Hobbes, Leviathan (1651), Everyman Edition 1943; trad. it. a cura di T. Magri, Leviatano,
Editori Riuniti, Roma 1976.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e769a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e773" publication-type="other">
I. Illich, Celebration of Awareness. A Call for Institutional Revolution, Calder &amp; Boyars, London
1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e783a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e787" publication-type="other">
R.P. Inman, Markets, Governments, and the «New» Political Economy, in A.J. Auerbach - M.
Feldstein (eds.), Handbook of Public Economics, 2 voll., North-Holland, Amsterdam 1987, pp.
647-777.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e800a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e804" publication-type="other">
S. Kelman, «Public Choice» and Public Spirit, in «The Public Interest», LXXXVII, primavera
1987, pp. 80-94.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e814a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e818" publication-type="other">
H. Kliemt, The Interest in Rules - A critical discussion of G. Brennan, J .M. Buchanan, in «The
Reason of Rules», University of Duisburg, Duisburg 1988 (mimeo).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e828a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e832" publication-type="other">
H. Kliemt, Papers on Buchanan and Related Subjects, Accedo-Verlag, Munich 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e843" publication-type="other">
E.C. Kolm, Le contrat social liberal, PUF, Paris 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e851a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e855" publication-type="other">
D.R. Lee, The Calculus of Consent and the Constitution of Capitalism, in «The Cato Journal»,
VII, 2, autunno 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e865a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e869" publication-type="other">
M. Lessnoff, Social Contract, Macmillan, London 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e876a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e880" publication-type="other">
S. Lombardini, Lo Stato nel pensiero degli economisti classici, in R. Finzi (a cura di), Il ruolo
dello Stato nel pensiero degli economisti, Il Mulino, Bologna 1977, pp. 17-58</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e890a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e894" publication-type="other">
S. Lombardini, Democrazia e mercato, in II metodo della scienza economica: passato e futuro,
UTET, Torino 1983, pp. 267-314.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e904a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e908" publication-type="other">
J.S. Mill, Considerations on Representative Government, in Essays on Politics and Society,
«Collected Works of J.S. Mill», XIX, University of Toronto Press, Toronto 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e918a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e922" publication-type="other">
L. Ornaghi, Mercato e politica nella teoria della Public Choice, in «Rivista Internazionale di
Scienze Sociali», 1978.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e933a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e937" publication-type="other">
A. Pedone, Regole costituzionali in materia di finanza pubblica, in «Politica economica», 1,
1985, pp. 11-122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e947a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e951" publication-type="other">
PH. Pettit, Virtus Normativa: Rational Choice Perspectives, in «Ethics», C, 4, luglio 1990, pp.
725-755.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e961a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e965" publication-type="other">
D. Reisman, The Political Economy of James Buchanan, Macmillan, Basingstoke 1989, Recen-
sione di J. Wiseman, in «The Economic Journal», C, 402, settembre 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e975a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e979" publication-type="other">
P. Ricoeur, John Rawls: de l'autonomie à la fiction du contrat social, in «Revue de
Métaphysique et de Morale», 3, 1990, pp. 367-384.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e989a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e993" publication-type="other">
F. Romani, Regole costituzionali e politica economica: il principio del pareggio di bilancio, in
La costituzione fiscale e monetaria, CREA, Roma 1983, pp. 51-73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1003a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1007" publication-type="other">
F. Romani, Introduzione, in B. Ackerman, La giustizia sociale nello Stato liberale, Il Mulino,
Bologna 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1018a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1022" publication-type="other">
F. Romani, Il contratto sociale, il dilemma del prigioniero e la rivincita di Hobbes, in «Fonda-
menti», 2, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1032a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1036" publication-type="other">
T. Romer, On James Buchanan's Contributions to Public Economics, in «Journal of Economic
Perspectives», II, 4, autunno 1988, pp. 165-179.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1046a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1050" publication-type="other">
N. Rowe, Rules and Institutions, The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1057a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1061" publication-type="other">
P. Salin, Démocratie et liberté, in «Commentaire», XXXVI, inverno 1986, pp. 676-681.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1068a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1072" publication-type="other">
M.T. Salvemini, Costituzionalismo monetario e fiscale, in «Politica economica», 1, 1985, pp. 123-
136.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1082a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1086" publication-type="other">
A. Sandmo, Buchanan on Political Economy. A Review Artide, in «Journal of Economic
Literature», XXVIII, 1, marzo 1990, pp. 50-65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1097a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1101" publication-type="other">
A. Schotter, The Evolution of Rules, in R.N. Langlois (ed.), Economics as a Process. Essays
in the New Institutional Economics, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge 1986, pp. 117-133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1111a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1115" publication-type="other">
R. Sugden, Contractarianism and Norms, Oxford University Press, Oxford 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1122a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1126" publication-type="other">
G. Tullock, The Calculus: Postscript after 25 Years; Comment, by R. Wagner, «The Cato
Journal», VII, 2, autunno 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1136a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1140" publication-type="other">
E. Ullman-Margalit, The Emergence of Norms, Oxford University Press, Oxford 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1147a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1151" publication-type="other">
E. Ullman-Margalit, Revision of Norms, «Ethics», C, 4, luglio 1990, pp. 756-767.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1158a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1162" publication-type="other">
V. Vanberg, Individual Choice and Constitutional Constraints. The Normative Element in
Classical and Contractarian Liberalism, in «Analyse &amp; Kritik», 8, 1986a, pp. 113-149.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1173a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1177" publication-type="other">
V. Vanberg, Spontaneous Market Order and Social Rules - A Critical Examination of F.A.
Hayek's Theory of Cultural Evolution, in «Economics and Philosophy», II, 1986b, pp.75-100.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1187a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1191" publication-type="other">
V. Vanberg, Morality and Economics. De Moribus est Disputandum, Social Philosophy &amp; Policy
Center, Transaction Books, Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1201a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1205" publication-type="other">
V. Vanberg, Rational Choice, Rule-following and Institutions: An Evolutionary Perspective,
Center for Study of Public Choice, George Mason University, Fairfax (Vir), 1989 (mimeo).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1215a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1219" publication-type="other">
A. Villani, Economia politica costituzionale e regole. Un'introduzione, in G. Brennan - J.M.
Buchanan, La ragione delle regole, F. Angeli, Milano 1991a.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1229a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1233" publication-type="other">
A. Villani, La giustizia secondo John Rawls. Da «A Theory of Justice» a «The Idea of an
Overlapping Consensus », ISU, Università Cattolica, Milano 1991b.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1243a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1247" publication-type="other">
A. Villani, La decisione di Ulisse, Scelte razionali e scelte morali, in «Fenomenologia e Socie-
tà», XV, 1, 1992, pp. 31-74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d16140e1258a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d16140e1262" publication-type="other">
S. Zamagni, Extended Rationality, Altruism, and the Justification of Moral Rules, University of
Bologna, Department of Economics, mimeo, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
