<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">ceskaliteratura</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50009330</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Česká literatura</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Ústav pro ceskou literaturu AV CR</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00090468</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">42686479</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>STUDIE</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Fragment a fragmentárnost</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
                  <surname>Hodrová</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1999</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>47</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40100605</issue-id>
         <fpage>3</fpage>
         <lpage>19</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Ústav pro českou literaturu AV ČR 1999</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/42686479"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This study represents a Chapter from a section devoted to the composition of a literary work and is part of a larger project called ‘The Poetics of a Work of Literature in the Twentieth Century’, which is being undertaken by the Theory Department of the Institute of Czech Literature. The fragment and fragmentariness in a twentieth-century literary work are a manifestation of a marked tendency towards discontinuity or in some cases towards continuity of a certain kind. There exist works of art that for various reasons remain fragments without, however, being preceived as such (the novels of Kafka and Ladislav Klíma’s Velký román, are cases in point); on the other hand, the fragment, that is to say an intentional fragment (such as a sketch or a synopsis), becomes an independent genre whose roots go back to Romanticism (for instance Novalis’s fragment). The fragment and fragmentarieness that manifests itself in the text in the widest possible number of ways (intentional incompleteness and sporadicity, ‘blank spots’ in the Story, the mixing of heterogeneous elements, the alternating of various genres within one work, and so on), we understand as a reaction to the idea about the work as a complete, inlernally unified and accomplished whole with a clear and single Sense, an idea that Classicism molleyeoddled, which was then to a large exient done by Realism and with it all so-called decadent literature (including tendencious, Socialist-Realist literature). The fragment and fragmentariness (with which is linked the idea of a sense that continuously defies being pinned down to any one definition, which follows from its quality of not being fully told, from suggestion, hints, silence, gaps and ‘ holes’) are, in the literature of the twentieth century, perceived as both a genre and also as approaches that can express the open nature of being and of the world better than the whole work can. Because fragmentary works often represent a work in a nascent state or in a state of transformation, they become a picture of a world that is, as Ladislav Klíma pointed out, ‘continuously creating itself’.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>cze</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
