<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">intrevquares</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>International Review of Qualitative Research</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">19408447</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19408455</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">irqr.2014.7.2.217</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/irqr.2014.7.2.217</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Seeing Experiences of Interdisciplinarity Through Student Artwork</article-title>
            <subtitle>Exploring Different Approaches to Analysis</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Costantino</surname>
                  <given-names>Tracie</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Guyotte</surname>
                  <given-names>Kelly</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Kellam</surname>
                  <given-names>Nadia</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Walther</surname>
                  <given-names>Joachim</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <title>About the Authors</title>
               <p>Dr. Tracie Costantino is assistant dean of faculty at the Rhode Island School of Design. Her research focuses on faculty development, creativity, interdisciplinary curriculum, and embodied cognition. In addition to numerous published journal articles and book chapters, Costantino has co-edited two books on aesthetic education:<italic>Essays on Aesthetic Education for the 21st Century</italic>(Sense, 2010) and<italic>Aesthetics, Empathy, and Education</italic>(Peter Lang, 2013).</p>
               <p>Kelly Guyotte is a doctoral candidate in art education at the University of Georgia. She received her BFA and MA in art education and worked as a high school art educator for five years. Her research interests include visual-verbal narrative methodologies, K–20 arts education, interdisciplinarity, creativity, STEAM education, and visual journals. Guyotte is a research assistant on a National Science Foundation grant exploring synergistic learning in a transdisciplinary design studio.</p>
               <p>Dr. Nadia Kellam, an associate professor in the College of Engineering at the University of Georgia, is co-director of the Collaborative Lounge for Understanding Society and Technology through Educational Research (CLUSTER). She is interested in professional identity formation of engineering students, the role of emotion in student learning, transdisciplinarity, synergistic learning, and the narratives of exemplar engineering educators. She designed the environmental engineering design studios and is now developing the new mechanical engineering design spine.</p>
               <p>Dr. Joachim Walther is assistant professor of engineering education research at the University of Georgia. He is co-director of CLUSTER, an interdisciplinary research group with members from engineering, art, educational psychology, and social work. His research interests include empathy in engineering students’ professional formation, reflection in engineering learning, and interpretive research methodologies in the emerging field of engineering education research.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>8</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>7</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>irqr.2014.7.issue-2</issue-id>
         <issue-title>Special Issue: A Day in the Arts: Tuning into the Aesthetics of Qualitative Research</issue-title>
         <fpage>217</fpage>
         <lpage>235</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2014 International Institute for Qualitative Research, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/irqr.2014.7.2.217"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This paper explores visual response methods as a representation of student learning in a college-level interdisciplinary curriculum integrating art and engineering. The visual response methods, specifically visual journals and postcards, are examples of authentic assessment and alternative data collection methods embedded in a mixed-methods (qualitative dominant) practitioner research case study. In the paper, we focus on different means for analyzing these visual responses (e.g., through hermeneutic analysis, document analysis, and narrative analysis) and deliberate the contribution of diverse analysis methods to the researchers’ understanding of students’ experiences of interdisciplinarity in this course.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>interdisciplinary</kwd>
            <kwd>visual journal</kwd>
            <kwd>visual analysis</kwd>
            <kwd>narrative analysis</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
