<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207396</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/592470</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR88413</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>David</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Pellauer</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">DePaul University.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>October 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>88</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>522216</issue-id>
         <fpage>543</fpage>
         <lpage>545</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hall, </surname>
               <given-names>W. David</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Paul Ricoeur and the Poetic Imperative: The Creative Tension between Love and Justice</source>. Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 2007. x+197 pp. $65.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/592470"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In this revised dissertation, W. David Hall argues that Paul Ricoeur’s religious writings can offer an important context for interpreting his philosophical project—that, in fact, Ricoeur’s philosophical writings take on more of a theological tenor over time, especially if one focuses on their growing emphasis on ethics. This development, Hall argues, culminates in a creative tension between love and justice that finds its peak in a confrontation between the ideas of autonomy and theonomy. “The love command lends an imperative structure to the ideal of love that opens it to moral judgment in general and ideals of justice in particular” (2), yet without turning into something reducible to the Kantian notion of a moral categorical imperative. Rather, what is at issue is a “poetic” use of the imperative in Ricoeur’s thought.</p>
      <p>Rather than simply reading Ricoeur’s work in chronological sequence to make this case, Hall aims for what he calls a “critical constructive interpretation” that will yield something like a “situated reading” of Ricoeur’s thought (4), one that will better demonstrate this thesis than Ricoeur’s own words do. Basically, the structure of the argument Hall proposes begins from what Ricoeur has to say about the idea of agency in relation to the understanding of selfhood. Hall then moves on to consider the narrative configuration of a meaningful existence that follows from this understanding. He then takes up questions that can arise regarding our practical experience and moral concerns from this perspective. It is the testimony of conscience that comes in at this latter level that brings in the theological perspective. It does so through a discussion of what Ricoeur has to say about the Golden Rule in relation to the love commandment and in relation to what Ricoeur calls a logic of superabundance, one that goes beyond any logic of equivalence. It is this idea of a possible logic of superabundance that leads in turn to a discussion of what Hall calls the economy of the gift and the poetic imperative that Hall sees in Ricoeur’s concept of a theonomy that stands over against Kant’s call for an autonomy that all too easily isolates people from one another. It is love that drives this poetic imperative, and what love calls for is something more than, not less than, justice.</p>
      <p>Hall sees that this argument as it develops across Ricoeur’s writings raises questions about the role of reciprocity in the Ricoeur texts he considers. He acknowledges that Ricoeur’s recognition that not all human relations are face‐to‐face leads him beyond a narrow call for solicitude and friendship at this level to a concern for the level of institutions as well. It is at this level of institutions that the question of justice really arises, and with it new questions regarding responsibility and possible reciprocity, particularly regarding our ability to respond to others who we may never meet face‐to‐face. As Hall says, “love often demands a dimension of self‐sacrifice, most notably in the form of renouncing a strict reciprocity” (150). His case could have been stronger here if he had incorporated Ricoeur’s discussions of the work of John Rawls and the antisacrificial notion of justice he saw there. Beyond this, Hall’s focal idea of a relation between love and justice marked by what he calls a poetic tension should also have included some discussion of what Ricoeur says in<italic>The Course of Recognition</italic>(Institute for Human Sciences Vienna Lecture Series, trans. David Pellauer [Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2005]; originally published as<italic>Parcours de la reconnaissance</italic>[Paris: Éditions Stock, 2004]) about the limits of existing philosophies of recognition, which he saw as not getting any further than a notion of reciprocal recognition in just the sense Hall criticizes. Ricoeur’s own answer was to begin there to lay out the idea of mutual recognition beyond mere reciprocity, a higher form of recognition that stands closer, as Hall anticipates, to something like the reception of a gift that expects nothing in return but which may lead to a second gift given to others. Readers who wish to build on Hall’s argument will want also to look at this last major book from Ricoeur.</p>
   </body>
</article>
