<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerhistrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The American Historical Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>American Historical Association</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00028762</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19375239</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3523280</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/530341</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reviews of Books</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Woolf</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>April 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>109</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>587019</issue-id>
         <fpage>470</fpage>
         <lpage>471</lpage>
         <page-range>470-471</page-range>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Barbarism and Religion: Volume Three, The First Decline and Fall J. G. A. Pocock</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/530341"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="index_only">
         <title/>
         <p>[[START 06A00070]] Reviews of Books and Films neered research in this latter area in "A Feminine Past? Gender, Genre and Historical Knowledge in England, 1500-1800," American Historical Review 102:3 [June 1997]: 645-79). But these are ungenerous caveats: this is a meticulously researched study in which analysis is ably supported by a range of impres- sive statistical data and well-chosen (and sometimes entertaining) case studies of individual readers, pub- lishers, and publications. ROSEMARY MITCHELL University of Leeds J. G. A. POCocK. [[END 06A00070]] [[START 06A00080]] Barbarism and Religion: Volume Three, The First Decline and Fall. New York: Cam- bridge University Press. 2003. Pp. xiii, 527. $60.00. In reviewing for this journal the first two volumes of J. G. A. Pocock's Barbarism and Religion, the present reviewer observed that there is a symphonic quality to Pocock's writing, as polyphonic lines in the form of concepts are spun out, developed, inverted, and brought into counterpoint with others. This third movement offers a scherzo reminiscent of the author's 1975 book, The Machiavellian Moment, and it sounds some of the same chords (republicanism, political cycles, civic virtue, arms vs. commerce). The subtitle of volume three is deceptively simple: it refers to the first (and best-known) volume of Edward Gibbon's masterpiece, which he published in 1776. That book commenced (after a very brief account of the structure of the Augustan principate) with the "Five Good" Antonine emperors from Nerva to Mar- cus Aurelius, and concluded (narratively) with Con- stantine's defeat of Licinius and restoration of a unified rule-a temporary resolution immediately fol- lowed by two chapters on Christianity that seem jarringly out of place, given the fact that Christians are scarcely mentioned through the previous fourteen chapters. Gibbon's readers had to wait until 1781 for the story to pick up again. Exposition of this "first decline and fall" in fact occupies only the last hundred pages of Pocock's volume and therefore serves as both a climax to the Pocockian story so far, and a bridge to the next volume. Volume one of Barbarism and Religion situated Gibbon intellectually within a number of different European "Enlightenments"; volume two located him on a different axis, among the various writers of "narratives of civil government" in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. (We are still missing the parallel vector running through ecclesiastical histori- ography, although Eusebius, Augustine, Orosius, and Otto of Freising figure prominently here. Christianity only begins to signal its importance with chapter fifteen of Gibbon; where he used ecclesiastical author- ities, up to that point, it was to document civil rather than sacred history.) Volume three moves in a third, diachronic dimension, tracing the transformations of key themes, in particular the idea of "decline and fall" itself, from very ancient origins up to the Scot Adam Ferguson's Progress and Termination of the Roman Republic (which appeared seven years after Gibbon's first volume and is thus offered for comparison rather than direct influence). The flight of concepts and motifs is dizzying, the lengthy quotations apposite, and as with the previous volumes, one can scarcely miss a sentence without losing a nuance or a parenthetical qualification. The theme of decline and fall, which informs the conception and beginning of Gibbon's book, would eventually yield to "barbarism and reli- gion" as its principal causes in later volumes (along with over-taxation, which Gibbon mentions at the close of chapter fourteen). But behind that idea, which only gradually emerged from Polybian political cycles via medieval notions of the translatio imperii, lay much else, including sequential recognitions of crucial turn- ing points in Roman history going back to Gracchan land reforms in the late second century B.C.E. The core problem, historiographically, remains how to explain why Gibbon, committed from an early stage to a Tacitean narrative, chose to begin his account not with the Julio-Claudians but instead at the "Antonine moment" of imperial zenith achieved by Trajan. (As he once did with cinquecento Florence, Pocock inclines to define major turning points or episodes, both historical and intellectual, in terms of "moments"-a historical Constantinean and historiographical Zosiman moment lie ahead, and the Machiavellian version even puts in a cameo appearance when this volume reaches the early eighteenth century.) Gibbon knew intimately the char- acter of Augustan rule and the flaws of the late republic; he had read his Sallust as well as Tacitus. The later imperial historians, especially Appian of Alexan- dria and Ammianus Marcellinus, also figure in this account as historians of decline, but of a decline that takes a great deal of time-all the way to the "Illyrian" recovery of the late third century-really to become unmistakeable. The subjects confronted by Gibbon's nearly two millennia of predecessors include the military problem of restless troops settling in an empire that has con- quered all its rivals and closed itself off from further expansion; the civic conflict between virtue and cor- ruption (or rather, the way in which virtue leads to military conquest and empire, which in turn produce an oriental softness); the role of the soldiers in making emperors and especially the legions' realization, in the Year of Four Emperors (68/69 C.E.), that emperors could be made "elsewhere than Rome"; the place of the Augustinian-Orosian "two cities" view of history; the vicissitudes in republicanism (an issue revived in the fifteenth century by Leonardi Bruni, who as a non-Roman concerned mainly with Florence was able to see the empire's longue duree for the first time as declinatio rather than translatio and to initiate, though not complete, a gradual transition in historiography from the latter to the former); and the extension of citizenship to the provinces, along, soon, with the capacity of provincials to be proclaimed emperor. All of these streams converge, not entirely satisfactorily AMERICAN HISTORICAL REVIEW 470 APRIL 2004 [[END 06A00080]] [[START 06A00080]] Methods/Theory from either Gibbon's or Pocock's point of view, in the making of the first volume of the Decline and Fall. In Pocock's summary of Gibbon, the Augustan principate was a system that bumped along for a quarter millennium until, following fifty years of mili- tary anarchy, the Illyrian Diocletian divided the empire into two halves ruled by two senior and two junior emperors. Diocletian himself abandoned any remain- ing pretence that the emperor was merely princeps and imperator, openly assuming virtually an Asiatic despo- tism, styled dominus and secluded from public access. This set the stage for the establishment of an entirely new kind of regime under Constantine in the next generation. The very resilience of the Augustan-Anto- nine system up to that point posed narrative and explanatory challenges for Gibbon in itself, since it occurred despite runs of weak emperors, intermittent monsters (Caligula, Nero, Domitian, Commodus, Ca- racalla), the progressive emasculation of the senate (effectively completed by Septimius Severus early in the third century), and the growing independence of the military. Gibbon's flowing recit is bracketed by peintures (the gallicisms are Pocock's) of Antonine civilization at the start and of Christianity in chapter fifteen. In between the beginning and end of his volume, Gibbon appears to have realized that he had, in a way, painted himself into a corner, given that he had over a thousand years still to narrate, and a radical shift in priorities and design proved necessary. Future volumes of the Decline and Fall would give both the foreign tribes and the Christians much greater prom- inence, and before the last volume's conclusion, a Tacitean account of the decline and fall of western antiquity would evolve into an "enlightened narrative" of the triumph of barbarism and religion, recovery from which had only really begun in Gibbon's own age of civility. This volume is every bit as persuasive as its prede- cessors and, perhaps because it is as much recit as the others were peintures, it is also rather more compelling a read. More than the first two volumes of his work, volume three of Barbarism and Religion leaves one hanging; like Gibbon and his first readers, we are only at the Milvian Bridge, pondering what will follow with Constantine. One hopes that, unlike those readers, we will not have to wait five years for the next episode. DANIEL WOOLF University of Alberta [[END 06A00080]] [[START 06A00090]] LAWRENCE W. MCBRIDE, editor. Reading Irish Histories: Texts, Contexts, and Memory in Modem Ireland. Port- land, Oreg.: Four Courts Press. 2003. Pp. 233. $55.00. The final essay of this collection closes with the following sentiment from Sean Farrell Moran: "Like Socrates and Plato who stood firmly against the influ- ence of myth in Athenian democracy, academic histo- rians will step in to attempt to correct the misconcep- tions of Irish citizens" (p. 218). In the previous essay, one such "academic historian," Ben Novick, stepped into the breach in the following fashion: "Writing, as discussed throughout this book, is a primary means of disseminating information" (p. 211). Socrates and Plato have indeed met their match. It is perhaps unfortunate that this collection, edited by Lawrence W. McBride, closes with one of the most arrogant pieces of scholarship that I have ever had the displeasure of reading. The conceit of the comparison quoted above, and the condescension of statements such as "Perhaps we should pity the peasants. They made the mistake of remembering their past incor- rectly" and "The common Irish man and woman must then be re-educated about Ireland's past and abandon their memories" (p. 218), make it difficult to commend the essay as a fine conclusion to an exceptional book. One can only hope that Moran is trying to be ironic. But it would be unfair to condemn this book on the basis of one author's misguided faith in the powers of the "academic historian." Indeed, the book, although most worthy at times, has enough problems without that. The intention of the collection is clearly estab- lished in the editor's preface: to "examine how a variety of historical narratives were delivered through the written word, but with special attention paid to how readers might have reacted to these texts" (p. 13). The difficulty is that the reader is the one consistent absentee from the essays that follow. From Paul Townend's chapter on the reading rooms of the na- tional movements of the late nineteenth century to Novick's chapter on the newspaper of the Irish Volun- teers, the reader is little more than a shadowy figure. Even the most basic details are ignored; there is no attempt to estimate circulation figures for books or newspapers. Anne Kane's attempts at "reconstructing" (p. 46) what a newspaper reader during the land war might have felt amounts to little more than an essay in speculative sociology. Paul Ricoeur and Clifford Geertz seem to get more attention than the actual people who "may have" (p. 46) and "could well have" (p. 56) responded to the newspapers examined. It also seems unlikely that any farmer facing eviction could have conceived of the land war as a "ritual process" (p. 45). But Kane's essay is not the only one at fault in this fashion. The extent of the readers' absence almost begs one to question why the editor made such a particular point of drawing "special attention" to the reader at all. This is not a fault particular to this book or to these essays. Beyond specific accounts by a reader reacting to a text, which in turn have all the inherent linguistic and interpretative pitfalls of any other text, there are very few ways to interpret the readers' response to any type of narrative. Timothy McMahon is one of the few authors in this collection who actually quotes from the men and women who attended the Gaelic Summer Colleges that he examines. His essay is one of the collection's most valuable as a result. Colin Barr's piece on university education, again valuable in its factual content, has nothing to say about the students or how the changes in the universities effected them AMERICAN HISTORICAL REVIEW 471 APRIL 2004 [[END 06A00090]]</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
