<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerhistrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The American Historical Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00028762</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19375239</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/ahr.111.4.1130</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Reviews of Books</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Methods/Theory</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Oliver W.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Holmes</surname>
               </string-name>
               <aff id="a1">Wesleyan University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>October 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>111</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>526084</issue-id>
         <fpage>1130</fpage>
         <lpage>1131</lpage>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>J. J. A.</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
               <surname>Mooij</surname>
            </string-name>.<source>Time and Mind: The History of a Philosophical Problem.<italic>Translated by P<sc>eter</sc>M<sc>ason</sc>. (Brill's Studies in Intellectual History, number 129.)</italic>
            </source>:<publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>.<year>2005</year>. Pp. 287. $134.00.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 American Historical Association. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>American Historical Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/ahr.111.4.1130"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The intimate relation of philosophy and history has given rise to a series of issues concerning the “question of time.” This book provides an extensive history of a central problem in the philosophy of time, and opens the preface with the question: “Can time exist independently of consciousness or mind?” J. J. A. Mooij addresses the history of this question and analyzes the answers and arguments extended on its behalf in their historical context. The historical scope extends from classical antiquity to the year 2000. Although one may have opined that “the problem of Time and Mind had been solved” either “by Newton around 1700, by Kant around 1800,” or “ by Bergson around 1900,” Mooij maintains, the question remains “open today” (p. 261).</p>
      <p>The Ionian cosmogonies of the sixth century b.c.e. explained how an ordered world evolved out of an undifferentiated initial state of “things.” In the fifth century, science became more particularly an inquiry into the ultimate constitution of material substance: the uniform and permanent “nature of things.” The notion of substance derives from tactile sensation. The belief in substantial things outside us reverts to the original detachment of self from the object. With Heraclitus of Ephesus, philosophy focused on knowing the thing, not on that which is known. Thought controls the phenomena as it constitutes the thinker. The problem of understanding nature was taken to a new level. The Milesian school of philosophers had moved it to the realm of the intellect in that they claimed the universe to be an intelligible whole. The manifold was to be understood as deriving from a sustaining principle or first cause, but was to be perceived in the phenomena.</p>
      <p>For Aristotle, chance is a cause, similar to nature as a cause. Natural motions operate both for a purpose and in accordance with necessity. They are purposive since the sequences of natural processes are not at random. Having set forth the principles, causes, and kinds of motions, Aristotle proceeds in the third and fourth books of his<italic>Physics</italic>to determine the nature of motion and to examine fundamental concepts, such as infinity, place, void, and time, associated with motion. It is at the end of the fourth book of the<italic>Physics</italic>, Mooij maintains, that Aristotle posits the principle, “there can be no time without the rational mind, that mind is only required to measure something that in other respects has full existence independently of the mind” (p. 77).</p>
      <p>In Book XI of his<italic>Confessions</italic>, Augustine formulated the dialectic between historical time and eternity: “Some such different times [past, present, future] do exist in the mind, but nowhere else that I can see. The present of past things is the memory; the present of present things is direct perception; and the present of future things is expectation. If we speak in these terms, I can see three times and I admit that they exist.” According Mooij, “for Augustine … the dependence of time on the soul or mind was only partial” (pp. 68, 78).</p>
      <p>In an effort to overcome David Hume's skepticism, Immanuel Kant attempted, among other things, to establish both the validity of knowledge and the impossibility of knowledge without sensory experience. The idea of times derives from the succession of our perceptions. For, as it is from the disposition of visible and tangible objects that we receive the ideas of space, it is also from the succession of ideas and impressions that we form the idea of time. Time, then for Kant, becomes a “necessary” representation that underlies all “time,” he remarks, “is therefore a purely subjective condition of our (human) intuition [ … ] and in itself, apart from the subject, is nothing” (p. 166). G. F. W. Hegel proceeded beyond Kant to posit that “the narration of history and historical deeds and events appear at the same time; a common inner principle brings them forth together.” In discussing Paul Ricoeur's approach to the question of time, formulated in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>, Mooij traces the philosophic traditions of idealism, phenomenology, and hermeneutics in that three‐volume work. For Ricoeur, “time requires narratives in order to manifest itself fully” (p. 240).</p>
      <p>Closely related to the philosophical problem of consciousness of time was the question of the meaning of time and duration in psychology and in literature. Although Mooij mentions William James's notion of “specious present” in passing, he fails to explicate James's perception of time, which attempted to provide an empiricist account of our temporal concepts through the influence of John Locke (p. 197). Apart from this caveat, the book's strength lies in its perceptiveness and breadth of interpretation of the history of the concept of time. Mooij's accuracy in comprehending and in transmitting the essence of such difficult and complicated philosophies is remarkable.</p>
   </body>
</article>
