<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">style</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Style</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00394238</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">23746629</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">style.40.4.314</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">style.40.4.314</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>ARTICLES</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Camus's<italic>The Fall</italic>: The Dynamics of Narrative Unreliability</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Marcus</surname>
                  <given-names>Amit</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</aff>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <p>
                  <bold>Amit Marcus</bold>(<italic>
                     <email xlink:href="amirmat@bezeqint.net">amirmat@bezeqint.net</email>
                  </italic>) is currently a postdoctoral scholar at the universities of Freiburg and Giessen. His research project, fictional narratives written in the first person plural, is supervised by Monika Fludernik and Ansgar Nünning. This is the third essay based on his dissertation, entitled “Self-Deceptive Narrating Characters: from the Subject in Analytical Philosophy to the Homo-diegetic Narrator, and Back,” which was supervised by Shlomith Rimmon-Kenan. The other two were published in<italic>Partial Answers</italic>4.1 (2006) and<italic>Style</italic>39.2 (2006).</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>Winter 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>40</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>style.40.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>314</fpage>
         <lpage>333</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2006 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/style.40.4.314"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Most scholars dealing with unreliable narration consider the unreliable narrator inferior to the reader in either knowledge or morality. This conception implies that the readers are more reliable than the unreliable narrator and, thanks to this difference, capable of identifying unreliabilty, with no consequences or ramifications for themselves. Although this view is not entirely wrong, the readers' superiority to the narrator may change if the readers either find out new details about the narrator that urge them to reevaluate their classification or discover something new about themselves that encourages them to reconsider their superiority. An interesting combination of these two possibilities is found in Camus's novella<italic>The Fall</italic>(<italic>La Chute</italic>). My interpretation of<italic>The Fall</italic>focuses on the triad narrator-narratee-reader and the narrator's rhetorical manipulations, maintaining that the text both undermines the binary opposition between “unreliable narrator” and “reliable reader” and has some general implications on the position of the reader towards fiction.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">During the past few decades, the widespread criticism of the key terms of such a conception of (un)reliable narration, like<italic>truth, rationality</italic>, and<italic>subjectivity</italic>, has encouraged narratologists to reconsider it. Wall, for example, significantly diminishes the gap between some unreliable narrators, such as Stevens in<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ishiguro</string-name>
               </person-group>'s<source>
                  <italic>The Remains of The Day</italic>
               </source>, and the reader, claiming that no narrator — or any human being — is entirely reliable, consistent, and rational (esp.<fpage>21</fpage>,<fpage>39</fpage>). Yet even in Wall's interpretation of the novel and its challenges to theories of unreliable narration, the reader must be more self-reflexive than the unreliable narrator in order to recognize the latter's mistakes and give a more coherent interpretation to Stevens's story.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Similar expressions can be found in<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Rimmon-Kenan</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>102</fpage>;<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Wall</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>30</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I share<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Yacobi</string-name>
               </person-group>'s view (<article-title>“Reader”</article-title>
               <fpage>7</fpage>) that the reader is inferior to any narrator in the sense that the former cannot directly approach the objects of the fictional world and has no access to a report of this world other than the one given to him by the latter. However, in my discussion of the reader's superiority to the narrator, I am not referring to this kind of ontological or existential gap but rather to the reader's belief that he or she excels the narrator in his or her moral qualities, cognitive abilities, or both. The argument that readers feel superior is stronger for the unreliable narrator whose cognitive abilities are deficient than for the unreliable narrator whose worldview is deformed (sometimes named “untrustworthy” [Lanser] or “discordant” [Cohn]). Principally, a reader may think that he or she shares with the narrator norms that society sees as deformed and recognize that, according to these norms, both he or she and the narrator are unreliable. Nonetheless, I believe that a reader who deviates from common moral values more often regards his or her own values as “truer” or “more reliable” and places his or her trust in the narrator that others call “untrustworthy.” In referring to unreliable narrators I abstain from using<italic>it</italic>, since I share with Zerweck the view that all kinds of unreliable narrators are personified, even though they are not necessarily homodiegetic.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I name the situation of the narration “a monological dialogue” because the words of the narratee are never directly provided in the text and everything that the reader is able to know or assume about him relies on the words of the narrator. The latter asks the narratee some questions, tells of his responses to the story, and even asks him to recount a similar story about his own life (<fpage>71</fpage>, for instance), but the voice of the narratee is never heard. Hence the text merely imitates a dialogue and never becomes one (see also<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fitch</string-name>
               </person-group>). Nevertheless, we shall see that the presence of the narratee stands out, arouses curiosity, and propels the story no less than that of the narrator. Indeed, one may attribute to the narratee the same deafening muteness that is attributed at the beginning of the text to the “gorilla” waiter (<fpage>6</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The fall of the woman, which might be perceived as the central event of the narrative (as regards both its importance and its location in the text), paradoxically promotes the fragmentation of the narrative and its decentralization (see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Felman</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>). On the shattering of self-image, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Brochier</string-name>
               </person-group>and again<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Felman</string-name>
               </person-group>(<fpage>169</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>), who has a subchapter on the disintegration of the witness.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I will later argue that this “individuality” is to a large extent collective, a typical product of a certain kind of society. See also<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Blanchot</string-name>
               </person-group>. The narrator, just like the narratee, is only ostensibly individual. It is well known that Camus added an afterword to the English version of the novella, one in which he portrays Clamence as the hero of his time—a portrait that embodies the illnesses of an entire generation (see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>King</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>87</fpage>;<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fortier</string-name>
               </person-group>). Blanchot adds that the narrator wears a mask that makes him impersonal, expresses human distresses, and has experiences so general that there is not even one reader who cannot relate him- or herself to him.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fortier remarks that situating the “scenery” of the narrative in Amsterdam, a city crowded with strangers and surrounded by water from all sides, helps the narrator to create an appropriate atmosphere, which will captivate the narratee and get hold of him.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quillard discusses the irony that is expressed by, among other means, the manner that the narrator addresses the narratee. Quillard quotes forms of address that are an anomaly in spoken French, such as “monsieur et cher compatriote,” at the end of the first chapter (<fpage>18</fpage>). These forms are an evidence of the narrator's disdain towards the narratee in the guise of a polite appeal, in accordance with the norms of polite society. Quillard contends that<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Camus</string-name>
               </person-group>'s irony employs a hermeneutic function similar to that of Socratic irony: it constitutes a dialogue in which the interlocutor must not accept the narrator's words at face value; he must, on the contrary, distrust the seemingly true and put everything in doubt. Hence the narratee may suspect the narrator's familiarity with him.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See, for example,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Clamence</string-name>
               </person-group>'s reference to<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Dante</string-name>
               </person-group>'s<source>
                  <italic>Divine Comedy</italic>
               </source>(explicitly on<fpage>91</fpage>) as well as to Christ and the New Testament (passim) and to the well-known Dutch painter<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Van Diyck</string-name>
               </person-group>(<fpage>139</fpage>). King points in her essay to structural elements as well as elements of meaning in the novella inspired by Dante's text.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">He says, for example,<article-title>“Soyons justes: il arrivait que mes oublis<italic>fussent</italic>méritoires”</article-title>(<fpage>54</fpage>).<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Clamence</string-name>
               </person-group>directly refers to this peculiarity (<fpage>8</fpage>). See also<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>King</string-name>
               </person-group>. Clamence's rhetorical devices mentioned here may be perceived as on the one hand bringing the narrator closer to the narratee (because they are adapted to his intellectual level) and on the other hand distancing him (because they mar the familiar atmosphere that the narrator tries to create).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clamence's narcissism may make the readers wonder whether the narratee exists as a real character or only as a projection of the narrator. Certain characteristics of the narratee differentiate him from the narrator and make it difficult to identify the narratee with one aspect or another of the narrator's soul. Especially prominent is the refusal of the narratee to confess to the narrator, despite the latter's constant pleadings. In this way the role-play persists through the novella: the narrator narrates (and verifies the narratee's attention once in a while), and the narratee listens (and sometimes interrogates, responds, smiles, or protests).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For a thorough treatment of the narrator's rhetorical devices, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Brochier</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">In this context, there are some fascinating connections between<italic>The Fall</italic>and<italic>Oedipus Rex</italic>, some of which are indicated by Blanchot. Oedipus's self-image, like Clamence's, was based during a great part of his life on escaping from the truth (although these are very different kinds of truths). Blanchot claims that both the classical Greek tragedy and the modern novella are centered on a “king” (with or without quotation marks) who reigns securely, until the fact that he has “one eye too many,” meaning excessive lucidity, dramatically changes his life and urges him to abdicate.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For Clamence's reexamination of his life and the way it is expressed in his narration, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fitch</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Blanchot comments that the fall of the narrator, just like the fall of each of us, has no real beginning. We fall and console ourselves with the assertion of a certain point at which our fall began.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">On this test, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fortier</string-name>
               </person-group>.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Felman</string-name>
               </person-group>discusses the kind of paradox in which the narrator is unable to experience, comprehend, and narrate the event that he relates.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Portier elaborately notes, in accordance with his structuralist methodology, words in the novella pointing upwards as opposed to words pointing downwards. Everything that goes deep and is thus literally and symbolically related to the fall arouses disgust in the narrator, whereas everything that rises or is associated with the state prior to the fall excites him.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The term “stage of existence” is based on the philosophy of the Danish philosopher Sèren Kierkegaard, who is counted, just like Camus, among the existentialist philosophers. According to Kierkegaard, there are three such stages: aesthetic, ethical, and religious. The aesthetic stage is identified by Kierkegaard with a hedonistic way of life. Each person chooses one of these stages and may choose another one at every phase of his life. Kierkegaard believes that the religious stage of existence is the highest and that it most fully realizes the goal of human existence. As opposed to this, Camus does not believe any more in the possibility of this stage of existence as a solution to the anguish of modern human being, and in his fictional and philosophical writings he asks to deal with a human world with no God.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">This idea of changing one circle of existence for another as a result of the revelation of an internal existential contradiction in one of the circles is also drawn from Kierkegaard's thought. Kierkegaard himself relies on Hegelian dialectics with regard to this; however, as opposed to Hegel, he believes that exposing the contradiction does not<italic>necessarily</italic>lead to a change that will solve it, but that every change in the existential sphere is the result of a<italic>chosen</italic>act.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">For Clamence's immersion in hedonism and the failure of this way of life for him, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Brochier</string-name>
               </person-group>,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>King</string-name>
               </person-group>, and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Portier</string-name>
               </person-group>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">As noted above, all of the narratee's responses are only inferable from Clamence's narration and are never spoken directly.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clamence argues that Christ was not really blameless, because the Massacre of the Innocents would not have taken place had he not come into the world.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">King justly refers to Clamence as a sort of Antichrist. Like the devil, he too falls from the heights of his vanity, and, like him, he betrays, after his fall, those who have cooperated with him, by his announcement of a universal guilt.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See also<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Zerweck</string-name>
               </person-group>'s general statement (citing<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Wall</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>23</fpage>): “[U]nreliable narrators in realist contemporary texts no longer necessarily highlight the unreliability of the fictional narrator<italic>per se</italic>. Instead, they question both “reliable” and “unreliable” narration and the distinction we make between them'” (<fpage>163</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I disagree with Fitch's claim that the only thing left of the narrator at the end of the novella is his presence, and the attempt to persuade the reader to confess of his own life. Fitch contends that the hermeneutic action at the end shifts from “the text in itself” to “the text for the reader,” as the mirror is turned to the latter. Admittedly, the narrator queries the truthfulness of every detail of his story; nonetheless, I believe that the general frame of the story: a life that is based on lies — a traumatic experience (or traumatic experiences) — disillusionment and guilt is not to be doubted. If the reader doubts these too, he or she will not be able to see the mirror that is directed at him or her. In my view, the mirror effect is created only if the narrator continues to be reflected in it until the end, even though it is no longer turned to him.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I agree with Blanchot about the ironic tone, including self-irony, shrouding the entire novella. Unlike Blanchot, however, I think that Clamence has a serious intention (the contrast between “serious” and “ironic” is Blanchot's) to shift the guilt from himself to his narratee. This intention is at the heart of Clamence's motivation to narrate his story.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Within this context, Brochier names Clamence an “intellectual terrorist,” arguing that intellect serves Clamence to gain power over others and to prove his superiority (<fpage>121</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <label>28</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fitch claims that the narratee of<italic>The Fall</italic>is the implied reader who has become a fictional character. However, I believe that just as the fictional narratee cannot be identified with the narrator, so he cannot be identified with the reader, although their attributes partly overlap. The specific attributes of the narratee, for example his sex (male), his age (forty years old, more or less), his profession (lawyer), and his origins (Parisian) do not necessarily correspond to those of the real or implied reader. Nevertheless, the responses of the narratee to the words of the narrator, for example his wonder in the face of the narrator's declaration of his desperate need for sympathy (“Je vois que cette déclaration vous étonne” [<fpage>35</fpage>]), his questions, for example the question concerning the fateful night to which the narrator hints (“Comment? Quel soir?” [<fpage>36</fpage>]), and, of course, his “courteous” silence (<fpage>70</fpage>), are shared by the implied reader. Like the narratee, the reader too is curious to know what the narrator has to say, is aroused by him to wonder and perturbation, and is “an embarrassed bourgeois,” sufficiently established and educated to be bothered by existential questions related to the meaning of life, death, love, freedom, responsibility, and guilt. Were it not for this, why would the narratee continue to listen to the words of the bothersome and egocentric narrator, and why would the reader continue to read them? The rhetorical devices employed by the narrator-actor, who desperately requires an audience, win him one that is much larger than the specific narratee whom he addresses.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <label>29</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">It is reasonable to argue that the implied author of<italic>The Fall</italic>, not the narrator, is the one who communicates with the reader indirectly, “behind the back” of the narrator. Nevertheless, my opinion is that Clamence's treatment of his narratee as an Everyman who may be exchanged with any other urges the readers to consider themselves included in the narrator's address to the narratee.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <label>30</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fitch stresses that<italic>The Fall</italic>demands from the reader more than what fictional texts usually do: the narrator requests the reader not only to use his or her imagination and identify with the life of the character as it is shaped by the author but also to examine his or her own moral qualities as a person. Unlike Fitch, I believe that<italic>The Fall</italic>is not an unusual text in this respect; its uniqueness is expressed in the rhetorical devices that the narrator employs in order to intensify the involvement of the reader.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <label>31</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Camus's novella undermines certain common presuppositions of the interpretation of the genre named “confessional fiction.” For example, Nave claims that the aim of fictional confession (like the aim of religious confession) is to achieve atonement, to purge oneself, and to be readmitted into society. She contends that confession as a spontaneous-voluntary act is natural and that therefore it evokes a feeling of truth and lacks the forgery and artificiality of the obligatory confession. Clamence's account, especially the paradoxes that he raises with regard to the goal of the confession and its truthfulness, does not enable us to accept Nave's argument without reserve.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <label>32</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fitch justly notes that the reader is not obliged at all to accept the general arguments of the narrator concerning human beings and the world. Similarly, Portier claims that, as opposed to the impression that the narrator tries to create, he does not end his story with the upper hand; the narratee does not simply have to accept his worldview. Unlike me, however, they do not propose alternatives to this worldview.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <label>33</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">A hermeneutic trap similar to the one set by Clamence is attributed to psychoanalysis. Popper argued that if Freud's patients agreed with his interpretation, this agreement was regarded as its confirmation, whereas if they disagreed with it,Freud named this disagreement “resistance,” explaining that the patient represses the truth that is a threat to his mental stability. Thus disagreement as well as agreement confirms the interpretation of the psychoanalyst. Therefore Popper argues, psychoanalytic theory is irrefutable.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <label>34</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Felman and Reilly deal with the concrete political and historical context of Camus's novella. Camus debated with Sartre and other prominent scholars of his time about the communist revolution, and he insisted on the injustice of the use of temporary violence and suppression even if it is meant to serve the purpose of creating a just society. Thus, according to Camus, regarding oneself and one's worldview as utterly pure and innocent as opposed to all others, as a communist of his time might have done, is potentially dangerous for society.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <label>35</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The attempt of the readers to evade the role that is ostensibly dictated to them by the text is in accordance with Iser's position as regards the constant tension between the two elements that construct the implied reader: textual structure and structured act (<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>). Iser contends that textual structure entails different possibilities of realization or concretization. My essay present a few of these possibilities for the reading of<italic>The Fall</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <label>36</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Camus's essay<italic>The Rebel</italic>is connected to<italic>The Fall</italic>in many ways. One interesting connection is between Clamence and different types of “metaphysical rebels” whom Camus describes in the preface of<italic>The Rebel</italic>, such as the dandy (<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <label>37</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">King's critique of Clamence emphasizes that, like other modern rebels whom Camus presents in his essay<italic>The Rebel</italic>, he too engages in a rebellion that has no positive basis that can enable him to surpass himself, and that therefore he fails. The inability to create such a positive basis is connected with his dichotomous worldview, which rejects any doubt and vagueness and concludes that anyone who is not wholly innocent is completely guilty.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <label>38</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See also King's criticism, pointing in a direction different from the one proposed above. King emphasizes that Clamence's interpretation of his behavior and its motives is not truer after the trauma that he experienced than it had been before: as much as he formerly believed himself entirely innocent, the fall makes him believe that all his deeds are purely egoistic. In this way the narrator moves from one extremity to the other and does not succeed in achieving a balanced self-image.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <label>39</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See also Reilly: “The text [of<italic>The Fall</italic>] implicitly challenges us to prove him [Clamence] wrong, but this means breaking the prison, not pretending that it isn't there” (<fpage>137</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <label>40</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Manfred Jahn suggests that the analysis of unreliable narration should consider the axis of<italic>development</italic>(that is, an unreliable narrator becoming more reliable as the story develops or vice versa) as well as the axis of<italic>degrees</italic>and the axis of<italic>aspects</italic>of unreliability (<fpage>85</fpage>). Jahn's suggestion is an important step towards understanding the dynamics of unreliable narration as proposed in this essay.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Blanchot, Maurice</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“La confession dédaigneuse.”</article-title>
               <year>1956</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Les critiques de notre temps et Camus</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>A. Blanc</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Garnier</publisher-name>,<year>1970</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Booth, Wayne C.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Rhetoric of Fiction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1961</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Brochier, Jean-Jacques</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Albert Camus: Philosophe pour classes terminales</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Balland</publisher-name>,<year>1979</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Camus, Albert</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>La Chute: Récit</italic>
               </source>.<year>1956</year>.:<publisher-name>Gallimard</publisher-name>,<year>1961</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Camus, Albert</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>L'Homme révolté</source>.:<publisher-name>Gallimard</publisher-name>,<year>1951</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Chatman, Seymour Benjamin</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Story and Discourse: Narrative Structure in Fiction and Film</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Cornell UP</publisher-name>,<year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Cohn, Dorrit</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Discordant Narration.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Style</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>34</volume>(<year>2000</year>):<fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Dickens, Charles</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>David Copperfield</italic>
               </source>.<year>1849–1850</year>.:<publisher-name>Random</publisher-name>,<year>1969</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Felman, Shoshana</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“The Betrayal of the Witness: Camus'<italic>The Fall</italic>.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Testimony: Crises of Witnessing in Literature, Psychoanalysis, and History</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Felman</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Dori Laub</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>1992</year>.<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fitch, Brian T.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“The Interpreter Interpreted:<italic>La Chute</italic>.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Narcissistic Text: A Reading of Camus' Fiction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of Toronto P</publisher-name>,<year>1982</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fortier, Paul A.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Une Lecture de Camus: La Valeur des Éléments descriptifs dans l'Oeuvre Romanesque</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Klincksieck</publisher-name>,<year>1977</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Iser, Wolfgang</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Act of Reading: A Theory of Aesthetic Response</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher-name>,<year>1978</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Jahn, Manfred</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Package Deals, Exxclusionen, Randzonen: Das Phänomen der Unverlä²ichkeit in den Erzählsituationen.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Unreliable Narration: Studien zur Theorie und Praxis unglaubwürdigen Erzählens in der englischprachigen Erzählliteratur</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Ansgar Nünning</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Wissenschaftlicher</publisher-name>,<year>1998</year>.<fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>King, Adele</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>Camus</source>.<year>1964</year>.:<publisher-name>Oliver</publisher-name>,<year>1966</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Kierkegaard, Søren</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Either/Or: A Fragment of Life</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Doubleday</publisher-name>,<year>1959</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lanser, Susan Sniader</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Narrative Act: Point of View in Prose Fiction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Princeton UP</publisher-name>,<year>1981</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Nave, Hannah</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Confession: A Study of a Genre</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Papirus</publisher-name>,<year>1988</year>. Published in Hebrew.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Nünning, Ansgar</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Unreliable, Compared to What? Towards a Cognitive Theory of Unreliable Narration Prolegomena and Hypotheses.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Transcending Boundaries: Narratology in Context</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Ansgar Nünning</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Narr</publisher-name>,<year>1999</year>.<fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Plato</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Republic</italic>
               </source>. Trans. and introd.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>H. K. P. Lee</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>,<year>1958</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Popper, Karl</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>1963</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Quillard, Genevieve</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Mécanismes ironiques et code socioculturel dans<italic>La Chute</italic>.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Le texte et ses langages</italic>
               </source>.<series>Albert Camus 14</series>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Raymond Gay-Crosier</string-name>
               </person-group>:<publisher-name>Lettres Modernes</publisher-name>,<year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Reilly, Patrick</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The Literature of Guilt: From Gulliver to Golding</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>,<year>1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1984–1988</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Rimmon-Kenan, Shlomith</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Narrative Fiction: Contemporary Poetics</italic>
               </source>.<year>1983</year>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>2002</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Wall, Kathleen</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“<italic>The Remains of the Day</italic>and Its Challenges to Theories of Unreliable Narration.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Journal of Narrative Technique</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>21</volume>(<year>1994</year>):<fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Yacobi, Tamar</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Fictional Reliability as a Communicative Problem.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Poetics Today</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>2</volume>(<year>1981</year>):<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Yacobi, Tamar</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Reader and Norms in Fictional Communication.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Hasifrut</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>2</volume>(<year>1985</year>):<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Zerweck, Bruno</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Historicizing Unreliable Narration: Unreliability and Cultural Discourse in Narrative Fiction.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Style</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>36</volume>(<year>2001</year>):<fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
