<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.28.3.0213</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.28.3.0213</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Introduction</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Allen</surname>
                  <given-names>Amy</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Dartmouth College</aff>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Steinbock</surname>
                  <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Southern Illinois University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>7</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">28</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.28.3.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>213</fpage>
         <lpage>218</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.28.3.0213"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This volume of articles contains highlights from the fifty-second annual meeting of the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP). The University of Oregon hosted our conference on October 24–26, 2013. All three of the plenary sessions for this conference constituted reflections on limits of various kinds: the limits of conceptual thinking, the limits of continental philosophy understood as a kind of post-Kantian quasi-transcendental enterprise, and the idea that SPEP's guiding orientation is an openness to experience that requires the Society to push against its own limits continually, to edge beyond itself. This common thread of reflection on limits has inspired the title of this volume: “Philosophy at/of the Limit.”</p>
      <p>Our keynote speakers for the 2013 meeting were Rudolf Bernet and Catherine Malabou, and we lead off this volume with their articles. Bernet's article, “The Limits of Conceptual Thinking,” is a fascinating reflection that draws on a diverse range of thinkers from Spinoza and Kant to Husserl and Heidegger to Deleuze. The centerpiece of the article stages an illuminating conversation between Heidegger and Deleuze on the nature and limits of conceptual thinking. Bernet draws out some surprising similarities in Heidegger's and Deleuze's critiques of modern, representational thinking, which turn on its objectivism, its subjectivism, and its logicism. Bernet also draws some parallels between Deleuze and Guattari's notion of philosophy as the creation of concepts and Heidegger's late work on the task of philosophical thinking. Despite his trenchant critique of modern, representational forms of conceptual thinking, Deleuze does not turn away from conceptual thinking altogether but reinterprets it as a fundamentally creative process driven by the need to respond to certain problems. Heidegger, by contrast, tends toward a more totalizing critique of conceptual thinking, though his account of the way of thinking bears some affinities to Deleuze's understanding of philosophy as the creation of concepts. Bernet argues that what ultimately explains this difference is Heidegger's and Deleuze's very different readings of early modern philosophy, specifically, Heidegger's lack of appreciation for Spinoza's anti-Cartesian understanding of concepts.</p>
      <p>Catherine Malabou's “Can We Relinquish the Transcendental?” offers a sustained critical engagement with the work of Quentin Meillassoux, particularly his book<italic>After Finitude</italic>, where Meillassoux argues for a relinquishing or an abandonment of the transcendental. As Malabou notes, relinquishing the transcendental means relinquishing Kant, especially the notion of a priori conditions of possibility, which also means relinquishing the foundation or cornerstone of continental philosophy. Malabou traces various twentieth-century attempts to relinquish the transcendental in the work of philosophers such as Heidegger, Derrida, and Foucault and then argues that none of these thinkers goes as far as Meillassoux. While Heidegger, Derrida, and Foucault relinquish the transcendental, Meillassoux abandons it, where this means that he abandons the idea of irreducibility. Malabou agrees with Meillassoux that, up to now, all attempts to abandon the transcendental have led to an embrace of a poetic mode of thinking that has reinforced a problematic split between continental philosophy and science. Unlike Meillassoux, however, Malabou thinks that the true abandonment of the transcendental cannot, as he suggests, leave the world as it is. Abandoning the transcendental has more radical implications than this, including accepting the idea that nothing about us is irreducible: our philosophical categories are reducible to biological concepts, which means that the transcendental itself is in the brain.</p>
      <p>Our third plenary session in 2013 was a new part of the program, the Co-director's Address. Modeled somewhat loosely on the APA Presidential Address, this session was designed to offer the outgoing co-director the chance to speak to the whole membership either about his or her own work or about a reflection on the state of the discipline. Anthony Steinbock, as outgoing co-director, chose the latter approach for his address, though his article, “SPEP and the Continental Divide,” clearly shows that the question of the identity and orientation of SPEP as an organization is as much philosophical as it is practical. Tracing distinct phases in the history of SPEP, Steinbock argues that SPEP's distinctive orientation is its openness to experience. This openness to experience is, of course, central to the methodology of phenomenology, but over the years maintaining this orientation has also pushed SPEP to be open to new styles and currents of thought that go beyond phenomenology. To be sure, this has at times been a conflictual process, as Steinbock recounts, but it has also been one that remains true to SPEP's core animating impulse. However, Steinbock also maintains that this fundamental internal openness and rootedness in experience compels us to resist the strict and dogmatic identification of SPEP with “continental philosophy,” especially where this is understood as the Other of “analytic philosophy.”</p>
      <p>The next section of the issue contains this year's prizewinning articles by emerging scholars. For 2013, the recipient of the Junior Scholar Prize is Timo Miettinen, whose article “Teleology Beyond Metaphysics: Husserlian Phenomenology and the Historical Consciousness of Modernity” argues for the distinctiveness of the phenomenological conception of historical teleology and defends this conception as a necessary component of historical thinking. The 2013 recipient of the Graduate Student Prize is Lauren Guilmette, whose article “In What We Tend to Feel Is Without History: Foucault, Affect, and the Ethics of Curiosity” seeks to uncover the affective dimensions of Foucault's genealogical method and thus to place his work in conversation with feminist and queer theorists of the affective turn.</p>
      <p>The next four sections consist of articles that were chosen from among the papers that were either selected or invited for presentation at the conference. As usual, these articles cover a wide range of themes, topics, and figures; from Aristotle and Fichte to Meillassoux and Malabou; from phenomenology of life and aesthetics to American politics, Critical Theory, and animal studies; from Heidegger's critique of technoscience to the intersection of psychoanalysis and neuroscience.</p>
      <p>The first of these four sections, entitled “Radicalizing Phenomenology,” consists of three articles, each of which pushes phenomenology beyond itself into exciting new directions. Frédéric Seyler's “Fichte in 1804: A Radical Phenomenology of Life?” compares two thinkers who stand at the ends of the chronological spectrum of the phenomenological movement—Fichte and Michel Henry—but who nevertheless share the common aim of offering a phenomenology of life. Seyler argues that this aim leads them to confront an unsurpassable limit, inasmuch as a phenomenology of life attempts to grasp something that is strictly invisible or ineffable: the absolute as life that lies beyond or underneath the subject/object split. Crina Gschwandtner's article, “Revealing the Invisible: Henry and Marion on Aesthetic Experience,” also discusses Henry and considers him in relation to Jean-Luc Marion, with a focus not on the religious implications of their work but, rather, on their aesthetics. Concentrating on the relationship between the visible and invisible and on the way that each thinker privileges the phenomenon of art, Gschwandtner uncovers parallels between and also critically interrogates Henry's and Marion's theories of art and the artist. Finally, in “Is a Hermeneutic Phenomenology Wide Enough? A Ricoeurian Reply to Janicaud's<italic>Phenomenology ‘Wide Open,’</italic>” Scott Davidson stages a critical engagement between Dominique Janicaud and Paul Ricoeur, arguing both that Janicaud's attempt to distance himself from hermeneutic phenomenology is unsuccessful and that the true significance of his minimal phenomenology has yet to be fully appreciated. Davidson further argues that reflecting on the relationship between minimal and hermeneutic phenomenology reveals important new possibilities for phenomenological reflection today.</p>
      <p>The next section, “Rethinking Science with Nietzsche, Heidegger, and Meillassoux,” consists of two articles that revisit aspects of the critique of scientism in nineteenth- and twentieth-century continental philosophy. Joshua Rayman's article, “Nietzsche on Causality,” contests the reading of Nietzsche as a scientific naturalist that is currently popular in Nietzsche studies. Rayman argues that this reading fails to appreciate the radical entailments of Nietzsche's critique of causality, which lies at the heart of his critiques of metaphysics and of the natural sciences. In his article, “Knowing, Counting, Being: Meillassoux, Heidegger, and the Possibility of Science,” Robert Gall responds to Quentin Meillassoux's influential critique of post-Kantian philosophy. Considering the work of Heidegger in detail, Gall argues that Heidegger's work provides ample resources for responding to Meillassoux's critique and that his emphasis on the priority of ontology in philosophy allows us to give a more comprehensive account of science than does Meillassoux's proposed return to a precritical style of philosophizing.</p>
      <p>The section entitled “Psychoanalysis: Between Neuroscience and Phenomenology” consists of two articles that probe the limits of psychoanalysis and its relation to other ways of thinking about consciousness and experience. Elizabeth Rottenberg's article, “Foreign Bodies: Psychoanalysis and Neuroscience,” considers the Oedipal dimensions of psychoanalysis's relationship to neurology. Rottenberg suggests that the desire to correlate the phenomena of psychic life with the structures and functions of the brain can be understood as a wish to return to the primal scene of the separation from neurology that was psychoanalysis's founding moment. Returning to this founding moment whereby Freud broke with the French neurologist Jean-Martin Charcot, Rottenberg argues that fundamental to psychoanalysis is a radical conception of trauma as essentially unlocatable, and this conception leads psychoanalysis to resist correlation with neuroscience. Laura McMahon's article, “Home Invasions: Phenomenological and Psychoanalytic Reflections on Embodiment Relations, Vulnerability, and Breakdown,” puts the psychoanalytic accounts of childhood development offered by Freud and Donald Winnicott into conversation with the phenomenological work of Heidegger and Merleau-Ponty. Drawing on these diverse traditions of thought, framed by an analysis of Ingmar Bergman's 1968 film<italic>Shame</italic>, McMahon explores the ways in which not only our bodies but also our lived space, as an extension of our embodied engagement with the world, are vulnerable to assault.</p>
      <p>Such vulnerability to assault raises questions of ethics that are central to the next section, entitled “Ethics and Reciprocity in Heidegger and Beauvoir.” Julie Kuhlken's article, “Heidegger and Aristotle: Action, Production, and Ethos,” considers Heidegger's practical philosophy, as expressed in his “Letter on Humanism,” in relation to his lectures on Aristotle from the 1920s. Through a discussion of Heidegger's distinctions between action and effecting and between ethics and ethos, Kuhlken argues that Heidegger's practical philosophy focuses less on ethics as it is typically understood today and more on the ancient notion of the good life. In “The Other (Woman): Limits of Knowledge in Beauvoir's Ethics of Reciprocity,” Ellie Anderson reassesses Beauvoir's ethics of reciprocity through a reading of her 1943 novel<italic>She Came to Stay</italic>. Anderson argues, against prominent readers of Beauvoir such as Penelope Deutscher and Debra Bergoffen, that central to Beauvoir's ethics is the recognition of the irreducible otherness or radical alterity of the other—and thus of a fundamental epistemic gap between self and other.</p>
      <p>The final section, “The Gift and the Animal: Rethinking Politics and Critical Theory,” brings together two articles in social and political theory. Alan Schrift's article, “Should Philosophers Still Read Mauss? Thoughts on Contemporary American Politics,” revisits Marcel Mauss's 1925<italic>Essay on the Gift</italic>and argues that its significance for thinking about contemporary politics has yet to be fully appreciated. Schrift finds in Mauss's work an approach to left-wing politics that avoids the binary opposition between Marxism and liberal individualism; as a result, Schrift argues, Mauss's political theory offers important resources for defending social democracy in the context of contemporary American politics. Eduardo Mendieta's article, “The Silence of the Sirens: Rereading<italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>with Kafka and Borges,” returns to the ur-text of Critical Theory and rereads it in light of what Mendieta calls “the animal question.” Weaving a trace among Homer's<italic>Odysseus</italic>, Plato's allegory of the cave, and Horkheimer and Adorno's<italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>, Mendieta argues that the animal question has haunted Western philosophy from the beginning and thus that a critical philosophy must also become an animal philosophy.</p>
      <p>The articles collected here represent the richness and diversity of philosophical work presented at SPEP and thus serve to vindicate Steinbock's vision, expressed in his Co-director's Address, of SPEP as an organization that is grounded in a fundamental openness to experience that leads it to continually push against its own limits and thus to reimagine itself.</p>
   </body>
</article>
