<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207516</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/600278</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR89325</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>W. David</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Hall</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Centre College.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2009</year>
            <string-date>July 2009</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>89</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>598689</issue-id>
         <fpage>443</fpage>
         <lpage>444</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ricoeur, </surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Reflections on the Just</source>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2007. 265 pp. $25.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2009 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/600278"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
         <italic>Reflections on the Just</italic>is a collection of essays addressing the idea of justice as a moral and a practical issue. This review will deal less with the individual essays than with the structure of the volume and the place the work occupies in the larger context of Paul Ricoeur’s thought. Ricoeur’s philosophical oeuvre spans more than fifty years and is vast, both in terms of scope and volume. He is likely to be remembered for two principal works, however: the three volumes of<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>(Chicago, 1984–88), in which he lays out what has become the decisive formulation of the idea of narrative identity, and<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>(Chicago, 1992), the title under which his Gifford Lectures were published. In the latter volume, Ricoeur focuses the idea of narrative identity on questions of moral theory. It is fair to say that Ricoeur’s philosophical production after this point functions less as stand‐alone projects than as clarification and extension of issues raised in<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>.</p>
      <p>This volume is something of a companion to Ricoeur’s earlier collection,<italic>The Just</italic>(Chicago, 2000), but positions the question differently. Ricoeur characterizes the aim of the earlier volume as a focused treatment of the relationship between justice as a moral ideal and justice as a system of institutions. “In the present volume, the adjective ‘just’ is traced back to its terminological and conceptual source, as we find it in Plato’s Socratic dialogues” (1). The volume is divided into three parts, titled respectively, “Studies,” “Readings,” and “Exercises.” This tripartite structure is one that appears constantly in Ricoeur's work. The essays in the first section isolate the idea of justice. In this initial section, Ricoeur brings thought to bear on the principal phenomenological structures through which the problematic of justice manifests itself: the necessary distance introduced into the question of justice by the imposition of a rule of justice, the relation of passivity and autonomy in the articulation of the imperative of justice, the paradoxical nature of authority, and the aporia that opens between the reflection of justice as an abstract, transhistorical ideal and justice as a historically conditioned set of institutional practices. The essays in the second section place the idea in the context of thought about justice. The principal figures who come into the discussion here are Kant, Weber, and Charles Taylor. The essays in the third section deal with the ideal of justice in the realm of practical, or regional, ethics; Ricoeur’s primary interests here are legal and medical ethics and their similarities, differences, and relations. In each of these proceeding sections, issues raised in the first section are taken up and dealt with at a progressively less abstract level. There is then a discernible trajectory that holds these essays together, one that might be characterized, without too much oversimplification, as a movement from abstract structuring of the idea to an analysis of practices by way of configuration. Those who have any previous experience of Ricoeur’s work will recognize this trajectory.</p>
      <p>This is not Ricoeur at his most accessible, and I would not recommend the work as an entrance point for engaging his corpus. The essays are tough going, and the essays in the second section are particularly difficult. The essays do deal with important themes in Ricoeur’s work, ones especially visible in his later writings. Many of the essays are introduced with footnotes that indicate a debt to previous works, and nearly all the essays make some reference to the “little ethics” of<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>but suggest that knowledge of these works is not necessary. This is not completely true in my estimation; it is difficult to discern where Ricoeur is headed in this volume if one knows little or nothing of where he has been. Some understanding may be gained without previous knowledge, but grounding in previous works is essential for a thorough understanding of this volume.</p>
      <p>In providing clarification of previous works,<italic>Reflections on the Just</italic>is exceptionally helpful. Of particular interest in this volume is the paradoxical nature of authority—What is authority? How is it legitimated? Is it claimed or granted?—the existence of vulnerability and passivity within autonomy and initiative, and the relationship between moral ideals and historical manifestation, questions that exist more on the margins of<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>. Those interested in Ricoeur’s religious thought will find little of direct interest here. Those who see a deep connection between his moral philosophy and his philosophy of religion will find some confirmation, but there are other places where the connections are more explicitly manifest.<italic>Reflections on the Just</italic>is best approached as a companion volume to earlier philosophical works, certainly<italic>The Just</italic>but perhaps more importantly<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>. As such, it holds an important place in Ricoeur’s oeuvre.</p>
   </body>
</article>
