<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">intestudquar</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100193</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>International Studies Quarterly</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Butterworth-Heinemann</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00208833</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">14682478</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2600387</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reproduction of Subjects in Historical Structures: Attribution, Identity, and Emotion in the Early Cold War</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Sanjoy</given-names>
                  <surname>Banerjee</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>1991</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>35</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>i324426</issue-id>
         <fpage>19</fpage>
         <lpage>37</lpage>
         <page-range>19-37</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1991 International Studies Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2600387"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>How does international interaction shape states' patterns of thought, emotion, and action? This paper examines the processes by which motives and practices feed each other in reproducing historical structures. An artificial intelligence model defines state-subjects as cultures combining special meanings that produce causal attribution, state self-identification, emotions, and action motives. These special meanings are built from subjective cultural categories describing social acts and group character of the self and others. Anger, pride, fear, and relief motivate action. A collection of such subject-cultures may produce a pattern of actions that reiterates the cultures. The model discriminates between those combinations of elements in special meanings which reproduce subjects and historical structures, and those which do not. The meanings discovered in such reproduction analysis can be validated by discourse analysis.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
