<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">quarrevibiol</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Quarterly Review of Biology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00335770</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15397718</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3071620</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/374515</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">QRB770404095</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Neural Sciences</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Apostolos P.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Georgopoulos</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Brain Sciences Center, Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Minneapolis, Minnesota</aff>
            <x xml:space="preserve"/>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2002</year>
            <string-date>December 2002</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>77</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>qrb.2002.77.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>482</fpage>
         <lpage>482</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>What Makes Us Think?: A Neuroscientist and a Philosopher Argue about Ethics, Human Nature, and the Brain</source>.<italic>By</italic>
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Jean‐Pierre </given-names>
               <surname>Changeux</surname>
            </string-name>
            <italic>and</italic>
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Paul </given-names>
               <surname>Ricoeur</surname>
            </string-name>;<italic>translated by</italic>
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>M B </given-names>
               <surname>DeBevoise</surname>
            </string-name>.<italic>Princeton (New Jersey): Princeton University Press</italic>. $29.95. x + 335 p; ill.; index. ISBN: 0–691–00940–6. [Originally published as<italic>Ce Qui Nous Fait Penser: La Nature et la Règle</italic>, by Editions Odile Jacob, 1998.]<year>2000</year>.</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/374515"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>If you would really like to know what makes us think, you will not get the answer by reading this book—the title is just a misnomer. The volume is a good after‐hours read on the views and exchanges of two prominent researchers, Jean‐Pierre Changeux, a neuroscientist, and Paul Ricoeur, a philosopher. They argue about a lot of issues, from evolution to brain to ethics, rarely reaching an agreement on the role of modern‐age neuroscience in shaping human values and experience. Changeux envisions an overarching role of neuroscience on human affairs. He writes, “[t]he knowledge that we are now in the process of piecing together about the human brain ought to allow us to have a clearer idea—I am perhaps overly optimistic—of the direction in which we wish to see human society develop” (p 27). Ricoeur holds steadfastly to every millimeter occupied by the totality of human experience and its unique value, seeing no special role in it for neuroscience<italic>qua neuro</italic>science. For example, the authors engage in the following exchange: “Changeux: … Today … I think that observational methods make it possible to obtain physical facts about subjective psychological states. A physics of introspection may even be possible. Are we in agreement on this point? Ricoeur: In humans a function is not reducible to an observable behavior.… There is a hermeneutics of daily life that gives introspection the dimension of an interpersonal practice.… This is what I find expressed in the phrase<italic>for intérieur,</italic>one’s heart of hearts—literally, a ‘forum’ in which one speaks to oneself. This heart of hearts has its own particular status that it would appear you will never succeed in explaining in your science. And so my answer to your question is no” (pp 67–69).</p>
      <p>In the course of the book, no real convergence is achieved; each one ends where he started, asserting his own beliefs, visions, and concerns. Has anything been gained in the process? The intense and occasionally pointed dialogues bring forth an incremental, but substantial clarification of the issues at hand, the issues at stake, and their potential (but not actual) interaction. The fact of the matter is that neuroscience has no privileged bearing on human affairs simply because it deals with the brain. Why push it to realms in which it does not belong?</p>
   </body>
</article>
