<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerjtheophil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">American Journal of Theology and Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01943448</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21564795</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">amerjtheophil.35.3.0195</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5406/amerjtheophil.35.3.0195</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Study of Religion after Davidson and Rorty</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Frankenberry</surname>
                  <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>10</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>September 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">35</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">amerjtheophil.35.3.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>195</fpage>
         <lpage>210</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2014 by the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/amerjtheophil.35.3.0195"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mark C. Taylor, After God (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2007), 12.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Robert C. Neville, Ultimates: Philosophical Theology, vol. 1 (Albany: State University of New York Press, 2013), 4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a detailed account, see Terry F. Godlove, Jr., Religion, Interpretation, and Diversity of Belief: The Framework Model From Kant to Durkheim to Davidson (Cambridge, NY: Cambridge University Press, 1989). For a briefer analysis and an explication of the important difference between interpretive priority (more abstract matters) and epistemic priority (more concrete matters), see Terry F. Godlove, Jr., "In What Sense Are Religions Conceptual Frameworks?," in Language, Truth, and Religious Belief: Studies in Twentieth-Century Theory and Method in Religion, ed. Nancy K. Frankenberry and Hans H. Penner (Atlanta: Scholars Press, 1999), 450-72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Terry F. Godlove, Jr., "Saving Belief: On the New Materialism in Religious Studies," in Radical Interpretation in Religion, ed. Nancy K. Frankenberry (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002): 10-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Scott Davis, Believing and Acting: The Pragmatic Turn in Comparative Religion and Ethics (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012), chap. 5. Also, see Davis, "Donald Davidson, Anomalous Monism and the Study of Religion," Method &amp; Theory in the Study of Religion 19, no. 3 (2007): 200-31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Thomas E. Lawson and Robert N. McCauley, Rethinking Religion: Connecting Cognition and Culture (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For their proposal of as many as ten implications of semantic holism for theories of religion, see Steven Engler and Mark Gardiner, "Ten Implications of Semantic Holism for Theories of Religion," Method &amp; Theory in the Study of Religion 22, no. 4 (2010): 283-92. See also their conclusion that Lawson and McCauley's work is flawed for specific reasons, in Engler and Gardiner, "Religion as Superhuman Agency: On Culture and Cognition," in Contemporary Theories of Religion: A Critical Companion, ed. Michael Stausberg (London: Routledge 2009), 22-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Hans H. Penner, Discovering the Buddha: Legends of the Buddha and Their Interpretation (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gabriel Levy, "False but Significant: The Development of Falsity in Religious Cognition in Light of the Holism of the Mental," Method &amp; Theory in the Study of Religion 24, no. 2 (2012): 143-65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>This aim is announced most recently in Alvin Plantinga, Where the Conflict Really Lies: Science, Religion, and Naturalism (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), but it is also the burden of Plantinga, Warrant and Proper Function (New York: Oxford University Press, 1993). My argument using Davidson against Plantinga's hypothetical scenario of widespread skepticism and mainly false beliefs was first presented in a public lecture at a meeting of the Institute for American Religious and Philosophical Thought in June, 2010. I abbreviate those remarks here but elaborate them in "The Fate of Radical Empiricism and the Future of Pragmatic Naturalism," in Pragmatism, Naturalism, and Religion, ed. Matthew C. Bagger (New York: Columbia University Press, forthcoming).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Donald Davidson, "What Metaphors Mean," in Inquiries into Truth and Interpretation (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1984), 245-64.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Tillich, Dynamics of Faith (NY: Harper &amp; Row Publishers, 1957), 48; and Paul Ricoeur, Freud and Philosophy: An Essay on Interpretation (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1970), 19.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Davidson, "What Metaphors Mean," 258.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Donald Davidson, "A Nice Derangement of Epitaphs," in Truth and Interpretation: Perspectives on the Philosophy of Donald Davidson, ed. E. Lepore (Oxford: Blackwell, 1986), 434.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Four of these essays,–"Paradoxes of Irrationality (1982)," "Incoherence and Rationality (1985)," "Deception and Division (1986)," and "Who is Fooled? (1997)"–have been collected in a posthumously published volume. See Donald Davidson, Problems of Rationality (Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press, 2004), 167-230.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Davidson, "Paradoxes of Irrationality," 170-71.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Davidson discusses how his highly abstract account deviates from Freud's in "Paradoxes of Irrationality," 181-85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Portions of this account are drawn from my chapter on "Weakening Religious Belief: Vattimo, Rorty, and Semantic Holism," in Weakening Philosophy: Essays in Honor of Gianni Vattimo, ed. Santiago Zabala (McGill-Queen's University Press, 2007), 273-96.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I owe this image to Linell Cady, who first used it in her plenary address to IARPT in 2010, published as "Religious Imagination in a Late Secular Age: Extending Liberal Traditions in the Twenty-First Century," American Journal of Theology and Philosophy 32, no. 1 (2011): 23-42. Cady cites Fessenden, "Unspirituality" (paper presented at a Social Science Research Council Consultation, Brooklyn, NY, March 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Richard Rorty, "Religious Faith, Intellectual Responsibility, and Romance," American Journal of Theology and Philosophy 17, no. 2 (1996): 121-40. This paper, the first major piece of his philosophy of religion, was presented at a conference I organized in Highlands, North Carolina, in June, 1995. The paper was published in this journal the following year and has been reprinted in several other places. Space does not permit me to consider the additional material that comprises Rorty's philosophy of religion or to elaborate on what I am calling his "aestheticized spirituality," but I hope to do so in another context.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rorty, "Religious Faith, Intellectual Responsibility, and Romance," 133.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Richard Rorty and Gianni Vattimo, The Future of Religion, ed. Santiago Zabala (New York: Columbia University Press, 2005), 37-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Richard Rorty, Achieving Our Country: Leftist Thought in Twentieth-Century America (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1998)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Richard Rorty, "Reply to Jeffrey Stout," in The Philosophy of Richard Rorty, The Library of Living Philosophers, vol. 32, ed. Randall E. Auxier and Lewis Edwin Hahn (Chicago and LaSalle, IL: Open Court, 2010), 548-49.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>This paper is adapted from the first three chapters of a book manuscript I am writing. It originated as the annual AJTP Lecture in conjunction with the American Academy of Religion meetings in Baltimore, Maryland, in November 2013. I am deeply grateful to Michael Raposa for inviting me to give the lecture, and to those who made helpful comments on that occasion.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
