<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">criticalinquiry</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Critical Inquiry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00931896</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15397858</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">20184397</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/589488</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">CI340310</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dickens and the Narratography of Closure</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Garrett</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Stewart</surname>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fnu1"/>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <season>Spring</season>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>34</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>589491</issue-id>
         <fpage>509</fpage>
         <lpage>542</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The University of Chicago. 0093-1896/08/3403-0011$10.00. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/589488"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fnu1">
               <p>The James O. Freedman Professor of Letters at the University of Iowa, Garrett Stewart is the author most recently of<italic>The Look of Reading: Book, Painting, Text</italic>(2006) and<italic>Framed Time: Toward a Postfilmic Cinema</italic>(2007). The present essay is drawn from the opening chapter of a book he is completing on the structural violence of Victorian fiction.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fnu2">
               <p>For her advice on the earliest draft of this essay, when the method was otherwise untried, I'm grateful to my colleague Judith Pascoe, as later to Bill Brown in the final stages of revision.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title/>
         <p>What follows marks out one experimental path, albeit a deviant and wildly hypothetical one, toward an analytic habit I have come to call<italic>narratography.</italic>It is concerned less with the ontology or essence of narrative form across media, its invariant rudiments, than are the usual deliberations of narratology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>Where narratology aspires to a science of transmedial procedures, narratography settles upon the immanent workings of a given medium and, in probing the conditioning operations of graphophonemic or photomechanical inscription, for instance, sets its sights in turn on formative constraints and discrepancies. Narratology abstracts from a given plot, in verbal or cinematic print, to its generalizable modalities. Honing in on the transacted space between genre and its specific phrasal or optical materialization, narratography focuses its attention on the mediate—which is to say, in narrative literature, on those linguistic effects that stand for represented action, of course, but that at the same time stand<italic>between</italic>it and any readerly comprehension.</p>
         <p>Closely attuned in this sense to the textures of execution, narratography has no primary stake in peeling away the layered functions of either language or celluloid, say, to lay bare the abstract girders of formal structure. It more often remains caught up, sometimes tripped up, by the surface adhesions of technique, where a certain resistance to governing narrative formats may well set in. Narratography would name one way of plotting out such resistance. Concerned alike—but separately—with the graphemes of literary manifestation and the graphic increments of visual texts, narratography is the calibration of storyline with its material sequence, from line to line, frame to frame. With written narrative in particular, it monitors the renegotiations of literary structure in the crevices of lexical and syntactic evocation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>Verbal adhesions can in this way yield analytic traction.</p>
         <p>Narratography charts how reading works to process not only the separate arcs of represented action but the tension and roughening of narrative<italic>in</italic>action. Its divergence from narratology has therefore to do with both scale and medium. Narratography stays occupied with the immediate membrane, verbal or visual, of processed effect. Left unexamined by narratology, and programmatically so, is the graphic difference, for instance, between prose and filmic inscription in narrative sequence. This, of course, pinpoints no failing of narratology, but its very mission. It keeps good company in this regard. To deserve its suffix, the kindred discipline of epistemology can't afford to indulge only in the kicking of stones and ignore extraterrestrial sightings. Nor can geology concentrate on sea cliffs and refuse to consider strip mines. Like its cousin ologies, the human science of narratology aspires to be global in its axioms. The result is a kind of lower limit to its focus. That's where narratography comes in: ad hoc, site specific, graphic at base, materially determined, medium-steeped. A recent collection of essays called<italic>Narratologies</italic>doesn't mean to dilute the methodological charter of its discipline with that titular pluralism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>There are many ways to skin a cat and always have been, but none of them leaves you with the surface features by which the feline makes its sinuous mark on recognition. Anatomy is one thing, even Northrop Frye would have been quick to acknowledge, criticism another.</p>
         <p>Before it was dubbed<italic>narratology</italic>, there was narrative morphology. Vladmir Propp, for instance, disclosed dramatic functions or vehicles rather than characters as the rudiments of the folk tale, abstract and commutable factors underlying portrayed events.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>Tapped in this way was the bedrock of the new science. Concerned not with the morphemes and phonemes of language but with the formative units of represented action, such analysis put up little resistance to being reborn, decades later, as structuralist narratology, when its schemata were mapped by A. J. Greimas onto a preformulated communications model of sender and receiver rather than, say, Propp's donor and helper functions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>This transition was smooth enough sailing, of course, because the message function and its means were figured as interior to plot rather than a question first of all of the carrying medium. For that more theory would have been needed—or more something.</p>
         <p>Narratology really came of age in the scanning and sorting of longer forms, where temporal as well as spatial paradigms are needed for compassing the transits of plot, its relays and returns. Going beyond the cross section of sociolects in the rudimentary narrative category of the Bakhtinian chronotope, later and more rigorous topologies of narrative chronos—preeminently in the work of Gérard Genette and Paul Ricoeur—examined the manifold mimesis of temporality, its gradients, shifts, and lacunae.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>Building on such investigations into the byways of narrative time, Peter Brooks went on to elaborate a Freudian model of the drives as motoring the temporal dynamics of narrative, including the unconscious pleasures of deferral, repetition, and closure, the latter always implied—as has been widely appreciated ever since Frank Kermode's<italic>The Sense of an Ending</italic>—by the durational telos of narrative.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Seeking the springs of narrative impulse beneath any given story, Brooks's work runs parallel to, though mostly independent of, the rise of cognitive narratology in film as well as literary studies. Both psychopoetics and cognitive theory seek beneath aesthetic medium for neural disposition or aptitude. For one approach narrative is a deep libidinal need, for the other an abiding perceptual skill. Certainly neither account depends on a given textual instance for the discussion of narrative as mental structuration. And when literature, in particular, offers the test case for such narratology, as it does so successfully in Brooks, the obvious prominence of temporal closure tends to be theorized with no necessary recourse to the local rhetoric of its facilitation, which is often thick on the ground even as plot tapers off. In the Freudian topologies of the chronic, if not the even more loosely conceived discursive chronotope in Bakhtin, analysis is mostly aimed at the timeline of plot rather than the<italic>timed</italic>effects of its verbal processing. But these effects often arrange a microplot all their own, especially when intractable narrative energies, building toward closure, cannot otherwise be released or concealed than by the strain of wording.</p>
         <p>It is hard to overstate the linguistic turn in the ontologization of narrative study, even when the linguistic medium is minimized in analysis or even when the further turn is taken, as with Brooks, into a psycholinguistics of unconscious narrative impulse.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>In this respect, Tzvetan Todorov's grammar of narrative offered, early on, the definitive structuralist breakthrough, where all predication of story begins in the disequilibrium necessary to unsettle a subject into questioning or quest.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>Things must be set right again over the length of narrative duration, brought round to rest, so that the time of story becomes the very course of restoration. For Todorov, mystery is only the most obvious of destabilizing forces. For this reason, the whodunit format of detective fiction becomes the quintessential narrative form. In the most grammatically parsed of all narratologies to follow, Roland Barthes's<italic>S/Z</italic>generalized the hermeneutic code of mystery and its keys to a broader field of interpretive enigma and re/solution and then, on the occasion of a single Balzac story, folded it together with his other linguistically modeled codes before slicing up their functional effects into over five hundred incremental and dovetailed “lexias.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In all such derivatives from the linguistic turn, segmentation is at the core of the enterprise; the lump presumptions of beginning, middle, and end are refined into smaller and smaller units of narrative ingredient. Granted, this morphological tendency leads, in Barthes, to so furious a subdivision of the text that the linguistic model seems almost to turn back to the linguistic effect itself, segmentation pulverized almost to the very granules of lexical succession. Almost but not quite; the “lexias” are never caught back up for Barthes in the syllabic and lexical tread of the narrative sentence itself. Barthes's scintillating precisions may not murder what they dissect, but neither do they rejoin the textual advance after tabulating its codes. The opposite of taxonomy does not guarantee a closer approach to narratography either. In a recent attempt, for instance, to outplay the psychotemporal dynamics familiar from Freud and Brooks with a yet more transgressive “energetics” out of Nietzsche, Lyotard, and Deleuze, Andrew Gibson has advocated a “postmodern narratology” of flow rather than structure, force rather than form.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>But his postmodern valorization of fluid impulse rather than architectonics in both cinematic and literary apprehension—once it is associated with a deterritorialized channeling rather than enchainment of words and images alike—isn't considered as a potential inherent to each medium, where it might have shed light on texts other than those brandishing their avant-garde provocations. While traditional narratology strives to universalize, this postmodern variant sets a premium on certain defiant reaches of experimentation. Issues of narrative closure and semiotic enclosure are nonetheless centrally at stake. So that yet again, as much with the description now of force as of morphological form before, we are offered a loaded account of narrative telos (or here, in many cases, its refusal) rather than a way of reading its maneuvers.</p>
         <p>Period-blind (in any partisan sense) but text-based and medium-bound, narratography is such a way. Beyond the broad reorientations of the linguistic turn, narratography is drawn as well to narrative impulses at work in the single turn of phrase—and not least when a long novel inches toward the irreversible constraints of its end. Even with language gradually dammed up in this way, or leaking unexpected associations under pressure, it seems fair to imagine that the flow of force is soonest discovered from within the framing structures of syntax. While honoring a disciplinary debt, for instance, to Todorov's grammar of narrative, any suitably tensed reading of Dickens needs as well a vigilant sense of grammar's own disruptive narrativity. Broader social realignments in the resolution of plot may of course distract us. Under the rule of poetic justice, the founding disequilibrium of Dickensian narrative seeks equity in the end, not just stability—seeks but does not always find. There may or may not be detection, reprisal, restitution. But there is always a continuous sentencing.</p>
         <p>Where narratology concerns the very formation of story, narratography notes the marked prose of its deformations. What arrests attention at the close of<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>is partly the labor it takes to arrest the unspoken violence of the final plot turn. Prose works phrase by mellifluous phrase to staunch the flow, to pull tight the tourniquet of marital closure before the last bloodletting of all desire. The rescue action is not a matter of rhetoric divorced from narrative, style from plot, but rather the requisition of the one by the other, writing by the agenda of represented event, in a bridled pace to the famous finish line(s). It is there, in a descent from the wedding chapel into the jostling Victorian cityscape, that hero and heroine begin making their no longer solitary way even as “the noisy and the eager, and the arrogant and the<italic>f</italic>roward and the<italic>v</italic>ain,<italic>f</italic>retted, and cha<italic>f</italic>ed, and made their usual uproar”—an uproar into which the new couple, accepting their lapsarian condition, “went” bravely “down,” the verb phrase five times reiterated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>Plot itself subsides into the tapestry of social acceptance. Until then, however, parallel plotting has worked overtime to throw the detective trajectory into dramatic relief against various backdrops of communal indifference. While Arthur Clennam, guilt-laden son of a grasping mercantile house that has been his only home, has been seeking all the while to know the nature of the crime for which his father died, still hoping to cleanse his conscience, in the counterplot the prison girl wronged by his parents is maneuvered into position to accept his hand in marriage. Without solving the crime, he marries the victim. But this convergence of plot strands in the love knot has allowed the detective line to slip away entirely—or, rather, to be summarily truncated. How so, and at what emotional cost, is the focus of this essay. How we go about noticing such repercussions is the methodological topic. The argument is inevitably twofold: a claim for something all but insufferable at the close of this vast troubling novel, something whose brunt is borne by the medium of prose itself, and a claim for the exemplarity of this burden as a proving ground of narratographic attention. For if a close graphing of the wording's covert narrative detonations keeps clearest track of the psychic violence beneath the placid tonalities of Dickensian rhetoric, then the methodological case for narratography—and precisely in view of the detection story's deep narratological valence—may in fact be made as well.</p>
         <p>With the yields of this narratographic approach still pending, what may appear paradoxical en route, given this essay's announced investment in the texture of the written, is that most of its evidence is for a good while entirely made up. I devise an imaginary narrative that springs from what goes wholly unsaid in a single Victorian novel, from what is at most inferred. This effort may appear in progress like an arbitrary concoction imposed upon the novel's quite recognizable convention: its sketchy (indeed euphemistic) handling of background details in a Victorian illegitimacy plot—in this case about a woman no sooner “marked” than written off. But the specter of paradox is in fact chimerical in this case. That is, narrative texts are always, in literary form, inscribing more than they straightforwardly announce. And straightforwardness is, in the case of plot analysis, exactly the issue. Against such linear momentum are inscribed phantom half stories—if not whole counterplots—along the underside of grammar, diction, and the forward drive of their meshed linguistic expectations.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Narratography</italic>is a term of engagement for the way we might sample and decipher that underlying excess, might enter into imaginative transference with its reticences as well as breached repressions at the level of wording itself, might let that wording tug at the thrust of story—even if it offers an intractable snag in the fabric of the supervening rhetorical design. At any point in a novel, but especially in the compressions and exclusions of its closure, narratography would offer a closely calibrated meter of vetoed alternatives. Registered by the ripple effects of the unsaid, these are verbal perturbations that inevitably fall below the radar of a general narratology, whose tendency, when trained (in both senses) on Victorian fiction, is to remain preoccupied more with the logic of closure—mortal, marital, sociopolitical—than with the logistics of foreclosure in the stress of wording itself. Yet it is only across the local ironies and evasions of the written that meaning may be found laboring away at its own construction, borne on the back of prohibited options—or, more to the point, interdicted ones—that may churn unworked in the eddying of the text. Narratology tends, in effect, to diagram structure, however dynamic. Narratography comes closer to graphing a process and its local machinations. If narratography, as posited at the start, is a calibration of storyline to material sequence, another way of conceiving this is to define narratography as a reading of style for its own plot.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>
         </p>
         <p>However fanciful and extreme the agenda of dredged-up narrative restoration in the coming pages, then, its oddness is only in the end heuristic. Such an exaggerated sense of the unwritten installs an alternate narrative universe far from the normal experience of any given novel. But it does so only to foreground the lesser but inevitable counterplay that operates along the line of any fictive response, including a whole range of metaphoric equivocations and reversals in the ambivalent slack of fictional language, its oscillations and ruses, its rhetorical saliencies, elisions, and outright silencings. These form the starting point for the following fictional part of this essay. But let it be clear up front: narratography isn't regularly concerned, and certainly not by definition, with the return of the repressed in so blatant a way as the coming fantasy suggests. Its response isn't as a rule counternarratological in this encompassing sense. But it does involve, in conception as well as in practice, a way of reading the textured pace of the written and its unruly skids against the overriding, the more abstract and immaterial, force of the plotted. I hope I have said enough to license in advance the present experiment, even though in its testing of latencies its operation lingers far out in left field before coming to bat for the text as we have it from Dickens.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Things are moving fast in this very direction as I write. The recent international surge in cognitive narratology is unsatisfied even with the generalizing potential of standing models, which are seen to privilege verbal operation in their general debt to a<italic>discours/récit</italic>paradigm. The inaugural volume in the Narratologia series out of Hamburg is in fact titled<italic>Narratology beyond Literary Criticism: Mediality, Disciplinarity.</italic>In an introduction by Jan Christoph Meister and the volume's two other collaborators, Tom Kindt and Wilhelm Schernus, the point of departure is clear: “No narratologist would dispute the fact that narration is a cross-medial phenomenon.” The volume is therefore devoted not to specifying its operations for different media but to finding a definition of narrative that first of all “must be medium-neutral” (Jan Christoph Meister, Tom Kindt, and Wilhelm Schernus, “Introduction,” in<italic>Narratology beyond Literary Criticism: Mediality, Disciplinarity,</italic>ed. Meister [Berlin, 2005], pp. xiii–xiv). The lead essay by cognitivist Marie-Laure Ryan goes in search of a “medium free theory,” one that “transcends disciplines and media” and that resists what she joins others in lamenting as the “verbal mold” into which narrative analysis has been cast, even in nonliterary media (Marie-Laure Ryan, “On the Theoretical Foundations of Transmedial Narratology,”<italic>Narratology beyond Literary Criticism,</italic>pp. 1–2, 11).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Narratography is medium specific, yes, but it does not privilege literary forms of narrative. It just registers, with less rush to generalization, their linguistic basis when, in fact, wording is the material form in question. In exactly this same spirit, my book<italic>Framed Time: Toward a Postfilmic Cinema</italic>(Chicago, 2007) attempts a comparable charting of cinematographic effects as narrative carriers. See especially the last chapter, “Media Archaeology, Hermeneutics, Narratography” (pp. 206–48). The only previous use of the term<italic>narratography</italic>I've seen comes from the realm of musicology (musicography?) and is deployed there in a quite different (or complementary) sense. For Lawrence Kramer, the term doesn't have a double valence pitched between<italic>fact of</italic>and<italic>study of</italic>—a sense carried, for instance, by the term<italic>geography</italic>. Nor does the suffix invite, as here, the strictly analytic denotation of a term like<italic>cartography</italic>. Rather, Kramer's musical “narratography” gravitates more toward the material than the epistemological sense associated with a noun form like<italic>photography</italic>or<italic>phonography</italic>: the inscribed thing itself rather than the assessment of it, by which Kramer has in mind the notations in music that develop across the staves as a kind of narrative line. See Lawrence Kramer,<italic>Music as Cultural Practice, 1800–1900</italic>(Berkeley, 1990), pp. 186–89.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>See<italic>Narratologies: New Perspectives on Narrative Analysis,</italic>ed. David Herman (Columbus, Ohio, 1999).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>See Vladimir Propp,<italic>Morphology of the Folk Tale,</italic>trans. Laurence Scott (Austin, Tex., 1968).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>See A. J. Greimas,<italic>Structural Semantics: An Attempt at a Method,</italic>trans. Daniele McDowell, Ronald Schleifer, and Alan Velie (Lincoln, Nebr., 1983). This linguistic turn is economically summarized, with Greimas as example, in the title chapter of Peter Brooks,<italic>Reading for the Plot: Design and Intention in Narrative</italic>(New York, 1984), pp. 16–17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>See Gérard Genette,<italic>Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method,</italic>trans. Jane Lewin (Ithaca, N.Y., 1980), and Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Time and Narrative,</italic>trans. Kathleen Blamey, Kathleen McLaughlin, and David Pellauer, 3 vols. (Chicago, 1984–88).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>See Brooks,<italic>Reading for the Plot,</italic>and Frank Kermode,<italic>The Sense of an Ending: Studies in the Theory of Fiction</italic>(New York, 1967).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>This said, of all narrative theorists of literary prose who remain in conversation with the scientific ranks of high narratology, Brooks is in practice no doubt the most richly alert, if not programmatically so, to the recruitment of local stylistic pressure by narrative form.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>See Tzvetan Todorov,<italic>Grammaire du Décaméron</italic>(The Hague, 1969) and<italic>The Poetics of Prose,</italic>trans. Richard Howard (Ithaca, N.Y., 1977); and David Herman,<italic>Universal Grammar and Narrative Form</italic>(Durham, N.C., 1995).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>See Roland Barthes,<italic>S/Z,</italic>trans. Richard Miller (New York, 1974).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>See Andrew Gibson,<italic>Toward a Postmodern Theory of Narrative</italic>(Edinburgh, 1996), where Brooks is discussed in other terms without direct engagement with his own discussion of Derrida, who is central to Gibson's poststructuralist approach as well and for whom form is the vitiated remainder of force no longer felt or understood as such; see Brooks,<italic>Reading for the Plot,</italic>p. 47. In Gibson's work, for all its synthesizing insight, the familiar limitations of narratology seem compounded, not just at the medial but at the panexplanatory level. It isn't just that the terms of<italic>flux</italic>and<italic>flow</italic>are not sufficiently grounded in a given medium to clarify a narrative's internal operation as such, whether achieved by the flickering cascade of the film image or the lability of experimental syntax and typography. (Indeed, moving between media for illustration, the posited fields of force are scanned in the same generalized “narrative” terms across the prose of Alain Robbe-Grillet and the cinema of Hans-Jurgen Syberberg, Henry Green, and Jean-Luc Godard alike.) Beyond this, Gibson's effort also seems curtailed even in its broader narratological ambitions by the author's own poststructuralist allegiance in regard to primary as well as secondary texts. This is because Gibson's method isn't quite an ology after all or even aimed consistently toward one, as his title would suggest, but rather a complex prolegomenon to a reading (or viewing) of postmodern textuality.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Charles Dickens,<italic>Little Dorrit,</italic>ed. Stephen Wall and Helen Small (1857; Harmondsworth, 1998), p. 787; hereafter abbreviated<italic>LD.</italic>
               </p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>By definition, of course, the discipline of stylistics is comparably engaged with a single medium at a time. Narratography, however, does more than specify a mode within this field of attention, does more than single out narrative (and its generic signposts) from other textual (and hence stylistic) manifestations. The differences run deeper. Stylistics is tabular, narratography linear. Stylistics sorts and quantifies, whereas narratography would read<italic>along.</italic>Its detected loops and setbacks, its braidings and slipknots, have their own “narratival” tension and sometimes an equally telling release. This is why narratography, as distinguished from a general stylistics, can be thought to calibrate the very plot of style itself—and sometimes its counterplot.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Barred Narrative</title>
         <p>Even with long-dead authors, criticism traditionally favors a grammar of the historical present. But bear with me, instead, for an exercise in the conjectural future, as we skim through next season's heralded back-story novel, or literary prequel, conceived some years before in the Manhattan office of a rather middlebrow but decidedly high-profile literary agent. It was there that a minor British novelist with some modest popular following even in the States, a respected Oxford lecturer in fiction as well, specializing in the English and Irish novel, had the seed of a new book firmly planted. “Can't you of all people think of another great book, Victorian would be just the ticket, deserving that Jean Rhys-style ‘other side of the story’ treatment? Tales from the madwoman's attic, you know. Hey, maybe three crazies at once.<italic>Dracula</italic>through the glazed eyes of those Transylvanian brides; a fugue of erotic soliloquies, how about it?<italic>The Wide Black Sea?</italic>”</p>
         <p>The agent's pitch, well rehearsed, was amiable and ingratiating at first, then a bit hectoring. “You know: a Lolita's<italic>Lolita,</italic>that bit. Maybe<italic>Sue Bridehead Revisited.</italic>” He was visibly proud of that one. “Just kidding, but you catch my drift. A gimmick, sure, but what isn't these days? Just don't give us<italic>Middlemarch</italic>by Dorothea's maid. Hey, maybe<italic>Casaubon in Love.</italic>Okay—but I'm serious in principle. It's almost foolproof. I know, I know, but it's fail-safe just because it<italic>has</italic>been done. Doesn't mean the idea's done in. It's just become a recognized subgenre: girls with pearl earrings and all.” That, too, got a frown. “Yeah, yeah, but I mean something bigger, more powerful, as I say, more Victorian. A character whose melodramatic story would be so gripping it would eclipse the original, pull the rug right out from under it, turn it inside out. People love that. Canon aura plus one-upmanship all at once.” Our author-to-be was growing defenseless exponentially, seeing his future unfold before him, if not yet the rave reviews.</p>
         <p>The upshot, and to instant fanfare, will eventually hit the shelves under the title<italic>The Story Left Behind.</italic>An advance blurb on the jacket, from Dame A. S. Byatt no less: “This stirring epistolary novel seizes upon the repressed underside of Victorian sexuality, and the covert sadism of its puritanical norms, and lets out the full wail of jailed desire.” Reviews follow suit. So what lost story has been lucratively restored this time? It hadn't, in fact, taken our lecturer-novelist long to land upon just the right source text. An unlikely candidate maybe, with so little to go on in its own pages. But that was exactly the hook—at least once the agent's prod had been administered.</p>
         <p>It had everything,<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>did—everything and then some, its mounting excesses cloaking a final suspect reticence. The black hole was just waiting—not to be plugged, as Dickens did, but to be plumbed and plundered. The trouble was mainly with the dense event horizon of the plot surrounding it. Even committed to the agent's idea, how could he ever get past that final massing of histrionic disclosure and at the same time get its unsaid consequences across? Whenever he had braved the novel in lecture, even with students who had kept up with the reading, his strategic eleventh-hour summary of the thickening plot always seemed like a shock tactic, an assault on both memory and credulity. The mold is set at the outset, he wanted the classes to see. It all begins, dozens of chapters back, with that sad-sack midlifer in crisis, Arthur Clennam, en route to London after two decades with the China branch of his deceased father's underspecified colonial enterprise: vague money, bad vibes. Arthur has drifted homeward again to his loveless mother to sniff out whatever the family secret was that had tormented his father on his deathbed. No sooner is he repatriated, and yet again realienated, than Arthur is perplexed to find that Mrs. Clennam has chosen to employ the daughter of a debtor's-prison inmate to do menial seamstress work. He knows he's onto something, but he can't separate his free-floating attraction to the diminutive prison girl, Amy Dorrit by name, from his sense that the family may owe her something more like accrued financial (than spontaneous emotional) interest.</p>
         <p>As suspicions mount, his sleuthing is suddenly derailed by more urgent concerns and by at least half a dozen apparently unconnected subplots. Above all, we see how the use-value of money always precedes its truth-value. Lots of money suddenly starts changing hands. Amy's poorhouse family comes into a fortune from the first of the novel's two unexpected wills, separating her from Arthur as the Dorrits embark on a showy Grand Tour even as he is getting embroiled in the national craze for stock speculation and ends up symmetrically imprisoned for debt himself. This is exactly what keeps him, feverish the while, from being privy to what the blackmailer Rigaud has independently discovered about Mrs. Clennam's prolonged conspiracy to defraud Amy: first of all, that Arthur's orphaned father had been forced by his rich uncle, under threat of disinheritance, to leave his lover and their new child to marry the well-heeled but heartless woman who became Mrs. Clennam and who has since perpetuated the family lie that she was Arthur's natural mother. But that is only the half of it. On his own deathbed years later, the guilt-stricken uncle had crafted, the blackmailer has found out, a bizarre will that is determined to leave something to someone even if the victimized illegitimate mother cannot be found or is found dead. Even a proxy recipient will help ease the old man's conscience, and it turns out that Amy has come to fill that place by a byzantine zigzag of descent.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Direct reparation for the uncle's cruelty has certainly been impossible. Mrs. Clennam had long ago driven the real victim and mother slowly mad, out of London, and finally, so we're told, to her death by consigning her to the keep of Ephraim Flintwinch, identical twin of her own factotum, Jeremiah, who connives with her in suppressing the inconveniently sentimental will of Uncle Clennam. Thus revelation wells up, only under duress, from a single late chapter. And, as the novelist is quick to assure his students, these complications are all just as congested and loony as they sound. It is only thanks to the blackmailer Rigaud's accidental meeting with Ephraim in Antwerp that this dark secret has sprung its leak. And why was Ephraim there? To escape creditors and debtor's prison, naturally—in other words, to twin this very motif. Inspired by his dubious success in managing Arthur's mother—as we learn in a single throwaway sentence during the climactic showdown between Rigaud and Mrs. Clennam—the second Flintwinch has joined the national craze for overinvestment after the death of his charge. The implied chiasm is sublime, as the novelist always nudges his students to appreciate. While lunatics have rashly speculated in corporate bonds, Ephraim has “speculated unsuccessfully in lunatics” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 852). Amy herself has been left poor again by the stock crash and can therefore meet Arthur on his own lowered terms. After the space-clearing demise of her father, all that plot needs now is another and more sudden death by freak accident (Rigaud's), a traumatic paralysis (Mrs. Clennam's), a swift sweep of the maternal secret under the rug again, and a new marriage (Arthur's to Amy) can begin on modest though emotionally solvent footing.</p>
         <p>Even that sizeable majority of his students with no allergies to happy endings still can't help but see the forced march to a marital closure. By contrast, all a new and oppositional novel would need to do in answering back to all this would be to dust off that secret of the real mother, her child torn from her, and let it breathe at last—breathe long enough to feel its own final asphyxiation. It wouldn't be easy, but the choice of novel seemed just right. In the event, not a single review would doubt it, either. The<italic>TLS</italic>is quite taken. Equally smitten is the<italic>London Review,</italic>which opens its lead notice celebrating “a tour de force that intrepidly impersonates the travails of an anonymous incarcerated madwoman who has forgotten her own name and signs only ‘the befallen one’ to a stream of letters penned as if in blood.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>The<italic>New York Times</italic>quickly weighs in as well, lending the achievement an eye-catching contemporary slant: “The poignant search for the birth parent in so many recent novels and literary memoirs, as in so many real-life stories—with their often thinnest of paper trails building slowly toward tentative letters across the gulf of years—is devastatingly reversed here. What happens, with an unholy sense of suspense, is that the hero's mother, banished to little more than a footnote in the original, rages her way back into plot—through her unmailed rants alone—to remake the whole lumbering thing in the battered image of her own accursed, accusatory words.”</p>
         <p>Not just the choice of foil text but the epistolary gamble itself certainly seems to have paid off. What began at the draft stage in indirect discourse quickly mutated into first person: all of it directly addresed as much to the scribbler herself as to<italic>that woman of flint, that Clennam woman whose given name I couldn't remember now to save my life. As if there were any life to save. All there is left for me is to keep telling the story over and over again, spelling it out in order to believe it. It seems too cruel to be true: the man gone, the son taken. And all this writing entrusted to Ephraim Flintwinch as go-between, of all people! What a name: the villain of steel who winches me tight with those bolts when I, as he calls it, “go off”? Oh, if only I could go off once and for all, one way or the other, rave my way past all this! But no, it just goes on, that sweaty beast my only medium to the world—the madhouse keeper, the drubber, and, worse, the forcer—until now, mercifully, when I have grown too old and shriveled even for his brute use. What can it matter anyway? After all those words, and these words, and these more, by now that miserable orphaned girl and mother, that no one, she who was once me, has almost succeeded in writing herself out.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>Playing off the working title for Dickens's own book,<italic>Nobody's Fault,</italic>our Oxford-don novelist had wanted initially to call this ingrown epistolary novel<italic>Nobody's Story.</italic>As academic chance would have it, he discovered to his dismay in the footnotes of a senior essay by an American exchange student that there was already a book of literary criticism (award-winning, he learned later) by this very title—on an earlier moment in the British novel, to be sure, but still…. The agent wasn't fazed, but it didn't sit well with the writer.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>The bloom was off. Especially because the claim of that scholarly study, bolstered by eighteenth-century economic and philosophical theory contemporaneous with the birth of the novel, was that we are free to invest in characters largely because they are unreal, common property, porous to the invasive imagination of the reader, unprotected by laws against trespass, let alone copyright. Quite by accident and entirely by contrast, our novelist's present trick was to reverse this whole received textual premise, to turn it quite literally “inside out,” as the agent had off-handedly suggested. How? By making a doomed and marginalized minor figure, one who appeared merely as an explanatory sidebar in the original plot, into a real character yearning to break her way through into her rightful place within a novelistic fiction.</p>
         <p>Though the fallback title worked out well enough in the end, the author's scruples against<italic>Nobody's Story</italic>appeared at the time a galling setback. So it was back to the drawing board, indeed to Dickens's own: his original sketchy notes for the story in his preserved chapter plans for<italic>Little Dorrit.</italic>At just the point in Dickens's outlined plot where all the madwoman's writings are to be finally discovered in a stash of letters, Dickens reminds himself to work this up in the actual drafting of the chapter. The note reads simply yet with that rhetorical resonance Dickens can lay claim to even when jotting notes to himself: “She had left her story”—with a careted insert after the first word, expanding the scant indication to “had implored to see her son.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>In fact, this brief telegraphic reminder is more than the novel itself makes good on. The mother's craving for a visit with her child is replaced by a capitulation to guilt, confession, and a plea for forgiveness. It's just as unlikely as it sounds, this sense of penance rather than victimhood—and just as briefly dispatched amid the other strained and improbable turns of the denouement. The missing mother's story itself goes missing, left in the dust by the momentum of the requisite marriage plot. There it was, then, the new title needed:<italic>The Story Left Behind.</italic>The wordplay wouldn't be too arcane for the trade press reader, nor too blatant either. Now you see it, now you don't.</p>
         <p>The whole plan was crafty enough. All depended on whether he could really pull it off. Or put it over. The grueling details of her halting story, a few of which the devoted reader of Dickens would recognize, should show through in disjointed fragments from the crazed meanderings of her letters: the long tunnel back to her singing lessons; her theatrical life behind the curtain; the sweet, sometimes impotent lover; his unfeeling, unexplained, unimaginable departure; the baby gone; the rage; the blankness; the irons on the ankles; the purges and batterings; and all those assaults when the keeper's wife was out or too drunk to hear or care; the whole long uninterrupted violation of everything she knew to be herself. Along with her own traumatic memories of the doings back in London, enough rumors would reach her through Flintwinch that eventually a spectral form of Dickens's main plot should also seem to have bled through between the lines of her own letters. Famous details ought to come across as the shadow story of her own emptiness and dementia, the dye stain that throws her own unslaked cravings into contrast. “Great stuff … keep plugging,” shot back the agent's email. And then the real inspiration struck.</p>
         <p>Right from the start, this unearthed epistolary underside of the omniscient triple-decker had seemed a canny enough move. But, as the writer burrowed deeper into the pangs of the suppressed story, a wilder idea slowly dawned and couldn't be shaken. Our novelist-critic decided to go for broke, cashing out his whole idea at a further metafictional level. It wasn't just that the source text in Dickens holds back more than its form can tolerate and is rather drastically warped out of shape by this containment action. It occurred to the writer that no reader would recognize this sooner, or with more ferocious eloquence, than the plot's own posthumous lover and mother, if only somehow she could be resurrected—or could not yet have died—when the novel arrived in print. She would make the story's ideal against-the-grain reader. What an idea: the madwoman reading<italic>Jane Eyre</italic>in her own attic! And the longer this idea got brooded over the more it seemed to have driven straight through gimmick to masterstroke. Textual empathy always approximates identification. Here we go the whole distance: the reader lost and found at once in the book that delineates and elides her own life. And amid the “trenchant ingenuity” the reviewers could be dreamed to applaud, there might be a further delicious twist. Our scholar-novelist could well imagine his most pretentious counterpart at Cambridge being forced to lecture enviously on the novel someday soon in his widely attended narrative theory course. One could almost hear him, strain in the voice and all: “Put simply, metalepsis takes place, for instance, when a character is, as if real, made present to his author or to the reading of his own novel. Thackeray reveled in it, among the Victorians, and we see it again in, ahem, last year's<italic>The Story Left Behind.</italic>” As for the agent, he balked at first, but came round after reading some more sample pages. “Beautiful—not just slick, beautiful—you've taken the whole subgenre and really upped the stakes. By all means run with it.”</p>
         <p>This was not just a sly turn but a full boomerang effect—along a slow arc, building momentum as it goes. After all those years expended in the feverish penning of an already smudged-out life, the heroine learns to her horror, the first hint dropped in a garbled remark by Flintwinch one besotted midnight, that it has all been for nought. She quickly teases out of him that her words were never in fact posted at all. They were shown to his twin brother instead (these circuitous details still from the novel itself), secreted away in a locked box by that infernal mirror image of her jailor, and then somehow returned to “her” Flintwinch for sequestering. And more maddening yet—here's the new twist, leaving the source text far behind—she learns that they had been lately sold for a song (a drinking song at that) to a respected gentleman who made up part of a large party one evening at the local alehouse and who, having heard the merest gist of her grief, wanted the whole chest of letters shipped to London. She learns, too, that this gentleman trafficker in recorded lives happens to be the famous novelist Boz, in town for some public appearance. Flintwinch had somehow horned in on the long round of toasts and grown talkative with the famous man, who let him know just the use he was hoping to make of these letters. Ephraim was assured on the novelist's departure that, if that poor unfortunate's tale is half as strong as he makes it sound, the good chap might look for the story of his mad female charge in a serialized fiction a year or so later—under assumed names all round of course (the novelist winked) and backdated (the latest fad) into the recent past. Looking for a big finish to a novel he'd been planning, Mr. Boz hoped her crazed tale would turn the trick. And in leaving he raised a glass to her, after ordering Ephraim's filled yet again:<italic>Count on it, my man, the madwoman will have left her story!</italic>
         </p>
         <p>This is to be the last chance, then, for her stolen and now resold life, its last chance for release from all this manacled, mangling silence. Time is a sickly blur until the novel numbers begin appearing. Even Ephraim is interested after his sluggish fashion and brings the first installment up to her after showing it round the pub in one of his stupid boasts. But wait. Little who? What did any of this have to do with her? Marseilles? That prison isn't<italic>her</italic>prison. Not that next one, either. As the numbers drag on, it comes to her ever so slowly. Comes to her that there, burning through all these aliases and inventions and irrelevant digressions, there is her own story blazing out at her after all as if through a chipped prism, facet by facet, time and again. Never by name, or even in person, nonetheless she sees her own poor self everywhere. From early on, she is the secret fact behind every deprivation of the hero's life, every jaded feeling with which he turns from the world.<italic>She is what is missing in him.</italic>Surely, then, she is what the novel will have to make up for, bring forward in the end. She hears echoes of her story in the words themselves, the sly chime of letters, the names for feelings that were hers to begin with. She hears echoes of her fear in Jeremiah's wife, that servant woman Affery, afraid of everything. She should be. She hears echoes of her nemesis in ClenNAM, MRS. And of the word<italic>son,</italic>her son, buried there in every<italic>prison.</italic>It makes her dizzy, this spin of letters, just like when she writes, the words thickening as she sounds them out.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Was I really to have come into money if I could have been found? Or if not, another girl long ago befriended like me by the same Mr. Do Right, the kindly befuddled Dorrit? That's sure a long way round the barn for Boz's reader. And so it is his niece Amy who finds herself in my place. And more and more in my place, I see, as the chapters peter out. They keep saying “Do Not Forget,” but no one seems willing to remember. There is that Rigaud or Blandois or Lagnier, whatever he chooses to call himself, the man of many names where I have none. However that greasy fraud is pronounced in French, there he is in English, that Rigaud, goading the old lady with snatched phrases from the will, rubbing it in. In the face of her haughty denials, why doesn't he at least read one of my letters to shut the old buzzard up—or force her hand? Even if they call me dead they can still give me a mouth.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>So if those letters Boz bought so cheap aren't up to his standards, why doesn't the great writer rewrite them himself, compress my ramblings, make 'em tell—isn't that the phrase? They'd tell, that's for sure, tell too much. Why am I brought back as a curse and a scourge—and then given no words to curse with? And even what leaks is lies. There's Flintwinch talking about me to his mistress, how “she had been always writing, incessantly writing—mainly letters of confession to you, and Prayers for forgiveness.” Never, never a one. No repentance. Just pent-up hate. And after all this, will that trunk of my letters never be produced? Will my secret be trapped away in the asylum of Affery's mind, where it will all seem like a dream anyway?</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>Strange how her affrights are always real, straight through to the end. She thinks I'm alive. Boz gives her that one last hallucination, which he knows to be true as well. She thinks I'm the force that's bringing the house down, not a ghost but a real presence. True enough, I'd gladly think. Listen to the way Affery begs Mrs. Clennam to let her take over my keep: “Only promise me, that, if it's the poor thing that's kept here, secretly, you'll let me take charge of her and be her nurse.” But, no, they all seem willing to agree, I've been “dead a score of years and more.” Not just that, for they say my dying coincided exactly with the moment “when Arthur went abroad.” Do they mean, does Boz mean, that in turning his back on his motherland—to join his father in the business out East—he as much as did me in? Or that without me here, even unknown to him, there was nothing left for the son on native ground? Even in their lies, they're never all wrong.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>And certainly not in their worst fears. I must copy it out, this passage, just to make sure I've got it right. What I hear is the servant Affery shivering to the bone with a sense of my frightful claim on them all:</italic>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>
                  <italic>“So much the worse,” said Affery, with a shiver, “for she haunts the house, then. Who else rustles about it, making signals by dropping dust so softly? Who else comes and goes, and marks the walls with long crooked touches, when we are all a-bed?”</italic>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>Affery knows. She really believes I'm lurking somewhere there, stirring or scratching, like the sound of my own quill maybe, trying to make myself heard. In all that sifting and silting and crumbling, she hears me gnawing away at the rotted fortress from within. But my raspings are not really “signals,” since no one can decipher them. No one in the house but that twitchy servant has ever taken the least notice of those scraped traces and scraps of me. So those crazings are only silent scars all up and down the plaster. The writing on the wall, I'd like it to be: a prophecy and a doom. Dust to dust for them all! But, no, there's no reason to hope that I alone could bring them low in their lies. So I suppose those muffled sounds Affery's so afeared of are more like me turning the very pages of the book that erases me. She's right in one way, I guess. While I read about it, read my way into it, this disintegrating Clennam world is my only abode. But, knowing better, I can't abide it.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>What?! No! Now suddenly the loathsome Rigaud is dead, too, and even this sweet justice ends up a bitter pill. Though he's squashed with his ugly moustache like a whiskered rodent under the beams of the house—the house that my living ghost has, after all, brought thundering down—there is no relief in this either. He's “rubbish” now, but always was. Affery's voice did come “with a shiver” when she spoke of my walled-up truth, and now I've shivered their timbers, all right. But my secret is buried in that villain's smashed brain. Oh, wait, bless her: here comes Tattycoram, who steals the chest from Miss Wade, who could never have known what to do with them, my letters, anyway. They scream of everything she has choked to death in herself. Of love not wanted, therefore not wanting. Now they are to be turned over to my boy's wife-to-be. At last. How will they at last come out, those words of mine, of me? I could almost write it myself, what I guess they call the “revelation scene.” Let Arthur learn of love's price from the written words of his own lost mother, voiced by his new motherly child bride reading to him in the prison, where he has long been too weak to read for himself.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>But, no, when the opportunity comes, she never says a word. She takes up that other unidentified book instead, reading aloud in prison just to kill time from some irrelevancy not even named or summarized. But what will Boz's own reader think, or those who listen to his book read aloud? What is that Little Amy doing? Why give a stay of execution to the false mother's reputation when it means denying the true mother's existence? Who could believe any of this? It's worse than if the old woman were still paying Amy wages to buy her off. And there's something more intolerable yet. Without telling him what the papers are, Amy asks Arthur himself to destroy the will, to burn it up—of all places!—in their last cozy prison fire on the eve of their wedding. What kind of prenuptial vow is this unspoken vow of silence? That incinerated legal document is the one written paper that actually mentions my name in writing. Boz must have noted it down, my name, after drinking with Flintwinch, but seems to have lost track of it as much as I have tried to. So, thanks now to that Little Dorrit, I am to go once and for all unspoken, untold. And, hardest to bear, it is Arthur who gives me over to my cremation. No need for Amy to tell him what it is that he burns, who I am, that I am, what I became. Perhaps she doesn't want him to feel bad about the denial of money to her, about the secret disinheritance.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>Even this one can't trust. She knows that once the old woman dies, and Arthur inherits the family money, she'll get all of it anyway, having married into it, despite the property laws, minus only the smaller portion that she might have used up long ago if it had come to her directly. How bad could Arthur feel for her over that? It's almost comic: that after all those years of being cheated out of it, the little victim comes into the old bat's money after all. Forget the will, then. What else is being plotted by Boz against my story? Why can't he know about me, my Arthur, about his mother who loved him, or at least the idea of him, loved him to melancholy and to madness? Why must he go to the altar still believing that the Clennam woman was his closest blood kin, thinking still that what was forbidden to him in her heart was actually a mother's love? So he'll appreciate Amy more? This is insupportable.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>And Arthur, or whoever you are, why are you doing it? After all your rifling in the basement looking for incriminating papers, hoping to right the family's wrongdoings, why are you no longer interested? Do you half guess? Do you no longer care? After this long mystery story you've been the detective in, why would you sit still in this way for the destruction of evidence? I know you're only a character, not my real son, but I still don't understand. Even if you yourself don't know what you're doing, what does the book mean by it, mean by you? What if she kept handing you things to toss in the fire for her? Would you really let her burn each of my letters, if it came to that, one after the other, without a flicker of curiosity? Don't you see that all this is just what it looks like, a funeral pyre? Don't you see what Amy is up to when she asks for a kiss as “charm”? Don't you see her turning your wedding pledge into an exorcism?</italic>
         </p>
         <p>
            <italic>So Boz is only another drunken boaster, I guess, like Rigaud or Ephraim. And so I don't leave my story here at all. I only leave behind the hope of its ever being told. Is this what novels always do to life, tear its heart out? Little Dorrit! What a weak, mean title. How much it hides away, how much it buries unmourned. Thinking of my stolen letters, then, and my baby taken, and my motherhood undone, I'd have called it The Undelivered. And then I'd know it was my story, and others might too…..</italic>
         </p>
         <p>Breaking off with its last anguished epistle into the void, off the book went to the agent, then in quick succession to press, print, and wide transatlantic acclaim. Everyone hears the heroine's story at last—and comes to see her point about Dickens's ending. Quoting the<italic>New York Review of Books:</italic>“All those unrewarded lives that the ruthless plot instinct keeps at bay in the juggernaut of Dickensian romance, all the deflections and submergences on which it fuels its progress, come back to haunt it in this searing tale of denied desire.”</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>This part of the backplot, unloaded in the thirtieth chapter of book 2, “Closing In,” is so convoluted that it takes a full-scale appendix by John Holloway to paraphrase it—not exactly to decrypt its intricacies (his version is as complicated as the original) but rather to confirm that they were actually as ornate and improbable as they seemed when eked out, in the heat of Rigaud's defiance, by the dialogue with Mrs. Clennam. See John Holloway, “The Denouement of Little Dorrit,” in<italic>LD,</italic>pp. 789–90.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>This and subsequent reviews are cited here unsigned to protect their authors, who don't yet know they will write them.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>The text whose title is under tacit copyright question at this temporary impasse is Catherine Gallagher,<italic>Nobody's Story: The Vanishing Acts of Women Writers in the Marketplace, 1670–1820</italic>(Berkeley, 1994). In relation to the novelistic “nobody” not just as fictive (hence invadable) but as social (hence structurally minoritized) character—both would apply to Arthur's banished mother—see Alex Woloch,<italic>The One vs. the Many: Minor Characters and the Space of the Protagonist in the Novel</italic>(Princeton, N.J., 2003).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Dickens, “The Number Plans,”<italic>LD,</italic>p. 831.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Dysclosure</title>
         <p>There is, as indicated at the start, a methodology behind the preceding madness, which a few pages of more familiar reading should be able to bring out. In this case fantasy is only a prelude to narratography. I've tried prying open the gap between Dickens's jotted plans for his finale and the actual pages that got sentimentally worked over and flattened out. One can virtually hear his implied italics the first time around, his rousing emphasis on “She had left her story,” and then the friction of its erasure later, turning the banned (or barred) mother first penitent, then silent. And even without this recourse to his number plans, we sense a tension in the plotting itself, as well as in the writing. Surely there is either undue scrupulousness or covert self-interest in Amy's last act before inscribing herself in the marriage book, where she becomes a Dorrit no more, but now Mrs. Clennam the second.</p>
         <p>What, then, is really at stake in her destruction of a private legal document before the signing of a public register? Perhaps she is acceding to Mrs. Clennam's wish to keep the secret from Arthur if, on reflection, she agrees that the truth would do him no particular good, or perhaps Amy herself is filling a void in his life without the risk of naming it just yet. But this merely helps the woman save face in the otherwise suddenly opened eyes of her victimized charge. Why<italic>wouldn't</italic>the truth have done him good after the long lie? And, anyway, do the dead have in their own right no claim on the living? Didn't Dickens for a moment see otherwise, in a flash of notebook inspiration potent enough to justify the contortions of the denouement, even while he later scrambled to smooth over that claim with an ameliorative vision of continuity rather than of rupture and return? What I am calling narratography is a way of listening in on these final exertions of the prose, transacted at the far margins of plot—and of eavesdropping, indeed, on their own scrambled figuration.</p>
         <p>As the chapter “Gone” executes the wrap-up and wind-down, the autumnal Clennam sits “listening to the voice as it read to him” and “heard in it” much of comfort—Amy's voice, of course, the only voice let through to him now. We notice that he is not said to have heard<italic>her</italic>exactly, let alone her words, but instead to have sensed in the aura of that voiced wording, heard<italic>in</italic>rather than from it, “all that great Nature was doing, heard in it all the soothing songs she sings to man,” harmony sealed tight by the inverted cognate object of “songs … sings.” But no rhetorical singsong can keep a certain psychic dissonance at bay, one that can be more closely registered by narratography. It may at first suggest Little Dorrit when Dickens writes, “At no Mother's knee but hers.” Yet she's a fiancée, remember, not a mother; he is referring instead to nature: “At no Mother's knee but hers, had he ever dwelt … on the harvests of tenderness and humility that lie hidden in the early-fostered seeds of the imagination” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 776). This is Wordsworth by the numbers, recalling<italic>The Prelude</italic>'s “Fair seed-time … Fostered alike by beauty and by fear,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>including that secondary intertextual slide, given the Clennam family context, toward the “Foster-child” and, yes, “Inmate Man” of the<italic>Intimations Ode</italic>and its mortal “prison-house.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The evocation pushes off again with a ripple of iambic monosyllables: “But, in the tones of the voice that read to him, there were memories of an old feeling of such things” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 776). Why the<italic>but?</italic>What is in fact being conceded by this concessive? The tension of tense itself seems to need graphing—even as it frustrates it. Arthur hears the music of autumn in the reading voice, the deepest rhythm of nature—even as, unlike most children, he has been forced to grow up without a comforting female presence in his life. But he does appear to have distant memories of that other kind of mother's knee, of feminine nurture itself, or at least its timbre, rather than just nature's abstract maternal personification. At least by osmosis from Amy's voice, the hero is lulled into feeling less deprived than he might. We, in our turn, can either let all this wash vaguely over us or pause to chart the unstable cultural and familial logic that impels it.</p>
         <p>We can do likewise with the sociopolitical logic of a burst of comic rather than lyric prose to follow at the wedding, where the ingenuity of lexical form again takes upon itself the role of softening its own content. The one character, Pancks by name, whose fate is not yet logged in or predictably tabled, must be commandeered by the wedding ritual. For this loose end is a true loose cannon, and his powder needs dampening. The pattern is not unfamiliar. The repeated self-division and self-doubling of characterization has already pictured for us the riven and nearly effaced hero, who was once to have shared honors with a satirized bureaucracy in the broad application of the novel's working title,<italic>Nobody's Fault</italic>. Clennam is a man haunted by his idiomatic doppelganger in the pronominal “nobody,” a self-cancelling ghost sprung from the vernacular substrate of the hero's own equivocated desire. The phantasmal negation first sneaks up on him in an unobtrusive fold of indirect discourse. Whose weakness could it possibly be to cloak a hopeless infatuation for a pretty younger woman like Pet Meagles? As Clennam protests too much in an extruded internal monologue, it is “nobody's, nobody's within his knowledge”—and this in the capping paragraph of the namesake chapter “Nobody's Weakness” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 200). In nonentity's name, rather than his own, is he often identified from this point on. The novel also literalizes, materializes, elsewhere such psychic splits in, for instance, the “mermaid” bifurcation of Arthur's former heartthrob, Flora Finching, half sympathetic disappointed widow, half blithering romantic virgin. Most Dickensian of all, given its linguistic register, is the character constellation of the two Flintwinches, with the<italic>twin</italic>at the punned-upon core of their shared surname offering a model for the way stylistics (here in the form of onomastics) can be angled toward a narratographic clue to the plot-long mystery involving their congenital rather than just uncanny likeness.</p>
         <p>As it happens, and for no other good reason than the parallelism, it is the divided Flora herself who appears on the arm of the last of these halved subjects in the novel's final illustration for the wedding party. There beside her is another two-faced social agent, Mr. Pancks, but one caught this time in the throes of his normalization. Half raging insurgent, half patient and mild-mannered friend, this is the character whose own eccentric surname spells out by perfect phonetic anagram that primal violence of humiliation in<italic>spank.</italic>Certainly with no pangs whatever, the actual retribution he exacts is to have molested his archenemy in public, assaulted and mocked him. In full view of the local populace in Bleeding Heart Yard, Pancks shears the locks of his hypocrite boss, the false patriarch Casby. Here is an act of pseudorevolutionary, and entirely local, defiance that nonetheless comes as close as the slum dwellers of the novel will ever get to that running of blood in the streets across the channel. No proletarian revolution for England, only the unrest that fuels the plot of ambition itself: a correction from within of the middle-class system.</p>
         <p>The vengefulness of Pancks's fiery radicalism, flaring up just two chapters before the end of the book—and thus closer to being a climactic moment in the novel's social counterpoint than one may tend to remember—must somehow be quenched if society is to get on with the business of business as usual, as well as its own patrilineal continuance through marriage. There is no better place to perform this dousing, this ritual cleansing, than at a wedding. Narratology's work is regularly concluded in such a ceremonial event. Narratography alone would keep reading on. What it hears in this case is a stunning concision of phrase at this marriage of the businessman down on his luck and the poorhouse scion moving up—a wedding that requires Mr. Pancks to snuff out his recent asocial fury in order to attend. Such is the legally sanctioned ritual at whose margins he is (parenthetically and proleptically) so richly remunerated for his glancing witness. In the bourgeois novel, quiescence needn't be its own, or only, reward—at least when the system is fully up, oiled, and running. “Mr Pancks”—parenthesis—“(destined to be chief clerk to Doyce and Clennam, and afterwards partner in the house)”—and on the sentence goes, as if earning this fate in advance: Mr. Pancks, “<italic>sinking the Incendiary in the peaceful friend</italic>, looked in at the door to see it done” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 785). The preceding run of phonetic irony is accompanied by its own graphic sinking from the capital I of “Incendiary” to the alphabetic as well as temperamental leveling of “friend.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>In its figural and alphabetic economy, that brief participial phrase is one of the great turns in all of Dickens, with its evoked soothing bath in the symbolic font of all fellow feeling. Overseen marital bonding, reduced to the “it” of pro forma social function (“to see it done”), is not only the antecedent but the prototype of those mercantile partnerships (here parenthetically foreordained) that are just as important as familial unions to the maintenance of the cultural order and of its communal symbolism. With the inspired phonetic play of “s<italic>in</italic>king the<italic>In</italic>c<italic>end</italic>iary<italic>in</italic>the peaceful fri<italic>end</italic>,” including a last sibilant hiss of singeing rage against the abluting waters of sentiment, the comedy of figuration itself submerges the full tenor of its vehicle.</p>
         <p>Glimpsed in the very metaphor of sinking, nonetheless, is the widespread suppression without which, for a Victorian writer like Dickens, social and financial amelioration cannot be achieved. That Dickensian phrase is so flexed and vibrant that one might almost miss the deadening of energy it depicts. Certainly the potential socialist time bomb that George Bernard Shaw found in this above all of Dickens's novels is by that one figurative turn ever so deftly defused, as if the energy of invention alone could make up for the return to conventionality in the described event.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>Given this cooling off of social unrest, this drowning out of its disquiet, to say nothing of its disclosed reward in the offing (chief clerk, then partner!), it is perhaps less of a surprise to see what follows. For Arthur himself, a page later and at last, loses even his longstanding sense of loss—of fundamental incompleteness—in a muted new social identity: sinking one part of himself into another as he had earlier imagined his drowning altogether, as “Nobody,” in the emotional river of no return.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>
         </p>
         <p>But this is really to say that the brief remainder of Dickens's last chapter has a major piece of psychological work to accomplish, whatever its other attenuated narrative tasks. Having desexed marriage, it must now unsex maternity. This figural task, defusing the cruel fate so lately revealed under its heading (the abandoned, maddened mother), is required so that the spectral shadow of the motherly does not swallow up Little Dorrit's marital role entirely under its symbolic rubric, or at least not hers alone. In order that Arthur should not be compromised by marrying his mother, he is turned into a feminized nurturing agent as well, his masculinity absorbed by new matrimonial purpose. In leaving off, the chapter goes about this work quite unobtrusively, in its very last paragraph, after holding us suspended on the threshold of the penultimate one. No sooner has the couple signed the marriage register, that is, than prose takes a deep breath for them and descends into their life of selfless service, a shared life fused in the final paragraph by assonance and alliteration alike in a coupling “inseparable and blessed.” Just before, “they paused for a moment on the steps of the portico, looking at the fresh perspective of the street”—that painterly dead metaphor—“in the autumn morning sun's bright rays, and then went down” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 787).</p>
         <p>In escorting the couple down across a magisterially cadenced passage, the prose takes off. In a bravura run of syntactic terracing, that phrasal verb, “went down,” cleansed of any condescension in its stairstepped descent (and massing its music, as noted at the start, against the coming din of “uproar”), strikes the keynote of four more clauses pivoted on it. The first two are fragments: “Went down into a modest life of usefulness and happiness.” Not “modest lives,” plural? No, their reward, if also perhaps their atonement, is to be at one. So it continues. And remember that the detached subject is not so far back as to have been forgotten; it's the newlyweds together that the prose speaks of still. “Went down to give a<italic>mother's</italic>care, in the fullness of time, to Fanny's neglected children no less than to<italic>their</italic>own” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 787; emphasis added). Modest utility has been subsumed to a single gender paradigm. Against such a figural conflation, it is hard to retrench.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Certainly the next sentence alone, even if it tried harder, couldn't set the trouble right, with its mention of that further “nurse and friend” (plural this time, unless synonymous) they also “give” to her wastrel brother Tip. Sprung from “give a mother's care,” its parallelism has grown derailing. Give a nurse? Give suck or succor? Further, too, the feminine dominates as sole antecedent in the pickup clause, where Tip is “never vexed by the great exactions he made of her” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 787). Of her—and of course of her new husband and partner. But whether Arthur is tacitly slotted in as bedside friend and brother-in-law or male nurse in this loose and dubious syntax, there was, as we saw, no ambiguity at all in the pronominal grammar of the preceding sentence, where, tendering along with Amy “a mother's care,” he has inherited the same maternal role from which he in his own right never took solace. He has answered the lack by embodying it—and not as psychological diagnosis any longer but as moral uplift within the last distended cadenza.</p>
         <p>For the protagonist to become his own lack, of course, is only a felt castration if he feels he has something to lose. And, thanks to Amy, Arthur doesn't realize that anything has been lost, that there has been any story to compare with hers, any love like it, or even one as strong in another and more fundamental way. Yes, in giving up the name Dorrit just before the close of her namesake novel, Amy has become her own antithesis in Mrs. Clennam, agent in turn of the same suppression, with the result that the most insidious role reversal yet, the real identity transfer, is that of Arthur for his own silenced maternal origin. Unprocessed mourning cannibalizes the other whose absence it cannot accept, whose very recognition the narrative has blocked in order to transmute it. As narratography (rather than narratology) is scaled to register along the lexical, syntactic, and figurative terrain of fictional prose itself, the arc of Dickensian plotting cannot afford in full view to lament its founding victim, nor let its hero elegize her, nor let the heroine acknowledge her let alone (and because of) the place she holds in her stead. And not being able to love the mother, or mourn her,<italic>the son has become her.</italic>Here lies the keenest if quietest violence of the novel: the double silencing of male as well as female energy even in their most defining of adult relations and the foisting of all connubial desire onto a life of communal duty instead.</p>
         <p>This is no bypass of typical Dickensian characterization but a recognizable path through it. What we have entered upon here—a much-frequented terrain in Victorian criticism—is the Dickensian prehistory of psychoanalysis. In her study of melancholia, Julia Kristeva deliberately casts the assumptions of “classic psychoanalytic theory (Abraham, Freud, and Melanie Klein)” into the voice of the aggrieved subject who must incorporate rather than relinquish a lost object that is ultimately resented for its absence. The headlong associational logic runs like this: “Because I love it, and in order not to lose it, I imbed it in myself; but because I hate it, that other within myself is a bad self, I am bad, I am non-existent, I shall kill myself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>The specter of male nonexistence in the case of Dickens's “Nobody” derives in part from the fact that the other within cannot ever be mourned. This is because, like the all-but-explicit suicidal drift of Clennam's consciousness itself, it is only partially recognized and then mostly in metaphors and slips of phrase. Arthur doesn't really think of drowning himself, even as he yearns for the river's oblivion. Nor can he let go of another life either, let alone his own, if it has never really been his to surrender. The absent mother cannot possibly be mourned, that is, because such a loss is already imbedded: incorporated<italic>as an absence</italic>. Even if Amy relents and he is finally wised up in years to come (after Mrs. Clennam's death, as the exposed woman herself proposes to Amy), still Arthur's self-predication might well remain entrammeled in the reversible snares of melancholia: even without killing myself, I am nonexistent, I am in essence a maternal descendent of nobody rather than a chosen lover of anyone, I am the mother I never (knew I) had.</p>
         <p>As far as the novel has chosen to go with its marriage plot, its prose shuts down on a stark model of psychic damage as much as on any healing tale of its local repair. And there is a curious symmetry in all this. The novel ends up being as much about substitute relations and deflected lines of dependence as is the ludicrously oblique will of the old Uncle Clennam: a narratively inset text (mostly paraphrased by allusion rather than quoted, except for a stinging phrase or two thrown out by Rigaud) that treats unknown and unrelated legatees as exchangeable proxies for wronged familial objects. In the novel on the other hand it is clear from early on, long before her service to Arthur in the prison-turned-nursery, that Amy, whose natural mother died in giving birth to her, has become a surrogate mother herself—“Little Mother,” as her addled charge Maggie dubs her—and for this deformation of girlhood all fingers are, of course, pointed at the shiftless father, William Dorrit. At the same time, all the vaguely erotic patriarchal fixation that pervades the novel as the flip side of its satire—all the worry it seems to invite over whether Amy is too young for the hero, drawn to him too much as a placeholder for her failed father, able to accept the one only upon the death of the other—is an attenuated characterological diffusion of a fiercer psychological insight. Oedipus is the least of it. Sure, Amy mothers Arthur as well as just nursing him. To this extent, at least, he may be getting what he wants. Amy as well: if her adored father was a child, why not her husband too? In structural terms, the necessary death of Amy's father in advance of the marriage would be narratology's way, one way at least, of tracing this pattern.</p>
         <p>But narratography's more tight-strung reaction is jarred, as we have seen, by a further dissonance in the conversion of roles. The unspoken psychic pressure on Dickens's stylistic cadenza reveals itself only by grammatical inference in the novel's final sentences, but inference having precisely to do with the momentum of narrative to this point. On the other side of the destabilized marital equation in which a lovelorn man finds a second mother in a wife, the false mother in<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>is not (yet) dead. So the new stand-in mother keeps the false mother's secret, rejecting the dead father's will (even in its intended financial benefit to her personally), and thus accrues instead a huge but inert power in her harbored knowledge. Discharged all but unconsciously as the end draws near, the banked force of this withheld knowledge can seem to backfire into prose. It isn't just that Amy implements (or even incorporates) Mrs. Clennam's manipulation of Arthur's consciousness; the hero is unsexed by both the syntax and figuration of the couple's envisioned future in the last paragraph. Across this intended resonance of this prose narratography makes its way, despite the greased wheels of closure, along the not-quite-covered tracks of wording itself, with its elided antecedents and collapsed grammatical identifications.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This is no bypass of typical Dickensian characterization, then—all this about displaced identification, introjected desire, figurative incorporation—but, again, a recognizable path through it, through and beyond its methods, in fact, and not only forward to psychoanalysis but back to founding determinations of the novel as genre. Issues of genealogy, personal as much as literary, are regularly—and regulatively—inseparable from the cultural dichotomies that a given historical genre arises to navigate. For Georg Lukács, it is the role of the postepic hero, from Greek tragedy to the nineteenth-century novel, to seek for a<italic>meaning</italic>that is no longer given (presumed) in everyday<italic>life,</italic>for a way to find<italic>essence</italic>again in mere<italic>existence.</italic>
            <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>An ontological given (being) has become instead the mainspring of an alienated epistemology (the quest[ion] of detected value). The terms are thus closely parallel to the dialectics, in Michael McKeon's commentary, of worth versus birth—class mobility versus natal status—as determined, in effect, by epistemological investigation versus ontological (or social) assumption—and as illustrated by a foundling plot like that of<italic>Joseph Andrews</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>A century farther along in the institution of the novel, of course, and turning further on the vacillating middle-class estimates of innate worth versus net worth, Arthur Clennam's withered sense of inner value stands in inverse proportion to the unrevealed truth of his birth. And what the orphaned Amy gets in her contracted nuptials, by the crisscrossed purposes of overcompensated loss, is less a second father than a denatured mirror inversion of the same imaginary mother she has succeeded, after years without one, in becoming. At the eleventh hour, Dickens's tacit changeling plot switches two motherless children at one stroke, bringing them into a perverse new exchange with a single maternal ghost.</p>
         <p>By contrast with its culminating evasions, Dickens's novel has begun on the level playing field of the genre. Ethics and epistemology are closely correlated at first in the hero's most pressing question: who has been wronged by my family, what guilt induced by my class station and inheritance? The question, however, does not survive the suppression of its eventual answer. It is gagged once and for all—and bound back into marital closure. For most of Dickens's story, the hero has been searching in the dank basement of his estranged domesticity for an incriminating family secret. As it turns out, that secret is the hero himself, his denied status as stepson the site of the crime. Clennam always felt guilty for not loving his mother and especially for not being loved by her. Now he needn't, because she isn't. But the secret of his birth, mitigating his ingrained sense of worthlessness in the eyes of the false mother, is leaked by narration only to be reabsorbed by characterization within the situational ethics of special pleading, spared shame, and the heroine's own perhaps incompletely examined motives.</p>
         <p>Here structuralism and dialectical historicism or, more to the point, narratology and genre theory openly converge—but under assault by the crossfire of a single novel's own unmastered textual ironies. The epistemological metaplot of detection that helps found the grammar of story in structuralist narratology must thus confront Dickens's deliberate upending of that format. His plot serves in this way to rehearse the inchoate maneuvers of the novel as fledgling form, negotiating between an emergent aesthetic of verisimilitude (realism) and an ethics of social station (plot reward), between the evidentiary and the providential. In a genre-deep rapprochement called out by the tensions of narratographic response, the true and the good, or in other words the touchstones of detection and restitution, are seen as correlative (but by no means equivalent) features of novelistic plotting. And they have surfaced in<italic>Little Dorrit,</italic>under duress, from their own prehistory. For here is a Victorian text whose closure asks us to accept that the epistemological motor of novelistic plotting must suddenly be subordinated to the matrimonial goal of its value-laden teleology.</p>
         <p>Overriding the detective prototype, such is the courtship novel in its most attenuated and dilatory form. Failing all lived cultural totality, failing even a structural unity capable of being mapped back onto the rendered world, the violence of this Dickensian ending is to settle for individual union at all costs, whatever unethical deceits must be prolonged, whatever truth must be deferred. Need it be said? The obvious alternative in the case of<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>would clearly have been less manageable by plot or genre. For Clennam to come to the marriage altar (as ethical reward for selfless devotion) to find it a symbolic baptismal font as well (the epistemological redemption of the abused child by a corrected parentage) would not have made for a readily stabilized closure in the marriage-plot mode. Rather, it would have left the hero with too much on his mind: an entirely reconstituted subjectivity, in fact, to be actively grappled with and rethought, rather than just a depleted self to be sunk gratefully in another. The failure of dialectical resolution is absolute. Forget social totality. Forget even formal unity. To stave off all further worry over the hero's status as son, his union, its figured prospects feminized, is reduced to the unitary.</p>
         <p>Yet the nagging fact remains, lodged right at the generic crux of ethics and epistemology. For there is no denying that the withheld truth would have had a decisive ethical charge, removing the unearned guilt of years, releasing the unloved son to a different autobiographic consciousness altogether. The promissory morality of soul mates as helpmates in the novel's last paragraph—they are returned to a society that has previously contributed to their exclusion, to perform what service they now can—is of course stationed to outbid all epistemological regret. Yet to the supposed selflessness of this social ethic, the self-knowledge of the hero has been entirely sacrificed. What might have done him good is subsumed to his doing good. A logic like this does have its own communal morality, of course, but only if articulated. Instead, we get, unadmitted, a sublimation of the sexual into the social subject. In this way the closural immanence of form within the compromises of Dickens's story is neither providential nor evidentiary but merely and remorselessly conventional. I say merely, because conjugal love has been unfleshed into duty by an ideology of the so-called work ethic; remorselessly, because the pace of closure excludes all talking back from within the plot; but not seamlessly, because the false notes remain, jangling, reverberant. They remain, that is, for the reader to read—and this as a certain lingering discord that outlasts plot itself. In what we've stumbled over in the novel's final paragraph the discrepancy between knowledge and desire takes the form of a verbal deviance writ small, a mere glitch or two at the level of agreement, a predication no longer justified in the linguistic sense nor in the ethical and the epistemological senses, given that it implies a not only vaguely morbid but a downright deceptive variant of the marital two-made-one. Dickens, that master vernacular syntactician of nineteenth-century prose, regularly flawless in the virtual subplots of his own periods and subordinations, is hereby caught out in a psychoanalytic as well as verbal solecism. That his hero is subsumed to the heroine in their giving together “a mother's care” to the next generation is more, as we've seen, than a Freudian slip of gender (dis)parity. Dipping into the future, this phrasing also reaches one generation back into the masked and misrepresented past. There is no need to exaggerate. The grammar itself would be only negligibly, perhaps negligently, off, if it were not so obviously onto something more deeply ingrained in the plot.</p>
         <p>Then, too, another slip of syntax has preceded this one in the same sentimental vein, where through indirect discourse Arthur muses on Amy Dorrit as the fixed point in his life, the “termination” (as in destination) of all its good: “Everything in its<italic>perspective</italic>led to her innocent figure” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 702; emphasis added). But disorientation within the extended painterly metaphor—life as a landscape with only one figure—has set in a sentence before and could easily have been prevented.<italic>Surveying the vista of his own poor story, Clennam saw all lines converge upon Amy:</italic>that might have been one version of the sentence's intent. Instead, the phrasal grammar is so thoroughly decoupled as to drift again into solecism: “Looking back upon his own poor story, she was its vanishing-point” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 702). A dangling modifier for a life left hanging. It is not just that the famously precinematic Dickens here breaks the 180-degree rule of continuity within point-of-view editing, so that directionality itself—and priority with it—spins on a dime. In this respect, Amy does unnervingly offer a rearview horizon as well as an arriving point of rest—as much lost maternal care as present alleviation. Beyond this spatial reversal, however, there is the grammatical lapse itself. For in the loosened grip of syntax, Amy is also, for Arthur, his life's preemption, eliding the male subject-position altogether at its evacuated focal point. Paradoxically, cooptively, with the pronoun “she” taking the hero (in his retrospective “looking”) as the only available antecedent, Clennam is as much feminized by such unlicensed syntax as he will later be in his grammatical subsumption to a mother's role. This whole moment of narrowed but totalized “perspective” is prototypical in its shift of scale and orientation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>Even in providing a graphic or painterly mastertrope for its own implied narratology of closure, the novel's summary gesture invites the less-settled narratography of contradiction in process.</p>
         <p>To call the subsequent lexical effacement of the feminized hero in the final paragraph a displacement and condensation respectively—of maternal absence<italic>upon</italic>and then<italic>within</italic>the very identification of the marriageable male—is to begin suggesting, with the unconscious of Dickensian grammar caught out in this way, where attention itself might be caught up by such a disjuncture. For<italic>unconscious</italic>is just the word. One can only follow out the prose's diffusive lines of stress in and through the transferential recognitions of that analytic session called reading. By the invested give- and-take of such legibility, in this and many another fictional case, the psycholinguistic trace of elided desire is offered up to registration. It comes to us, as we bring our recognition to it, along the serial slippage between plot and its inscriptive medium, between the manifest propulsion of event and a subterranean impetus glimpsed on the run in the kinks of wording. Concerning the unrevealed mother, we can never be sure what Dickens meant to finesse or massage or avoid or foreclose or, alternately, what he himself as author may have entirely repressed in the psychodynamic of his narrative plotting in<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>from chapter plan to finished book. All we know is that his<italic>writing</italic>appears to be no more than half conscious of these operations—no more, but no less. It is this reciprocal remainder under the transferential analysis I am here calling narratography that keeps the legible text<italic>in play</italic>across the more imperious s/pacings of plot.</p>
         <p>Traditional narratology well knows the implacable nature of plot's marital vanishing point. But it is narratography that can take up with a story where narratology and sometimes even where plot leaves off. Granted, the fantasy phase of this essay's experiment has, in its extremity, respected no proper bounds. But in just this way I hope it might appear exemplary, at least in this following sense: to remind us that a narrative's most urgent, disturbing, even insurgent meanings often come through between the lines of plot, subliminal, figured rather than denoted. Narratology knows all too well the stranglehold and exclusions of the marriage story. Narratography would experience them from the ground up, patrolling the fold between a book's rhetoric and its actual writing.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Fictional Truth</italic>, Michael Riffaterre sees the subtextual energy of fiction standing in the same relation to plot as does the unconscious in Freud to the system of conscious perception.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>Like the unconscious, and revealed only in signs or symptoms of the otherwise functionally repressed, subtexts are therefore timeless, reversible, and cumulative. If denied maternity (its removal by death or its falsification) locates one such subtext in<italic>Little Dorrit</italic>—strung along in counterpoint to the failed father motif, for instance—that matrilineal subtext has its perverse and unexpected returns across the marital trajectory of the son himself, as he is sped along the monorail of its domesticating engine toward the anticipated point of rest and its gender assimilation. Any such subtext, according to Riffaterre, is a phenomenon transcendent to change or if you will subtendent to it. It thereby lies, in the last sentence of his study, “outside the realm of time and … impervious to its ravages.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>Plot is the map of those ravages. Narratology understands this. Narratography would, as I say, reexperience it—and do so in a transferential exchange, against the medial flow, between a nervously cued attention and the insinuated unconscious of the text itself.</p>
         <p>Now psychoanalytic, now generic and historical, broader methodologies collide—merge and rework each other—across the medial (in this case linguistic) workings of text, including their workings upon us. That dialectical interplay of historicist (over against idealist) discourse out of which the novelistic genre arose, stressed by McKeon as epistemological versus ethical, does not vanish into its hermeneutic spiral. Such a dialectic sustains the very terms of reading's feedback loops, where the checks and balances of thematized form and formalized value are reconfigured yet again in the zone of uptake—a<italic>response</italic>by no means detached, as etymology might suggest, from the judgments associated with responsibility. Whether or not, for such reasons, we would want to call narratography an ethics of reading in its own right, one thing is clear. Its formal vigilance is anything but cold to the exposed ethical discrepancies of content. Exactly because it does not subordinate medial hypersensitivity to a broader comprehension of a governing narrative system, it can become a rigorously epistemological mode of textual attention.</p>
         <p>Narratography is keyed to the vicissitudes of plot as they are ferried along the routes and detours of syntax itself and the micromanagement of its lexical succession, including both the elisions and the blind spots of overdetermined figuration. Between the science of narratology and the practice of narratography, the basic methodological difference remains. Whatever narrative essentially may<italic>be</italic>as modal form, criticism might also want to ask how—and just where—a given narrative does what it does at once for, to, and with the reader. In registering this, narratography draws out a difference within—as well as across—the increments of narrative meaning. It thereby charts more closely the junctures and disjoins between rhetoric and writing, the imprinted inferences that may evade intent. Only in this way can it begin to graph the latently inscribed across the novelistic surface of the said. Hence the wager behind this paper's fantasized novel. The unnamed mother of Nobody is scarcely a universal plot matrix. Nonetheless, and though not typically personified in anything like this way, writing is always giving voice to, or at least loosing words for, more than it narrates, calling out on the run its own contradictions and evasions, telling more than the told.</p>
         <p>So I return to that invented novel one last time, anomalous though it is, as an exemplar of more familiar novelistic tendencies in order to make clear the methodological implications its concoction does<italic>not</italic>entail. Narratography per se has nothing to do with the conjuration of wholesale counternovels. Albeit an assiduous close reader of fiction, that Oxford don is no practitioner of narratography—or at least not in anything we've heard from him here. He is a virtual biographer, in other words a fiction writer. The contrapuntal tale of the lost mother takes to an extreme dilation the fleeting thoughts anyone might have in learning of her so suddenly, and then learning no more, and then being denied even the closural satisfaction of watching the hero find out the stunning truth, even if it only transpired for the reader in a second or two of reflective recoil from the headlong settlements of the plot. But the work of narratography (a matter always of diction, syntax, punctuation, figuration) comes later—most intensely when the very word<italic>mother's</italic>(possessive in every sense) is seen to assimilate the male hero to its lexical confines across the prose cadence, and ghostly grammatical antecedence, of plot's immediate marital aftermath.</p>
         <p>In conjuring up the conceptual field of such effects, we might turn to set theory and picture a Venn diagram by which narratography is defined as exactly the zone of overlap between narratology and stylistics. Narratography would be shaded in there by the very shadings and incremental gradations of prose in the thick and thin of its own action as linguistic incident. Here emerges, in sum, the heuristic value of a so-called<italic>Story Left Behind</italic>in staging by exaggeration the everyday wake of narrativity in verbal process. Any narrative sentence may have its dramatic prehistory. It need not necessarily be distended or suddenly truncated, not by definition brutal or suppressed or moving or any one thing in particular, and not necessarily longer than the plotted tension of the preceding paragraph or even sentence. But narrative prehistory is manifest as a forward pressure nonetheless. That's why this essay's approach is in fact “narratival” rather than strictly stylistic (whatever that might mean)—and often dialectical as such. And why its instinct for intensive reading comes into sync with the impetus of plotted structure rather than just local representation. And why, further, even in imagining an entire shadow plot, the inflated exception developed in the fictional phase of this essay can still prove the rule of the minuscule. Whole lives, of course, don't usually lie battered, absented, and returned by deformation under the tread of such<italic>friction</italic>in prose. Broad swaths of plot aside, it is rather in the immediate pace of reading that some aspect or facet of an advancing story is often bent noticeably out of shape. Narratography becomes, in this sense, the tracking of syntax and of the words it marshals for the impinging microplots, one after the other, of their own proximate backstories.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>William Wordsworth,<italic>The Prelude, Or, Growth of a Poet's Mind,</italic>in<italic>Selected Poems and Prefaces,</italic>ed. Jack Stillinger (Boston, 1965), bk. 1, ll. 301–2, p. 199.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Wordsworth, “Intimations of Immortality from Recollections of Early Childhood,”<italic>Selected Poems and Prefaces,</italic>ll. 66, 82, pp. 187–88.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>In a further phonetic play suggested to me by Hilary Schor after a lecture that inevitably sounded out the phonetic texture of this passage, there is also the wedding of noun and pronoun in “door … it done”—as it spells out the scene's marital assimilation of the Dorrit to the Clennam name.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>See George Bernard Shaw,<italic>Shaw on Dickens,</italic>ed. Dan H. Lawrence and Martin Quinn (New York, 1985).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>The chapter “Nobody's Weakness” closes with Arthur ruminating gloomily (and rather opaquely) about how “it might be better to flow away monotonously, like the river, and to compound for its insensibility to happiness with its insensibility to pain” (<italic>LD,</italic>p. 200). Though “flow away” seems at first only a metaphor, so abstract and disembodied is the reverie that there is a kind of phantasmal grammatical alternative trickling into the melancholic drift of the prose. In this way that second infinitive of compensation or complementation may also faintly evoke a sense that Arthur indeed wishes to mix materially with the lethal waters, literally (and more idiomatically) to “compound … with” them.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>If this is a case of Barthesian narratology in which the “character” of the hero is intersected by the semiotic “figure” of maternity (see Barthes,<italic>S/Z,</italic>pp. 67–68), such subtextual evidence of the linguistic turn in narrative analysis remains a verbal turn whose full textual irony can only be graphed along the slippery slope of grammatical number itself in the very immanence (rather than the abstract model) of the linguistic operation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Julia Kristeva,<italic>Black Sun: Depression and Melancholia</italic>, trans. Leon S. Roudiez (New York, 1989), p. 11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>Narratography thus intercepts even the subtlest narratologies of closure. Where a critic like D. A. Miller might distinguish between the “nonnarratable” future of the new Clennam marriage (beyond the needs and scope of story) and the more explicit bar at the end to its “unnarratable” predecessor in the disbanded love match (beyond story's tolerance), narratography would detect the strain of that renewed exclusion of the mother. See D. A. Miller,<italic>Narrative and Its Discontents: Problems of Closure in the Traditional Novel</italic>(Princeton, N.J., 1981).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>See Georg Lukács,<italic>The Theory of the Novel: A Historico-Philosophical Essay on the Forms of Great Epic Literature,</italic>trans. Ann Bostock (Cambridge, Mass., 1971).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>See Michael McKeon,<italic>The Origins of the English Novel, 1600–1740</italic>(Baltimore, 1987).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Certainly this passage offers an example, at least as much as does the novel's last paragraph, of Dickens's typical effort at focalizing the approach to closure around the self set aside from—and individuated anew against—the social overview. In<italic>The Way We Argue Now: A Study in the Cultures of Theory,</italic>Amanda Anderson compares this inward turn to the shift in Foucault's thinking from a panoptics of power relations to more localized “practices of the self,” the latter paradigm recalling those “modest Dickensian endings” in which “the glare of omniscience is relinquished and the<italic>perspective</italic>descends to meld with the participant's view” (Amanda Anderson,<italic>The Way We Argue Now: A Study in the Cultures of Theory</italic>[Princeton, N.J., 2006], p. 142; emphasis added).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>See Michael Riffaterre,<italic>Fictional Truth</italic>(Baltimore, 1990).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Ibid., p. 111. Even Riffaterre's approach to the structuring unsaid of textual writing can be seen to represent on its own terms a shift from the ontology of narrative toward its epistemology at the level of form rather than content. By the deliberate provocation of his title, his semiotic narratology is interested not just in the structural essence of fiction as art but in its specific<italic>truth:</italic>a story's immanent signifying patterns in their subtextual disclosure.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
