<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">JR</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/663745</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR921009</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af9" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Barbra</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Barnett</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af9">Loyola University, New Orleans.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>January 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>92</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>662286</issue-id>
         <fpage>138</fpage>
         <lpage>139</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Regan</surname>,<given-names>Ethna</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Theology and the Boundary Discourse of Human Rights</source>. Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press, 2010. xii+243 pp. $44.95 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2012 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/663745"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This book offers a constructive and critical engagement between Christian theology and human rights. Ethna Regan challenges the perception that theology and human rights are at cross-purposes, demonstrating the mutually constructive and critical possibilities of engaging human rights theologically and of a theology that takes seriously claims to individual human rights. Though small in size, the book is densely packed with careful theological analysis, often corroborated with insights gained from human rights activism.</p>
      <p>Regan’s chief impetus for writing the book is the assumption that rights talk is anathema to theology. She addresses this assumption from several distinct perspectives: via definition, description, theological construction, and critical analysis. As a matter of defining human rights, Regan aims to show that one of the bases for the perceived opposition between theology and human rights lies in an overly narrow conception of the nature and scope of human rights discourse. Given her experiences working with street children in Trinidad, Regan rejects the view that human rights discourse merely defines human beings as atomistic, autonomous rights-bearers with few ethical imperatives. To correct the perception that human rights and theology are mutual antagonists, she articulates a definition of human rights as a “dialectical boundary discourse,” by which she means that human rights ought to be understood as a rich discourse that operates within a specified sphere. As a discourse, human rights consist in more than the lowest limits of ethical conduct. They express an intrinsic conviction that humans ought to flourish and that certain conditions can destroy, distort, or thwart the potential for human flourishing. Human rights discourse does not itself define human flourishing or delineate the conditions of human flourishing, but rather adopts a<italic>via negativa</italic>, drawing on examples from human experience to articulate conditions that prevent, disrupt, or damage capacities to flourish. In this way, human rights discourse adopts a role that Regan describes as “protective marginality,” not serving as ends in themselves but located at the margins of ethics, carving out a space within which ethical life may be possible, leaving the task of fuller development of ethics within this sphere to other discourses. By defining human rights as a dialectical boundary discourse of protective marginality, Regan shows that there is no necessary conflict between theological ethics and theological anthropologies, on the one hand, and human rights, on the other.</p>
      <p>With this understanding of human rights, Regan shows how secular human rights and Christian theology engage in common themes, interests, and areas of concern, arguing that both have in the recent past and could continue in the future to benefit from a reciprocity of critique. In this descriptive mode, Regan discusses the emergence and development of liberation theology but also highlights intellectual engagement with human rights discourse of the hierarchy of the Roman Catholic Church from the end of WWII to the post–Second Vatican Council era. While reverent toward the deepening and thickening of the church’s vision of the human person, Regan also challenges the institutional church to reflect on apparent moments of dissonance between its theory of human personalism and praxis.</p>
      <p>Not content to engage the discourses of theology and human rights by way of definition and description, Regan constructively engages both discourses, building on the work of Karl Rahner, Johann Baptist Metz, and Paul Ricoeur. The heart of the text is this constructive mode. Regan develops a theological anthropology that sees human flourishing, the aim of human being, in a “generosity of existence” (15), which is grounded in and flows from a capacity for God (76). Generosity of existence is the idea that life consists in both giving and receiving toward greater flourishing of oneself, others, and a community of being (112). The notion of generosity of existence includes a capacity for self-determination and is therefore protected by a human rights discourse that seeks to defend a zone of individual human autonomy. But this theological anthropology is not exhausted by individual autonomy. Rather, it links an individual capacity for self-determination to a responsibility for “making oneself” in response both to God and to the embeddedness of human life (82). In this sense, human rights ought to be taken seriously by any theologian who believes human beings ought to orient their lives to God, because violations of human rights severely impair this capacity and impede the possibility of responding to a divine call. She attributes the revelation of a mystical dimension to human rights activism to the insights of liberation theology, which highlights a divine element embedded in the struggle for human rights. But Regan also sees liberation theology as contributing several insights to secular liberal human rights discourse, including an awareness and acknowledgment of the systematic and structural constraints that limit the capacities of the poor of the world to flourish, and highlighting the importance of basic sociocultural rights.</p>
      <p>In addition to developing a theological anthropology, Regan lays the groundwork for a human rights praxis of “just memory,” drawing on the work of Paul Ricoeur. Situating human rights discourse between the memory of suffering and the hope for a better future, Regan develops an ethics toward just memory, which includes allowing individuals to face the scars and wounds of memory in order to work through the past (101), enabling the pragmatic use of memory throughout a community through construction of narrative (101–2), and articulating an ethical-political duty of remembrance for purposes of preventing destructive tendencies, allowing the possibility of forgiveness, and retaining a heritage of victimization to counter the historical tendency to celebrate victors (102). Regan discusses the report of human rights violations and their individual and societal impacts, produced by the Office of the Catholic Archdiocese of Guatemala, as an example of how such an ethic can be put into practice.</p>
      <p>Regan returns to the perceived oppositional relationship between theology and human rights by critical engagement with postliberal, new traditionalist theology. She challenges the false dichotomy that is evidenced in the disdain for and rejection of secular liberal politics in the writings of such thinkers as John Milbank, Stanley Hauerwas, and Daniel Bell and demonstrates the potential fruitfulness of ethical engagement in the overlapping space between the<italic>civitas dei</italic>and<italic>civitas terrena</italic>. This is the province of human rights discourse, the quest for imperfect human justice for the provisional time.</p>
      <p>The text covers a lot of ground, delving into many of the touch points between theology and human rights and endeavoring to demonstrate how those points can be sources of mutual enrichment rather than conflict. At times the comprehensive scope of the text, which draws on the insights of so many, makes it a challenging read and leaves the reader wanting more development and illustration of the fruits of the author’s argument. Overall, the text is an important contribution to the constructive engagement between theology and human rights discourse and is a serious challenge to those in either camp who would peremptorily reject the insights of the other.</p>
   </body>
</article>
