<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">signs</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Signs</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00979740</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456943</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">25195203</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/521054</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">SIGNS60363</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Remembering the Future; or, Whatever Happened to Re‐Vision?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"/>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Liedeke</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Plate</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Institute for Gender Studies and Department of Comparative Arts and Cultural StudiesRadboud University, Nijmegen</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>Winter 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>33</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>518276</issue-id>
         <fpage>389</fpage>
         <lpage>411</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/521054"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <p>Versions of this article were presented at the Contemporary Women’s Writing Network conference, For Love or Money? Contemporary Women’s Fiction in the Marketplace, which took place at the University of Wales, Bangor, in April 2006; at the Technologies of Memory in the Arts conference of the Radboud University, Nijmegen, in May 2006; and at the Sixth European Gender Research conference, Gender and Citizenship in a Multicultural Context, in Łódź, in September 2006.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
      <notes notes-type="epigraph">
         <disp-quote>
            <p>Perhaps it is time to remember the future, rather than simply to worry about the future of memory.</p>
            <p>—Andreas Huyssen,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 29</p>
         </disp-quote>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In her essay, “When We Dead Awaken: Writing as Re‐Vision,” Adrienne Rich famously wrote, “Re‐Vision—the act of looking back, of seeing with fresh eyes, of entering an old text from a new critical direction—is for women more than a chapter in cultural history: it is an act of survival” (Rich<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf63">1972</xref>, 18). Rich’s words are well known. They have been quoted many times throughout the past three and a half decades, usually to underscore the need for women to revisit the past and get to know it differently in order to change the future.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>Rich’s call for re‐vision, in the sense of retelling the stories that make up our common cultural heritage from the perspective of postcolonialism, feminism, and gender and queer studies, has transformed not only our understanding of the past but also our understanding of how we come to such an understanding. Literary history, historiography, and history<italic>tout court</italic>will never be the same again. The bell has tolled for the<italic>grands récits</italic>, the grand narratives that served to bolster the legitimacy of the ruling social institutions (Lyotard<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf46">1984</xref>). According to the French historian Pierre Nora, this fragmentation of History into histories is one of the reasons for the current obsession with memory. “The ‘democratization’ of history,” he argues, “takes the form of a marked emancipatory trend among peoples, ethnic groups, and even certain classes of individuals in the world today; in short, the emergence, over a very short period of time, of all those forms of memory bound up with minority groups for whom rehabilitating their past is part and parcel of reaffirming their identity” (Nora<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf54">2002</xref>). Paradoxically, it would appear that it is precisely the re‐vision impulse that has led to what Andreas Huyssen has identified as “a fundamental crisis in our imagination of alternative futures” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 2). Today, indeed, it is generally understood that history is a story that is told in the interest of a particular group of people and that there is always another side to every story. As a result, the past is no longer this distant “foreign” country but a space open to multiple revisits from the perspective of the present.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>“Historical memory today is not what it used to be,” Huyssen writes, adding, “untold recent and not so recent pasts impinge upon the present. … The past has become part of the present in ways simply unimaginable in earlier centuries” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 1).</p>
      <p>The profound change that has taken place in our relation to the past also has far‐reaching consequences for the way we envision the future: “In effect, it was the way in which a society, nation, group or family envisaged its future that traditionally determined what it needed to remember of the past to prepare that future; and this in turn gave meaning to the present, which was merely a link between the two” (Nora<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf54">2002</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>As I wish to argue here, the fact that the past has become so much a part of the present may well explain why re‐vision no longer serves to envision new futures. In<italic>The Production of Presence</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">2004</xref>), the German new philologist Hans Ulrich Gumbrecht characterizes contemporary historical culture as a “broad present” (121) that leaves the future for all practical purposes “inaccessible” (120), outside the reach of our collective imagination. As the question in the title of this article indicates, my concern is with re‐vision as something we seem to have lost: “whatever happened to re‐vision” expresses my surprise and confusion as I discover that something has gone missing. As I will argue, what seems to have disappeared is a clear sense of where we want to be in the future, the sense of rewriting or revisiting the past in order to change the future. More than anything, perhaps, it is the future as a collective project that seems to be forgotten, relegating visions of a better world or a just society to the discourses of a particular (nineteenth‐century) ideological formation, a “chapter in cultural history,” as Rich already suspected.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>It is this sense of futures past that concerns me here, and I hear it resounding in Huyssen’s phrase used as an epigraph above. For, as he does, I believe “it is time to remember the future, rather than simply to worry about the future of memory” (Huyssen<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 29).</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>See Fetterley<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf24">1978</xref>; Gilbert and Gubar<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf26">1979</xref>; DuPlessis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf19">1985</xref>; Greene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf27">1991a</xref>; Ostriker<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf57">1993</xref>; Plate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf60">1995</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf61">2000</xref>; Howe and Aguiar<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf38">2001</xref>; Komar<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf43">2003</xref>; White<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf75">2004</xref>; Widdowson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf76">2006</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>“The past is a foreign country. They do things differently there,” is the well‐known opening sentence of Leslie P. Hartley’s<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf32">1953</xref>novel,<italic>The Go‐Between</italic>, famously alluded to in David Lowenthal’s analysis of cultural uses of the past,<italic>The Past Is a Foreign Country</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf45">1985</xref>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>As Mary Eagleton and Susan Watkins write in their introduction to the special issue of the<italic>Journal of Gender Studies</italic>on “The Future of Fiction: The Future of Feminism,” “To speculate about the future necessarily involves thinking about the past and, for both fiction and feminism, anticipation about the future demands reflection on what has gone before. … While as a political movement the origin and the end‐point are less clear, the backward glance and the forward‐looking, sometimes utopian, aspiration are essential to the politics” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf20">2006</xref>, 115).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Huyssen writes, “the main concern of the nineteenth‐century nation‐states was to mobilize and monumentalize national and universal pasts so as to legitimize and give meaning to the present and to envision the future: culturally, politically, socially. This model no longer works” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 2).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>What was re‐vision?</title>
         <p>The recurrence of Rich’s re‐vision “with its crucial inserted hyphen” (Sanders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>, 7) as a critical term throughout the last decades of the twentieth century establishes it as a key concept for feminist literature. In the 1970s and 1980s, Rich’s notion of re‐vision became the rallying cry for a broad variety of women rewriting the classics of Western literature, “galvaniz[ing] a generation of feminist authors to reply with texts of their own” (Howe and Aguiar<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf38">2001</xref>, 9). Arguably, this happened for two related reasons. First, it fit into the political agenda of the so‐called second wave of feminism. Second, Rich’s re‐vision articulated a lesbian imperative that also formulated a feminist practice of reading and writing: to change the future, to create new scenarios for life. Opening the past to alternative stories meant opening the future to new possibilities, and realizing that things could be different was to change the course of history. As Rich put it:<disp-quote>
               <p>Until we can understand the assumptions in which we have been drenched we cannot know ourselves. And this drive to self‐knowledge, for women, is more than a search for identity: it is part of our refusal of the self‐destructiveness of male‐dominated society. A radical critique of literature, feminist in its impulse, would take the work first of all as a clue to how we live, how we have been living, how we have been led to imagine ourselves, how our language has trapped us as well as liberated us, how the very act of naming has been till now a male prerogative, and how we can begin to see and name—and therefore live—afresh. A change in the concept of sexual identity is essential if we are not going to see the old political order reassert itself in every new revolution. We need to know the writing of the past, and know it differently than we have ever known it; not to pass on a tradition but to break its hold over us. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf63">1972</xref>, 18–19)</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>As Rich defines it, “re‐vision … is an act of survival” because it leads to autonomy and self‐determination. By identifying sources of oppression and charting their mechanics of reproduction, re‐vision was meant to retrieve an authentic sense of self that was not defined by patriarchal society. To reveal that there is nothing natural about the stories that sustain social organization and its gendered division of labor was to rescue women from the confines of domesticity. Indeed, revealing that they are stories to begin with, myths that are passed off as timeless truths but that can be told differently, was considered the first step in the process of emancipation that was to lead, through the stages of consciousness‐raising and political action, to the radical transformation of the public sphere. French feminist Hélène Cixous voices views similar to Rich’s when she asks what would happen if the myths that sustain the patriarchal order were to be demystified and claims, “Then all the stories would have to be told differently, the future would be incalculable, the historical forces would, will, change hands, bodies; another thinking as yet not thinkable will transform the functioning of all society” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf14">1981</xref>, 93). Gesturing toward all those women re‐writers re‐visioning the great narratives of the West while resonating intertextually with Rich’s words, Cixous adds:<disp-quote>
               <p>Well, we are living through this very period when the conceptual foundation of a millennial culture is in process of being undermined by millions of a species of mole as yet not recognized.</p>
               <p>When they awaken from among the dead, from among the words, from among the laws. … (Cixous<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf14">1981</xref>, 93)</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Writers obviously had a key role to play in this historical transformation of culture. Their business is the writing of stories, and more so perhaps than most of their contemporaries, they are people who are astutely aware of the power of language to frame experience. Besides, although re‐vision is political in its implications, it is also and quite simply a narrative strategy. It is a tool for generating stories, a rewriting machine, as it were. To rewrite the classics of world literature, to retell the biblical narratives, the myths of Greek and Roman antiquity, or the Grimm brothers’ fairy tales, is to tap into the huge reservoir of stories that is our cultural imaginary and to release their inherent capacity for yielding new narratives. Brushing criticisms of parasitism aside, critics confidently assert that there is much creativity involved in the telling of “the other side of the story” (Hite<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf37">1989</xref>; see also DuPlessis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf19">1985</xref>; Greene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf27">1991a</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>Of course, the originality of a rewriting lies not in its being sprung “spontaneously from the vital root of genius,” as Edward Young defined creativity a long time ago in his “Conjectures on Original Composition” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf79">[1759] 1971</xref>, 339).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>Rather, what makes a rewriting significant is its play with another work (and, arguably, with the limits of cultural and literary property).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>It is precisely its being both faithful and unfaithful to it, its writing both within and against the tradition, that makes a rewriting interesting and rewarding.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In the late 1970s and early 1980s, with the rewritings of Margaret Atwood, Angela Carter, Sara Maitland, Michele Roberts, Emma Tennant, Jeanette Winterson, and Christa Wolf, to name just a few, feminist re‐vision took off as (almost) a literary genre in its own right.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>While feminist scholars of literature such as Judith Fetterley called for a “resisting reader” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf24">1978</xref>, xx)—a reader who would resist what she termed “the<italic>immasculation</italic>of women by men” (xx)—published writers took Rich’s words to heart and actually produced such resisting readings in new and creative texts. There seemed to be no doubt: what were needed were new stories, or at least other stories, and one way to produce those alternative stories was through wide‐scale and multiple retellings of mythic narratives. For, as critics agreed, the retelling of the classics from a new point of view constituted a radical critique of the literary tradition and of the culture it served to legitimate (e.g., Ostriker<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf55">1982</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf56">1986</xref>; DuPlessis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf19">1985</xref>). This, in turn, would “provide the conditions for changing the culture that the literature reflects” (Fetterley<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf24">1978</xref>, xx). In fact, this idea still has currency. In her recently published book,<italic>Adaptation and Appropriation</italic>, Julie Sanders writes, “what is often inescapable is the fact that a political or ethical commitment shapes a writer’s, director’s, or performer’s decision to re‐interpret a source text” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>, 2). “There is frequently heartfelt political commitment standing behind acts of literary appropriation or ‘re‐vision’” (7). Likewise, Peter Widdowson maintains, “re‐visionary novels almost invariably have a clear cultural‐political thrust. That is why the majority of them align themselves with feminist and/or postcolonial criticism in demanding that past texts’ complicity in oppression … be revised and re‐visioned as part of the process of restoring a voice, a history and an identity to those hitherto exploited, marginalized and silenced by dominant interests and ideologies” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf76">2006</xref>, 505–6).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>For allegations of parasitism, see, e.g., Jorge Luis Borges, who writes of “those parasitic books which situate Christ on a boulevard, Hamlet on La Cannebière or Don Quixote on Wall Street” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf9">1964</xref>, 39). Borges obviously had in mind the kind of works U.S. copyright law calls “derivative.” As defined in Circular 14 of the U.S. Copyright Office, “Copyright Registration for Derivative Works” (revised July 2006), a “derivative work” is “a work based upon one or more pre‐existing works, … in which a work may be recast, transformed, or adapted” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.copyright.gov/circs/circ14.pdf"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.copyright.gov/circs/circ14.pdf</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>In fact, Paul Saint‐Amour argues in<italic>The Copywrights</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf67">2003</xref>), rewritings understand “the Romantic mythology of creation ex nihilo as a form of conquest‐narrative, one that ought not to be blithely embraced by the subjects of conquest, occupation, enslavement, and other multigenerational historical traumas. In their constitutive gestures of recirculation, [they] recognize that this notion of a vacuum into which radically new things may come is a less tenable fantasy to those whose lives and works are violently and conspicuously predetermined by anterior structures of domination” (216).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Compare Saint‐Amour, who argues that the rewriting “always achieves a part of its meaning in relation to intellectual property law” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf67">2003</xref>, 215).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>See Plate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf60">1995</xref>; Genette<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf25">1997</xref>; Sanders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf68">2001</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>; Widdowson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf76">2006</xref>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>The question of genre is a vexed and much disputed one, too complex to be fully addressed here (see, e.g., Derrida<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf17">1981</xref>and Marcus<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf48">1994</xref>). My point is that in the late 1980s and early 1990s, increasing critical attention was given to feminist intertextuality and metafiction (see, e.g., Greene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf27">1991a</xref>; Barr<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf4">1993</xref>; and Boehm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf8">1995</xref>), identified as forms, movements, or genres of their own. The rewritings and re‐visions I am concerned with here can be identified as belonging to what Gayle Greene terms “a movement in contemporary … women’s fiction” that she defines as “a form of feminist fiction—feminist metafiction—that concerns women writers’ relation to ‘the tradition’” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf27">1991a</xref>, 1). Compare also Peter Widdowson, who speaks of a “sub‐genre of contemporary fiction” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf76">2006</xref>, 496).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Interestingly enough, this “clear cultural‐political thrust,” while the most important characteristic of re‐visionary fiction in Widdowson’s analysis, is also the one least developed. In this article, I am precisely challenging the taken‐for‐grantedness of the political thrust of rewritings. It might be worth noting that Widdowson’s article was published while this one was under review.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Motives for re‐vision</title>
         <p>The prime motives for feminist rewritings in the 1970s and 1980s were political and cultural. Re‐vision was motivated by a desire to counter a tradition of silence and alleged misrepresentation. Enabling authorship, it aimed at re‐presentation, both in the literary sense of a (new) depiction in words and in the political sense of the term. It was formulated as a challenge to the existing literary canon that was activated by profound disagreement with or disbelief in the texts of the past.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>Thus Cixous’s manifesto for women’s writing, “The Laugh of the Medusa,” first published in English translation within the pages of this journal thirty years ago, refutes the classical versions of the myth of Medusa and claims: “You only have to look at the Medusa straight on to see her. And she’s not deadly. She’s beautiful and she’s laughing” (Cixous<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf13">1976</xref>, 885).</p>
         <p>Equally central to re‐vision is its being grounded in a notion of a shared female experience. Beyond all the differences that separated women across class, color, and culture, there was a sense of “recognizing a problem shared” (Whelehan<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf74">2005</xref>, 10). For instance, in her account of the emergence of her novel<italic>Cassandra</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf78">1984</xref>), Wolf recounts how, as she was reading Aeschylus’s play about the battle of Troy and its aftermath, she located “a ‘mistake’ on Aeschylus’s part. Never would she [Cassandra] have said this,” she writes. Never would Cassandra mourn for Agamemnon. “Not if I knew her as well as I thought” (Wolf<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf78">1984</xref>, 150). Similarly, Maitland justifies the rewriting of old stories by having one of her characters, caught in a fairy‐tale scenario neither of her choosing nor of her liking, explain how fairy tales do not match women’s actual experiences:<disp-quote>
               <p>The old stories do not lie; that is their rule. … But although they do not lie, they omit. They tell us about the frog turned into a Prince, but they never tell us about the Prince turned into a frog; though the divorce statistics uphold the frequency of this version. They do not tell us about the women who prefer dragons to knights; nor about the ones who prefer cottages to palaces, honest independent work to silk gowns. … And they never, never let on that there are those of us who prefer jam doughnuts to orgasms, an interesting day’s work to grand passion, a Sainsbury’s supermarket trolley to a pumpkin coach. (Maitland<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf47">1993</xref>, 72–73)</p>
            </disp-quote>The success of feminist re‐vision as a narrative strategy to re‐present female experience and bring about cultural change undoubtedly contributed to its booming in the 1990s. Writers who formulated alternative pasts through rewritten stories were critically supported by scholars such as Susan Suleiman, whose desire for narrative—and hence, for past and future, for stories that involve, as Mary Eagleton and Susan Watkins remind us, “a beginning and an end” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf20">2006</xref>, 115)—explicitly takes the form of a desire for rewritings. “Not the same old story, to be sure, or if the same old story, then rewritten, rewritten,” Suleiman writes in a chapter on feminist intertextuality in<italic>Subversive Intent</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf72">1990</xref>, 169). In the fictions of Valerie Martin, Sena Jeter Naslund, Pia Pera, Alice Randall, Jacqueline Rose, and Marina Warner, among many others, classics of Western literature are retold from the point of view of female characters, yielding fascinating stories while delegitimizing the familiar ones. These rewritings of canonical works from the standpoint of the margins are not limited to voicing women’s differences from men. Equally important are the intersections of gender with sexuality, social class, and ethnicity. Thus the stories of Jekyll and Hyde’s maid (Martin<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf49">1990</xref>) and of Captain Ahab’s wife (Naslund<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf53">1999</xref>), for instance, give us more complex pictures of life in London at the turn of the nineteenth century or of early nineteenth‐century America, while Randall’s<italic>The Wind Done Gone</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf62">2001</xref>) presents us with the perspective of the enslaved on Southern plantation life and on Reconstruction. We find out what moved Job’s wife finally to cry out to him to “curse God and die” (Job 2:9; Chedid<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf12">1993</xref>), and we learn of Jane Fairfax’s thoughts in Joan Aiken’s “companion volume to<italic>Emma</italic>” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf2">1990</xref>). We hear Lolita’s side of the story in<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>(Pera<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf58">1999</xref>) and Albertine’s account of her affair with Marcel, the narrator of Proust’s<italic>In Search of Lost Time</italic>, in Rose’s novel<italic>Albertine</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf64">2001</xref>). Of course, women are not the only ones to avail themselves of this productive narrative strategy: Theodor Roszak wrote<italic>The Memoirs of Elizabeth Frankenstein</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf65">1995</xref>), John Updike gave us the story of Hamlet’s mother in<italic>Gertrude and Claudius</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf73">2000</xref>), and, most recently, the Dutch author Arthur Japin published his portrayal of Lucia, Casanova’s first love (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf42">2005</xref>).</p>
         <p>Ever since Sandra Gilbert and Susan Gubar’s<italic>The Madwoman in the Attic</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf26">1979</xref>), Jean Rhys’s “hugely influential” re‐vision of<italic>Jane Eyre</italic>has served as the exemplary case of how “we may never view that novel … in the same light once we have had access to the critique implicit in [the re‐vision]” (Sanders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>, 98). This is because, as Steven Connor points out, in engaging with the literary past, rewritings “engage with the history of beliefs and attitudes to which those originals have belonged and which they have helped to shape” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf15">1996</xref>, 167). But the success of feminist re‐vision in the literary marketplace is not only to be put on the account of its critical effectiveness. The mutual dependency of canonical work and rewriting is a complex relationship that operates on several levels. Surely it is because the canon embodies some of the fundamental values of a culture or a nation that feminist writers target its key texts as in need of re‐vision. Canons, however, continue to exist precisely by virtue of their texts being challenged and reinterpreted. Regardless of how critical they may be, rewritings paradoxically contribute to sustaining the very same canon they are challenging. Connor’s concept of “fidelity‐in‐betrayal” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf15">1996</xref>, 167), emphasizing that however much a rewriting may compromise the authority of a text that is culturally central, it can never simply deny it, for “the rewritten text must always submit to the authority of an imperative that is at once ethical and historical” (167), hints at the ways in which rewriting may well be “an inherently conservative genre” (Sanders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>, 9). Derek Attridge confirms: novels that rewrite well‐known texts “offer themselves not as challenges to the canon, but as canonic—as already canonized, one might say. They appear to locate themselves within an established literary culture, rather than presenting themselves as an assault on that culture” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf3">1996</xref>, 169).</p>
         <p>Seen in the light of canon formation, then, re‐vision is a necessary and integral part of canonicity, adding to a canon’s cultural capital rather than transforming or overturning it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>Seen from the perspective of the publishers, however, it may well be the interdependency of canonical text and rewrite—its being, as Attridge says, “already canonized”—that makes rewritings particularly interesting. Whereas rewritings have long been known to be a form of productive reception that contributes to the canonicity of texts while deriving critical attention and authority from them, the success of feminist re‐vision in the literary marketplace is equally linked to changes in the book‐publishing industry that are due to the globalization of capital. In the 1970s, the financial success of a publishing house depended on a large publishing list, which was achieved through economies of scale and a high gross margin due to printing a large number of copies in one print run. In the 1980s, capitalism shifted to a model of short‐turnover cycles of capital: short lead times with a small number of copies, low stocks, and regular reprints (Harvey<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf33">1989</xref>). One of the most visible effects of this global shift is that publishers rely increasingly on front lists, generating more and more of their overall sales from fewer books and fewer authors. “Given a choice, publishers would rather release a new title from a bestselling author with a proven customer base than take a chance on a title written by an unknown author,” the executive summary of Simba Information’s<italic>Business of Consumer Book Publishing 2005</italic>report states, adding wryly, “The reasons are pure economics” (Simba Information<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf70">2005</xref>, 2). It is in this post‐Fordist economic context that rewriting emerges as a literary genre that allows for feminist literary and political aims to be realized in a commercially viable form. Indeed, capitalizing on the way in which the canonical work or author functions as a brand name, publishers of rewritings happily exploit the canonical name’s wide recognition and its function as guarantee of a standard of quality and of certain aesthetic or narrative pleasures. Because the rewriting has an existing readership to whom it can be sold as part and parcel of that which it rewrites, it requires the launching not of a new and unknown author (which often entails costly publicity and marketing expenses) but of a product that belongs to the prestigious predecessor.</p>
         <p>Rewritings of texts that are still under copyright illuminate this process. First published in Italian in 1995 and subsequently issued in a Dutch translation in 1996, Pera’s rewriting of<italic>Lolita</italic>from the eponymous character’s perspective was blocked from publication in the United States by Vladimir Nabokov’s son, Dmitri, who claimed copyright infringement. The case was settled with Dmitri Nabokov writing a preface to the novel and half of Pera’s royalties going to PEN (Poets, Playwrights, Essayists, and Novelists).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>According to Nabokov, Pera is trading on the celebrity of<italic>Lolita</italic>, “seek[ing] inspiration, fortune and fame” from his father’s world‐famous novel. Taking Pera’s lawyer up on his argument that<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>is a “transformative” work, Nabokov observes: “<italic>My Fair Lady</italic>,<italic>West Side Story</italic>, Stoppard’s<italic>Rosencrantz and Guildenstern</italic>, Updike’s<italic>S</italic>, Jean Rhys’s<italic>Wide Sargasso Sea</italic>… all had been safely tucked into the public domain when the ‘transformations’ were penned.<italic>Lolita</italic>isn’t in the public domain, and won’t be until well into the next millennium when its copyright expires” (Nabokov<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf52">1999</xref>, viii). The distinction, no doubt, is important; texts under copyright require dues to be paid, and their authors or estates can file suit to see their rights honored. Yet in their attempts to keep unauthorized rewritings at bay, they reveal a mechanism that is inherent to all rewriting, the effects of which are of the order of brand recognition.</p>
         <p>What I am contending, then, is that as books become commodities, marketability plays an important role in the emergence of re‐vision as a popular literary genre. Whereas for feminist writers, rewriting is a literary form that combines narrative strategy with feminist praxis, for publishers, re‐vision is a means of selling books with low risks and low marketing costs. Rewritings can be marketed according to the mechanics of branding. This we see clearly in the strategies devised to sell re‐visions on the basis of the prestige that is to be gained from their being associated with canonical names, as when Aiken’s<italic>Jane Fairfax</italic>is dubbed “a companion volume to<italic>Emma</italic>.” In the bookstores, text and rewrite are juxtaposed or presented in boxed sets—<italic>Gone with the Wind</italic>and its sequel,<italic>Scarlett</italic>, by Alexandra Ripley; or Daphne du Maurier’s<italic>Rebecca</italic>and Susan Hill’s<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>Book covers and flaps explicitly refer to the precursor text, while layout and lettering reinforce the connection established between text and rewrite. For instance, the mass‐market paperback edition of<italic>Rebecca</italic>published, like Hill’s<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf36">1994</xref>), by Avon Books, states on its back cover:<disp-quote>
               <p>REBECCAONE OF THE BESTSELLINGNOVELS OF ALL TIMESand don’t miss the exciting and long‐awaited conclusionMRS. DE WINTER</p>
            </disp-quote>Similarly, the November 1994 Avon Books edition of<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>states on its back cover:<disp-quote>
               <p>MRS.deWINTERThe breathtaking, long‐awaited sequel to<bold>Daphne du Maurier's</bold>classic tale of romantic suspenseREBECCA</p>
            </disp-quote>On the former book cover, no reference is made to the author of this “exciting and long‐awaited conclusion,” nor is there any indication it might not be the same as<italic>Rebecca</italic>’s. In contrast, on the latter, the name of the author of<italic>Rebecca</italic>is not only given but also emphasized, while leaving out the name of the author of the book at hand altogether. Clearly, the name of the author of<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>is secondary to what we might call the<italic>Rebecca</italic>brand. Although Hill is a respected writer, the name Susan Hill is not what is taken to sell the book; rather, it is<italic>Rebecca</italic>with its slightly gothic lettering, its aura of romantic mystery, its best‐sellerdom.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Widdowson lists the following essential characteristics of the genre: re‐visionary novels “write back” to canonic texts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf76">2006</xref>, 501), represent a challenge to the views they claim, and do so explicitly, in order to “denaturalise the original” (503); they “exemplify the more general historicising tendency of contemporary fiction to oscillate dialectically between past and present” (504), show how “past fiction<italic>writes</italic>its view of things into history” (505), and thus “almost invariably have a clear cultural‐political thrust” (505).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Attempts to stop the publication of rewritings such as<italic>The Wind Done Gone</italic>and<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>on account of their taking a free ride on the back of their precursor’s success can be seen to ignore the publicity resulting from rewritings. Indeed, one of the effects of rewriting is that it makes readers grab for the original—witness, for instance, the success of Virginia Woolf’s<italic>Mrs. Dalloway</italic>in the wake of Michael Cunningham’s rewriting of it in<italic>The Hours</italic>. For a detailed account of these copyright cases, see Saint‐Amour’s<italic>The Copywrights</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf67">2003</xref>, 207–20).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>A similar case occurred just a few years later, with Randall’s rewriting of<italic>Gone with the Wind</italic>from the perspective of Scarlett’s half‐sister, a mulatto slave on Scarlett’s plantation. The case was settled with the novel continuing in distribution with the label “An Unauthorized Parody” and a financial contribution being made by Randall’s publishers to Morehouse College, a historically black liberal arts college in Atlanta (see Saint‐Amour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf67">2003</xref>, 207–17]; see also<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                            xlink:href="http://www.thewinddonegone.com"
                            xlink:type="simple">http://www.thewinddonegone.com</ext-link>).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>It is worth noting that both<italic>Scarlett</italic>and<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>are authorized sequels to texts that are still under copyright.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>The anxiety of affluence?</title>
         <p>As I chart whatever happened to re‐vision and explore what remains of what Christian Moraru terms its “saliently political and cultural agenda” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf50">2001</xref>, 143), I cannot ignore the logic of consumer society that turns the publishing of feminist re‐visions of classic texts into the apparent happy marriage of feminism and commercialism, commercialism that increasingly rules the entire contemporary Western world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>My point is not that money has become the norm (cf. Eagleton<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf21">2003</xref>, 16). Rather, I wish to argue that in a culture in which, as Zygmunt Bauman has it, “whatever we do … is a kind of shopping, an activity shaped in the likeness of shopping” or “is derived from the pragmatics of shopping” (Bauman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>, 73–74), our understanding of re‐vision itself similarly becomes assimilated to the logic of shopping. Let me explain. According to Bauman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf6">2005</xref>), our present condition is characterized by fluidity. Life is liquid, our jobs impermanent, and our relations volatile. With everything a matter of choice, shopping around becomes our prime activity (and “continuous partial attention,” as Linda Stone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf71">2006</xref>] phrases it, our condition): scanning, surveying, comparing, and remaining ever on the alert for new possibilities, other opportunities, better offers.</p>
         <p>What I wish to argue, then, is that just as in Bauman’s perspective, “the world becomes an infinite collection of possibilities[,] a container filled to the brim with a countless multitude of opportunities” (Bauman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>, 61), so does the past. Rather than singular and subject to interpretation, the past is something we conjure up for its own sake, for the pleasure of imagining “how we would have related, intellectually and with our bodies, to certain objects … if we had encountered them in their own historical everyday worlds” (Gumbrecht<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">2004</xref>, 124). And as we do so, “we reject the question of what benefits we might expect from engaging the past,” for, as Gumbrecht points out, “any possible answer to the question of practical benefits will limit the range of modalities through which we can indulge in the past—and simply enjoy our contact with it” (125). In this light, re‐vision is no longer a matter of revisiting the past in order to project new futures, as Rich and Cixous had it, or of thinking that rewriting would have a demythologizing effect, as Carter thought it would (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf11">1983</xref>, 71). Rather, the retelling of well‐known stories from alternative points of view becomes part of the shopping, of “scanning the assortment of possibilities, examining, touching, feeling, handling the goods on display … putting some of them in the trolley and others back on the shelf” (Bauman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>, 73). For instance, Disney does not just issue the film<italic>Aladdin</italic>. Among the merchandising paraphernalia there is also<italic>Disney's Aladdin: The Genie’s Tale</italic>(Kreider<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf44">1993</xref>) and<italic>Disney's Aladdin: Jasmine’s Story</italic>(Elder<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf22">1997</xref>). These two books exemplify the way in which re‐vision has become an integral part of product marketing and a matter of personal choice. As bedtime approaches, parents turn to their offspring and ask: whose story do you want to hear tonight? Jasmine’s? The Genie’s? Aladdin’s? In fact, the manipulating of consumer goods Bauman speaks of happens quite literally in the Upside Down Tales series for children where, after reading the classic tales of Snow White, of Hansel and Gretel, or of Little Red Riding Hood, the reader is invited to flip over the book and read the story again as told from the point of view of the stepmother, the witch, or the wolf (Black<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf7">1991</xref>; Rowland<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf66">1991</xref>; Heller<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf35">1995</xref>). “I know you’ve heard the story of Little Red Riding Hood and the wolf who eats her and her granny,”<italic>The Wolf</italic>
            <italic>’s Tale</italic>begins. “Well, I’m the wolf. William is my name, and I’m going to tell you the real story” (Rowland<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf66">1991</xref>, 1). Taking the old adage that “there is another side to every story” to the letter, the upside‐down book combines the technique of re‐vision with its spatial phenomenological manifestation, producing its new critical direction as tangible materiality and consumer product.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>I owe my heading “the anxiety of affluence” to Imelda Whelehan, who looks back on thirty‐five years of feminist fiction in<italic>The Feminist Bestseller</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf74">2005</xref>). Her argument intersects with mine at points, as when she argues that “the problems which beset the heroines of the 1970s classics were never resolved” (Whelehan<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf74">2005</xref>, 6). “Nowhere is this more apparent,” she writes, “than in the open endings of the novels where the central character may find herself alone, or on the threshold of decisions, always looking back” (5). She might as well be talking about re‐vision.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Consuming memories</title>
         <p>Obviously, the vogue for shopping for alternative pasts has direct consequences for the ways in which rewriting affects cultural memory. Transforming our relationship to the past, to tradition, and to the founding myths of culture, it equally undermines the possibility of projecting the future—of representing the future as project.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Whereas rewriting has long been a powerful political and ideological tool in the shaping and reshaping of collective memory, its critical effectiveness in a literary marketplace that increasingly works according to the logics of consumption is transformed. Today, memory and shopping are linked, not only because consumerism is an integral part of contemporary commemorative practices but also because memories and memorability are central to a society of consumption that has embraced experience as its key marketing concept. In their handbook of business strategy and innovation,<italic>The Experience Economy: Work Is Theatre and Every Business a Stage</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf59">1999</xref>), Joseph Pine and James Gilmore argue that “Experiences represent an existing but previously unarticulated<italic>genre of economic output</italic>” (ix). Attempting to convince companies that they ought to “script and stage compelling experiences,” as the blurb on the book’s front flap reads, they write: “In the emerging Experience Economy, companies must realize that they make memories, not goods” (Pine and Gilmore<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf59">1999</xref>, 100). An economy that is geared toward producing memories should certainly make us wary of the kind of memory into which we are buying. Producing competing memories as consumer goods, it is also an economy that puts re‐vision at the heart of economic culture and consumerism at the center of rewriting as a memory‐practice.</p>
         <p>The much advertised launch of Canongate’s series the Myths at the 2005 Frankfurter Buchmesse exemplifies how rewriting has not only reached center stage within culture but become big business as well. The series, which was touted as “the most ambitious simultaneous world‐wide publication ever undertaken” (Byng<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf10">2005</xref>), is a joint enterprise involving some twenty‐five international publishing houses worldwide, with plans for the publication, over the next three decades, of myths retold “in a contemporary and memorable way” by authors such as Margaret Atwood, Chinua Achebe, A. S. Byatt, and Donna Tartt. One of the first books issued in the series is Winterson’s<italic>Weight</italic>, a retelling of the myth of Atlas and Heracles that can be read as a programmatic statement for the series. In the introduction Winterson explains the choice of subject as one that imposed itself on her: “When I was asked to choose a myth to write about, I realized I had chosen already. The story of Atlas holding up the world … was waiting to be written. Re‐written. The recurring language motif of<italic>Weight</italic>is ‘I want to tell the story again’” (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, xiv). Thematizing rewriting, Winterson’s leitmotif not only bolsters her endorsement of the Myths as “a marvelous way of telling stories—re‐telling stories for their own sakes, finding in them permanent truths about human nature” (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, xvi) but also of rewriting and retelling as freed of teleological (historical) time. Mixing autobiography with myth—“I wrote it directly out of my own situation” (xiv); “My girlfriend says I have an Atlas complex” (97)—Winterson follows the traditional distinction between historical (linear) time and mythical (cyclical) time, linking the desire to tell the story again with the inability to break free from “the gravitational pull of past and future” (99): “The pull of past and future is so strong that the present is crushed by it. We lie helpless in the force of patterns inherited and patterns re‐enacted by our own behaviour” (99).</p>
         <p>Drawing in particular on the analogy between the demigod carrying the world on his shoulders and the storyteller holding up her fictional world, Winterson’s self‐mythologizing as Atlas—her retelling of the mythical adventures of the Titan in the first person—extends the relevance of<italic>Weight</italic>beyond authorial metafiction. The storyteller, indeed, is not just the writer of fictions; she is also the teller of the story of her own life, and in this sense, rewriting retains its existential drive to project human existence narratively. Winterson’s narrative rests upon the simile of the book of nature. “The strata of sedimentary rock are like the pages of a book, each with a record of contemporary life written on it,” she writes, using black and red lettering and varying letter size to highlight the materiality and mediality of writing (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, ix; cf. Hayles<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf34">2002</xref>). Proceeding to retell the beginning of the world—“In the beginning there was nothing” (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 3), we read in a reformulation of Genesis 1:1–2, which might be Winterson’s or Atlas’s—the narrator, rejecting the notion that all “the rest is history” (5), explains: “All the stories are here, silt‐packed and fossil‐stored. The book of the world opens anywhere, chronology is one method only and not the best” (6).</p>
         <p>In contrast to the teleology and chronology of history, myth is a singular time‐space, a chronotope fusing present, past, and future. As Atlas recounts his story, he tells how he can “hear the world beginning. Time plays itself back for me. … I realise I am carrying not only this world, but all possible worlds. I am carrying the world in time as well as in space. … I am carrying its potential as well as what has so far been realised” (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 25). While the world embodies the myth as “a narrative whose beginning and ending continually inform the middle” (Coupe<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf16">1997</xref>, 97), Atlas represents myth as eternal return and, with that, myth as tragic destiny (see Eliade<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf23">1991</xref>, especially 34–46). Indeed, when Atlas, relieved from his burden by Heracles so that he can carry out one of the latter’s labors, comes to the Garden of the Hesperides to fetch the three golden apples, Hera tells him the rules of the mythical game. Reminding him that “Mother Earth’s greatest gift” is “knowledge of past and future,” she explains, “The apples you have taken are your own past and future. … The third apple is the present … made from your past, pointing toward the future. Which is it, Atlas? Only you can decide” (Winterson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 72–73). Hera speaks of choice; in contrast, Atlas speaks of fate: “There is no choice,” he says. “There is Fate. No man escapes his fate” (75). The goddess disagrees: “There was no enchantment, Atlas. You could not see the tree as it is. You could not see the changefulness of the world. All these pasts are yours, all these futures, all these presents. You could have chosen differently. You did not” (75).</p>
         <p>In the clash of perspectives, Winterson seems on the side of Atlas, defending the mythical rather than the historical view of things. Whereas in Hera’s view, destiny is a matter of choice, in theirs, “life reads like fate” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 97). “We are in the gravitational pull of past and future. It takes huge energy—speed‐of‐light power—to break that gravitational pull. How many of us ever get free of our orbit?” Winterson asks (99). Dismissing notions of free will along with self‐help courses as “fancy” (99) and delusional, Winterson looks for a different end in the telling itself: “I thought that if I could only keep on telling the story, if the story would not end, I could invent my way out of the world” (139).</p>
         <p>“I chose this story above all others because it’s a story I’m struggling to end. … That’s why I write fiction—so that I can keep telling the story. … Always a new beginning, a different end,” Winterson writes toward the close of her narrative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 137). Linking the desire for retelling with the inability to formulate a conclusion and the necessity for an open ending, Winterson has Atlas walk away, yet presents this “very particular end not found elsewhere” (xiv) as but one possibility among several, the choice of which is ultimately left to the individual reader’s personal preference: “no one knows its composition,” Winterson observes. “Dark matter could be conventional matter, … or it could even be black holes. Or it could be Atlas holding up the universe. But I think it is Atlas and Laïka walking away” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf77">2005</xref>, 151).<italic>Weight</italic>’s multiperspectival ending underscores its status as inaugural retelling of myth for a twenty‐first century that can only assimilate more pasts into its ever broadening present. In this sense, the Myths seems typical for the contemporary take on re‐vision. Whereas the names of the authors hold the promise of retellings with a critical edge—Achebe having given us<italic>Things Fall Apart</italic>as a reply to and a thorough undermining of Joseph Conrad’s<italic>Heart of Darkness</italic>(see Moyers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf51">1989</xref>; Achebe<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf1">1990</xref>), and neither Atwood nor Winterson is a stranger to rewriting as cultural critique—Winterson’s phrase and its appropriation by the series’ editor make us suspect differently. “We want to tell the story again,” as the series’ editor Jamie Byng puts it on Canongate’s Web site, speaks of the storyteller’s desire for and delight in language; of the pleasure of telling stories, of keeping the stories alive by retelling them. Inevitably also meaning “we want to<italic>sell</italic>the story again,” retelling becomes a retailing strategy, promising ever new and improved reading experiences that are as ephemeral as any other consumer experience. Speaking neither of learning from the past nor of projecting a new future, mythical retellings accord perfectly with the logic of the times and an economy of perpetual innovation to which they immediately become assimilated. Containing the seeds of its renewal and transformation in permanence, mythical retelling is not only the actualization of one of the possibilities already inscribed in the (mythical) book of the world. It is also the emblem of re‐vision as inescapably part of consumer culture.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>Memory and project are two sides of the same coin, Jean‐Claude Guillebaud writes in “Entre mémoire et projet” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf29">2006</xref>, 47).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>In the past decades two related trends converge in the emergence of re‐vision as a privileged literary genre. On the one hand, the logic of post‐Fordist marketing accounts for the increase in published re‐visions. Simply put, re‐visions are interesting to publishers because they are cultural products that entail low marketing costs. On the other hand, the logic of consumer society that turns shopping into the archetype of our activities in the world extends to our relationship with the past. We turn to the past for myriad possibilities. These possibilities are to enrich our present, not to imagine alternatives to it. This is because the present is no longer “a short moment of transition” between “the past as a ‘space of experience’ and the future as an open ‘horizon of expectations’” (Gumbrecht<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">2004</xref>, 120).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>Rather, in a world of consumers, the present is all there is, and this present is “becoming broader,” for it includes the many recent and not so recent pasts we do not wish to leave behind (Gumbrecht<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">2004</xref>, 121; cf. Huyssen<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 1–2).</p>
         <p>Characteristic of this new attitude toward the past are the closing words of Sanders’s recently published volume,<italic>Adaptation and Appropriation</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>), in the Routledge Critical Idiom series. Opening her final paragraph with the claim that “We need then to restore to the subgenres or practices of adaptation and appropriation a genuinely celebratory comprehension of their capacity for creativity, and for comment and critique,” she concludes: “Adaptation and appropriation … are all about multiple interactions and a matrix of possibilities. They are, endlessly and wonderfully, about seeing things come back to us in as many forms as possible” (Sanders<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf69">2006</xref>, 160). This is the rhetoric of hedonistic liberalism, celebrating multiplicity and pluralism for its own sake, for the choices it allows; it is Fredric Jameson’s postmodernity whose “relationship to the past is that of a consumer adding another rare object to the collection, or another flavour to the international banquet” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf40">1998</xref>, 129). Typically, there is no word about the future re‐vision might help to envision, no sense of “memory as a means to liberation” (Greene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf28">1991b</xref>, 291), of the interlocking of memory and the feminist project, of looking back in order to move forward. On the left, concerns about the disappearance of the future and capitalism’s increasing monopoly on it are growing, as are laments about the loss of a sense of historical time as a teleology moving away from a past from which we could learn and into a future that would be different (see Gumbrecht<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">2004</xref>, 120; see also Jameson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf41">2005</xref>). There are those who are bitter about it, complaining, as does Terry Eagleton in<italic>After Theory</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf21">2003</xref>), that “Over the dreary decades of post‐1970s conservatism, the historical sense had grown increasingly blunted, as it suited those in power that we should be able to imagine no alternative to the present” (Eagleton<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf21">2003</xref>, 6–7). Yet few of us have been willing to acknowledge that if today, “the past is selling better than the future” (Huyssen<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">2003</xref>, 20), this is because re‐vision has taught us that the past holds infinite possibilities and has sold us on the idea that “for the possibilities to remain infinite, none may be allowed to petrify into everlasting reality” (Bauman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>, 62).</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Gumbrecht developed this argument earlier in his chapter titled “After Learning from History” in<italic>In 1926: Living at the Edge of Time</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf30">1997</xref>, 411–36; see especially 420–21).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc6">
         <title>Postscript</title>
         <p>How, then, are we to get out of the impasse and return a sense of vision to re‐vision? If rewriting is indeed change (see Moraru<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf50">2001</xref>, 144), is change a positive value in itself? In his discussion of what he terms “radical typology,” Laurence Coupe emphasizes what he sees as myth’s “permanent possibility,” its “dynamic tension between the already and the not yet” (Coupe<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf16">1997</xref>, 106). As Coupe argues, “all myths presuppose a previous narrative, and in turn form the model for future narratives” (108). In consequence, it is not toward demythologization (which is, after all, oriented toward the past and works, as Coupe points out, “in terms of closure” [108]) but toward remythologization that rewriting as re‐vision ought to aspire: to work toward disclosure, opening narratives to ever new re‐visions, and thus to “evade the stasis of doctrine” (110). “Permanent possibility,” “narrative dynamism”—Coupe’s terms echo distinctly with Bauman’s liquidity and should therefore be regarded with similar suspicion. More crucially, Coupe’s understanding of myth (derived from Paul Ricoeur) relies on a sense of utopia that is external to the rewriting it informs. As he explains, myth “is synonymous with a ‘social imagination’ which functions by virtue of a dialectic between ‘ideology’ and ‘utopia.’ … Without [ideology], we would have no sense of society or tradition; without [utopia], we would simply equate the given society and tradition with eternal truth” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf16">1997</xref>, 96). The question remains: in the absence of utopia, what role for re‐vision?</p>
         <p>An alternative end to my account of the fate of re‐vision and its place in feminism today presented itself when, recently, a student came to me to discuss a possible subject for her bachelor’s thesis. She wanted to write something that would contribute to the current debate: a feminist topic, she said, but not, as she put it, “women on the barricades.” One idea she had was to write about Anita Diamant’s<italic>The Red Tent</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf18">1997</xref>). This novel tells the story of the biblical Dinah, daughter of Leah and Jacob. My student had picked up the book while on holiday in Spain and had been deeply moved by it. It had transformed her views on the Bible and made her rethink the relation of women to the biblical narratives.</p>
         <p>My encounter with this student suggests another way of thinking about the political value of rewriting. Countering all the more blasé signals my students were giving me that it was most naive to think the retelling of stories from another point of view could have any political impact, it is evidence that women’s rewritings of classic texts can still affect young women, still make them think and make them want to contribute to the discussions, the debates that shape the public sphere. Although we need, of course, to factor in serendipity—the student was on holiday and thought she had discovered a little‐known book when in fact it was a<italic>New York Times</italic>best seller—there is definitely a sense in which her discovery marked a moment in her life and signals the development of a feminist consciousness (broadly defined as a certain awareness of gender identity combined with a critical position in respect to misogyny and patriarchy and a conviction that things can be changed). There is no denying that increasing individualization at all levels of society has caused the loss of a sense of collective action and political projects. This is equally true for ideas of improvement, emancipation, and modernization, the responsibility of which has largely been shifted to the individual, whose “human rights,” as Bauman argues, are redefined as “the right of individuals to stay different and to pick and choose at will their own models of happiness and fitting life‐style” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">2000</xref>;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf6">2005</xref>, 29). In this deregulated and privatized sociopolitical context that knows no common cause, re‐vision can only fail to formulate enabling fictions for a better future for all. Yet in its capacity to speak to individuals, it can still draw them into visions of community and collectivity. Re‐vision may thus not be the lifeline that is to haul us out of patriarchy any more, but as a structure of address that engages readers into contemplating differences, it remains one of the ways in which we keep sane and critical and thinking, moved by the stories of long‐forgotten lives into participating in an open public sphere.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed">
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="rf1">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Achebe, Chinua. 1990. “An Image of Africa: Racism in Conrad’s<italic>Heart of Darkness</italic>.” In his<italic>Hope and Impediments: Selected Essays</italic>, 1–20. New York: Doubleday/Anchor.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf2">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Aiken, Joan. 1990.<italic>Jane Fairfax: A Novel to Complement</italic>Emma<italic>by Jane Austen</italic>. London: Gollancz.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf3">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Attridge, Derek. 1996. “Oppressive Silence: J. M. Coetzee’s<italic>Foe</italic>and the Politics of Canonisation.” In<italic>Critical Perspectives on J. M. Coetzee</italic>, ed. Graham Huggan and Stephen Watson, 168–90. New York: St. Martin’s.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf4">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Barr, Marleen S. 1993.<italic>Lost in Space: Probing Feminist Science Fiction and Beyond</italic>. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf5">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Bauman, Zygmunt. 2000.<italic>Liquid Modernity</italic>. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf6">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 2005.<italic>Liquid Life</italic>. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf7">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Black, Sheila. 1991.<italic>Hansel and Gretel; The Witch’s Story</italic>. Secaucus, NJ: Carol.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf8">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Boehm, Beth A. 1995. “Feminist Metafiction and Androcentric Reading Strategies: Angela Carter’s Reconstructed Reader in<italic>Nights at the Circus</italic>.”<italic>Critique: Studies in Contemporary Fiction</italic>37(1):35–49.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf9">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Borges, Jorge Luis. 1964. “Pierre Menard, Author of the<italic>Quixote</italic>.” In his<italic>Labyrinths: Selected Stories and Other Writings</italic>, ed. Donald Yates and James Irby, 36–44. New York: New Directions.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf10">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Byng, Jamie. 2005. “Myths: We Want to Tell the Story Again.” Edinburgh: Canongate.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.canongate.net/myths"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.canongate.net/myths</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf11">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Carter, Angela. 1983. “Notes from the Front Line.” In<italic>On Gender and Writing</italic>, ed. Michelene Wandor, 69–77. London: Pandora.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf12">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Chedid, Andrée. 1993.<italic>La femme de Job</italic>[The wife of Job]. Paris: Calman‐Levy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf13">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Cixous, Hélène. 1976. “The Laugh of the Medusa.” Trans. Keith Cohen and Paula Cohen.<italic>Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society</italic>1(4):875–93.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf14">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 1981. “Sorties.” Trans. Ann Liddle. In<italic>New French Feminisms: An Anthology</italic>, ed. Elaine Marks and Isabelle de Coutivron, 90–98. New York: Schocken.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf15">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Connor, Steven. 1996.<italic>The English Novel in History, 1950 to 1995</italic>. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf16">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Coupe, Laurence. 1997.<italic>Myth</italic>. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf17">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Derrida, Jacques. 1981. “The Law of Genre.” Trans. Avital Ronell. In<italic>On Narrative</italic>, ed. W. J. T. Mitchell, 51–77. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf18">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Diamant, Anita. 1997.<italic>The Red Tent: A Novel</italic>. New York: Picador.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf19">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">DuPlessis, Rachel Blau. 1985.<italic>Writing beyond the Ending: Narrative Strategies of Twentieth‐Century Women Writers</italic>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf20">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Eagleton, Mary, and Susan Watkins. 2006. “Introduction.” In their “The Future of Fiction: The Future of Feminism,” special issue of<italic>Journal of Gender Studies</italic>15(2):115–17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf21">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Eagleton, Terry. 2003.<italic>After Theory</italic>. New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf22">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Elder, Vanessa. 1997.<italic>Disney’s Aladdin: Jasmine’s Story.</italic>New York: Disney Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf23">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Eliade, Mircea. 1991.<italic>The Myth of the Eternal Return: Or, Cosmos and History</italic>. Trans. Willard Trask. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf24">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Fetterley, Judith. 1978.<italic>The Resisting Reader: A Feminist Approach to American Fiction</italic>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf25">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Genette, Gérard. 1997.<italic>Palimpsests: Literature in the Second Degree</italic>. Trans. Channa Newman and Claude Doubinsky. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf26">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Gilbert, Sandra, and Susan Gubar. 1979.<italic>The Madwoman in the Attic: The Woman Writer and the Nineteenth‐Century Literary Imagination</italic>. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf27">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Greene, Gayle. 1991a.<italic>Changing the Story: Feminist Fiction and the Tradition</italic>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf28">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 1991b. “Feminist Fiction and the Uses of Memory.”<italic>Signs</italic>16(2):290–321.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf29">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Guillebaud, Jean‐Claude. 2006. “Entre mémoire et projet” [Between memory and project]. In<italic>La mémoire, pour quoi faire?</italic>[Memory: What’s it for?], ed. Alain Houziaux, 47–73. Paris: Éditions de l’atelier/Éditions Ouvrières.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf30">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Gumbrecht, Hans Ulrich. 1997.<italic>In 1926: Living at the Edge of Time</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf31">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 2004.<italic>The Production of Presence: What Meaning Cannot Convey</italic>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf32">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Hartley, Leslie Poles. 1953.<italic>The Go‐Between</italic>. London: Hamish Hamilton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf33">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Harvey, David. 1989.<italic>The Condition of Postmodernity: An Enquiry into the Origins of Cultural Change</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf34">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Hayles, N. Katherine. 2002.<italic>Writing Machines</italic>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf35">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Heller, Catherine. 1995.<italic>Snow White: The Untold Story</italic>. Secaucus, NJ: Carol.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf36">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Hill, Susan. 1993.<italic>Mrs. de Winter</italic>. New York: Sinclair‐Stevenson.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf37">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Hite, Molly. 1989.<italic>The Other Side of the Story: Structures and Strategies of Contemporary Feminist Narrative</italic>. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf38">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Howe, Mica, and Sarah Appleton Aguiar. 2001. “Introduction.” In their<italic>He Said, She Says: An RSVP to the Male Text</italic>, 9–17. Madison, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf39">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Huyssen, Andreas. 2003.<italic>Present Pasts: Urban Palimpsests and the Politics of Memory</italic>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf40">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Jameson, Fredric. 1998. “Transformations of the Image in Postmodernity.” In his<italic>The Cultural Turn: Selected Writings on the Postmodern, 1983–1998</italic>, 93–135. London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf41">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 2005.<italic>Archaeologies of the Future: The Desire Called Utopia and Other Science Fictions</italic>. London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf42">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Japin, Arthur. 2005.<italic>In Lucia’s Eyes</italic>. Trans. David Colmer. New York: Knopf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf43">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Komar, Kathleen L. 2003.<italic>Reclaiming Klytemnestra: Revenge or Reconciliation</italic>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf44">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Kreider, Karen. 1993.<italic>Disney’s Aladdin: The Genie’s Tale</italic>. Racine, WI: Western.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf45">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Lowenthal, David. 1985.<italic>The Past Is a Foreign Country</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf46">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Lyotard, Jean‐François. 1984.<italic>The Postmodern Condition: A Report on Knowledge</italic>. Trans. Geoff Bennington and Brian Massumi. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf47">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Maitland, Sara. 1993.<italic>Women Fly When Men Aren’t Watching: Short Stories</italic>. London: Virago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf48">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Marcus, Laura. 1994.<italic>Auto/biographical Discourses: Theory, Criticism, Practice</italic>. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf49">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Martin, Valerie. 1990.<italic>Mary Reilly</italic>. New York: Doubleday.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf50">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Moraru, Christian. 2001.<italic>Rewriting: Postmodern Narrative and Cultural Critique in the Age of Cloning</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf51">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Moyers, Bill. 1989. “Interview with Chinua Achebe.” In<italic>A World of Ideas</italic>, ed. Betty Sue Flowers, 333–44. New York: Doubleday.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf52">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Nabokov, Dmitri. 1999. “On a Book Entitled<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>.” Preface to<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>, in Pera 1999, vii–x.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf53">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Naslund, Sena Jeter. 1999.<italic>Ahab’s Wife, or, the Star‐Gazer: A Novel</italic>. New York: William Morrow.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf54">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Nora, Pierre. 2002. “The Reasons for the Current Upsurge in Memory.”<italic>Tr@nsit Online</italic>22.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.iwm.at/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=285&amp;amp;Itemid=463"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.iwm.at/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=285&amp;Itemid=463</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf55">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Ostriker, Alicia Suskin. 1982. “The Thieves of Language: Women Poets and Revisionist Mythmaking.”<italic>Signs</italic>8(1):68–90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf56">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 1986.<italic>Stealing the Language: The Emergence of Women’s Poetry in America</italic>. Boston: Beacon.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf57">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 1993.<italic>Feminist Revision and the Bible</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf58">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Pera, Pia. 1999.<italic>Lo’s Diary</italic>. Trans. Ann Goldstein. New York: Foxrock.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf59">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Pine, B. Joseph, and James H. Gilmore. 1999.<italic>The Experience Economy: Work Is Theatre and Every Business a Stage</italic>. Boston: Harvard Business School Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf60">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Plate, Liedeke. 1995. “Visions and Re‐Visions: Female Authorship and the Act of Rewriting.” PhD dissertation, Indiana University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf61">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 2000. “Dis/Remembering the Classics: Female Identity and the Act of Rewriting.” In<italic>Gendered Memories</italic>, ed. John Neubauer and Helga Geyer‐Ryan, 65–74. Amsterdam: Rodopi.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf62">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Randall, Alice. 2001.<italic>The Wind Done Gone</italic>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf63">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Rich, Adrienne. 1972. “When We Dead Awaken: Writing as Re‐Vision.”<italic>College English</italic>34(1):18–30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf64">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Rose, Jacqueline. 2001.<italic>Albertine</italic>. London: Chatto &amp; Windus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf65">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Roszak, Theodor. 1995.<italic>The Memoirs of Elizabeth Frankenstein</italic>. New York: Random House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf66">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Rowland, Della. 1991.<italic>Little Red Riding Hood; The Wolf</italic>
               <italic>’s Tale</italic>. New York: Carol.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf67">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Saint‐Amour, Paul K. 2003.<italic>The Copywrights: Intellectual Property and the Literary Imagination</italic>. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf68">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Sanders, Julie. 2001.<italic>Novel Shakespeares: Twentieth‐Century Women Novelists and Appropriation</italic>. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf69">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">———. 2006.<italic>Adaptation and Appropriation</italic>. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf70">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Simba Information. 2005.<italic>Business of Consumer Book Publishing 2005</italic>. Stamford, CT: Bowker.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf71">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Stone, Linda. 2006. “Attention: The Real Aphrodisiac.” Paper presented at O’Reilly Emerging Technology conference, San Diego, March 7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf72">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Suleiman, Susan Rubin. 1990.<italic>Subversive Intent: Gender, Politics, and the Avant‐Garde</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf73">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Updike, John. 2000.<italic>Gertrude and Claudius</italic>. New York: Knopf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf74">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Whelehan, Imelda. 2005.<italic>The Feminist Bestseller: From Sex and the Single Girl to Sex and the City</italic>. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf75">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">White, Rosie. 2004. “Visions and Re‐Visions: Women and Time in Michèle Roberts’s<italic>In the Red Kitchen</italic>.”<italic>Women: A Cultural Review</italic>15(2):180–91.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf76">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Widdowson, Peter. 2006. “‘Writing Back’: Contemporary Re‐Visionary Fiction.”<italic>Textual Practice</italic>20(3):491–507.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf77">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Winterson, Jeanette. 2005.<italic>Weight: The Myth of Atlas and Heracles</italic>. Edinburgh: Canongate.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf78">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Wolf, Christa. 1984.<italic>Cassandra: A Novel and Four Essays</italic>. Trans. Jan van Heurck. London: Virago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf79">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Young, Edward. (1759) 1971. “Conjectures on Original Composition.” In<italic>Critical Theory since Plato</italic>, ed. Hazard Adams, 338–47. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
