<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">sociology</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50010375</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Sociology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>British Sociological Association Publications Limited</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00380385</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14698684</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">42855681</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>NARRATING CRISIS: THE DISCURSIVE CONSTRUCTION OF THE 'WINTER OF DISCONTENT'</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Colin</given-names>
                  <surname>Hay</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>1996</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>30</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40108657</issue-id>
         <fpage>253</fpage>
         <lpage>277</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/42855681"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The winter of discontent continues to exert a powerful hold over the British political imaginary. It acts as a discursive key to a collective mythology seemingly appealed to, and conjured, in each wave of industrial unrest, in each hint of political turmoil and, until recently, whenever the election of a Labour Government looked credible. In this paper I consider the rhetorical strategies and linguistic devices deployed by the tabloid media in the narration of the events of the winter of 1978-79. I argue for an interpretation of the winter of discontent as a moment of state crisis. By crisis however I do not refer to the mere accumulation of contradictions but rather to a moment of transition, a moment of decisive intervention. Within such a framework, the winter of discontent emerges as a strategic moment in the transformation of the British state, and perhaps the key moment in the pre-history of Thatcherism. For, as I hope to demonstrate, the initial appeal of the New Right was premised upon its ability to offer a convincing construction of the winter of discontent as symptomatic of a more fundamental crisis of the state. In such a moment of crisis, a particular type of decisive intervention was called for. In this discursive construction of crisis the New Right proved itself capable of changing, if not the hearts and minds of the electorate, then certainly the predominant perceptions of the political context. It recruited subjects to its vision of the necessary response to the crisis of a monolithic state besieged by the trade unions. This was perhaps the only truly hegemonic moment of Thatcherism. It occurred well before Mrs Thatcher entered Number 10. It is thus not surprising that one of the most enduring and distinctive legacies of Thatcherism has been the new political lexicon of crisis, siege and subterfuge born of the winter of discontent.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d12779e126a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e130" publication-type="other">
Abercrombie, N. et al. 1984. The Dominant Ideology Thesis. London: Allen and Unwin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e141" publication-type="other">
Althusser, L. 1971. 'Ideology and Ideological State Apparatuses', in Lenin and Philo-
sophy and Other Essays. London: New Left Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e155" publication-type="other">
Benn, T. 1990. Conflicts of Interest: Diaries 1977-80. London: Hutchinson.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e162a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e166" publication-type="other">
Block, F. 1987. 'Beyond Relative Autonomy: State Managers as Historical Subjects',
Revising State Theory: Essays in Politics and Postindustrialism. Philadelphia: Temple
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e180a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e184" publication-type="other">
Butler, D. and Kavanagh, D. 1980. The British General Election of 1979. London:
Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e198" publication-type="other">
Callaghan, J. 1987. Time and Chance. London: Collins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e209" publication-type="other">
Clarke, S. 1988. Keynesianism, Monetarism and the Crisis of the State. London: Edward
Elgar.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e219a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e223" publication-type="other">
Coates, D. 1980. Labour in Power. London: Longman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e230a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e234" publication-type="other">
Coates, D. 1989. The Crisis of Labour. London: Philip Allen.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e241a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e245" publication-type="other">
Coates, D. 1994. The Question of UK Decline: The Economy, State and Society. London:
Harvester Wheatsheaf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e260" publication-type="other">
Connell, I. 1980. 'Television News and the Social Contract', in S. Hall et al. (eds.)
Culture, Media, Language. London: Hutchinson.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e274" publication-type="other">
Cunnison, S. and Stageman, J. 1992. 'Male Power, Industrial Action and Changing
Consciousness', in Feminizing the Unions: Challenging the Culture of Masculinity. London:
Aveburv.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e287a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e291" publication-type="other">
Debray, R. 1973. 'Time and Polities', in Prison Writings. London: Allen Lane.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e298a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e302" publication-type="other">
Derrida, J. 1982. 'White Mythologies', in Margins of Philosophy. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e309a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e313" publication-type="other">
Dorfman, G. A. 1983. British Trade Unionism Against the Trades Unions Congress.
London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e327" publication-type="other">
Eldridge, J. 1992. 'News, Truth and Power', in Glasgow Media Group, Getting the
Message. London: Roudedge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e338a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e342" publication-type="other">
Flanagan, R. J. et al. 1983. Unionism, Economic Stabilisation and Incomes Policies:
European Experience. Washington DC: The Brookings Institute.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e352a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e356" publication-type="other">
Fowler, R. 1991. Language in the News: Discourse and Ideology in the Press. London:
Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e366a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e370" publication-type="other">
Gamble, A. 1994. Britain in Decline: Economic Policy, Political Strategy and the British
State. Fourth edition. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e380a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e384" publication-type="other">
Gastil, J. 1992. 'Undemocratic Discourse: A Review of Theory and Research on
Political Discourse', Discourse &amp; Society 3:469-500.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e394a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e398" publication-type="other">
Glasgow Media Group. 1976. Bad News. London: Roudedce and Keean Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e405a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e409" publication-type="other">
Glasgow Media Group. 1980. More Bad News. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e417a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e421" publication-type="other">
Glasgow Media Group. 1982. Really Bad News. London: Writers and Readers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e428a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e432" publication-type="other">
Gourevitch, P. et al. 1984. Unions and Economic Crisis: Britain, West Germany and
Sweden. London: Allen and Unwin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e442a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e446" publication-type="other">
Gramsci, A. 1971. Selections from Prison Notebooks. London: Lawrence and Wishart.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e453a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e457" publication-type="other">
Hall, S. 1973. 'The Determinations of News Photographs', in S. Cohen and J. Young
(eds.). The Manufacture of News. London: Sage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e467a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e471" publication-type="other">
Hall, S. 1980. 'Encoding/Decoding', in S. Hall et al. (eds.). Culture, Media, Language.
London: Unwin Hyman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e481a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e485" publication-type="other">
t'Hart, P. 1993. 'Symbols, Rituals and Power: The Lost Dimensions of Crisis
Management', Journal of Contingencies and Crisis Management 1:36-50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e496a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e500" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994a. 'Crisis and the Discursive Unification of the State', in P. Dunleavy and J.
Stanyer (eds.) Contemporary Political Science 1 994. Belfast: Political Studies Association.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e510a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e514" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994b. 'Labour's Thatcherite Revisionism: Playing the Politics of Catch-Up',
Political Studies 42:700-8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e524a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e528" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994c. 'Thatcherism, Post-Thatcherism and the Crisis of the British State:
Adulterated Conservatism vs. Thatcherite Revisionism?', unpublished manuscript.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e538a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e542" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994d. 'The Structural and Ideological Contradictions of Britain's Post-War
Reconstruction', Capital and Class 54:25-60.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e552a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e556" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994e. 'Werner in Wunderland: Or Notes on a Marxism Beyond Pessimism
and False Optimism', in F. Sebäi and C. Vercellone (eds.) Ecole de la Régulation et
Critique de la Raison Economique. Paris: Editions L'Harmattan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e569a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e573" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994f. 'Moving and Shaking or Cowering and Quaking? Towards a Strategic-
Relational Approach to Local Economic Development', paper presented at the ESRC
Local Community Power Conference. London School of Economics, December.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e587a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e591" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1994g. 'Majorism and the Politics of Crisis-Mangement: Thatcherism with
a Grey Face, or Post-Thatcherism', paper presented at Faculty of Law, Kyushu
University, Fukuoka, Japan, December.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e604a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e608" publication-type="other">
Hay C. 1995a. 'Structure and Agency: Holding the Whip Hand', in D. Marsh and G.
Stoker (eds.) Theories and Methods of Political Science. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e618a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e622" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1995b. 'Mobilisation through Interpellation: James Bulger, Juvenile Crime and
the Construction of a Moral Panic', Social and Legal Studies 5,2:197-224.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e632a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e636" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1995c. 'Narrative as Meta-Narrative: Post-Modern Tension and the Efface-
ment of the Political', Transformation 1,1:243-52.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e646a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e650" publication-type="other">
Hay, C. 1996. Re-stating Social and Political Change. Buckingham: Open University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e660a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e664" publication-type="other">
Hitchens, C. 1979. 'Strange Death of a Social Contract', New Statesman, 26 January.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e672a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e676" publication-type="other">
Hodge, R. and Kress, G. 1979. Language as Ideology. London: Roudedge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e683a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e687" publication-type="other">
Holly, W. 1989. 'Credibility and Political Language', in R. Woback (ed.) Language,
Power and Ideology. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e697a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e701" publication-type="other">
Holmes, M. 1985. The Labour Government, 1974-79. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e708a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e712" publication-type="other">
Jessop, B. 1980. 'The Transformation of the State in Post-War Britain', in R. Scase
(ed.) The State in Western Europe. London: Croom Helm.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e722a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e726" publication-type="other">
Jessop, B. 1990. State Theory: Putting the Capitalist State in its Place. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e733a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e737" publication-type="other">
Jessop, B. and Stones, R. 1993. 'Old City and New Times', in L Budd and S.
Whimster (eds.) Global Finance and Urban Living. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e748a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e752" publication-type="other">
Keane, J. 1984. Public Life and Late Capitalism. Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e762a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e766" publication-type="other">
Keith, M. 1993. Race, Riots and Policing: Lore and Disorder in a Multi-Racist Society.
London: University College London Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e776a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e780" publication-type="other">
Koselleck, R. 1988. Critique and Crisis: Enlightenment and the Pathogenesis of Modern
Society. Oxford: Berg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e790a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e794" publication-type="other">
Kress, G. 1985. 'Ideological Structures in Discourse', in T. A. van Dijk (ed.) Handbook
of Discourse. Analysis, Volume 2: Dimensions of Discourse. London: Academic Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e804a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e808" publication-type="other">
Laclau, E. 1977. Politics and Ideology in Marxist Theory. London: New Left Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e815a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e819" publication-type="other">
Marquand, D. 1988. The Unprincipled Society: New Demands and Old Politics. London:
Fontana.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e830a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e834" publication-type="other">
Marsh, D. 1992. The New Politics of British Trade Unionism: Union Power and the
Thatcher Legacy. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e844a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e848" publication-type="other">
Middlemas, K. 1991. Power, Competition and the State, Volume 3: The End of the Post-War
Era, Britain since 1974. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e858a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e862" publication-type="other">
Minkin, L. 1991. The Contentious Alliance: Trade Unions and the Labour Party.
Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e872a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e876" publication-type="other">
Morley, D. 1992. Television, Audiences and Ctdtural Studies. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e883a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e887" publication-type="other">
Morley, D. and Silverstone, R. 1990. 'Domestic Communications', Media, Culture
and Society 12:31-56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e897a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e901" publication-type="other">
Overbeek, H. 1990. Global Capitalism and Britain's Decline. London: Hutchinson.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e909a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e913" publication-type="other">
Philo, G. 1990. Seeing and Believing: The Influence of Television. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e920a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e924" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. 1984. Time and Narrative, Volume 1. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e931a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e935" publication-type="other">
Taylor, R. 1982. 'The Trade Union "Problem" in British Polities', in B. Pimlott and
C. Cook (eds.) Trade Unions in British Politics. London: Longman.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e945a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e949" publication-type="other">
Taylor, R. 1993. The Trade Union Question in British Politics: Government and Unions
Since 1945. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e959a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e963" publication-type="other">
Thompson, J. B. 1988. 'Mass Communication and Modern Culture: Contribution to
A Critical Theory of Ideology', Sociology 22:359-83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e973a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e977" publication-type="other">
Thompson, J. B. 1990. Ideology and Modern Culture. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e985a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e989" publication-type="other">
Todorov, T. 1977. Mikhail Bakhtin: The Dialogical Principle. Manchester: Manchester
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e999a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e1003" publication-type="other">
Trew, T. 1979. 'Theory and Ideology at Work', in R. Fowler et al. (eds.) Language and
Control. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e1013a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e1017" publication-type="other">
TUC Media Working Group. 1979. A Cause for Concern: Media Coverage of Industrial
Disputes January-February 1979. London: TUC Publication.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e1027a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e1031" publication-type="other">
van Dijk, T. A. 1985. Levels and Dimensions of Discourse Analysis, in van Dijk (ed.).
Handbook of Discourse Analysis, Volume 2: Dimensions of Discourse. London: Academic
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d12779e1044a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d12779e1048" publication-type="other">
Warde, A. 1982. Consensus and Beyond: The Development of Labour Party Strategy Since
the Second World War. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
