<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">atlantis</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50001091</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Atlantis</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The Spanish Association of Anglo-American Studies (AEDEAN)</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">02106124</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24757782</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>"Memory Lives Inside Us": Writing as Memory Traces in "The Secret Staircase" / “La memoria vive en nuestro interior”: la escritura como huella de la memoria en "The Secret Staircase"</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Sonia</given-names>
                  <surname>Villegas-López</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">37</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24757752</issue-id>
         <fpage>45</fpage>
         <lpage>62</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Asociación Española de Estudios Anglo-Norteamericanos (AEDEAN)</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24757782"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The Secret Staircase is the title given to an installation presented by Caroline Isgar and Michèle Roberts at the Foundling Museum of London in 2008, and also to the accompanying book, a collection of Isgar's drawings and Roberts's eighteen narrative pieces, meant as a souvenir of the exhibition. Roberts tells the story of a daughter's recollection of her childhood and her life with her mother on the occasion of the latter's approaching death. Each piece is inspired by an object belonging either to the past or to the experience of the mother's confinement in a hospice. Roberts's contribution to the installation constitutes a memory text in its own right, and suggests that writing is the actual trace that can bring the past to life and the means by which the daughter comes to terms with the mother figure. The Secret Staircase es el título de la exposición presentada por Caroline Isgar y Michèle Roberts en el Foundling Museum de Londres en 2008, y también el del libro que la ilustraba, una colección de los dibujos de Isgar y dieciocho narraciones breves, proyectados como souvenir de la exposición. Roberts cuenta los recuerdos de infancia de una hija junto a su madre con ocasión de la inminente muerte de ésta. Cada texto se inspira en un objeto que pertenece al pasado o a la experiencia de confinamiento en el hospital. La contribución de Roberts constituye en sí misma un texto de la memoria y sugiere que la escritura es la verdadera huella que devuelve el pasado a la vida y el medio por el cual la hija se reconcilia con la figura materna.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1564e123a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1564e130" publication-type="other">
This research is part of a larger project funded by the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness
(MINECO) entitled "Nuevos paramétras crfticos en torno al concepto de la huella y su aplicaciön a la literatura
reciente en lengua inglesa" (FFI2013-44154-P). The Secret Staircase was later exhibited at the Rook Lane Arts
Centre in Frome, Somerset, to commemorate International Women's Day in 2012.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1564e146a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1564e153" publication-type="other">
In her lecture "The Place of Imagination" (1994) Roberts confesses that her return to her figures of
mother and daughter is meant to evoke part of her childhood in France, a time which she recreates as paradise:
"They stand in, these images of lost bliss, as images of something even more specific than childhood: she who
is paradise itself for the baby, the growing child: the mother" ([1994] 1998, 20). For a thorough review of
this topic in Roberts's fiction, see Laura Lojo's recent article on the notion of the maternal body as paradise in
Robert's short story "Charity" (1994). She claims that this perspective is adopted by a narrator who positions
herself as a child, and whose vision is "dependant on language, memory and mythic reconstructions of her own
past" (Lojo 2012, 33).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1564e182a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1564e189" publication-type="other">
In her interpretation of Freudian psychology Madelon Sprengnether conceives the figure of the spectral
mother as the recurrent metaphor of the presence of the absent, prompted by memory. The mother's body
becomes in his view the locus of desire and endless return; its loss the necessary step for ego formation: "The
mother's body becomes that which is longed for yet cannot be appropriated, a representative of both home
and not home, and hence, in Freud's terms, the site of the uncanny. As both origin and Other, the preoedipal
mother escapes the equally devastating effects of idealization and erasure, allowing for the possibility of maternal
discourse as well as a non-phallocentrically organised view of culture" (Sprengnether 1990, 9).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1564e215a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1564e222" publication-type="other">
Early rhetoricians like the author of Ad Herenium considered this "artificial memory," or artificiosa, as the
basis of ars memoriae (Ricoeur 2004, 62).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1564e233a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1564e240" publication-type="other">
In From Beast to the Blonde, Marina Warner studies the status of fairy tales as historical documents which
give an account of women's daily experiences, as they illustrate their particular rites of passage and the relevance
of maternal figures in their lives. The resonance of Mother Goose is taken by Warner "either as a historical source,
or a fantasy of origin" which she can trace into ancient traditions, like the Islamic or the Christian, and which
adds credibility to the stories (1994, xxiii).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="d1564e268a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e272" publication-type="other">
Anderson, Linda. 1990. "The Re-Imagining of History in Contemporary Women's
Fiction." In Plotting Change. Contemporary Women's Fiction, edited by Linda Anderson,
129-41. London: Edward Arnold.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e285a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e289" publication-type="other">
Bachofen, J. J. 1967. Myth, Religion, and Mother Right. New York: Princeton UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e296a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e300" publication-type="other">
Caruth, Cathy. 1991. "Introduction." American Imago 48 (4): 417-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e307a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e311" publication-type="other">
—. 1996. Unclaimed Experience: Trauma, Narrative, and History. Baltimore: The Johns
Hopkins UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e322a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e326" publication-type="other">
Chodorow, Nancy. 1978. The Reproduction of Mothering: Psychoanalysis and the Sociology
of Gender. Berkeley: The U of California P.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e336a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e340" publication-type="other">
Collingwood, R.G. (1956) 1993. The Idea of History. Oxford: Oxford UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e347a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e351" publication-type="other">
Erll, Astrid. 2011. Memory in Culture. Basingstoke: Palgrave MacMillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e358a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e362" publication-type="other">
Felski, Rita. 1995. The Gender of Modernity. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e369a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e373" publication-type="other">
Fetterley, Judith. 1978. The Resisting Reader: A Feminist Approach to American Fiction.
Bloomington, IN: Indiana UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e383a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e387" publication-type="other">
Freud, Sigmund. 1930. Civilization and its Discontents. London: Hogarth Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e395a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e399" publication-type="other">
Frow, John. 1997. Time and Commodity Culture: Essays in Cultural Theory and
Postmodernity. Oxford: Oxford UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e413" publication-type="other">
Hirsch, Marianne. 1989. The Mother/Daughter Plot: Narrative, Psychoanalysis, Feminism.
Bloomington: Indiana UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e423a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e427" publication-type="other">
Hirsch, Marianne and Valerie Smith. 2007. "Feminism and Cultural Memory: An
Introduction." In Theories of Memory: A Reader, edited by Michael Rossington and
Anne Whitehead, 224-9. Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e440a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e444" publication-type="other">
Irigaray, Luce. 1993. Sexes and Genealogies. New York: Columbia UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e451a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e455" publication-type="other">
Isgar, Caroline and Michèle Roberts. 2008. The Secret Staircase. London: The Foundling
Museum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e465a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e469" publication-type="other">
Jacobus, Mary. 1987. "Freud's Mnemonic: Women, Screen Memories, and Feminist
Nostalgia." Michigan Quarterly Review 26 (1): 117-39.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e480a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e484" publication-type="other">
Krell, David Farrell. 1990. On Memory, Reminiscence, and Writing: On the Verge.
Bloomington: Indiana UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e494a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e498" publication-type="other">
Kristeva, Julia. 1980. "Motherhood According to Giovanni Bellini." In Desire in
Language: A Semiotic Approach to Literature and Art, edited by Leon S. Roudiez, 237-
70. New York: Columbia UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e511a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e515" publication-type="other">
Kuhn, Annette. 1995. Family Secrets: Acts of Memory and Imagination. London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e522a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e526" publication-type="other">
—. 2010. "Memory Texts and Memory Work: Performances of Memory in and with
Visual Media." Memory Studies 3 (4): 298-313.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e536a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e540" publication-type="other">
LOJO, Laura. 2012. "Recovering the Maternal Body as Paradise: Michèle Roberts's
'Charity'." Atlantis 34 (2): 33-47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e550a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e554" publication-type="other">
Lowenthal, David. 1985. The Past Is a Foreign Country. Cambridge: Cambridge
UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e565a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e569" publication-type="other">
Merleau-Ponty, Maurice. 1958. Phenomenology of Perception. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e576a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e580" publication-type="other">
Radstone, Susannah. 2007. The Sexual Politics of Time: Confession, Nostalgia, Memory.
London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e590a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e594" publication-type="other">
Rich, Addrienne. 1995. On Lies, Secrets and Silences. New York: WW. Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e601a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e605" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1982. Time and Narrative. Chicago: The U of Chicago P.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e612a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e616" publication-type="other">
—. 2004. Memory, History, Forgetting. Chicago: The U of Chicago P.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e623a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e627" publication-type="other">
RiTSON, Joseph. 1810. Gammer Gurton's Garland, or the Nursery Parnassus. London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e635a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e639" publication-type="other">
Roberts, Michèle. 1992. Daughters of the House. London: Virago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e646a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e650" publication-type="other">
—. 1997. Impossible Saints. London: Little Brown</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e657a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e661" publication-type="other">
—. (1994) 1998. "The Place of Imagination." In Food, Sex and God: On Inspiration and
Writing. London: Virago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e671a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e675" publication-type="other">
—. 2012. Ignorance. London: Bloomsbury.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e682a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e686" publication-type="other">
Samuel, Raphael. 2012. Theatres of Memory: Past and Present in Contemporary Culture.
London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e696a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e700" publication-type="other">
Sprengnether, Madelon. 1990. TheSpectralMother: Freud, Feminism, andPsychoanalysis.
Ithaca: Cornell UP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e711a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e715" publication-type="other">
Warner, Marina. 1994. From the Beast to the Blonde: On Fairy Tales and Their Tellers.
London: Vintage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1564e725a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1564e729" publication-type="other">
Woolf, Virginia. (1939) 2002. "A Sketch of the Past." Moments of Being: Autobiographical
Writings, 78-160. London: Pimlico.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
