<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">histantrfuenoral</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000658</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Historia, Antropología y Fuentes Orales</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Universitat de Barcelona, Publicacions; Diputación Provincial de Granada, Centro de Investigaciones Etnológicas Ángel Ganivet; Ajuntament de Barcelona, Arxiu Històric de la Ciutat</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">11361700</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">27753200</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Denuncia social</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Jóvenes y drogas: Neoliberalismo, exclusión social y olvido</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>María</given-names>
                  <surname>Epele</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>33</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i27753185</issue-id>
         <fpage>131</fpage>
         <lpage>150</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright Historia, Antropología y Fuentes Orales</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/27753200"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Oponiéndose a la perspectiva que reduce toda problemática vinculada a las drogas al orden del exceso y descontrol, este trabajo interroga la articulación entre ciertas consecuencias del capitalismo neoliberal en Argentina y la variación en las prácticas de consumo de drogas en conjuntos sociales vulnerables. Particularmente, examino el vínculo entre el sufrimiento social generado por la violencia cotidiana y el trauma crónico engendrado por la pobreza y la exclusión social y el consumo de cierta sustancia popularmente denominada "pasta". La producción del olvido, la fragmentación de la memoria y la disociación son los estados que los usuarios asocian y/o promueven con el uso de esta sustancia. De este modo, el argumento de este trabajo consiste en que mientras el uso de drogas se convierte en una de las pocas alternativas que los jóvenes disponen para aliviar el sufrimiento social asociado con la destitución social, esta condena al olvido limita el potencial para que los recuerdos y las experiencias se conviertan en materia prima para el trabajo de la memoria, la constitución de una capital emocional compartido e identidades sociales complejas. /// This work, opposing to the perspective that reduces all problems related with drugs to excess and lack of control, deals with the articulation between some consequences of neoliberal capitalism in Argentina and the variation in practices of drug taking in vulnerable social groups. It analizes especially the link between social suffering generated by day-to-day violence, chronical trauma engendered by poverty and social exclusion, and the taking of a substance popularly called "pasta". Production of forgetfulness, fragmentation of memory and dissociation are the conditions associated or promoted by consumers through the use of this substance. The point of this work is that while the use of drugs becomes one of the few alternatives young people have to aliviate social suffering associated with social destituteness, it condemns to forgetfulness the potential for memories and experiences to become prime material for the work of memory and the constitution of a shared emotional capital and complex social identities.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>Memoria</kwd>
            <kwd>neoliberalismo</kwd>
            <kwd>exclusión social</kwd>
            <kwd>olvido</kwd>
            <kwd>violencia</kwd>
            <kwd>drogas</kwd>
            <kwd>Buenos Aires</kwd>
            <kwd>Memory</kwd>
            <kwd>neoliberalism</kwd>
            <kwd>social exclusion</kwd>
            <kwd>oblivion</kwd>
            <kwd>violence</kwd>
            <kwd>drugs</kwd>
            <kwd>Buenos Aires</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>spa</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d6735e170a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e177" publication-type="other">
Esta investigaeión fue realizada gracias a la colaboración del Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones
Científicas y Técnicas (CONICET) Argentina, y a la Reentry Grant de la Fundación Antorchas.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e187a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e196" publication-type="other">
Véase Stimson, G., Des Jarlais, D. y Ball, A., Drug Injection and HIV Infection. Global Dimension and Local
Responses. Pensylavania, University London College Press, 1998. Bourgois, P., In search of respect. Selling
crack in El Barrio. New York, Cambridge University Press, 1995; y Bourgois, P., and Bruneau, J., "Needle
Exchange, HIV infection, and the Politics of Science: Confronting Canada's Cocaine Injection Epidemic with
Participant Observation", Medical Anthropology, 18, (2000), ps. 325–350.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e215a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e222" publication-type="other">
Beccaria, L. y López, N., Sin Trabajo. Las Características del Desempleo ysus Efectos en la Sociedad Argen-
tina. Buenos Aires, Losada, 1996.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e232a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e239" publication-type="other">
Epele, M., "Changing Cocaine Consuming Practices. Neoliberalism, HIV-AIDS and Death in an Argenti-
ne Shatytown", Substance Abuse &amp;amp; Misuse, 38 (9), (New York, 2003), ps. 1181–1207.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e250a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e257" publication-type="other">
Svampa, M. (ed.), Desde Abajo. La transformación de las identidades sociales. Buenos Aires, Biblos, 2000.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e264a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e271" publication-type="other">
Véase Herman, J., Trauma and Recovery. New York, BasicBooks, 1992. Farrell, K., Post-traumatic Cultu-
ra. Injury and Interpretation in the Nineties. Baltimore, The John Hopkins University Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e281a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e288" publication-type="other">
Windschuttle, K., "La caída del comunismo y el fin de la historia", Historia, Antropologia y Fuentes Ora-
les, 15 (Barcelona, 2001), ps. 17–45.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e298a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e305" publication-type="other">
Tafalla, M., Theodor W. Adorno. Una Filosofia de la Memoria. Barcelona, Herder, 2003.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e312a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e319" publication-type="other">
Tafalla, op. cit., p. 65.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e326a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e333" publication-type="other">
Tonglet, J., "¿Tienen Historia los Pobres?". En: ¿Por qué Recordar?, Barcelona, Granica, 2002, ps. 51–57.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e341a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e348" publication-type="other">
Bourdieu, P., The Globalization Myth and the Welfare State. Acts of Resistance. Against the Tyranny of the
Market. New York, The Mew and Polity Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e358a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e365" publication-type="other">
Farmer, P., "On Suffering and Structural Violence: A view from Below". En: Social Suffering. Klein-
man, A. , Das, V., y Lock, M.(eds). Berkeley, University of California Press, 1997, ps. 261–283. Kleinman,
A., "Violence, Culture and the Politics of Trauma". En: Writing and the Margin. Discourse Between Anthro-
pology and Medicine. Berkeley, University of California Press, 1995, ps. 173–189.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e381a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e388" publication-type="other">
Veáse Young, A., "Suffering and the Origin of Traumatic Memory". En: Social Suffering, Kleinman, A.,
Das, V., y Lock, M.(eds.). Berkeley, University of California Press, 1997, ps. 245–261 y The Harmony of Illu-
sions. Inventing Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder. Princeton, Princeton University Press, 1995.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e401a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e408" publication-type="other">
Por ejemplo véase Dansky, B., Brady, K., y Saladin, M., "Victimization and PTSD in Individuals with Subs-
tance Use Disorders: Gender and Pacial Differences", American Journal of Drug and Alcohol Abuse, 22–1 (Mew
York, 1996), ps 75–93; y Thompson Fullilove, M., Fullilove, R., Smith, M., Winkler, K., Micheal, C., Pan-
zer, P., &amp; Wallace, R. , "Violence, Trauma and Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Among Women Drug Use",
Journal of Traumatic Stress, 6–4 (1993), ps. 533–542.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e427a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e434" publication-type="other">
Baer, H., Singer, M., y Susser, 1., "lllicit Drugs: Self Medicating the Hidden Injuries of Opression". En:
Medical Anthropology and the World System. A Critical Perspective, Wesport, Bergin et Garvey, 1997, ps
125–158. Epele, M., "Violencia y Trauma. Politicas del Sufrimiento Social entre usuarias de drogas". Cua-
dernos de Antropologia Social, 14, (Buenos Aires, 2002), ps. 117–137.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e450a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e457" publication-type="other">
Rieoeur, P., "El olvido en el horizonte de la prescripción". En: ¿Por qué Recordar?, Barcelona, Granica,
2002, ps-73–80.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e468a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e475" publication-type="other">
Rapoport, M., Historia Económica, Politico y Social de la Argentina (1880–2000). Buenos Aires, Edicio-
nes Macchi, 2000.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e485a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e492" publication-type="other">
Basualdo, E., Acerca de la Naturaleza de la Deuda Externa y la definitión de una estrategia politico. Bue-
nos Aires, Universidad Nacional de Quilmes, 2000. Barbeito, A. y Lo Vuolo, R. La modernizatión excluyen-
te. Buenos Aires, Losada, 1992. Beccaria, L. y López, N., Sin Trabajo. Las caracteristicas del desempleo ysus
efectos en la sociedad argentina. Buenos Aires, Losada, 1996.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e508a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e515" publication-type="other">
INDEC (Instituto Nacional de Estadisticas y Censos de la República Argentina). Informe de Prensa Oe-
tubre 2002, Mayo 2004.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e525a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e532" publication-type="other">
Epele, M., 2003. Y Intereambios, Prevención del VIH-SIDA en Usuarios de Drogas. Resultados de un Pro-
yecto de Investigación e Intervención. Buenos Aires, Intereambios, 1999.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e542a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e549" publication-type="other">
Tiscornia, S., "Violencia Policial, Derechos Humanos y Peformas Policiales". Delito y Sociedad, 14 (Bue-
nos Aires, 2000), ps. 9–20. Y Méndez, J., "Problemas de Violencia llegal: Una Introducción". En: La(in)efec-
tividad de la ley y la exclusión en América Latina. Buenos Aires, Paidós, 2002, ps. 31–36.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e562a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e569" publication-type="other">
Duschatzky, S., y Corea, C., Chicos en Banda. Los Caminos de la Subjetividad en el declive de las institu-
ciones. Buenos Aires, Paidós, 2002.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e580a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e587" publication-type="other">
Sedronar, Primer Estudio Nacional sobre Uso de Drogas. Buenos Aires, Presidencia de la Nación de la
República Argentina, 1999.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6735e597a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6735e604" publication-type="other">
Connors, M., "Stories of Pain and the Problem of AIDS Prevention: Injecting Drug Withdrawal and its
Effect on Pisk Behavior". Medical Anthropology Quarterly, 8–1 (1994), ps. 47–68.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
