<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">transformation</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50010910</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Transformation</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Sage Publications, Ltd.</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">02653788</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">17598931</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">90008100</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Article</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>On Being Theologically Educated</article-title>
            <subtitle>Ten Key Characteristics</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Farr</surname>
                  <given-names>Bernard C.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Senior Residentiary Fellow at the Oxford Centre for Mission Studies, Oxford, UK</aff>
               <bio>
                  <p>Dr. Bernard C. Farr is Senior Residentiary Fellow at the Oxford Centre for Mission Studies, St Philip and St James Church, Oxford, UK.</p>
               </bio>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>October 2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">29</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e90008098</issue-id>
         <fpage>260</fpage>
         <lpage>276</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/90008100"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>Abstract</label>
            <p>Formal Christian theological training/education is unsurprisingly diverse. This diversity in theological training encompasses: providers and beneficieries from different denominations of modern Christianity, curricula and contents, and aims. If one supposes that theological training is imparted within or in direct/indirect relations with communities of faith (which likely possess different notions of theology and theological training/education) one is compelled to ask: What is ‘theological education’? Is this quest worth the effort?</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <label>Keywords</label>
            <kwd>community</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>context</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>education</kwd>
            <x>,</x>
            <kwd>theological</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <fn id="fn1">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>This question, it must be noted, implies a prior question: ‘What kind(s) of person should be a theologically educated person(s)?’ I am assuming that the answer to this question is that all kinds of persons should as a base threshold be theologically educated to the degree that is fit for the purpose of their being as fully as possible mature in their faith.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn2">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>For more on ‘thrownness’ see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inwood M (1999) Thrownness and Facticity, http://www.blackwellreference.com/public/tocnode?id=g9780631190950_chunk_g978063119095021_ss1-6 (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn3">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williams R (2004) CEFACS Lecture, Birmingham, http://www.archbishopofcanterbury.org/articles.php/1847/cefacs-lecture-birmingham-centre-for-anglican-communion-studies (accessed 18 February 2010)</mixed-citation>. Williams’ lecture should be read as a complement to this paper as it expands on topics I can thus leave aside.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn4">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>The pietists took this too far. In educational terms it is interesting to look at Rousseau and Pestalozzi as they thought through how educational theory may be re-worked with such considerations in view, though of course they each went their own distinctive way when proposing answers (on this, see:<mixed-citation publication-type="other">http://www.heinrich-pestalozzi.de/en/documentation/fundamental-ideas/religion/</mixed-citation>). For the epistemological role of personal knowledge see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Polanyi M (1958) Personal Knowledge: Towards a Post-Critical Philosophy. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn5">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>The quote ‘Education is not filling a bucket, but lighting a fire’. See for more on the source of this quote,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">‘Education Is Not Filling a Bucket, but Lighting a Fire’, i202 Fall 2009, http://courses.ischool.berkeley.edu/i202/f09/blog/education-not-filling-a-bucket-lighting-a-fire (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn6">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>It is worth attending to everything that Simone Weil says on the topic of ‘attention’. See, for example,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cameron S (2003) The Practice of Attention: Simone Weil’s Performance of Impersonality, Critical Inquiry 29(2), 216–252, Winter, http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/374026 (accessed 18 February 2010)</mixed-citation>;<mixed-citation publication-type="other">von der Ruhr M (2007) Simone Weil – An Apprenticeship in Attention. London: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn7">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Just in Time (JIT) is the Japanese quality practice of kaizen. See SPAEF (2008) A Review of the Adoption of Just in Time Method and Its Effect on Efficiency, http://www.spaef.com/article.php?id=118 (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn8">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>On his years at Oxford, see his autobiography,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Blue L (2004) Hitchhiking to Heaven: An Autobiography. London: Hodder and Stoughton.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn9">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">for an example, Berkouwer GC (1965) Studies in Dogmatics: The Work of Christ. Kampen: J.H. Kok N.V.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn10">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">works cited in Note 6. Cameron’s article also appears in her 2007 book Impersonality: Seven Essays, Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press, which can be accessed at http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=-ZKlEpU9C4AC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;lpg=PA108&amp;dq=The+Practice+of+Attention:+Simone+Weil+Performance+of+Impersonality&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=88obWpacGE&amp;sig=yAoAJeWnwDs7wN4Vkhb47sgClHg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=emYvUPeUAonB0QWSlYDgDA&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Practice%20of%20Attention%3A%20Simone%20Weil%20Performance%20of%20Impersonality&amp;f=fa</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn11">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>A comment usually attributed to William Temple, former Archbishop of Canterbury who is reported a saying over and over, ‘Christianity is the most materialistic religion … ’</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn12">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>On ‘facticity’, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inwood M (1999) Thrownness and Facticity, http://www.blackwellreference.com/public/tocnode?id=g9780631190950_chunk_g978063119095021_ss1-6 (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn13">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>David Jenkins persistently recommended that in reading the Bible the reader has always to ask ‘How did people think then which led them to put it like that?’ He provided the following as an example. The writers of the gospels lived at a time when demon possession was the available conceptuality if a person fell to the ground writhing and foaming at the mouth. In the Middle Ages, the conceptuality within which explanation arose was that of the humours of the body and the cure would have been blood-letting. In medicalized 21st century conceptuality, it would be said that the person was having an epileptic fit and the needed response is to keep calm and re-assure.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn14">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>There is a case, however, for seeing research as necessarily being involved in its first stage in ‘strangemaking’. It is only by making the commonplace first of all ‘strange’ that one can attain the critical distance required for research to proceed. Ethnomethodology makes this its primary mode of practice. Garfinkel, its originator, analysed in detail the methods used by people in everyday life to account for (make sense of) their activities for themselves and for others. He thus saw ethnomethodology as the study of commonsense knowledge of social structures so as to make sociological reasoning analysable. Ethnomethodology was the subject of fierce debate within sociology departments. Some of its insights have been taken into mainstream sociological theory, particularly through the work of Anthony Giddens.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn15">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>See the classic study,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barnes DR, Britton JN and Torbe M (1989) Language, the Learner, and the School. Portsmouth, NH: Boynton/Cook</mixed-citation>. It argues that stress on ‘proper English’ can inhibit non-middle-class children from expressing themselves in the kind of language they use at home, while ‘learning’ for all too many students means guessing what answers the teacher expects – in ‘school language’ of course. The final section makes important recommendations on the major issue of language across the curriculum – what sort of language is really appropriate in multicultural schools? A charismatic evangelical teacher-training student I supervised some years ago was convinced that modern teenagers can understand Christian doctrine if only the teacher can find the right teaching methods including exciting visual aids. He admitted failure having tried.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn16">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">R. C. Miller RC (2010) The Language Gap and God: Religious Language and Christian Education. Philadelphia, PA &amp; Boston, MA: Pilgrim Press, http://www.religion-online.org/showbook.asp?title=2300 (accessed 18 February 2010)</mixed-citation>. Chapter 5, ‘Discernment and Commitment’ is based on IT Ramsey who argued that religious language is grounded in personal experience and personal disclosure. This understanding of religious language is experientially grounded in that when we communicate with each other personal disclosure occurs. Ramsey argued that we come to encounter God it is also by way of personal disclosure. Ramsey’s theological work thus continues the traditional theological view that all religious language is analogical, and the religious vocabulary that we create always involves the language of analogy.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn17">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matthew 13:52</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn18">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">‘Playing before God: Theology and Play in Dialogue’, http://forum.llc.ed.ac.uk/si2/gabelman.pdf (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn19">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">the review of Hays E (2009) Holy Fools &amp; Mad Hatters: A Handbook for Hobbyhorse Holiness. Notre Dame, IN: Forest of Peace Books, by Brussat F &amp; Brussat MA, at http://www.spiritualityandpractice.com/books/books.php?id=7089</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn20">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>This is partly an allusion to Wittgenstein on language games but I am emphasising the sense of play to add to what he says of games, life and travel. On language games, see more in<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-religion/ (accessed 18 February 2010)</mixed-citation>: Some properties of language-games can be noticed in Wittgenstein’s several examples and comments. They are, first, a part of a broader context termed by Wittgenstein a form of life (see below). Secondly, the concept of language-games points at the rule-governed character of language. This does not entail strict and definite systems of rules for each and every language-game, but points to the conventional nature of this sort of human activity. Finally, Wittgenstein’s choice of ‘game’ is based on the over-all analogy between language and game, assuming that we have a clearer perception of what games are. Still, just as we cannot give a final, essential definition of ‘game’, so we cannot find ‘what is common to all these activities and what makes them into language or parts of language.’</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn21">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tracy D (1975) Theology as Public Discourse. The Christian Century 92(10), 287–287.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn22">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brueggemann W (1978) The Prophetic Imagination. Philadelphia, PA: Fortress Press, 13.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn23">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Little M, Jordens CFC and Sayers E-J (2003) Discourse Communities and the Discourse of Experience, Health 7(1), 73–86.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn24">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zizioulas JD (1985) Being as Communion. New York, NY: St. Vladimir’s Seminary Press.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn25">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zizioulas JD (2007) Communion and Otherness: Further Studies in Personhood and the Church. Edinburgh, UK: T. &amp; T. Clark Publishers.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn26">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>I have been sent for review a book on queer Christology (Christology beyond the orthodox margins). It is interesting to note reactions when I have left the book on the table to see whether people comment. Perhaps the most common reaction is that such a book should not even be in my reading list – such is the fear of the margin and beyond. The study of belief revision (expansion, revision, contraction) has become a branch of philosophy. See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gardenfors P (1992) Belief Revision. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn27">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cootsona GS (2007) The Telos of Beauty: A Common Quest for Theologians and Scientists, The Global Spiral, an e-publication of Metanexus Institute, http://www.metanexus.net/Magazine/tabid/68/id/10032/Default.aspx (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn28">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Magister S (2008) Pope: The Proof of God Is Beauty, http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=30760 (accessed 18 February 2010).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn29">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>This is of course a term associated with Paul Ricoeur. I share much of what he is aiming for but I use the term here independently of his use. See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kearney R (Ed.) (1996) Paul Ricoeur: The Hermeneutics of Action. London: Sage.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn30">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>I am indebted for this distinction to colleagues at St Paul’s Limuru, Kenya, who offer an MA in Community Care and HIV/AIDS which delivers actual care and training of carers as an intrinsic part of the qualification. The terms were used by a visiting party from Cote d’Ivoire who were comparing their own theology curriculum with that of the SPL MA which is premised on theology being expressive response to the world as it is held before God. OCMS led the design of this MA.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn31">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>‘The action turn’ stands over against ‘the linguistic turn’ that was a development in Western philosophy during the 20th century. Its most important characteristic is its focus on philosophy and language. Ludwig Wittgenstein’s influence is strong as the term follows from his claim that philosophical problems arise from a misunderstanding of the logic of language and his later comments on language games. See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reason P &amp; Torbert WR (2001) The Action Turn: Toward a Transformational Social Science: a further look at the scientific merits of action research. Concepts and Transformations 6(1), 1–37 (available at http://www.peterreason.eu/Papers/Transformational_Social_Science.pdf)</mixed-citation>. See also<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rorty RM (Ed.) (1992) The Linguistic Turn: Essays in Philosophical Method. Chicago, IL: The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn32">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baker GP &amp; Hacker PMS (2005) Wittgenstein: Understanding and Meaning (2nd ed.). Oxford, UK: Blackwell Publishing.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
