<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">modernphilology</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="ucp-id">mp</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Modern Philology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00268232</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15456951</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/662147</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MP80148</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Why Devils Came When Faustus Called Them</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Genevieve</given-names>
                  <x/>
                  <surname>Guenther</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">New York</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2011</year>
            <string-date>August 2011</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">109</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">660269</issue-id>
         <fpage>46</fpage>
         <lpage>70</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2011 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/662147"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <verse-group>
         <verse-line>Certainly, even at this time I do most plainly see</verse-line>
         <verse-line>The devils to be about me round, which make great preparation,</verse-line>
         <verse-line>And keep a stir here in this place which only is for me.</verse-line>
         <verse-line>Neither do I conceive these things by vain imagination,</verse-line>
         <verse-line>But even as truly as mine eyes behold your shape and fashion.</verse-line>
         <attrib>(N<sc>athaniel</sc>W<sc>oodes</sc>,<italic>The Conflict of Conscience</italic>[1581])</attrib>
      </verse-group>
      <p>In his 1632<italic>Histriomastix</italic>, a key text of early modern antitheatricality, the Puritan lawyer William Prynne reported that a devil had once appeared “on the stage at the Belsavage Play-house, in Queen Elizabeth's dayes (to the great amazement of both the actors and spectators) while they were there prophanely playing the History of Faustus (the truth of which I have heard from many now alive, who well remember it) there being some there distracted with that fearful sight.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">1</xref>Prynne repeated this story about Christopher Marlowe's<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>(1594) to argue that stage plays were inherently evil, but these rumors about extra devils circulated even among more neutral commentators. For instance, in a note written on the last page of a sixteenth-century monograph, one G. J. R. recorded the experience of “certain players at Exeter, acting upon the stage the tragical story of Dr. Faustus the conjurer”:<disp-quote>
            <p>As a certain number of devils kept every one his circle there, and as Faustus was busy in his magical invocations, on a sudden they were all dashed, every one harkening the other in the ear, for they were all persuaded, there was one devil too many amongst them; and so after a little pause desired the people to pardon them, they could go no further with this matter; the people also understanding the thing as it was, every man hastened to be first out of doors. The players (as I heard it) contrary to their custom spending the night in reading and in prayer got them out of the town the next morning.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">2</xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
      </p>
      <p>When we take these rumors seriously, what do they tell us? Critics of Renaissance drama have tended to assimilate these strange tales into what we know to be scandalous about Marlowe: his deliberate provocations, his political equivocations, his uncanny ability, as Leah Marcus puts it, to produce plays “hovering on the razor's edge of exaltation and transgression.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">3</xref>But what finally accounts for audiences believing that Marlowe's drama conjured an actual devil in particular? This is not a question about why early moderns believed in magic. Rather this is a question about why they believed that the dramatic representation of magic had the power to make a spirit appear.</p>
      <p>The answer to this question lies partly in the doctrinal and aesthetic assumptions that audiences in the early 1590s brought with them to Marlowe's theater.<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>was first performed in the wake of a fundamental shift in the way that magic was characterized and taught in English Protestant theology. In the late 1580s and early 1590s, just before<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>premiered, popular Protestant devotional writers such as George Gifford and William Perkins attacked the traditional understanding of conjuration as a tool wielded by the magician himself, who had been imagined to command devils by iterating a version of the performative formula “in the name of the divine, I conjure you no more to resist, but to appear and be obedient.” These Protestant preachers brought remarkably corrosive skepticism to bear on the essentialist linguistic assumptions underlying the belief that devils could be conjured with performative language while simultaneously maintaining or even buttressing theological justifications for the idea that devils, and Satan in particular, intervened in people's lives via the instrumentality of the magician. What the reformers argued is that magical language has no intrinsic spiritual efficacy—that it cannot control the devil or any other supernatural being—yet in so arguing they did not go on to dismiss conjuration as a superstitious fiction. Rather, they placed magic within a providential eschatology, recasting it as an expression of God-permitted diabolical agency. Devils appeared to magicians, the reformers argued, because Satan himself staged conjurations as theatrical spectacles, which he used instrumentally to ensnare people into damnation. In this account of magic, the formula of conjuration functioned as a script that cued devils to appear and behave as if they had been commanded, and this theatrical, but not ontologically performative, spectacle of human power over devils not only compounded the reprobation of the magician himself but also, the reformers warned, produced aesthetic responses in witnesses to the conjuration that would anger God and lead him to withdraw his salvific grace.</p>
      <p>Marlowe seems to have realized that this revisionary account of magic, which produced theological meaning from audiences' interest in spectacles of conjuration, had powerful dramatic potential—and that it had circulated widely enough in the cultural imaginary to be recognized on the popular stage—for in<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>he represented the mechanism of conjuration in precisely the reformers' terms.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN4">4</xref>Marlowe's Faustus is a man so invested in the idea that spiritual efficacy inheres in the material, in bodies and texts, that he believes there is “virtue” in the “heavenly words” that seem to conjure Mephistopheles forth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN5">5</xref>Mephistopheles, however, tells Faustus explicitly that his magical words worked only “<italic>per accidens</italic>” (1.3.47) and that in truth he appeared only in the hope that he could “get” Faustus's “glorious soul” (1.3.50). Yet Faustus persists, his misgivings about magic repeatedly overcome by Mephistopheles' ability to stage magical pageants and dumbshows populated by apparently embodied spirits. These spectacles suggest to Faustus that in hell the individuated personhood delineated by the body's boundaries will last in a spiritual form that the magician may inhabit and control. But it goes without saying that this ocular proof of embodied immortality is only theatrical spectacle, in all its ontological insufficiency. Yet at some performances of<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>in the last decade of the sixteenth century, this fact—that the instrument of Faustus's damnation is the very spectacle represented on stage—seemed to produce a mirror effect in spectators who feared that their own interest in Faustus's magic was theologically dangerous. The metatheatrical doubling solicited their terrifying identification with Faustus, whereby their absorption in the events on stage served as evidence of their own reprobation. At times this evidence seems to have been overwhelming enough to cause collective hysteria, as if whole groups of people involved in productions of Faustus, like the despairing sinner in<italic>The Conflict of Conscience</italic>, felt suddenly convinced that devils had flown to the scene, having panicked that God had judged them irredeemable for their investment in the play. In<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>, then, Protestant anxiety about salvation and popular desire for entertainment converged to produce historically contingent aesthetic effects. Marlowe's brilliant strategy for Faustus was to exploit the reformist understanding of magic as at once theatrical spectacle and theological instrument in order to produce an aesthetic instrumentality in which onstage performativity—the staging of conjuration—generated effects that offstage performativity quite obviously could not.</p>
      <p>* * *</p>
      <p>The Protestant attack on the idea of intrinsically magical language was an inflection of the broadly confessional attack on sacramentality. Arguments connecting the formula for conjuration to the Catholic Eucharist began to emerge in Germany and Denmark in the 1560s and ’70s, and these arguments were imported into England by a distinctly heterogeneous group of devotional writers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN6">6</xref>Gifford and Perkins are often reductively characterized as Puritans, perhaps for their early interest in Presbyterianism, although in fact they both embraced the Elizabethan settlement before they published their major tracts on magic.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN7">7</xref>Other writers who rehearsed the continental account of conjuration had little association with nonconformity: Henry Holland, for instance, was settled in his London living by the establishment dean of Westminster, and Robert Burton, the author of<italic>The Anatomy of Melancholy</italic>(1621), used the opportunity of his Oxford fellowship to ignore theological controversy almost entirely. James I (then James VI of Scotland) repeated verbatim the new Protestant arguments about magic in his 1597<italic>Daemonologie</italic>, as did the seventeenth-century physician John Cotta in<italic>The Triall of Witchcraft</italic>(1616).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN8">8</xref>The new reformed discourse of magic was, then, generated in pastoral, academic, royal, commercial, and theatrical spaces to various and divergent ends. Historians of the English reformation have generally seen the emergence of a reformist theory of magical language as linked to pastoral attempts to discredit “cunning” men and women as medical authorities and to reinterpret witchcraft as a form of spiritual affliction.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN9">9</xref>But this model of the pastorate attacking popular practices from above, as it were, in order to consolidate its own spiritual authority against the traditions of the laity tends not to provide for the breadth of perspectives and interests that generated and disseminated the new account of the spiritual instrumentality of representation.</p>
      <p>It may at first seem as if the reformers did not allow for the theological instrumentality of signs at all, for their primary argument is that human representation has no performative efficacy in the spiritual realm. The supposedly sacred signs of conjuration—the figures and characters carved into the protective circle, the gestures enacted to awe demons, and the words pronounced in the conjuration itself—are all, the reformers argue, simply “natural” or material things; as such, they cannot force supernatural creatures to obey human will. Thus Gifford wonders how the magician could be “so foolish as to imagine” that spiritual beings are “affected by the virtue of words, gestures, figures, or such like.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN10">10</xref>“All words made and uttered by men,” Perkins elaborates, “are in their own nature but sounds framed by the tongue, of the breath that comes from the lungs; and that which is only a bare sound, in all reason can have no virtue in it to cause a real work, much less to produce a wonder.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN11">11</xref>Even the text of scripture itself has no essential efficacy: “The truth is,” Holland ruefully explains, that Satan “nothing regards the outward letter of the Word [any] more than [magicians'] characters, signs, crosses, figures, &amp;c.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN12">12</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Yet, although they maintain that the letter of the Word lacks the performative power to conjure devils, the reformers nonetheless argue that biblical texts, as well as signs made sacred by scriptural authorization, do have spiritual efficacy when deployed properly by preachers. Under the right conditions, such signs can produce or strengthen faith and prepare the believer to receive God's grace, which otherwise might run off, as it were, like rainwater on rocky ground. For the reformers, the Eucharist exemplifies the spiritual instrumentality of the letter. “Though it be a thing above [its] common and natural use,” Perkins explains, eucharistic bread, as an efficacious sign, has “the power and property…to seal and signify unto every believing receiver the body of Christ, [for] thereupon we have warrant from Christ's own commandment, ordinance, and example to use it” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, 137–38). Such a spiritual impression is not produced automatically, however, but according to the inward attitude and intent of those who participate in the ritual (not<italic>ex opere operato</italic>, that is, but<italic>ex opere operantis</italic>). Perkins elaborates: “There is not any such force or efficacy of making us holy inherent or tied unto the external figures”; rather, all such efficacy is “an inseparable companion of true faith and repentance, and of such as turn unto the Lord.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN13">13</xref>For Perkins, those who “turn unto the Lord” do so by using the Eucharist as a figure for interpretation, or an instrument of intellectual meditation that increases repentance and faith. The meditation on the spiritual significance of the sacrament is a special means of eschewing the materiality of the letter and dedicating the inward self to God, a dedication that in turn, the reformers argue, readies the believer to feel and know God's saving mercy.</p>
      <p>In these instrumentalist eucharistic hermeneutics, then, letter and spirit are not exactly equivalent to vehicle and tenor: the letter does not just signify the spirit in a purely referential sense; rather, if used with the proper intention, the letter enables the spirit to enter the soul as a sacred gift to the believer. Thus in his commentary on Corinthians Calvin argues, “These words, L<sc>etter</sc>and S<sc>pirit</sc>, pertain nothing to exposition [i.e., typological allegory], but to force and fruit.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN14">14</xref>Unlike the signs of magic, which supposedly produce the outward embodiment of spirits, the Eucharist functions asa vehicle for an idea that works regeneratively in the inward person, if it is interpreted, or used, with a felicitous spiritual intention. This theory of efficacious allegorical hermeneutics, while sustaining an Aristotelian conception of instrumentality, radically devalues the materiality of the sign, giving it only contingent force. And it is this commitment to material contingency that motivates the reformers' identification of conjurers with Catholic priests who attempt to make God present in bread by pronouncing what Reginald Scot calls Latin “babbles.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN15">15</xref>Indeed, the prestidigitator's phrase “hocus pocus” is based on “<italic>hoc est enim corpus meum</italic>,” finding its genealogical root in the Catholic Mass or, more precisely, in the Protestant argument that Catholic priests do the work of the devil in claiming that their articulations have the performative efficacy to invoke the presence of God.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN16">16</xref>
      </p>
      <p>Yet despite their critique of the Catholic Eucharist as a sacrilegious and inefficacious conjuration, the reformers hold that the devil does, in fact, come when the magician calls him. The premise that devils are being conjured all the time is so fundamental to their polemic that it is never debated or even really discussed. With their commitment to providentialism, they assume that a personified Satan must be using people's desires for magical efficacy as a weapon of spiritual attack. But even if we accept this premise for the sake of argument, the question still arises: how does the magician's language manage to conjure the devil when it lacks power? Although its essence is merely material, Perkins answers, conjuration nonetheless has “another nature in regard of its immediate relation to the devil, to whom it is a sign” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, 132). In its second nature, conjuration works not by essential performativity but<italic>per accidens</italic>(1.3.47). It functions to manifest not the magician's power to command spirits with language but his inward alienation from the spirit of God. As Perkins insists, although “signs, characters, and figures [are] no whit effectual in themselves,” they do “serve for watchwords unto Satan,” revealing that “the user thereof hath his heart secretly indented…for the accomplishment of [Satan's] intended works” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, 53–54). Perkins's rhetoric here is of spiritual warfare: “watchword” is a military term denoting a preconcerted signal to begin an assault. But in this case the devil attacks not with violence but with the apparent satisfaction of desire. As soon as he apprehends his watchwords, he appears and, as Gifford puts it, “doth…feign himself to be bound.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN17">17</xref>In other words, Satan attacks the soul of the magician by behaving as if he had been conjured by the magician's language. “In all conjurations,” Perkins goes on to say, “when [Satan] is raised by the Sorcerer, he is willing to be adjured by all the holy names of God that are in the Scripture, to the end that he may more deeply seduce his own instruments, and make them to think that…names will bind him &amp; force him to yield unto their desires in the particular, when indeed there is no such matter” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, 151). (As Burton iterates it, “There is [no] power at all in those spells, charms, characters, and barbarous words, but that the Devil doth use such means to delude them,<italic>ut fideles inde magos</italic>[so that he might keep those magi faithful to him].)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN18">18</xref>To believe that “names will bind” the devil and force him to yield to desire is, in these writers' accounts, to believe that human beings may rise above their fundamentally wretched place in the cosmos, that they may escape their irreducible dependence on God's grace for any satisfaction that would transcend mortality. And to fail to see God as at once the source and the limit of all transcendent satisfaction is to fail to see the need for faith.</p>
      <p>Now if Satan's goal is to ruin the magician's faith, his further goal, according to these preachers, is to use the magician as what Perkins calls “his own instrument” to undermine the faith of others beside the magician himself. “As Satan used the serpent in the beginning to seduce our first parents from the obedience of God's word,” Holland argues, “so is it not to be doubted that after the fall he uses man himself as his instrument by magical arts to withdraw men from faith in the promise of their redemption by Christ.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN19">19</xref>Satan performs this feat, the reformers warn, by staging his false conjuration as a theater piece that has the instrumental end of producing aesthetic responses in spectators that incline them toward false belief. “The power of this Prince of darkness…manifests itself herein,” Perkins insists, “by works of wonder, transcendent in regard of ordinary capacity, and diversely dispensed by his chosen instruments of both sexes… sometime by Enchantment, sometime by rare sleights and delusions… and all to purchase himself the admiration, fear, and faith of the credulous world, which is usually carried away, with affectation and applause of signs and wonders” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, “Epistle Dedicatory,” 2v). If “wonder” here is ontological, engendered by a frightening yet awe-inspiring encounter with a supernatural being, it is also theatrical, produced by the aesthetic “enchantment” and the spectacular “rare sleights and delusions” that generate precisely the “admiration” and “fear” that sixteenth-century literary theory defines as the dual effect of the most elevated dramatic modes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN20">20</xref>And this wonder in turn inspires the “affectation”—that is, the affection or delight—that leads spectators to offer “applause.” Such applause expresses, for the reformers, “faith” in magical power, the very antithesis of the justification that leads to salvation. The reformers thus imagine that the devil may use theater to produce an aesthetic delight that in turn will help damn his victims. Indeed, the reformers never posit anything approaching a modern model of theatrical experience, in which staged illusions, institutionally marked out as such, are cultivated and consumed as ends in themselves; rather, they imagine that forms of theatrical cognition and pleasure undermine the habits of mind that sustain faith and thus are by definition instruments producing disastrous theological effects. The reformers thus warn their readers to avoid participating in spectacles of magic at all costs or, at least, to monitor their responses to such spectacles very carefully and root out the sources of any pleasure they might feel with intensive self-examination and repentance, lest their enjoyment corrupt their faith or undermine their certainty of their own salvation.</p>
      <p>In the reformers' accounts, then, faith itself is performative since it has no objective ontological status outside of the acts of consuming representations that either produce or obscure it. The performativity of faith even has a constant witness: God himself, who surveils the subject's invisible performances very closely. For it turns out, in these arguments, that God monitors people's aesthetic responses to theatrical representations as well as their thoughts about their responses. These feelings and thoughts at once manifest and transform the quality of one's faith, judged by God when he decides to save or damn the soul. Indeed, it is God who allows Satan to use the magician instrumentally; or, more specifically, it is God who uses Satan instrumentally, as he did in the book of Job, to test the faith of his professed believers, and confirm the declining fortunes of nonbelievers, by indirectly producing and directly scrutinizing human beings' inward responses to diabolical spectacle and drama.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN21">21</xref>Holland explicitly argues that God uses Satan's magic so that he may both “fatherly forewarn his Saints to pass their dwelling here [on earth] with all diligence, to avoid the contagion of the wicked with whom they have any conversation,” and “in justice punish them who would not receive his truth,” sending these reprobates “strong delusions that they may believe lies.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN22">22</xref>For Holland, God's active, providential intervention into the world via Satan's theater of magic is, in a strange way, a blessing that allows the faithful to recognize their own sins and infirmities, giving them the opportunity to repent. In his view, even the magician himself can repent and be saved.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN23">23</xref>For Perkins, by contrast, God's use of Satan as his instrument is less an opportunity for the faithful than an interrogation of the individual subject, whose response to the magician's strong delusions reveals the predestined fate of his immortal soul. Glorified by his own power above all, Perkins's God uses Satan's magic “to avenge himself on Man for his ingratitude” and “to try and prove his people, whether they will cleave to him and his Word, or seek unto Satan and his wicked Spirits” (<italic>Discourse of the Damned</italic>, “Epistle Dedicatory,” 5r–v).</p>
      <p>* * *</p>
      <p>When in his opening soliloquy Faustus resolves to learn the secrets of magic, he articulates a phrase that echoes those used by the reformers to describe the signs that serve as “watchwords” for Satan: “lines, circles, schemes, letters and characters!” Faustus cries, “ay, these are those that Faustus most desires” (1.1.53–54). With this phrase, Faustus signals to the audience that he is the conjurer their ministers warned them about, the magician who most desires to possess the signs of magic for their purported spiritual power “to gain a deity” (1.1.65). And at first such signs do seem to have spiritual force, for Faustus does manage to conjure up the devil's emissary in Mephistopheles. When the spirit responds obediently to his commands, Faustus, delighted, exclaims: “I see there's virtue in my heavenly words!” (1.3.28). But Mephistopheles goes on to explain that he appeared not because Faustus's conjuration enforced him to rise but because he recognized the watchwords that indicate that the enchanter has a relation in his mind to the devil. When Faustus demands to know whether his “conjuring speeches” (1.3.46) in fact raised him, Mephistopheles replies (in lines that we have already partly quoted):<verse-group>
            <verse-line>That was the cause, but yet<italic>per accidens</italic>
            </verse-line>
            <verse-line>For when we hear one rack the name of God,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Abjure the Scriptures, and his savior Christ,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>We fly in hope to get his glorious soul,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Nor will we come, unless he use such means</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Whereby he is in danger to be damned:</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Therefore the shortest cut for conjuring</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Is stoutly to abjure the Trinity,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>And pray devoutly to the prince of hell.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(1.3.47–55)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
      </p>
      <p>Dismissing the notion that magical signs have essential spiritual efficacy, Mephistopheles explains that magical language works performatively in the spiritual realm only by its accidental as opposed to essential qualities, or by its second nature regarding its relation to the devil. It was not any force in the literal instruments of conjuration—the lines, circles, characters, letters, or the utterance of the invocation—that induced him to appear. Rather, it was the mere fact that Faustus took to conjuring at all that raised the “hope” in Mephistopheles that the devil might “get his glorious soul,” and only in this hope did the spirit “fly” to the scene.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN24">24</xref>Hence, as Mephistopheles goes on to explain, magic is not even the most effective instrument with which to invoke the devil's presence, for it is not the most direct “means” whereby the magician “is in danger to be damned.” To conjure the devil, one need just “stoutly…abjure the Trinity, / And pray devoutly to the prince of hell.” As if disdaining the idea that he neglected to use any tool of magical efficacy, Faustus assures Mephistopheles that he has already taken this shortest of shortcuts: “So Faustus hath already done, and holds this principle: / There is no chief [<italic>sic</italic>] but only Beelzebub, / To whom Faustus doth dedicate himself” (1.3.56–58). With this reply, Faustus both performs and confirms what the reformers would call his inward relation to Satan.</p>
      <p>But why, then, does Faustus have this relation in his mind to the devil? As the reformers argued about the magician, Faustus inclines to the devil because he rejects faith, which is to say that he refuses to believe that God promises him immortal happiness. Indeed, critics have long since noticed that Faustus has complete aphasia on the subject of mercy—in his first soliloquy, of course, he omits the lines of 1 John that promise forgiveness to those who repent, rather perversely proclaiming instead that the Bible insists “we must sin, / And so consequently die…an everlasting death” (1.1.46–48).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN25">25</xref>But Faustus erases the promise of God's mercy because he disdains the dualistic Christian metaphysics that underlie that very promise. Christian dualism is taken for granted in the play even by Mephistopheles, who makes a clear distinction between body and soul, radically subordinating the value of the former to the latter. When Faustus orders him to attack the old man, the devil replies: “his faith is great / I cannot touch his soul. / But what I may afflict his body with / I will attempt, which is but little worth” (5.1.79–82). In contrast to his conjured companion, Faustus values the body more than the soul, as if for him the truly sacred communion were found not in the valence of symbolic bread but in the juicy and perfumed grapes he gives to the hugely pregnant duchess, who has been longing for fruit through the dearth of winter.</p>
      <p>Faustus's investment in embodiment is less social, though, than epistemological: he implicitly denies the assumption that signification should dematerialize consciousness, and that “real” meaning should be fundamentally allegorical. Indeed, Faustus eschews allegorical interpretation. He never reads past the letter, as it were, to search for spirit; he never seeks what recedes beyond the textual mark as if it were the invisible, impalpable, transcendent truth. To read in that way is to perform faith. The old man, for instance, describes faith as the first step on an unfolding journey to salvation, calling it “the way of life / By which sweet path thou may'st attain the goal / That shall conduct thee to celestial rest” (5.1.37–39). The striking catachresis of the “goal” that becomes the boatman or the angel that will “conduct” the believer to “celestial rest”—not to mention the pun that makes “way of life” at once a method and a path with duration—emphasizes the strange requirement that faith places on the believer to seek in thought what is not only absent but also deferred beyond any end that he can conceive for himself. Faustus refuses this injunction to read the Word and the world allegorically, to perform faith by consuming representation like a Protestant.</p>
      <p>Faustus enters into the play with his antiallegorical habit of mind firmly in place. In his opening soliloquy, he not only ignores the scriptural promise of salvation but also never acknowledges that every profession he considers and abandons resounds as a figure for salvation. In his refusal to read allegorically, Faustus articulates but does not hear that the study of each art stands as a metonym for a larger spiritual quest to come to God; he makes visible but does not see the eschatological trajectory in which the ends of earthly things are themselves means to move the soul toward an invisible, deferred ending in heaven.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN26">26</xref>Thus Faustus begins with Aristotle, asking whether “to dispute well” is “logic's chiefest end” (1.1.8). When he concludes that it is, and that this “art” affords “no greater miracle” (1.1.9), he decides to abandon its study since he has already “attained the end” (1.1.10). This seems fair enough, since merely to dispute may well indeed seem a rather limited goal, yet in the very next line, as Faustus actually renounces the art, he bids “<italic>on kai me on</italic>, farewell” (1.1.12), and the significance of what he is abandoning changes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN27">27</xref>Faustus is abandoning not just the form of disputation but the opportunity to study being and nonbeing, existence itself; yet Faustus seems to think he understands the mysteries of ontology since he has mastered the external form of the art that is the vehicle for its study. In the same manner, Faustus renounces the law with an almost Pauline critique, calling it a form of “external trash” (1.1.35), yet, from the perspective of faith, even the Justinian rule “if one and the same thing is bequeathed to two persons, one should have the thing itself, the other the value of the thing”—which Faustus dismisses as a case of “paltry legacies” (1.1.30)—may be seen as a vehicle with which to ruminate on the very problem of having a self split into body and soul, with one part, “the thing,” going to the earth after death and the other part, “the value of the thing,” going to the spiritual domain that God judges it deserves.</p>
      <p>But Faustus feels little need to read allegorically, to seek the signification that transcends direct presentation, for he never imagines spirit or even presence as anywhere but in signs themselves. Despite striking moments of doubt and panic in which he senses he is deceived, he consistently reads with the belief that spirit is entirely immanent in the letter. That is why he so loves the signs of magic: the lines, circles, schemes, and characters that apparently perform “the metaphysics of magicians” (1.1.51) by seeming to enact visibly, palpably, and presently that letter and spirit, and matter and soul, are one.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN28">28</xref>The fantasy that objects have spiritual efficacy provides his consolation. Indeed, Faustus seems even more invested in the spiritual power of the materiality of the sign than is the devil himself: when at one point Lucifer warns Faustus to “not think of God” (2.3.92), Faustus responds by vowing “never to look to heaven, / Never to name God” (2.3.95–96), as if naming God or performing acts that mark or deal in “the outside” of things were equivalent to thinking about God—as if naming and thinking were phenomenologically identical or produced the same results. For Faustus, naming suffices: for him spirit inheres in surfaces, and being therefore exists only in embodied form. And Faustus manifests this principle both in his epistemology and in his very sense of subjectivity itself. When Faustus reflects on his achievements in medicine—his having helped “whole cities” (1.1.21) to escape plague—he decides that such successes are worthless, and that only by being able to “make men…live eternally, / Or, being dead, raise them to life again” (1.1.24–25) were the medical profession “to be esteemed” (1.1.26). Faustus is not abandoning medicine here in order to take up divinity, as if he thought that the prolongation of earthly life were less vital than the pastoral care of immortal souls. Rather, Faustus is revealing that he conceives of eternal life itself as something that must entail embodiment, the literal survival or resurrection of the body.</p>
      <p>Faustus depends on fantasies of embodiment because he imagines no being, no self, grounded in the soul at all, neither in the future of salvation nor even in the present, where the identity of the man “Faustus” might seem to emerge from some invisible core within. For Faustus, there is simply nothing there: when Faustus refers to himself in the third person, for example (“I charge thee wait upon me whilst I live, / To do what ever Faustus shall command” [1.3.37–38]), or when he addresses himself with his name (“why Faustus, hast thou not attained that end?” [1.1.18]), it often seems as if he were swerving away from speaking from the phantasmic inward plenitude of an “I,” or as if he needed to imagine himself as a bounded object, seen from the outside in his mind's eye, in order to articulate himself (and thus could make himself present only by naming himself “Faustus”).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN29">29</xref>Faustus must name himself, conceive of himself from the outside, as it were, because he never identifies with his soul.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN30">30</xref>Faustus finds his soul to be alien to him, so much so that he feels it to be a burden he would be happy to be rid of (“why wert thou not a creature wanting soul?” he cries out desperately at one point [5.2.105]). There is some theological justification for Faustus's dissociation. Perkins, for instance, argues that “God is the life of the soul” just as “the soul is the life of the body.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN31">31</xref>With God residing inwardly as his immortal, animating essence, Faustus views his soul only as an absent, impalpable other to which he knows he is responsible but about which he feels that it is “not Faustus.” Subject to this vertiginous alienation from his soul, Faustus takes salvation to be a fate that entails the very annihilation of his identity, an annihilation more complete and terrifying to him than that imposed by earthly death itself.</p>
      <p>Faustus's rejection of faith is both producer and product of his sense that salvation will entail his own erasure, because it alienates him from his soul by alienating him from God; it is both producer and product of his determination not to read “past” what is material and embodied to what is intangible, because it gives him the sense that the intangible will turn out to be nothing. Yet Faustus's lack of faith does not enable him to feel that there is in fact no life after death. On the contrary, Faustus is obsessed with the afterlife and with hell specifically, about which he repeatedly questions Mephistopheles. Not that Faustus believes what Mephistopheles tells him about hell, however: he scoffs, “come, I think hell's a fable” (2.1.130) when the devil informs him that “hell hath no limits, nor is circumscribed / In one self place; for where we are is hell, / And where hell is, must we ever be” (2.1.124–26). Faustus will not imagine hell as a universally diffused, Augustinian state of privation; rather, he insists on imagining hell as an extension or reproduction of the university where he currently resides. In response to Mephistopheles' insistence that he himself is “damned, and…now in hell” (2.1.140), Faustus impatiently replies, “how now, in hell? Nay, and this be hell, / I'll willingly be damned here! What, walking, disputing, / etc.” (2.1.141–43). “Damned here…walking, disputing, etc.”: Faustus reveals how much it matters to him that hell be a place, and not a state of the soul. Faced with a salvation that seems to entail his annihilation in the disappearance or dissolution of his body, Faustus is comforted by the idea of a hell where he will walk and dispute, where he can have reading groups with the “old philosophers” (1.3.62) and where “the infernal spirits” will “swarm” (1.1.117) to his lectures. Imagining hell as a continuation of his brilliant academic career, Faustus simply sees damnation as the better choice.</p>
      <p>Obsessed with his afterlife yet disdaining to be dissolved into God's heaven, Faustus develops a relation in his mind to the devil as his solution to his dilemma. By adopting the “metaphysics of magicians,” Faustus finds a way, he thinks, to control the terms of his own death, securing for himself an eternity of continued embodiment and lack of self-transcendence. Indeed, at first Faustus passionately catalogs the epicurean marvels that he will command his spirits to procure—the “orient pearl” (1.1.85), the “princely delicates” (1.1.87)—but it becomes increasingly clear over the course of the play that whatever worldly rewards magic may afford him are secondary. Thus when Valdes promises Faustus that by magic he will gain fame and sex and money if only he will “be resolute” (1.1.135), Faustus answers in a way that tells more than he knows: “Valdes,” he says, “as resolute am I in this / As thou to live” (1.1.136–37). His resolution to live indicates less Faustus's determination to satisfy himself than his determination to save himself, to use magic to self-create the materialized afterlife, the embodied end, he most ardently desires. Thus the ability to conjure up and play with spirits is what he wants; magical personation enables him to face his own death and what is then to come, for it enables him to experience being, as Faustus believes, already in hell, where he will not only continue to walk, dispute, eat, and give lectures but also participate in delightful entertainments that celebrate personation itself. That is why Faustus is so easily distracted from repentance and doubt by the apparently trivial shows that the devil stages for him, or that he thinks he conjures up himself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN32">32</xref>Far from being inexplicably minor applications of the exalted magical power Faustus supposedly possesses, those pageants and dumbshows are at the very core of the satisfaction that Faustus looks to magic to afford him. The spirits personating poetic figures give Faustus visible evidence that he too may remain embodied after death, perhaps in an even more heroic form than the one he inhabits in earthly life. Of course, this representation of embodied forms by the devil is the very theatrical pretense to which the Protestant witchcraft writers referred. Yet Marlowe makes Mephistopheles' pretense much more subtle than the one imagined even by Perkins in his fierce obsession with Satan's wiles. Whereas the Protestant witchcraft writers assumed that Satan would feign himself to be bound by conjuration, Marlowe has Mephistopheles deceive Faustus not by feigning to be bound (for the spirit clearly defies Faustus's commands at many points along the way) but by feigning hell to be a place where bodies last (and are in fact more beautiful than those on earth) and where they perform delightful spectacle after delightful spectacle that Faustus may not only watch but perform in as an actor himself.</p>
      <p>When, for instance, Faustus attempts to make his eternal end immediately by signing the diabolical contract that he believes will ensure that he remains forever an embodied spirit “in form and substance” (2.1.72), and when he discovers to his utter horror that despite his signing of the contract, his body remains a disobedient vehicle for the invisible hand that writes “<italic>Homo fuge</italic>” (2.1.76) on his arm, Mephistopheles manages to distract Faustus from his dramatic crisis simply by going to “fetch him somewhat to delight his mind” (2.1.82). The devil exits stage left, then:<verse-group>
            <verse-line>
               <italic>Enter[s] [again] with devils, giving crowns and rich apparel to Faustus; they dance, and then depart</italic>.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>F<sc>austus</sc>. Speak Mephistopheles, what means this show?</verse-line>
            <verse-line>M<sc>ephistopheles</sc>. Nothing Faustus, but to delight thy mind withal,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>And to show thee what magic can perform.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(s.d., 2.1.83–85)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
      </p>
      <p>In contrast to the riddling texts that use Faustus's body and that demand interpretation, “this show,” although allegorical in the morality tradition, here means “nothing.” It demands no interpretation, no deferral of significance, no acknowledgment of transcendence. It is all surface. The “crowns” and the “rich apparel” that the devils give Faustus emblematize the attention to materials and to outsides that characterizes both life in hell and a certain kind of disinterested aestheticism which in this context functions only to deceive. Over and over, Mephistopheles tricks Faustus into believing that the shows conjured up in the theater of hell's delights find their ends in the enjoyment of their own performance. Perhaps his most telling trick is to seem to make “music” (2.3.30) with Amphion simply to provide “sweet pleasure” (2.3.25) to Faustus. Amphion along with Orpheus usually exemplifies the dream of an instrumental aesthetics, a beauty that can pacify beasts and even compel rocks and stones to organize themselves into cities with its moving sweetness of song. But Mephistopheles makes this sweet pleasure seem inconsequential, as he makes all magic seem inconsequential, as if magic were a production that celebrated only itself, showed only “what magic can perform,” or as if the delight inspired by the spirits personated on stage had no effect. But, of course, there will be an effect, no end of effect, just not yet.</p>
      <p>* * *</p>
      <p>I would now like to return to the rumor circulated by Prynne about the performances of<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>that seemed to conjure “the visible apparition of the Devil on the stage” to the “great amazement of both the actors and spectators…there being some there distracted with that fearful sight.” The ambiguity of Prynne's final phrase, “there being some there distracted with that fearful sight,” suggests both that the participants in the performance were distracted by the fearful sight of the devil appearing among them and that the devil appeared among them exactly because some participants were already driven to distraction by a fearful sight. And what else was this latter sight but the representation of conjuration itself? If you imagined magic as a spectacle meant to produce thoughts and feelings that would be watched and judged by both devils and God, to apprehend yourself taking pleasure in the staging of conjuration was to sense yourself being led into reprobation. Let us take, for example, the divertissement we have just quoted, in which Mephistopheles brings in devils who give “crowns and rich apparel” to Faustus and “dance and depart.” Mephistopheles is quite obviously entertaining the audience with this spectacle as much as he is entertaining the magician himself. And he is doing so after having made the audience complicit in his intent to deceive Faustus with his confiding aside: “I'll fetch him something to delight his mind” (2.1.82). To characterize “delight” as what would fatally distract Faustus from thoughts of God and repentance is to remind the audience that delight is theologically suspect in this context, and as such is something to be resisted. Yet how could the audience not delight, at least somewhat, in the unusual sight of jewels and embroidered brocade glittering bright, in the sweet sound of the music playing as graceful devils moved in intricate patterns, in the very qualities of lightness and harmony that the moving figures exuded into the heavens? To disdain these things would be to disdain the sensuous pleasures of theater itself. Yet how could spectators also not have felt anxious about their delight if they believed that it indicated that they were in spiritual danger? Such anxiety indeed sometimes reached such a pitch of collective tension that audiences became convinced there was “one too many devils among them,” as G. J. R. put it. But the palpable sense that devils had actually appeared in the playhouse was precisely the theatrical effect that Marlowe attempted to produce: in order to tie the aesthetic effects of his play to the theological effects of magic, he had Mephistopheles proclaim at the outset that he had been summoned not because there was any “virtue” (1.3.28) in Faustus's words, but because Faustus's interest in magical language indicated he was “in danger of being damned” (1.3.52).</p>
      <p>It is not only when Mephistopheles first appears and contextualizes his invocation in terms of the reformed understanding of magic that the play attempts to cast its spectators as active participants in a production that has theological import. Take, for example, the knight's refusal to remain on the scene when Faustus conjures at the Duke of Vanholt's palace. The knight seems like a throwaway character, a mere opportunity for Faustus to perform yet another trivial prank, but he also enacts the reformed doctrine that Marlowe deploys to make the audience anxious about their own interest in magical spectacles. As if assessing everything through a lens of faith (he begins most of his statements with the preface, “I'faith”), the knight reacts to Faustus in the exemplary Protestant manner: on the one hand, he entirely devalues the magician's abilities (when Faustus promises to “accomplish” the duke's request by the “power” of his “spirit” [4.1.43–44], the knight spits out contemptuously, “I'faith that's nothing at all” [1.3.45]); on the other hand, he seems to fear the spiritual implications of witnessing the invocation performed through the instrumentality of the magician. Accordingly, he leaves the hall when Faustus begins, as if refusing to risk the danger of being interested in or pleased by a magical sight.</p>
      <p>The play implicitly opposes the attitude and behavior of this doctrinally exemplary character to those of the audience on the ground and in the galleries, who have not only gathered but paid their own coin to watch a staging of a historical magician's courtly spectacles. Indeed, by conflating theatrical and magical shows, and by staging that conflation in ways that implicate the audience in the action,<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>repeatedly attempts to compel its spectators to identify almost involuntarily with characters who are invested in the effects of magic. When the scholars ask Faustus to produce Helen, for instance, the play positions these scholars as members of the audience who desire to see a conjuration, while it subsumes the audience into the group of scholars by having the boy actor playing Helen move through the paying crowd. (Allardyce Nicoll has argued that the stage direction “music sounds, and Helen passeth over the stage” [s.d., 5.1.26] implies that the actor entered from one side of the yard, walked through the audience, and exited at the other side.)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN33">33</xref>And the play stages this scene to attempt to produce the diabolical wonder, the very combination of erotic admiration and fear, that Perkins identified as augmenting the devil's power. As the boy actor makes his way through the close-pressed groundlings, his body becomes tactile and almost invasive, polluting the visual domain of spectatorship with the presence of materiality. That polluting presence may well be frightening as much as erotic, not least because Faustus commands the scholars, and by extension the audience, to “be silent, for danger is in words,” as if their hushed attention were the only prophylactic against the transformation of this feminine impersonation into a violent diabolical horror.</p>
      <p>Yet the structure of theatrical identification changes when the actor returns to the stage as Helen and Faustus are swept up into their erotic union. Then it is Faustus who consumes and is ravished by Helen as an impersonation, and insofar as the audience becomes swept up in the high power of Marlowe's heroic verse and in the actors' ability to project erotic desire and fulfillment, they too become transported by the pleasures of the illusion of rhetorical and theatrical embodiment. The play increases the terror of the pleasure of this identification by juxtaposing this celebration of magical and theatrical mimesis to the theological imperatives of the old man, who appears here specifically in contrast to Helen's conjuration. The old man's theological directives (“break heart…and mingle it with tears” [5.1.40]) remind the audience of their obligation to attend to their faith just at the moment when their inclinations are being most sorely tested by the erotics of the spectacle that they are witnessing. In making the audience aware of the requirements of faith while ravishing them with theatrical spectacle, the play lays bare the dangers of identification with Faustus, whose desire to consider repentance is repeatedly obscured by his absorption in the shows Mephistopheles stages. Yet again and again the audience is invited to enjoy Mephistopheles' spectacles while being made aware that the aesthetic effects of these same spectacles serve to bring Faustus ever closer to the point at which it would be too late for him to repent. Even when Faustus acts less as a passive consumer of Mephistopheles' theater pieces and more as a jester who seeks to “delight” his patrons “with some mirth” (4.1.90), the audience is encouraged to feel that Faustus represents their interests, as it were, since even his cheapest tricks stand as forms of social wish fulfillment. If Faustus and Mephistopheles are able to slap around the pope and his friars despite their curses, not only do they thereby confirm the reformed argument about magic (which of course dismisses any<italic>maledicat Dominus</italic>as being entirely ineffective), but they also enact the desire of any hot-blooded apprentice who would fully enjoy beating up one of his nation's enemies. Or, again, by selling the horse courser a bum steed and then undoing him by disappearing his leg, Faustus would provide vicarious if gruff satisfaction to any resentful spectator who had been fleeced by, essentially, the used-car salesman of his day. In both its high and low pleasures, then,<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>solicits identification with its hero, attempting to increase the audience's queasy sense of sympathy with a magician being led to his damnation.</p>
      <p>And just as the play solicits sympathy with Faustus in its spectacle and its comedy, so does it invite pity for Faustus in its tragedy. Such pity emerges from a slightly different kind of theatrical identification, however. Rather than accompanying the spectator's recognition that a character shares his or her interests, pity may arise when the spectator recognizes the character's otherness, when he apprehends or infers that the character suffers inwardly in an extraordinary way. Yet in pity the spectator also identifies in some sense with the tragic character, for he feels psychic pain in his imagination of the character's suffering. For Levinas, for instance, pity, as an expression of the subject's irreducibly asymmetrical obligation to the other, is fundamental to ethics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN34">34</xref>But in<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>, pity has no salutary ethical or moral value; on the contrary, the play explicitly contrasts the quality of human pity to that of divine mercy, thereby fashioning pity for Faustus as an aesthetic response that undermines the spectator's faith in God. It is the old man who thus devalues tragic pity. After Helen leaves the stage for the first time, the old man tells Faustus that an “angel” hovers over his head “with a vial full of precious grace” to “pour” into his “soul” (5.1.54–56), and he urges Faustus to repent—to “break heart, drop blood, and mingle it with tears” (5.1.40)—warning him that he has endangered his inward soul “with such flagitious crimes of heinous sins / As no commiseration may expel / But mercy, Faustus, of thy Savior sweet, / Whose blood alone must wash away thy guilt” (5.1.43–46). “Commiseration” is, of course, the contemporaneous word for the pity inspired by tragedy; Sidney uses it as such in<italic>The Defense of Poesy</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN35">35</xref>The old man argues, then, that Faustus is no less damnable for being pitiful, yet his argument, orthodox as it may be, not only makes God seem somehow less compassionate than even the crudest member of the audience moved by Faustus's suffering but also makes his justice seem all the more inscrutable.</p>
      <p>The play's implication that God lacks compassion and, even more capriciously, that he has subjected Faustus to some inexorable, necessary damnation, is concentrated in Faustus's final soliloquy, where the audience witnesses Faustus struggling to save himself:<verse-group>
            <verse-line>O I'll leap up to my God! Who pulls me down?</verse-line>
            <verse-line>See, see where Christ's blood streams in the firmament!</verse-line>
            <verse-line>One drop would save my soul, half a drop: ah my Christ—</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Ah, rend not my heart for naming of my Christ;</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Yet I will call on him—O spare me Lucifer!</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Where is it now? ’Tis gone: and see where God</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Stretcheth out his arm, and bends his ireful brows!</verse-line>
            <attrib>(5.2.77–83)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
      </p>
      <p>It is utterly clear that Faustus's inner life is tortured. The longing and the sense of exile invoked by his cries (“see, see where Christ's blood streams…one drop would save my soul…ah my Christ”) are utterly palpable yet horribly answered by sharp internal pain, as if an invisible claw slashed at Faustus's heart for its very longing (“Ah, rend not my heart for naming of Christ”). And by this rending sharpness Faustus becomes all the more alienated from mercy, as if he were confronted with the hallucination of Christ's blood disappearing (“Where is it now? ’Tis gone”), or as if God himself looked down in the sternest, most unforgiving judgment (“see where God / Stretcheth out his arm, and bends his ireful brows!”). But what makes God seem entirely confounding is not merely that he seems to all too ready to squash Faustus, as if Marlowe's hero were nothing more than a scurrying, terrified bug, but also that Faustus himself finally seems horrified by damnation yet remains utterly exiled and bereft of any chance for his soul to find rest because he manifests the very same habit of mind he displayed in his opening soliloquy. He still feels that he can live only in his body, addressing the earth as if it could hide him from God by hiding his body (“Then will I headlong run into the earth: Earth gape! O no, it will not harbor me” [5.2.87]). He still feels like salvation is an annihilation worse than death, and for that very reason he cannot help but prefer either to be in endless pain in hell or to have no soul at all (“O no end is limited to damned souls! / Why wert thou not a creature wanting soul?” [5.2.104–5]). And he still thinks that his soul is flesh and that his flesh will endure forever in hell (“Now body, turn to air, / Or Lucifer will bear thee quick to hell / O soul, be changed into little water drops, / And fall into the ocean, ne'er to be found” [5.2.116–19]). Thus he can do nothing but call on God in a gasping panic (“My God, My God!” he cries, just before the devils enter to drag him away). Is he not performing the old man's injunction to “break heart, drop blood, and mingle it with tears”? Yet God rejects him (“My God, my God, look not so fierce on me!” [5.2.120]).</p>
      <p>But even if Faustus performs the affects of repentance, he cannot repent and be saved in the strict theological sense because until the very end he exhibits the inward disposition of the faithless magician who must choose to be duped by Satan. But why does he have such an inward disposition in the first place? Is it indeed that God has predestined Faustus to hell, subjected him to the most miserable necessity? For Paul Ricoeur, the question of “the scandalous theology of predestination to evil” is the tragic question par excellence, which is why the tragic is always, in Ricoeur's formulation, “a temptation to despair” in its display of the “hostile transcendence to which the hero is prey.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN36">36</xref>But Marlowe's play, as much as it also invites the audience to despair, stages something more subtle and finally more wrenching than blank divine vengeance, for in fact it employs the more charitable theology represented by Holland rather than that of Perkins: Faustus may indeed repent, and God may indeed change his mind. The possibility of repentance provides the suspense that makes the play dramatic rather than merely iconographical, and that gives force and fear to those apparently trivial spectacles that repeatedly persuade Faustus not to perform his inward penance. Yet at the same time, there does seem to be something fated in the way that Faustus is introduced to the audience with a habit of mind that makes it impossible for him to take his given opportunities to repent.<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>thus brings the audience right up against the nondialectical, and therefore tragic, contradiction of the theology of grace: the fact an omnipotent and supposedly loving God permits creaturely suffering, or, in terms more specific to the play, that God rejects a man who cries out to him simply because that man thinks like a dramatist rather than an allegorist.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN37">37</xref>Milton, on his part, tries to solve this problem at the heart of Christianity with a theodicy of human insufficiency—the archangel Raphael notoriously tells Adam not to seek to know things above his ken—but Marlowe's play lays bare the ethical poverty of this strategy (not least because it is hard to see what Faustus has done with his magic that is really so evil: Ask questions about the stars? Put on some shows? Find a pregnant woman some grapes?).</p>
      <p>Even to consider these questions, let alone to feel stirred or moved by them, is, it seems, to begin to doubt the goodness of God.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN38">38</xref>And to doubt the goodness of God, even if you still believe in his existence, is to slide into what was generally understood in the period as atheism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN39">39</xref>Perhaps that is why Prynne accused acting companies of “prophanely” playing the history of Faustus despite the fact that the play stages the orthodoxy of the unrepentant magician's damnation. Or perhaps something else was at stake in Prynne's sense that the play was profane. Insofar as Faustus is compelling as a tragic character, his play will reveal the inexorable negativity at the heart of Protestant Christianity; it will lay bare not that damnation is predestined but that salvation itself entails self-obliteration into the absolute otherness of an inscrutable God. From a humanist perspective such Christianity is fundamentally tragic because the life that it offers universalizes all sensuous particularity, all subjectivity signified or even felt in the material embodiment of persons and texts. But the ultimate effect of Marlowe's play is not simply for the audience to doubt whether they should continue to desire God and salvation; rather, it is for the audience terrifyingly to feel that God is watching them doubt and, bending down his “ireful brows,” judging their thoughts and feelings and condemning them to the damnation that they are compelled to contemplate. And in a context where magic was a theatrical show created by the devil but permitted by God so he could see whether his subjects would, as Perkins put it, cleave to him or to the devil and his wicked instruments, to cleave in compassion to Faustus was to sense yourself entering into alliance with the devil, alienated from the inscrutable source of your immortal soul.</p>
      <p>* * *</p>
      <p>By characterizing Faustus's magic as efficacious only because his interest in it signified that he was inclined to be damned, Marlowe turned the aesthetic strategies of dramatic forms into instruments that produced effects that seemed to have soteriological consequences. Yet he dramatized the reformers' arguments not because he wrote his play to disciplinary ends (it is hard to imagine Marlowe having an interest in reforming his audience's faith). Rather, Marlowe made the aesthetics of<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>instrumental to increase the cultural and material power of his art. He knew full well that immediate, popular, and even naive theatrical experiences motivate the distribution of such power; from an ambitious and brilliantly cunning playwright's point of view, they are the means to that very end. And in writing<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>, Marlowe was not just cunning, but fearless. If he argued, as Richard Baines claimed, that “the first beginning of Religion was only to keep men in awe,” it still could not have been an easy thing, when atheism was a felony and religious discourse saturated all of English life, to maintain such a demystifying view of the ideological function of the sacred.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN40">40</xref>Yet Marlowe used belief in the devil and in God himself as his dramatic instrument to wrench the psychic and social force of religious experience away from its dominant institutional contexts and to place it in the peripheral space of the theater, which he, above all his immediate contemporaries, was creating as a charged, extraordinary, and charismatic social space.</p>
      <p>In saying this, I am not arguing that Marlowe “appropriated” the sacred from its dominant institutional contexts. On the contrary, the rumors of devils appearing on the Faustian stage belie that model of the relationship between the dramatic and the theological in which the theater evacuates the spiritual content from theological forms only to stage those forms within a sphere of rational disenchantment that supposedly frames the experience of a play.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN41">41</xref>Such a model relies on a modern, indeed modernist, understanding of theater as a compartmentalized zone of experience where entertainment has no further end than its own production and consumption, and where aesthetic efficacy, if it exists at all, remains limited to art's ability to contain the contradictions of ideology. Theatrical representation clearly had a certain kind of autonomy in Marlowe's England, produced and consumed as it was in its own institutional space, yet at the same time, as I hope I have been able to show, that very representation could be understood by antitheatrical writers and theatergoers alike as an instrument that had theological ends. Another way to put this claim is to say that theater was not always understood as a disenchanted product of human agency. When the reformers argued that Satan staged theater pieces through the instrumentality of the magician to the end of creating beliefs in the audience that would augment his own power, they were quite capable of imagining that such spectacles were well-crafted illusions without needing to go on to posit that the devil was an ideological fiction. The rumors of the Faustian devils powerfully demonstrate that even representations that announced their own theatricality—even illusions that were institutionally marked out as such—could still be understood as having theological consequences. Those who believed that the devil came when Faustus called him may have been fully invested in their faith, but they were never so gullible as to believe that the actors were anything but players. They were subjected to (and by) their culture simply just enough to fear that the pleasure and grief those players inspired served as damning evidence of the worth of their souls. It is this spiritual instrumentality of embodied representation that Marlowe exploited to his own dramatic and institutional purposes. That audiences subjected to the power of Marlowe's play feared that devils were flying to the scene to drag their souls to hell resoundingly attests to the success of his theatrical strategy.</p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
            <label>1.</label>
            <p>William Prynne,<italic>Histriomastix: The Player's Scourge, or Actor's Tragedy</italic>(London, 1633), 556r.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN2" fn-type="other">
            <label>2.</label>
            <p>G. J. R., quoted in E. K. Chambers,<italic>The Elizabethan Stage</italic>, 4 vols. (Oxford University Press, 1923), 3:424. Chambers cites other rumors of the same kind, such as the incident to which Thomas Middleton referred in his 1604<italic>Black Book</italic>when he attempted to describe someone's unruly coif: “he had a head of hair like one of my devils in Dr. Faustus when the old Theater cracked and frightened the audience” (424). Samuel Rowland also liked to say that Edward Alleyn would wear a cross on his surplice when he played Faustus for fear that he might be in the presence of devils. See Gareth Roberts, “Necromantic Books: Christopher Marlowe,<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>and Agrippa of Nettesheim,” in<italic>Christopher Marlowe and English Renaissance Culture</italic>, ed. Darryll Grantley and Peter Roberts (London: Scolar, 1996), 157.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN3" fn-type="other">
            <label>3.</label>
            <p>Leah Marcus,<italic>Unediting the Renaissance: Shakespeare, Marlowe, Milton</italic>(New York: Routledge, 1996), 42. See also Harry Levin,<italic>The Overreacher: A Study of Christopher Marlowe</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1951), 121; Michael Goldman, “Marlowe and the Histrionics of Ravishment,” in<italic>Two Renaissance Mythmakers: Christopher Marlowe and Ben Jonson</italic>, ed. Alvin Kernan (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1977), 40; and Richard Halpern, “Marlowe's Theater of Night:<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>and Capital,”<italic>ELH</italic>71 (2004): 472. For Halpern, the extra devils locate Marlowe's ability to transform theater's internal ontological lack into a generative force.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN4" fn-type="other">
            <label>4.</label>
            <p>Paul Kocher (“The Witchcraft Bias in Marlowe's ‘Faustus,’”<italic>Modern Philology</italic>38 [1940]: 9–36) and Barbara Traister (“<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>: Master of Self-Delusion,” in<italic>Christopher Marlowe's “Doctor Faustus</italic>,” ed. Harold Bloom [New York: Chelsea House, 1988], 77–92) have noted that Marlowe used the reformed theory of magic in<italic>Doctor Faustus,</italic>although both critics have elided the reformers' emphasis on the theatrical nature of conjuration and its relevance to the play's dramatic effects.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN5" fn-type="other">
            <label>5.</label>
            <p>Christopher Marlowe,<italic>Doctor Faustus, A- and B-Texts (1604, 1616)</italic>, ed. David Bevington and Eric Rasmussen (Manchester University Press, 1993), 1.3.28, hereafter cited parenthetically. Because I am interested in Marlowe's use of Protestant attacks on magic, I cite the A text of the play, which consistently manifests the theology underlying reformist polemics. For the theologies of the A and B texts, see Marcus,<italic>Unediting</italic>, chap. 2.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN6" fn-type="other">
            <label>6.</label>
            <p>See Conrad Platz,<italic>Kurtzer, Nottwendiger, und Wollgegrundter bericht</italic>(n.p., 1565); and Niels Hemmingsen,<italic>Admonitio de superstitionibus magicis vitandis</italic>(Copenhagen, 1575). On Platz, and the German case more broadly, see Robert Scribner, “The Reformation, Popular Magic, and the ‘Disenchantment of the World,’”<italic>Journal of Interdisciplinary History</italic>23 (1993): 475–94; see also Stuart Clark, “Protestant Demonology: Sin, Superstition, Society (c. 1520–c. 1630),” in<italic>Early Modern European Witchcraft: Centres and Peripheries</italic>, ed. Bengt Ankarloo and Gustav Henningsen (Oxford University Press, 1990), 45–81, and<italic>Thinking with Demons: The Idea of Witchcraft in Early Modern Europe</italic>(Oxford University Press, 1997), 435–526.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN7" fn-type="other">
            <label>7.</label>
            <p>In 1590 and 1591, Gifford wrote two pamphlets arguing against schism and preached from the established pulpit of St. Paul's Cross; he published his longest work on magic,<italic>A Dialogue Concerning Witches and Witchcraftes</italic>, in 1593. In<italic>An Exposition of the Symbole or Creed of the Apostles</italic>(London, 1595), William Perkins invoked the Thirty-Nine Articles—or, as he called it, “the Booke of the articles of faith agreed upon in open Parliament”—as expressing what he called the “true faith” (501). For the scope of Gifford's pamphleteering, see Alan MacFarlane, “A Tudor Anthropologist: George Gifford's<italic>Discourse</italic>and<italic>Dialogue</italic>,” in<italic>The Damned Art: Essays in the Literature of Witchcraft</italic>, ed. Sydney Anglo (New York: Routledge, 1977), 140–55; and Christopher Haigh, “The Taming of the Reformation: Preachers, Pastors, and Parishioners in Elizabethan and Early Stuart England,”<italic>History</italic>85 (2000): 572–88. For Perkins as defender of the Elizabethan settlement, see W. B. Patterson, “William Perkins as Apologist for the Church of England,”<italic>Journal of Ecclesiastical History</italic>57 (2006): 252–69.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN8" fn-type="other">
            <label>8.</label>
            <p>See James I,<italic>Daemonologie</italic>, ed. G. B. Harrison (1597; repr., London: Lane, 1924), 17; and John Cotta,<italic>The Triall of Witchcraft</italic>(London, 1616). See also Alexander Roberts,<italic>A Treatise of Witchcraft</italic>(London, 1617); and Thomas Cooper,<italic>The Mystery of Witchcraft</italic>(London, 1617). In the interest of concision, I will confine my discussion of the tracts on magic to those published in England around the time<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>was first performed.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN9" fn-type="other">
            <label>9.</label>
            <p>For the narrative of the Protestant pastorate attempting to discredit cunning men and women, see Keith Thomas,<italic>Religion and the Decline of Magic: Studies in Popular Beliefs in Sixteenth and Seventeenth Century England</italic>(1971; repr., Oxford University Press, 1997), 151–279, esp. 263–67; Clark, “Protestant Demonology,” and<italic>Thinking with Demons</italic>, 457–71; and Scott McGinnis, “‘Subtiltie’ Exposed: Pastoral Perspectives on Witch Belief in the Thought of George Gifford,”<italic>Sixteenth Century Journal</italic>33 (2002): 665–86. For the pastoral reinterpretation of witchcraft as spiritual affliction, see Clark,<italic>Thinking with Demons</italic>, 438–71; Alexandra Walsham,<italic>Providence in Early Modern England</italic>(Oxford University Press, 1999), esp. 25–28; and Nathan Johnstone,<italic>The Devil and Demonism in Early Modern England</italic>(Cambridge University Press, 2006), chaps. 3–4.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN10" fn-type="other">
            <label>10.</label>
            <p>George Gifford,<italic>A Discourse of the Subtle Practice of Deuilles by Witches and Sorcerers</italic>(London, 1587), Biiv.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN11" fn-type="other">
            <label>11.</label>
            <p>William Perkins,<italic>A Discourse of the Damned Art of Witchcraft</italic>(London, 1608), 134–35. Further references to this text will appear parenthetically.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN12" fn-type="other">
            <label>12.</label>
            <p>Henry Holland,<italic>A Treatise Against Witchcraft;</italic>[and]<italic>A Short Discourse Shewing the Most Certain and Principal Means Ordeined of God to Discover, Expell, and to Confound all the Sathanicall Inventions of Witchcraft and Sorcierie</italic>(London, 1590), 5, I3r. For a reading connecting the reformers' ordinary language philosophy to scientific empiricism, see Stuart Clark, “Magical Power of Signs,” in his<italic>Thinking with Demons</italic>, 281–93.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN13" fn-type="other">
            <label>13.</label>
            <p>Willam Perkins,<italic>A Golden Chaine, or The Description of Theology</italic>(London, 1591), 127.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN14" fn-type="other">
            <label>14.</label>
            <p>John Calvin,<italic>A Commentarie upon S. Paule's Epistles to the Corinthians</italic>, trans. Thomas Tymme (London, 1577), 226, fol. Ggiiv.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN15" fn-type="other">
            <label>15.</label>
            <p>Reginald Scot,<italic>The Discoverie of Witchcraft</italic>, ed. Montague Summers (1584; London: Rodker, 1930), 234.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN16" fn-type="other">
            <label>16.</label>
            <p>In the first chapter of<italic>Duessa as Theological Satire</italic>(Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1970), D. Douglas Waters provides a comprehensive discussion of the Protestant characterization of the Catholic priest as a conjurer.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN17" fn-type="other">
            <label>17.</label>
            <p>Gifford,<italic>Discourse of the Subtle Practice</italic>, F4v.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN18" fn-type="other">
            <label>18.</label>
            <p>Robert Burton,<italic>The Anatomy of Melancholy</italic>, ed. Holbrook Jackson (1621; New York Review of Books, 2001), 1.205.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN19" fn-type="other">
            <label>19.</label>
            <p>Holland,<italic>Treatise Against Witchcraft</italic>, B3v.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN20" fn-type="other">
            <label>20.</label>
            <p>For “admiration” as a tragic effect, along with the Aristotelian “pity” and “fear,” see, e.g., Philip Sidney,<italic>An Apology for Poetry, or The Defense of Poesy</italic>, ed. Geoffrey Shepherd (1595; Manchester University Press, 1965), 118.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN21" fn-type="other">
            <label>21.</label>
            <p>For accounts of the eschatological instrumentality of the devil in various providential schema, see Jeffery Burton Russell,<italic>Mephistopheles: The Devil in the Modern World</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1986), 25–58; Walsham,<italic>Providence</italic>, 8–15; and Johnstone,<italic>Devil and Demonism</italic>. See also Peter Lake's interesting discussion of diabolical agency in Lake and Michael Questier,<italic>The Anti-Christ's Lewd Hat: Protestants, Papists, and Players in Post-Reformation England</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2002), 40–53.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN22" fn-type="other">
            <label>22.</label>
            <p>Holland,<italic>Short Discourse</italic>, G4r.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN23" fn-type="other">
            <label>23.</label>
            <p>“If any such be sorry and begin to show any tokens of true repentance, which either have sought unto or practiced any sorcery…they must be wisely informed and comforted, for Jesus Christ can and will cast forth an unclean spirit, if in truth of heart with weeping and fasting, and mourning, he be sought unto by repentance” (ibid., 15, K4r).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN24" fn-type="other">
            <label>24.</label>
            <p>The fact that Rafe and Robin are able to conjure Mephistopheles from Constantinople, making him “vexed” with their “charms” (3.2.32), may seem to contradict the reformist doctrine that the devil articulates here, and indeed the “second nature” of magical signs seems always to raise the hope in devils that they might get the souls of those that use them. But Mephistopheles does not really perform conjuration for the clowns—he not only declines to feign to enter into their service but even translates them into an ape and a dog—because Rafe and Robin are not really in danger of being damned, having no real desire to commit themselves to the devil.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN25" fn-type="other">
            <label>25.</label>
            <p>See, e.g., C. L. Barber, “The Forme of Faustus' Fortunes Good or Bad,” in<italic>Creating Elizabethan Tragedy: The Theater of Marlowe and Kyd</italic>, ed. Richard Wheeler (University of Chicago Press, 1988), 87–130. Barber argues that Faustus suffers from the theological condition of despair.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN26" fn-type="other">
            <label>26.</label>
            <p>Edward Snow argues that Faustus uses the word “end” in his opening soliloquy to mean not “an opening upon immanent horizons,” but a “termination,” so that “having ‘attained’ [an] end means that he has arrived at the end of it, used it up, finished with it” (“Marlowe's<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>and the Ends of Desire,” in Bloom,<italic>Marlowe's</italic>“<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>,” 54).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN27" fn-type="other">
            <label>27.</label>
            <p>
               <italic>On kai me on</italic>is the transliteration of the Greek for “being and not being.” As Bevington and Rasmussen note, the phrase is not in fact Aristotelian but from Gorgias (<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>,<italic>A- and B-Texts</italic>, 110 n. 12).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN28" fn-type="other">
            <label>28.</label>
            <p>As Graham L. Hammill has argued, “When Faustus chooses necromantic books [he] unwittingly chooses signifiers whose materiality mark his desire for a signified as his own ontological insufficiency” (<italic>Sexuality and Form: Caravaggio, Marlowe, and Bacon</italic>[University of Chicago Press, 2000], 316).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN29" fn-type="other">
            <label>29.</label>
            <p>Whereas someone like Tamburlaine, for example, almost exclusively uses the third person in the self-aggrandizing style of Julius Caesar, Faustus, although he shares some of Tamburlaine's mighty bombast, uses the third person even, or even especially, in his most wretched moments: “Ah Christ my savior, seek to save / Distressed Faustus' soul” (2.3.82–83).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN30" fn-type="other">
            <label>30.</label>
            <p>Snow has already marked this about Faustus: “When the possibility of the transmigration of souls is envisioned,…the ‘I’ identifies not with the soul…but with what remains behind when it is gone” (“Ends of Desire,” 67).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN31" fn-type="other">
            <label>31.</label>
            <p>William Perkins,<italic>A Salve for a Sicke Man</italic>(Cambridge, 1595), 7. Ian Watt has remarked that in<italic>Doctor Faustus</italic>the soul seems to be “an invisible but immortal stranger within, God's hostage” (<italic>Myths of Modern Individualism</italic>[Cambridge University Press, 1997], 45).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN32" fn-type="other">
            <label>32.</label>
            <p>The theatrical “triviality” of Faustus's magic has long since exercised critics of the play. See, e.g., Levin, who decries the “incongruity between the…seemingly endless possibilities envisioned by Faustus' speeches and their all too concretely vulgar realization in the stage business” (<italic>Overreacher</italic>, 120–21); and Halpern, who laments more broadly that the play stages an “aesthetics of disappointment” (“Marlowe's Theater,” 467).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN33" fn-type="other">
            <label>33.</label>
            <p>See Allardyce Nicoll, “Passing Over the Stage,”<italic>Shakespeare Survey</italic>12 (1959): 47–55. For details on the layout of the Bell Savage, see Herbert Barry, “The Bell Savage Inn and Playhouse in London,”<italic>Medieval and Renaissance Drama in England</italic>19 (2006): 121–43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN34" fn-type="other">
            <label>34.</label>
            <p>See esp. Emmanuel Levinas,<italic>Otherwise than Being, or Beyond Essence</italic>, trans. Alphonso Lingis (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, 1999). For a critique of this ethical basis as eliding the potential for monstrosity or inhumanity in the other, see Slavoj Žižek, “Neighbors and Other Monsters: A Plea for Ethical Violence,” in Slavoj Žižek, Eric L. Santner, and Kenneth Reinhard<italic>, The Neighbor: Three Inquiries in Political Theology</italic>(University of Chicago Press, 2006), 136–90. Žižek does not entirely discard pity as an ethical category, but instead requires that it be supplemented to counterbalance its excess.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN35" fn-type="other">
            <label>35.</label>
            <p>See Sidney,<italic>Apology for Poetry</italic>, 35.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN36" fn-type="other">
            <label>36.</label>
            <p>See Paul Ricoeur,<italic>The Symbolism of Evil</italic>, trans. Emerson Buchanan (Boston: Beacon, 1967), 212, 323.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN37" fn-type="other">
            <label>37.</label>
            <p>As Jonathan Dollimore has argued, the play implicitly stages the question of “how is evil possible in a world created by an omnipotent God” (<italic>Radical Tragedy: Religion, Ideology, and Power in the Drama of Shakespeare and His Contemporaries</italic>, 3rd ed. [Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2004], 117).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN38" fn-type="other">
            <label>38.</label>
            <p>Alan Sinfield has made a similar point in<italic>Faultlines: Cultural Materialism and the Politics of Dissident Reading</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1992), 230–37.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN39" fn-type="other">
            <label>39.</label>
            <p>See David Riggs,<italic>The World of Christopher Marlowe</italic>(New York: Holt, 2004), 30–31. See also the classic study on the construction of atheism in the period, Lucien Febvre's<italic>The Problem of Unbelief in the Sixteenth Century: The Religion of Rabelais</italic>, trans. Beatrice Gottlieb (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1982); and David Wootton, “New Histories of Atheism,” in<italic>Atheism from the Reformation to the Enlightenment</italic>, ed. Michael Hunter and David Wootton (New York: Oxford University Press, 1992), 13–54.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN40" fn-type="other">
            <label>40.</label>
            <p>Richard Baines, quoted in Paul H. Kocher, “Marlowe's Atheist Lecture,” in<italic>Marlowe: A Collection of Critical Essays</italic>, ed. Clifford Leech (Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1964), 160. Nicholas Davidson has argued, by contrast, that the opinions attributed to Marlowe in the Baines libel were unexceptional in the period. See his “Christopher Marlowe and Atheism,” in Grantley and Roberts,<italic>Marlowe and English Renaissance Culture</italic>, 129–47.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="FN41" fn-type="other">
            <label>41.</label>
            <p>For the original argument that early modern drama evacuated spiritual forms of their content, see Stephen Greenblatt, “Shakespeare and the Exorcists,” in<italic>Shakespearean Negotiations: The Circulation of Social Energy in Renaissance England</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1988), 94–128.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
