<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">signs</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Signs</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00979740</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456943</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3488236</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/429806</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">SIGNS300423</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Book Reviews</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Edrie</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Sobstyl</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Vancouver</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>30</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>signs.2005.30.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>2261</fpage>
         <lpage>2265</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Gender in the Mirror: Cultural Imagery and Women’s Agency</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Diana </given-names>
               <surname>Tietjens Meyers</surname>
            </string-name>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002.</product>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Gender and Agency: Reconfiguring the Subject in Feminist and Social Theory</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Lois </given-names>
               <surname>McNay</surname>
            </string-name>. Cambridge: Polity Press, 2000.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author(s).</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/429806"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Subjectivity, agency, selfhood. These concepts, sometimes taken to be synonymous, continue to merit attention from feminist theorists. We may loosely divide feminist thinking on these topics into two threads: the concrete, based on experiential aspects of women’s agency, and the theoretical, aiming to sort out underlying metaphysical and political questions. Two recent works follow this informal divide: Diana Tietjens Meyers’s<italic>Gender in the Mirror</italic>represents the former thread, while Lois McNay’s<italic>Gender and Agency</italic>takes up the latter. That is not to say that Meyers’s work is free of theoretical foundations or that McNay’s book has no practical application—on the contrary. The difference lies more in starting points, so that the two volumes will appeal to somewhat different audiences, though it is instructive to read them together. Both authors exhibit impatience with some treatments of subjectivity, and both can be read as attempting to set discourse about agency on a more practical path.</p>
      <p>Meyers is well known for her contributions to feminist thinking about selfhood.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>In this volume she is especially interested in the impact that potent imagery rooted partly in social convention has on women’s perceptions of themselves, on the one hand, and on the possibility that such images are surmountable barriers to women’s freedom, on the other. She begins by asserting that “outbreaks of intellectual mischief and perhaps even obtuseness [also] tend to cluster at these sights of inquiry” (2). This illustrates her frustration with those feminist theorists who minimize the power of gender conventions until such conventions become “a pesky phantasm that we can dispatch without too much trouble” (3). She is also critical of those writers who offer women a stark choice: either voluntary identity in a group or essentialism. She seeks a middle path, working to preserve a robust notion of gender and an empowering individualist model of agency without creating false unity among women.</p>
      <p>Accordingly, Meyers examines the role of a series of gender‐specific images in women’s agency, addressing pronatalism, mother‐child imagery, the family, narcissism, aging, and sexuality. Each of these topics could occupy a book, and one hopes that Meyers will expand on the ideas developed here. The strength of this approach is the familiarity of the subject matter to a large audience—although not to all women—and Meyers strives to remain conscious of the fact that she cannot make universal claims about women. But many readers will find something in the text that resonates with their own experience. (Meyers’s discussion relies in part on interviews with women.) For example, when she criticizes “matrigyno‐idolatry” (32) or the pressure to become a mother, she does not merely report on tensions that some women face. Nor does she simply analyze the power of social discourse to manipulate women’s choices. Rather, she sticks to her middle path, demonstrating persuasively that there is currently no space in matrigyno‐idolatrous discourse for genuine autonomy for women, and she makes a parallel point for each set of images she examines. Whatever choice one makes—including the choice to remain childless, which, she correctly points out, is seldom considered by feminist theorists—there is a cultural image ready at hand to define and constrict women’s agency.</p>
      <p>This is where theories of feminist agency typically run into trouble, and Meyers’s view, despite its grounding in experience, is no exception. She argues that “what is important for women’s self‐determination is that, whether they choose to become mothers or not, they find discursive means to symbolize their particular relations to motherhood and through these self‐figurations resist their homogenization in matrigynist ideology” (54). Women are to consider “what it would be like to inhabit a proposed figuration by constructing scenarios in which the figuration guides their conduct and by viscerally imagining themselves acting out those scenarios” (55). She makes similar claims about the other cultural images she explores, and she always insists that such “discursive innovation is not by itself enough” (55). The problem arises not over the apparent similarity between these acts of imagination and the gender performativity Meyers rejects but over what else is needed.</p>
      <p>Meyers is not so naive as to hold that careful screening and imaginative trope play will automatically yield a liberatory model of individual agency. She insists that the self‐figurations that “survive this vetting must become embedded in the cognitive, emotional, and corporeal structures that shape agency and that function as criteria of self‐appraisal. To agentically integrate dissident self‐figurations, women must command skills that enable them to invest emotionally in these tropes and to reconfigure their embodied values as well as their patterns of thought and volition in accordance with them” (55). How? Partly through changes in child‐rearing practices and the social order more generally, but Meyers’s view presumes that the skills for emotional investment and revision of values and volition are already available to most women. However, it can be argued that many women lack these skills and find it arduous to embed new figurations in their cognitive, emotional, and corporeal selves. It is hard to see how any amount of screening and play will take us from image to agency. A more productive approach would be to focus on developing those skills (including through changes in the social order), but that option is constrained in part by the predominance of the very imagery of which Meyers is critical. She uses commanding language in her argument for experimentation with new subjectivities—women<italic>must</italic>screen,<italic>must</italic>viscerally imagine,<italic>must</italic>embed new self‐images,<italic>must</italic>command skills. This makes it easy to miss her recognition of the insufficiency of such measures, as does the relative lack of detailed proposals for restructuring the social order. Yet one cannot simply flout the power of cultural images in women’s lives. By exposing the feedback loop between self‐image and agentic skills in a patriarchal order, Meyers establishes that image and agency are not two distinct paths. Her emphasis may be on imagery, but it is clear that image and large‐scale political change must proceed together.</p>
      <p>McNay’s<italic>Gender and Agency</italic>, while differing from<italic>Gender in the Mirror</italic>in focus, shares in Meyers’s vexation with existing approaches to agency. McNay is particularly suspicious of theorists of cultural studies who “impute to certain everyday practices a kind of inherently subversive status” (4). She argues that the widely deployed idea of everyday resistance has no impact when the interplay between individual behavior and social norms is ignored: “This, in turn, indicates the necessity of contextualizing agency<italic>within power relations</italic>in order to understand how acts deemed as resistant may transcend their immediate sphere in order to transform collective behavior and norms” (4, emphasis added). One can see that McNay is explicitly conscious of the tension that lurks in Meyers’s work, and the point is repeated throughout the book: “Analysis of the way in which certain subversive practices may get taken up and collectivized is important if resistance is to mean anything other than the truism that individuals do not reproduce social norms in a straightforward fashion” (129). Yet even more than Meyers’s, McNay’s argument glides from the language of mandate in her proposals (analogous to Meyers’s “musts”) to the language of possibility and potential in the results: a new theory of contextualized feminist agency could, may, might lead to collective action and greater freedom for women.</p>
      <p>Where Meyers looks at images, McNay examines theorists: Pierre Bourdieu, Judith Butler, Paul Ricoeur, and Cornelius Castoriadis. In each case McNay lays out what she takes to be the merits of each writer’s views, while asking how the important step for feminists, from theory to action, is to be taken. And in each case the answer to this question is elusive. This is due in part to internal differences between the writers McNay considers. It is far from clear that Butler’s views on the body inform the same idea of agency as Ricoeur’s theory of narrative, for example, and as the text grows increasingly complex the very concept of agency seems to recede. This elusiveness is also partly due to the critique of theory itself. While striving to preserve the value in each competing view of subjectivity, McNay draws the reader’s attention to such serious drawbacks that one despairs for these theories altogether.</p>
      <p>Whatever the starting point for investigation of agency, and whatever correctives are proposed, there must be both individual and social uptake of those changes in order for them to have any impact on women’s lives. Meyers faces this necessity more squarely in her final chapter on sexuality, where she points out that female sexual agency cannot change without concurrent changes in masculine sexual identity, although the problem of how to effect such changes remains. Similarly, McNay writes hopefully about creative connection and interdependence with others, but in her work—perhaps because of her reliance on a fractious group of theorists—these “others” remain largely abstractions. The discomforts in social roles of which she writes are not just between the self and a set of institutions or expectations; they are between the self and other people, people with their own specificity and their own discomforts. Despite—or perhaps because of—her emphasis on collective action, McNay seems to defer genuine selfhood to some future possible world. Nevertheless, McNay’s emphasis on collective action is a helpful complement to Meyers’s focus on imagery.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>See especially Diana Tietjens Meyers,<italic>Self, Society, and Personal Choice</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1989), and Diana Tietjens Meyers, ed.,<italic>Feminists Rethink the Self</italic>(Boulder, CO: Westview, 1997).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
