<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">analisesocial</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50001058</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Análise Social</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Gabinete de Investigações Sociais</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>journal-series-title</meta-name>
               <meta-value>Segunda Série</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00032573</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21822999</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41010296</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Educação e transformação social</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Carlos A.</given-names>
                  <surname>Emediato</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1978</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>14</volume>
         <issue>54</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40045662</issue-id>
         <fpage>207</fpage>
         <lpage>217</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement/>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41010296"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>A educaçao é vulgarmente considerada um importante instrumento impulsionador da transformacäo social. Alias, segundo a teoría liberal, a educaçao foi sempre considerada urna via para a mobilidade social e a chave do progresso individual e social. Todavía, foi nos anos 60 que a educaçao começou a atrair as atençôes dos economistas, dos políticos, dos organismos internacionais e dos movimentos revolucionarios. Com efeito, tiveram lugar certos acontecimentos que levaram a olhar mais de perto os processus e as instituiçôes educacionais. A elaboraçâo de teorías económicas da educaçao constituí um indicativo deste descente interesse pela educaçao e pelo saber. A concepçâo económica do « capital humano » contém, porém, pressupostos ideológicos que reforçam o modelo capitalista da sociedade. De qualquer modo, a educaçao, em termos de descimentó económico e mobilidade social, foi posta em evidencia em todos os países capitalistas desenvolvidos. Nos países capitalistas subdesenvolvidos, a crescente industrializaçâo também salientou o papel da educaçao na mudança social. Mas, além dos problemas do desenvolvimento capitalista nos países desenvolvidos e da industrializaçâo nos países capitalistas subdesenvolvidos, os anos 60 e os principios dos anos 70 proporcionaran! outras razöes para destacar a importancia da educaçao nas mudanças sociais. Designadamente, as reformas educacionais socialistas em Cuba, na China e, mais recentemente, em diversos países africanos constitiiem inspiraçao para novos e importantes estudos. Na revoluçâo socialista há a consciência de que a luta das classes também se manifesta nas escolas. Por outro lado, as teorías de confuto, marxistas e näo marxistas, também se aplicam à análise das reformas educacionais nas sociedades capitalistas. Estas teorías tentam estabelecer as bases para uma sociedade alternativa, baseada no valor do trabalho. Efectivamente, um projecto de mudanças educacionais como parte integrante de um processo de revoluçâo cultural deriva lógicamente de uma análise de classe das contradiçôes existentes na vida económica, política e cultural como um todo. L'éducation est d'habitude considérée un important outil impulsif de la transformation sociale. D'ailleurs, selon la théorie libérale, l'éducation a été toujours considérée comme une voie pour la mobilité sociale et la clef du progrès individuel et social Cependant c'est dans les années 60 que l'éducation a commencé à attirer l'attention des économistes, des politiques, des organismes internationaux et des mouvements révolutionnaires. En effet des événements ont eu Heu qui nous ont obligé de regarder, de plus près, les procès et les institutions de l'éducation. L'élaboration de théories économiques de l'éducation est un signe de cet intérêt croissant à l'égard de l'éducation et du sovoir. La conception économique du « . capital humain » a, toutefois, des présuppositions idéologiques qui renforcent le modèle capitaliste de la société. De toute façon, l'education, en termes de croissance économique et mobilité sociale, a été mise en évidence dans tous les pays capitalistes développés. Dans les pays capitalistes sous-développés, l'industrialisation croissante a aussi souligné le rôle de l'éducation dans la transformattion sociale. Mais, outre les problèmes du développement capitaliste dans les pays développés et de l'industrialisation dans les pays capitalistes sous-développés, les années 60 et les débuts des années 70 ont rendu possibles d'autres raisons pour remarquer l'importance de l'éducation dans les changements sociaux. Nommément les réformes éducationnelles socialistes à Cuba, en Chine et, plus récemment, dans plusieurs pays africains, sont une inspiration pour de nouvelles et importantes études. Dans la révolution socialiste, il y a la conscience que la lutte des classes se manifeste aussi à l'école. D'autre part, les théories de conflit, marxistes et non marxistes, s'appliquent aussi à l'analyse des réformes éducacionnelles dans les sociétés capitalistes. Ces théories essayent d'etblir les bases pour une société alternative, basée sur la valeur du travail. En effet, un projet de transformations éducationnelles en tant que partie intégrante d'un procès de révolution culturelle découle logiquement d'une analyse de classe des contradictions existentes dans la vie économique, politique et culturel comme un tout. Education is generally considered as an important instrument stimulating of social change. Besides, according to the liberal theory, education has always been considered as a path for the social mobility and the key for the individual and social progress.Nevertheless it was in the sixties that education start calling the attention of economists, politicians, international organisms and revolutionary movements. As a matter of fact there took place some events that led to look closer the educational processi and institutions. The elaboration of economic theories on education is a sign of this increasing interest in education and knowledge. But the economic conception of the « human capital » has some ideological presuppositions that reinforce the capitalist model of society. Anyway education, in terms of economic growth and social mobility became conspicuous in every developped capitalist country.In the under developped capitalist countries the rising industrialization has also underlined the role of education in social change. But, beyond those problems, concerning the capitalist development in developped countries and the industrialization in underdevelopped capitalist countries, the sixties and the beginnings of the seventies gave other reasons for remarking the importance of education in social change. Namely the socialist educational reforms in Cuba, China and, more recently, in several African countries are an inspiration for new and important studies. In the socialist revolution there is the consciousness that the class struggle also shows itself in school clearly 1 .On the other side, the conflict theories, marxist or non-marxist, also apply to the analysis of the educational reforms in capitalist societies. These theories try to establish the grounds for an alternative society, based on the value of work. Indeed a project of educational change as part and parcel of a processus of cultural revolution logically derives from a class analysis of the contradictions existing in the economic, political and cultural life as a whole.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>por</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d21164e113a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e120" publication-type="other">
M. J. Bowman, «The Human Investment Revolution in Economic Thought», in
Sociology of Education, vol. 39, 1966, pp. 111-138.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e130a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e137" publication-type="other">
M. Blaug, A Selected Annotated Bibliography in the Economics of Education,
Institute of Education, London University, 1964.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e147a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e154" publication-type="other">
M. Blaug, Economics of Education: A Selected Annotated Bibliography, Per-
gamon Press. 1966.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e164a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e171" publication-type="other">
W. G. Bowen, «Assessing the Economic Contribution of Education: An Apprai-
sal of Alternative Approaches», in Higher Education, Londres, 1961-63.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e182a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e189" publication-type="other">
M. Blaug, «The Correlation Between Education and Earnings: What Does It
Signifv?». in Hieher Education, Amsterdão. Elsevier Publishing Company.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e199a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e206" publication-type="other">
J. karabel e A. H. Halsey, «Educational Research: A Review and An Interpre-
tation», in Power and Ideology in Education, Nova Iorque, Oxford University Press,
1977.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e219a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e226" publication-type="other">
Ver Talcott Parsons, «Equality and Inequality in Modern Society or Social
Stratification Revised», in Sociological Inquiry, n.° 40, Primavera de 1970.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e236a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e243" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricœur, «Réforme et Révolution dans l'Université», in Esprit, n.&lt;sup&gt;os&lt;/sup&gt; 6-7,
Paris, 1968,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e253a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e260" publication-type="other">
A teoria de Paulo Freire até 1970 inclui a publicação de Education for Criticai
Consciousness, Pedagogy of the Opressed, and Cultural Action for Freedom, além de
numerosos artigos.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e273a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e280" publication-type="other">
Paulo Freire, «Education as the Practice of Freedom», in Education for Critical
Consciousness. Nova Iorque. The Seabury Press. 1973. pp. 5 e 7</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e291a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e298" publication-type="other">
Id. ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e305a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e312" publication-type="other">
Id. «Cultural Action for Freedom», in Harvard Education Review, «Mono-
graph Series», n.° 1, 1970, p. 28.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e322a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e329" publication-type="other">
Paulo Freire. «Pilgrims of the Obvious», in Risk, vol. 11. n.° 1. 1975, d. 15.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e336a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e343" publication-type="other">
Id., Cartas à Guiné-Bissau, Rio de Janeiro, Paz e Terra, 1977, p. 16.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e350a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e357" publication-type="other">
Henry Levin, «Educational Reform: Its Meaning?», in H. Levin e M. Carnoy,
The Limits of Educational Reform, Nova Iorque, David McKay, 1976, p. 38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e367a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e374" publication-type="other">
Id., ibid.,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e382a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e389" publication-type="other">
Samuel Bowles, «Unequal Education and Social Division of Labor», in M.
Carnoy, Schooling in a Corporate Society, Nova Iorque, David McKay, 1975. p. 61.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e399a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e406" publication-type="other">
Louis Althusser, «State and State Apparatuses», in Lenin and Philosophy,
Modern Reader, 1971.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e415" publication-type="other">
Pierre Bourdieu, A Economia das Trocas Simbólicas, São
Paulo, Ed. Perspectiva, 1974.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e424" publication-type="other">
P. Bourdieu e J. C. Passeron, La Reproduction, França,
Les Éditions de Minuit, 1970.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e434a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e441" publication-type="other">
Michael Spence, «Job Market Signalling», Quarterly Journal of Economics,
vol. Lxxxvii, Agosto de 1973.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e451a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e458" publication-type="other">
M. Carnoy e M. Carter, Theories of Labor Market, Education, and Income
Distribution, Stanford University.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e468a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e475" publication-type="other">
Martin Carnoy, «Class Analysis and Investment in Human Ressources: A
Dynamic Model», in Review of Radical Political Economy, Outono /Inverno de 1971.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21164e485a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21164e492" publication-type="other">
Samuel Bowles, Class Power and Mass Education,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
