<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">ecologysociety</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50015787</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Ecology and Society</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Resilience Alliance</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">17083087</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26268007</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Synthesis</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Influence of Philosophical Perspectives in Integrative Research</article-title>
            <subtitle>a Conservation Case Study in the Cairngorms National Park</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Evely</surname>
                  <given-names>Anna C.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">¹</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Fazey</surname>
                  <given-names>Ioan</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">²</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Pinard</surname>
                  <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">¹</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Lambin</surname>
                  <given-names>Xavier</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">¹</xref>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">
               <label>¹</label>Institute of Biological Sciences, Aberdeen University,</aff>
            <aff id="af2">
               <label>²</label>University of Wales, Aberystwyth</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>Dec 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">13</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26267950</issue-id>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2008 by the author(s)</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26268007"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>ABSTRACT.</label>
            <p>The benefits of increasing the contribution of the social sciences in the fields of environmental and conservation science disciplines are increasingly recognized. However, integration between the social and natural sciences has been limited, in part because of the barrier caused by major philosophical differences in the perspectives between these research areas. This paper aims to contribute to more effective interdisciplinary integration by explaining some of the philosophical views underpinning social research and how these views influence research methods and outcomes. We use a project investigating the motivation of volunteers working in an adaptive co-management project to eradicate American Mink from the Cairngorms National Park in Scotland as a case study to illustrate the impact of philosophical perspectives on research. Consideration of different perspectives promoted explicit reflection of the contributing researcher’s assumptions, and the implications of his or her perspectives on the outcomes of the research. We suggest a framework to assist conservation research projects by: (1) assisting formulation of research questions; (2) focusing dialogue between managers and researchers, making underlying worldviews explicit; and (3) helping researchers and managers improve longer-term strategies by helping identify overall goals and objectives and by identifying immediate research needs.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <label>Key Words:</label>
            <kwd>adaptive co-management</kwd>
            <kwd>interdisciplinarity</kwd>
            <kwd>philosophy</kwd>
            <kwd>social–ecological resilience</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>LITERATURE CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aars, J., X. Lambin, R. Denny, and A. C. Griffin. 2001. Water vole in the Scottish uplands: distribution patterns of disturbed and pristine populations ahead and behind the American mink invasion front. Animal Conservation 4:187–194.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Agrawal, A. 1999. Enchantment and disenchantment: the role of community in natural resource conservation. World Development 27:629–649.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bammer, G. 2005. Integration and implementation sciences: building a new specialization. Ecology and Society10: 6. [online] URL: http://www.ecolog yandsociety.org/vol10/iss2/art6/.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barry, D., and M. Oelschlaeger. 1996. A science for survival: values and conservation biology. Conservation Biology 10:905–911.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhasker, R. 1989. The possibility of naturalism. Harvester Wheatsheaf, Hemel Hasmpstead, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bourdieu, P. 1991. The peculiar history of scientific reason. Sociological Forum 6:3–26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brandt, R. B. 1957. The languages of realism and nominalism. Philosophy and Phenomenological Research 17:516–535.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown, R. H. 1987. Positivism, relativism, and narrative in the logic of the historical sciences. The American Historical Review 92:908–920.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown, J. R. 1998. Explaining the success of science. Pages 1136–1152 in M. Curd and J. A. Cover, editors. Philosophy of science: the central issues. Norton, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bruce, A., C. Lyall, J. Tait, and R. Williams. 2004.Interdisciplinary integration in Europe: the case of the Fifth Framework programme. Futures 36:457–470.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burgess, J. P. 1983. Why I am not a nominalist. Notre Dame Journal of Formal Logic 24:93–105.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Byrne, L. 2005. Powered by politics: reforming parties from the inside. Parliamentary Affairs 58:611–620.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Callicott, J. B., L. B. Crowder, and K. Mumford. 1999. Current normative concepts in conservation. Conservation Biology 13:22–35.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chakravarrty, A. 2004. Structuralism as a form of scientific realism. International Studies in the Philosophy of Science 18:151–171.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cheng, A. S., L. E. Kruger, and S. E. Daniels. 2003. “Place” as an integrating concept in natural resource politics: propositions for a social science research agenda. Society and Natural Resources 16:7–104.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Crane, A. 1999. Are you ethical? Please tick yes or no. On researching ethics in business organizations. Business Ethics 20:237–248.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Craik, C. 1997. Long-term effects of North American mink Mustela vison on seabirds in western Scotland. Bird Study 44:303–309.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Crockett, C. 1950. The confusion over nominalism. The Journal of Philosophy 47:752–758</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Czech, B., and P. R. Krausman. 1997. Distribution and causation of species endangerment in the United States. Science 277:1116–1117.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Department for Environment Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA). 2003. Biodiversity youth engagement project final report. [online] URL: htt p://www.defra.gov.uk/schools/pdf/cyp-bio-report-print. pdf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dyson, S., and B. Brown. 2006. Social theory and applied health research. Open University Press, Glasgow, Scotland.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eger, M. 1993. Hermeneutics as an approach to science: Part I. Science and Education 2:1–29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eger, M. 1997. Achievements of the hermeneutic–phenomenological approach to natural science: a comparison with constructivist sociology. Man and World 30:343–367.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eigenbrode, S. D., M. O’Rourke, J. D. Wulfhorst, D. M. Althoff, C. S. Goldberg, K. Merrill, W. Morse, M. Nielsen-Pincus, J. Stephens, L. Winowiecki, and N. A. Bosque-Pérez. 2007.Employing philosophical dialogue in collaborative science. Bioscience 57:55–64.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fazey, I., J. A. Fazey, J. G. Salisbury, D. B. Lindenmayer, and S. Dovers. 2006. The nature and role of experiential knowledge for environmental conservation. Environmental Conservation 33:1–10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferreras, P., and D. W. Macdonald. 1999. The impact of American mink Mustela vison on water birds in the upper Thames. Journal of Applied Ecology 36:701–708.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Feyerabend, P. K. 1962. Explanation, reduction and empiricism. Minnesota Studies in the Philosophy of Science 3:28–97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Feyerabend, P. K. 1981a. Realism, rationalism and scientific method. Philosophical Papers 1, Cambridge University Press, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Feyerabend, P. K. 1981b. Problems of empiricism. Philosophical Papers 2, Cambridge University Press, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Firestone, W. A. 1987. Meaning in method: the rhetoric of quantitative and qualitative research. Educational Researcher 16:16–21</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fox, H. E., C. Christian, J. C. Nordby, O. R. W. Pergams, G. D. Peterson, and C. R. Pyke. 2006.Perceived barriers to integrating social science and conservation. Conservation Biology 20:1817–1820.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gadamer, H. G. 1993. Truth and method. J. Weinsheimer and D. Marshall, translators. Continuum, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gewirth, A. 1954. Subjectivism and objectivism in the social sciences. Philosophy of Science 21:157–163.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gittell, M. 1980. Limits of citizen participation: the decline of community organisations. Sage Publications, Beverly Hills, California, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Graybill, J. K., S. Dooling, V. Shandas, J. Withey, A. Greve, and G. I. Simon. 2006. A rough guide to interdisciplinarity: graduate student perspectives. Bioscience 56:757–763.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hellman, G. 2001. On nominalism. Philosophy and Phenomenological Research 62:691–705.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Houston, S. 2001. Beyond social constructivism: critical realism and social work. British Journal of Social Work 31:845–861.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Huntington, H. P. 2000. Using traditional ecological knowledge in science: methods and applications. Ecological Applications 10:1270–1274.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Husserl, E. 1962. Ideas. Collier, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Husserl, E. 1965. Phenomenology and the crisis of philosophy. Harper Torchbooks, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kotchen, M. J., and S. D. Reiling. 2000.Environmental attitudes, motivations, and contingent valuation of nonuse values: a case study involving endangered species. Ecological Economics 32:93–107.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kuhn, T. S. 1977. The essential tension: selected studies in scientific tradition and change. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, Illinois, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lane, M. B., and G. McDonald. 2005. Community based environmental planning: operational dilemmas, planning principles and possible remedies. Environmental Planning and Management 48:709–731.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lawrence, R. L., and D. A. Deagen. 2001.Choosing public participation methods for natural resources: a context-specific guide. Society and Natural Resources 14:857–872.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lélé, S., and R. B. Norgaard. 2005. Practicing interdisciplinarity. BioScience 55:967–975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Macdonald D. W., C. M. King, and R. Strachan. 2006. Introduced species and the line between biodiversity conservation and naturalistic eugenics. Key Topics in conservation Biology. [online] URL: http://bio.waikato.ac.nz/pdfs/staff/cmking/macdonald_king_and_strahan_2007.pdf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Manchester, S. J., and J. M. Bullock. 2000. The impacts of non-native species on UK biodiversity and the effectiveness of control. Journal of Applied Ecology 37:845–864.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marcuse, H. 1965. On Science and phenomenology. Pages 279–290 in R. S. Cohen and M. W. Wartofsky, editors. Boston studies in the philosophy of science, 2. Humanities Press, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marran, T., and H. Henttonen. 1995. Why is the European mink (Mustela lutreola) disappearing? A review of the process and hypotheses. Annales Zoologici Fennici 32:47–54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mayer, P. 2006. Biodiversity—the appreciation of different thought styles and values helps to clarify the term. Restoration Ecology 14:105–111.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Millennium Ecosystem Assessment (MA). 2005.Millennium ecosystem assessment. Ecosystems and human well-being. Island Press, Washington, D.C., USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moran, D. 2000. Introduction to phenomenology. Routledge, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morgan, G., and L. Smircich. 1980. The case for qualitative research. Academy of Management. The Academy of Management Review 5:491–500.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newell, W. H. 2001. A theory of interdisciplinary studies. Issues in Integrative Studies 19:1–25.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nyhus, P. J., F. R. Westley, R. C. Lacy, and P. S. Miller. 2002. A role for natural resource social science in biodiversity risk assessment. Society and Natural Resources 15:923–932.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Olsson, P., C. Folke, and F. Berkes. 2004. Adaptive co-management for building resilience in socio–ecological systems. Environmental Management 34:75–90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Orr, D. W. 2002. Four challenges of sustainability. Conservation Biology 16:1457–1460.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parsons, S. D. 1999. Why the “transcendental” in transcendental realism? Pages 151–168 in S. Fleetwood, editor. Critical realism in economics: development and debate. Routledge, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Peterson, M. N., T. R. Peterson, M. J. Peterson, R. R. Lopez, and N. J. Silvy. 2002. Cultural conflict and the endangered Florida Key deer. Wildlife Management 66:947–968.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Petrie, H. G. 1976. Do you see what i see? The epistemology of interdisciplinary inquiry. Journal of Aesthetic Education 10:29–43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Redpath, S. M., B. E. Arroyo, F. M. Leckie, P. Bacon, N. Bayfield, R. J. Gutiérrez, and S. J. Thirgood. 2004. Using decision modeling with stakeholders to reduce human–wildlife conflict: a raptor-grouse case study. Conservation Biology 18:350–359.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reich, S. M., and J. A. Reich. 2006. Cultural competence in interdisciplinary collaborations: a method for respecting diversity in research partnerships. American Journal of Community Psychology 38:51–62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reynolds, J. C., M. J. Short, and R. J. Leigh. 2004.Development of population control strategies for mink Mustela vison, using floating rafts as monitors and trap sites. Biological Conservation 120:533–543.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, P. 1978a. Explanation and understanding: on some remarkable connections among the theory of text, theory of action, and theory of history. Pages 149–166 in C. E. Reagan and D. Stewart, editors. The philosophy of Paul Ricoeur. Beacon Press, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, P. 1978b. Existential phenomenology. Page 75–85 in C. E. Reagan and D. Stewart, editors. The philosophy of Paul Ricoeur. Beacon Press, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, P. 1978c. Structure, word, event. Pages 109–119 in C. E. Reagan and D. Stewart, editors. The philosophy of Paul Ricoeur. Beacon Press, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robertson, D. P., and B. Hull. 2001. Beyond biology: toward a more public ecology for conservation. Conservation Biology 15:970–979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roebuck, P., and P. Phifer. 1998. The persistence of positivism in conservation biology. Conservation Biology 13:444–446.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ryan, R. L., R. Kaplan, and R. Grese. 2001.Predicting volunteer commitment in environmental stewardship programme. Journal of Environmental Planning and Management 44:629–648.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref70">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sawa, R. J. 2005. Foundations of interdisciplinary: a Lonergan perspective. Medicine, Health Care and Philosophy 8:53–61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref71">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shepherd, A., and C. Bowler. 1997. Beyond the requirements: improving public participation in EIA. Environmental Planning and Management 40:725–738.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref72">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shepard, K. F., G. M. Jensen, B. J. Schrnoll, and J. Gwye. 1992. Alternative approaches to research in physical therapy: positivism and phenomenology. Physical Therapy 73:34–47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref73">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Skinner, B. F. 1957. Verbal behaviour. Macmillan, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref74">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Skinner, B. F. 1965. Science and human behaviour. Macmillan, New York, New York, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref75">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sneed, J. D. 1982. Structuralism and scientific realism. Erkenntnis 19:345––370.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref76">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Song, S. J., and M. M. M’Gonigle. 2001. Science, power and system dynamics: the political economy of conservation biology. Conservation Biology 15:980–989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref77">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Soulé, M. E. 1985. What is conservation biology? BioScience 35:727–734.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref78">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Steffy, B. D., and A. J. Grimes. 1986. A critical theory of organization science. The Academy of Management Review 11:322–336.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref79">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stoll-Kleeman, S., and T. O’Riordan. 2002.Enhancing biodiversity and humanity. Pages 295–310 in T. O’Riordan and S. Stoll-Kleeman, editors. Biodiversity, sustainability and human communities, protecting beyond the protected. The University of Cambridge Press, Cambridge, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref80">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Strachan, C., R. Strachan, and D. Jefferies. 2000.Preliminary report on the changes in the water vole population of Britain as shown by the national survey of 1989–1990 and 1996–1998. The Vincent Wildlife Trust, London, UK.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref81">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Scottish Government. 2006. Statistics.[online] URL: http://www.scotland.gov.uk.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref82">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Toulmin, S. 1972. Human understanding. Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref83">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tress, G., B. Tress, and G. Fry. 2004. Clarifying integrative research concepts in landscape ecology. Landscape Ecology 20:479–493.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref84">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Viskovatoff, A. 2002. Critical realism and Kantian transcendental arguments. Cambridge Journal of Economics 26:697–708.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref85">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Volunteer Development Scotland (VDS). 2007.Volunteer Deveopment Scotland homepage.[online] URL: http://www.vds.org.uk.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref86">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Walpole, M. J., and H. J. Goodwin. 2001. Local attitudes towards conservation and tourism around Komodo National Park, Indonesia. Environmental Conservation 28:160–166.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref87">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Weber. E. P. 1998. Pluralism by the rules: conflict and cooperation in environmental regulation. Georgetown University Press, Washington, D.C., USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref88">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Weston, M., M. Fendley, R. Jewell, M. Satchell, and C. Tzaros. 2003. Volunteers in bird conservation: insights from the Australian Threatened Bird Network. Ecological Management and Restoration 4(3):205–211.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref89">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">White, R., A. Fischer, H. P. Hansen, R. Varjopuro, J. Young, and M. Ademescu. 2005. Conflict management, participation, social learning and attitudes in biodiversity conservation. [online] URL: http://www.alternet.info/SITE/UPLOAD/DOCUMENT/outputs%5CANet_WPR4_2005_03_Confl_Part_SL_Attitudes2.pdf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref90">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wondolleck, J. M., and S. L. Yaffee. 2000. Making collaboration work: lessons from innovation in natural resource management. Island Press, Washington, D.C., USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref91">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yeung, H. W. 1997. Critical realism and realist research in human geography: a method or a philosophy in search of a method? Progress in Human Geography 21:51–74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
