<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">histsocres</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000891</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Historical Social Research / Historische Sozialforschung</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01726404</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">44425359</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Special Issue: Critique and Social Change: Historical, Cultural, and Institutional Perspectives</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Critique and Social Change: An Introduction</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                  <surname>Kern</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                  <surname>Laux</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Insa</given-names>
                  <surname>Pruisken</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">42</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40185962</issue-id>
         <fpage>7</fpage>
         <lpage>23</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© GESIS</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/44425359"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This introduction of the HSR Special Issue on "Critique and Social Change: Historical, Cultural, and Institutional Perspectives" addresses the question of how critique and social change are interrelated. Conflicts and disputes are considered to be a major source of critique. We distinguish three types of conflicts: (1) Value conflicts result from the ongoing process of rationalization and the differentiation of relatively autonomous "value spheres" (Weber) such as politics, economy, science, law, etc. (2) The growth and expansion of these value spheres, e.g. the growth of capitalism, in turn produce new forms of inequalities and leads to distributional conflicts. (3) As questions of distribution and inclusion are closely linked, critique also originates from identity conflicts, which address the social recognition of individuals and collectivities. In order to understand how critique is related to social change, we suggest that critique can be studied either as a condition for or as an effect from social change. Based on this distinction we provide an overview over the contributions of this volume.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1421e147a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1421e154" publication-type="other">
Celikates (2009)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1421e161a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1421e168" publication-type="other">
Mahoney and Goertz 2006, 230</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Special References</title>
         <ref id="d1421e184a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e188" publication-type="other">
Adloff, Frank, and Larissa Pfaller. 2017. Critique in Statu Nascendi? The Reluc-
tance towards Organ Donation. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 24-40. doi:
10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.24-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e201a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e205" publication-type="other">
Centemeri, Laura. 2017. From Public Participation to Place-Based Resistance.
Environmental Critique and Modes of Valuation in the Struggles against the Ex-
pansion of the Malpensa Airport. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 97-122. doi:
10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.97-122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e225" publication-type="other">
Diaz-Bone, Rainer. 2017. Discourses, Conventions, and Critique — Perspectives of
the Institutionalist Approach of the Economics of Convention. Historical Social
Research 42 (3): 79-96. doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.79-96.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e238a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e242" publication-type="other">
Dosdall, Henrik, and Byron Rom-Jensen. 2017. Letting Lehman Go. Critique,
Social Change and the Demise of Lehman Brothers. Historical Social Research
42 (3): 196-217. doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.196-217.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e260" publication-type="other">
Kem, Thomas, and Thomas Laux. 2017. Revolution or Negotiated Regime Change?
Structural Dynamics in the Process of Democratization. The Case of South Korea
in the 1980s. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 245-74. doi: 10.12759/
hsr.42.2017.3.245-274.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e276a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e280" publication-type="other">
Kusche, Isabel. 2017. The Accusation of Clientelism: On the Interplay between
Social Science, Mass Media, and Politics in the Critique of Irish Democracy. His-
torical Social Research 42 (3): 172-95. doi: 10. 12759/hsr.42.2017.3. 172-195.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e293a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e297" publication-type="other">
Münnich, Sascha. 2017. Outside Powers. The Moral Economy of Anti-Financial
Movements 1870-1930 and Today. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 123-46.
doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.123-146.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e310a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e314" publication-type="other">
Pruisken, Insa. 2017. Institutional Logics and Critique in German Academic Sci-
ence. Studying the Merger of the Karlsruhe Institute of Technology. Historical
Social Research 42 (3): 218-44. doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.218-244.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e327a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e331" publication-type="other">
Sachweh, Patrick. 2017. Criticizing Inequality? How Ideals of Equality Do — and
Do Not — Contribute to the De-Legitimation of Inequality in Contemporary Ger-
many. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 62-78. doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.62-
78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e347a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e351" publication-type="other">
Schwarz, Christine. 2017. Going Underground: Merging Collaboration with Micro-
Resistance. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 41-61. doi: 10.12759/hsr.42.
2017.3.41-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e365a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e369" publication-type="other">
Wallmeier, Philip. 2017. Exit as Critique. Communes and Intentional Communities
in the 1960s and Today. Historical Social Research 42 (3): 147-71. doi:
10.12759/hsr.42.2017.3.147-171.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d1421e391a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e395" publication-type="other">
Akchurin, Maria, and Cheol-Sung Lee. 2013. Pathways to empowerment: Reper-
toires of women's activism and gender earnings. American Sociological Review
78 (4): 679-701.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e408a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e412" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C. 1982. Theoretical Logic in Sociology: Positivism, presupposi-
tions, and current controversies, Volume 1. Berkely: University of California
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e425a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e429" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C. 1987. Twenty Lectures. Sociological Theory Since World War
II. New York: Columbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e439a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e443" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C. 1990. Core solidarity, ethnic outgroups, and social differenti-
ation. In Differentiation Theory and Social Change. Comparative and Historical
Perspectives, ed. Jeffrey C. Alexander and Paul Colomy, 267-93. New York: Co-
lumbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e460a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e464" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C. 2002. On the Construction of Moral Universals. The Holo-
caust from War Crime to Trauma Drama. European Journal Of Social Theory 5
(1): 5-85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e477a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e481" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C. 2004. Cultural Pragmatics: Social Performance between
Ritual and Strategy. Sociological Theory 22 (4): 527-73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e491a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e495" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C., and Philip Smith. 2002. The Strong Program in Cultural
Theory. Elements of a Structural Hermeneutics. In Handbook of Sociological
Theory, ed. Jonathan H. Turner, 135-50. New York: Springer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e508a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e512" publication-type="other">
Alexander, Jeffrey C., Bernhard Giesen, and Jason L. Mast, eds. 2006. Social Per-
formance. Symbolic action, cultural pragmatics, and ritual. Cambridge: Cam-
bridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e525a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e529" publication-type="other">
Beach, Derek, and Rasmus Brun Pedersen. 2013. Process-Tracing Methods. Ann
Arbor: The University of Michigan Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e539a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e543" publication-type="other">
Benhabib, Seyla. 1999. Kulturelle Vielfalt und demokratische Gleichheit: politische
Partizipation im Zeitalter der Globalisierung. Frankfurt a. M.: Fischer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e554a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e558" publication-type="other">
Bennett, Andrew, and Jeffrey T. Checkel. 2015. Process tracing: From philosophi-
cal roots to best practices. In Process Tracing. From metaphor to analytical tool,
ed. Andrew Bennett and Jeffrey T. Checkel, 3-38. Cambridge: Cambridge Uni-
versity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e574a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e578" publication-type="other">
Berger, Peter L., and Thomas Luckmann. 1966. The Social Construction of Reality:
A Treatise in the Sociology of Knowledge. London: Penguin Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e588a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e592" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc, and Eve Chiapello. 2005. The New Spirit of Capitalism. London,
New York: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e602a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e606" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc, and Laurent Thévenot. 1999. The Sociology of Critical Capacity.
European Journal of Social Theory 2 (3): 359-77.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e616a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e620" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc, and Laurent Thévenot. 2006. On Justification: Economies of Worth.
Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e630a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e634" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc, and Laurent Thévenot. 2014. Über die Rechtfertigung. Hamburg:
Hamburger Edition.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e645a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e649" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc, Axel Honneth, and Robin Celikates. 2014. Sociology of Critique or
Critical Theory? Luc Boltanski and Axel Honneth in Conversation with Robin
Celikates. In The Spirit of Luc Boltanski. Essays on the Pragmatic Sociology of
Critique, ed. Simon Susen and Brian S. Turner, 561-89. London: Anthem Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e665a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e669" publication-type="other">
Boltanski, Luc. 2010. Soziologie und Sozialkritik. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e676a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e680" publication-type="other">
Castells, Manuel. 2010. The Power of Identity. Oxford: Blackwell Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e687a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e691" publication-type="other">
Castoriadis, Cornelius. 1998. The Imaginary Institution of Society. Cambridge, MA:
MIT Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e701a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e705" publication-type="other">
Celikates, Robin. 2009. Kritik als soziale Praxis: Gesellschaftliche Selbstverständi-
gung und kritische Theorie. Frankfurter Beiträge zur Soziologie und Sozialphilo-
sophie 13. Frankfurt a. M.: Campus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e718a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e722" publication-type="other">
Collier, David. 2011. Understanding Process Tracing. PS: Political Science and
Politics 44 (4): 823-30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e733a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e737" publication-type="other">
Coser, Lewis A. 1984. Introduction. In The Division of Labor in Society, ed. Emile
Durkheim, ix-xxiv. New York: The Free Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e747a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e751" publication-type="other">
Dahrendorf, Ralf. 1979. Lebenschancen. Anläufe zur sozialen und politischen Theo-
rie. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e761a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e765" publication-type="other">
Diaz-Bone, Rainer. 2015. Die "Economie des Conventions": Grundlagen und
Entwicklungen der neuen französischen Wirtschaftssoziologie. Wiesbaden:
Springer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e778a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e782" publication-type="other">
Dörre, Klaus, Stephan Lessenich, and Hartmut Rosa, eds. 2009. Soziologie — Kapi-
talismus — Kritik. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e792a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e796" publication-type="other">
Durkheim, Emile. 1964. The Divison of Labor in Society. New York: Free Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e803a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e807" publication-type="other">
Earl, Jennifer. 2007. The cultural consequences of social movements. In The
Blackwell Companion to Social Movements, ed. David A. Snow, Sarah A. Soule
and Hanspeter Kriesi, 508-30. Maiden, Oxford, Victoria: Blackwell Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e821a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e825" publication-type="other">
Eisenstadt, Shmuel N. 1982. The Axial Age: The Emergence of Transcendental
Visions and the Rise of Clerics. European Journal of Sociology 23 (2): 294-314.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e835a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e839" publication-type="other">
Fraser, Nancy. 1997. Justice Interruptus: Critical Reflections on the postsocialist
Condition. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e849a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e853" publication-type="other">
Geertz, Clifford. 1973. Thick Description: Toward an Interpretive Theory of Cul-
ture. In The Interpretation of Cultures: Selected Essays, ed. Clifford Geertz, 3-30.
New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e866a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e870" publication-type="other">
Giugni, Marco, Doug McAdam, and Charles Tilly, eds. 1999. How Social Move-
ments matter. Minneapolis, London: University of Minnesota Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e880a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e884" publication-type="other">
Goertz, Gary, and James Mahoney. 2012. A Tale of Two Cultures. Princeton, Ox-
ford: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e894a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e898" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1992. Faktizität und Geltung. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e906a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e910" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1995a. Theorie des kommunikativen Handelns, Band 1. Frank-
furt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e920a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e924" publication-type="other">
Habermas, Jürgen. 1995b. Theorie des kommunikativen Handelns, Band 2. Frank-
furt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e934a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e938" publication-type="other">
Hirschman, Albert O. 1985. Exit, Voice, and Loyalty: Responses to decline in
Firms, Organizations, and States. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e948a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e952" publication-type="other">
Honneth, Axel. 1994: Kampf um Anerkennung. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e959a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e963" publication-type="other">
Kern, Thomas. 2007. Modernisierung und Demokratisierung: Das Erklärungspoten-
zial neuerer differenzierungstheoretischer Ansätze. Kölner Zeitschrift für Sozio-
logie und Sozialpsychologie 59 (1): 30-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e976a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e980" publication-type="other">
Kern, Thomas. 2008: Soziale Bewegungen. Ursachen, Wirkungen, Mechanismen.
Wiesbaden: VS-Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e991a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e995" publication-type="other">
Kern, Thomas. 2009. Cultural Performance and Political Regime Change: The
Democratic Transition of South Korea in the 1980s. Sociological Theory 27 (3):
291-316.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1008a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1012" publication-type="other">
Laux, Thomas. 2015. Nationalstaatliche Prozesse oder globale Strukturen? Eine
Analyse der Mechanismen zur Gleichstellung von Frauen im Recht. Berliner
Journal für Soziologie 24 (4):531-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1025a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1029" publication-type="other">
Laux, Thomas. 2016. Die Institutionalisierung von Lohngleichheitsrechten. Eine
vergleichende Analyse von OECD Staaten. Zeitschrift fur Soziologie 45 (6): 393-
409.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1042a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1046" publication-type="other">
Lepsius, M. Rainer. 1990. Interessen, Ideen und Institutionen. Opladen: Westdeut-
scher Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1056a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1060" publication-type="other">
Luhmann, Niklas. 1998. Die Gesellschaft der Gesellschaft. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhr-
kamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1070a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1074" publication-type="other">
Mahoney, James, and Gary Goertz. 2006. A Tale of Two Cultures: Contrasting
Quantitative and Qualitative Research. Political Analysis 14: 227-49.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1085a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1089" publication-type="other">
Marshall, Thomas Humphrey. 1992. Citizenship and Social Class, in Inequality and
Society, ed. Jeff Manza and Michael Sauer, 1-7. New York: W.W. Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1099a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1103" publication-type="other">
Mayntz, Renate. 2002. Zur Theoriefahigkeit makro-sozialer Analysen. In Akteure —
Mechanismen — Modelle. Zur Theoriefahigkeit makro-sozialer Analysen, ed. Re-
nate Mayntz, 7-43. Frankfurt a. M., New York: Campus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1116a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1120" publication-type="other">
Mayntz, Renate. 2004. Mechanisms in the Analysis of Social Macro-Phenomena.
Philosophy of the Social Sciences 34 (2): 237-59.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1130a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1134" publication-type="other">
Melucci, Alberto. 1996. Challenging Codes. Collective Action in the Information
Age. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1144a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1148" publication-type="other">
Munch, Richard. 1995. Dynamik der Kommunikationsgesellschaft. Frankturt a. M.:
Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1158a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1162" publication-type="other">
Parsons, Talcott. 1965. Full Citizenship for the Negro American? A Sociological
Problem. Daedalus 94 (4): 1009-54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1173a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1177" publication-type="other">
Potthast, Jörg. 2001. Der Kapitalismus ist kritisierbar. Le nouvel esprit du capita-
lisme und das Forschungsprogramm der "Soziologie der Kritik". Berliner Jour-
nal fur Soziologie 24 (4): 551-62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1190a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1194" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1976. Interpretation Theory: Discourse and the Surplus of Meaning.
Fort Worth: Texas Christian University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1204a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1208" publication-type="other">
Rosa, Hartmut. 2009. Kapitalismus als Dynamisierungsspirale — Soziologie als
Gesellschaftskritik. In Soziologie, Kapitalismus, Kritik. Eine Debatte, ed. Klaus
Dörre, Stephan Lessenich and Hartmut Rosa, 87-125. Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1225" publication-type="other">
Rucht, Dieter, and Friedhelm Neidhardt. 1999. Methodological Issues in Collecting
Protest Event Data. In Acts of Dissent: New Developments in the Study of Protest,
ed. Dieter Rucht, Ruud Koopmans and Friedhelm Neidhardt, 65-89. Lanham:
Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1241a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1247" publication-type="other">
Rucht, Dieter. 1991: Sociological Theory as a Theory of Social Movements. A
Critique of Alain Touraine. In Research on Social Movements. The State of the
Art in Western Europe and the United States, ed. Dieter Rucht, 355-84. Frankfurt
a. M.: Campus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1263a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1267" publication-type="other">
Rüschemeyer, Dietrich. 1977. Structural Differentiation, Efficiency, and Power.
The American Journal of Sociology 83: 1-25.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1278a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1282" publication-type="other">
Schimank, Uwe, and Ute Volkmann. 1999. Gesellschaftliche Differenzierung.
Bielefeld: Transcript.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1296" publication-type="other">
Schimank, Uwe. 2013. Gesellschaft. Bielefeld: Transcript.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1303a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1307" publication-type="other">
Schimank, Uwe. 2015. Modernity as a functionally differentiated capitalist society:
A general theoretical model. European Journal of Social Theory 18 (4): 413-30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1317a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1321" publication-type="other">
Schumpeter, Joseph A. 1975: Capitalism, Socialism, and Democracy. New York:
Harper.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1331a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1335" publication-type="other">
Schütz, Alfred, and Thomas Luckmann. 1973. The Structures of the Life-World.
Evanston: Northwestern University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1345a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1349" publication-type="other">
Sorensen, Aage B. 2000. Toward a Sounder Basis for Class Analysis. The American
Journal of Sociology 105 (6): 1523-58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1360a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1364" publication-type="other">
Swidler, Ann. 1986. Culture in Action: Symbols and Strategies. American Sociolog-
ical Review 51 (2): 273-86.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1374a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1378" publication-type="other">
Tilly, Charles. 2008. Contentious Performances. Cambridge: Cambridge University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1388a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1392" publication-type="other">
Touraine, Alain. 1971. The Post-Industrial Society. Tomorrow's Social History:
Classes, Conflicts and Culture in the Programmed Society. New York: Random
House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1405a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1409" publication-type="other">
Touraine, Alam. 1981. The Voice and the Eye. An Analysis of Social Movements.
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1419a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1423" publication-type="other">
Touraine, Alain. 1995. Critique of Modernity. Oxford, Cambridge: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1430a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1434" publication-type="other">
Vobruba, Goerg. 2010. Die Gesellschaft der Leute. Wiebaden: VS Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1442a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1446" publication-type="other">
Vobruba, Goerg. 2017. Die Kritikkontroverse. Probleme der Unterscheidung von
Praxis und Theorie. Soziologie 46 (2): 173-90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1456a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1460" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1958. Science as a Vocation. Daedalus 87 (1): 111-34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1467a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1471" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1968. Economy and Society. An Outline of Interpretive Sociology.
Berkely: University of California Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1421e1481a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1421e1485" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. 1986. Gesammelte Aufsätze zur Religionssoziologie (Band 1). Tü-
bingen: J.C.B. Mohr.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
