<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerjtheophil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">American Journal of Theology and Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01943448</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21564795</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">amerjtheophil.35.2.0093</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5406/amerjtheophil.35.2.0093</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Self-Reliance and the Portability of Pragmatism</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Neville</surname>
                  <given-names>Robert Cummings</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>14</day>
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>May 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">35</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">amerjtheophil.35.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>93</fpage>
         <lpage>107</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2014 by the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/amerjtheophil.35.2.0093"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Flush with the juices of adolescence, American philosophy declared independence from its European parentage in the work of Ralph Waldo Emerson and his generation. In 1837, Emerson addressed the Harvard Phi Beta Kappa Society on the occasion of its inaugural meeting for the year, which he called a "holiday." Emerson began: I greet you on the recommencement of our literary year. Our anniversary is one of hope, and, perhaps, not enough of labor. We do not meet for games of strength or skill, for the recitation of histories, tragedies, and odes, like the ancient Greeks; for parliaments of love and poesy, like the Troubadours; nor for the advancement of science, like our contemporaries in the British and European capitals. Thus far, our holiday has been simply a friendly sign of the survival of the love of letters amongst a people too busy to give letters any more. Perhaps the time is already come when it ought to be, and will be something else; when the sluggard intellect of this continent will look from under its iron lids and fill the postponed expectations of the world with something better than the expectations of mechanical skill. Our day of dependence, our long apprenticeship to the learning of other lands, draws to a close. The millions that around us are rushing into life, cannot always be fed on the sere remains of foreign harvests. Events, actions arise, that must be sung, that will sing themselves.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>"The American Scholar," in<italic>Selected Writings of Emerson,</italic>ed. Brooks Atkinson (New York: The Modern Library, 1940), 45.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For an early expression of this, see his<italic>Nature</italic>beginning with the introductory paragraph, Ibid., 3. I have discussed Emerson's notion of an "original relation to the universe" in<italic>Religion in Late Modernity</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 2002), 188–99.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Edwards wrote, "I answer, the affections are no other, than the more vigorous and sensible exercises of the inclination and will of the soul." See his<italic>A Treatise concerning Religious Affections,</italic>ed. John E. Smith, vol. 2 in<italic>The Works of Jonathan Edwards</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1959), 96. Note that the affections are not the inclinations but the exercises of them, and it is the exercises as habitual behavior that Edwards proceeds to analyze. Smith's fine introduction to that volume spells out the European figures with whom Emerson took himself to be in conversation.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, for instance, his early essay, "Some Consequences of Four Incapacities," in<italic>The Essential Peirce,</italic>vol. 1, ed. Nathan Houser and Christian Kloesel (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1992), chap. 3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, for instance,<italic>The Religious Affections,</italic>119–121.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I have systematized Peirce's semiotic theory with an eye to being able to say what make certain interpretive experiences "religious experiences" when drugs (or the devil) can constitute the material reality of religious symbols; see "A Semiotic Theory of Religious Experience," in<italic>Experience, Interpretation, and Community: Themes in John E. Smith's Reconstruction of Philosophy,</italic>ed. Vincent M. Colapietro (Newcastle upon Tyne, UK: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2011), 43–78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a detailed analysis of these matters, see Wesley J. Wildman's<italic>Religious and Spiritual Experiences</italic>(Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2011), especially chap. 7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The language of "carrying across" is my own, developed in the theory of truth defended at length in<italic>Recovery of the Measure</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989), pt. 1. That theory was inspired in significant measure by Edwards's theory of signs as well as that of Peirce.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Edwards discussed beauty in his writings from adolescence onward. Many of his major discussions are in<italic>Ethical Writings: The Works of Jonathan Edwards,</italic>vol. 8, ed. Paul Ramsey (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1989). The language of "consent to being in general" is in<italic>The Nature of True Virtue,</italic>in that volume, 537–628.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Immanuel Kant,<italic>Critique of Pure Reason,</italic>trans. Norman Kemp Smith (London: Macmillan, 1956), 20, B xii–xiii.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, for instance, Husserl's<italic>Ideas,</italic>trans. W. R. Boyce Gibson (New York: Collier Books, 1962), 46, where he wrote, "The World is the totality of objects that can be known through experience, known in terms of orderly theoretical thought on the basis of direct present experience."</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On the important distinction between experience in British Empiricism and in pragmatic philosophy, see John E. Smith's<italic>The Spirit of American Philosophy</italic>(rev. ed. (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1984), especially chap 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Terrence W. Deacon,<italic>Incomplete Nature: How Mind Emerged from Matter</italic>(New York: W. W. Norton, 2012), especially chaps. 0–5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Peirce's essay "Pragmatism," in<italic>The Essential Peirce,</italic>vol. 2, chap. 28</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>
               <italic>The Essential Peirce,</italic>vol. 1, chaps. 2 and 3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kant wrote, in reference to the succession of representations of a house in the temporal order of inner sense: That which lies in the successive apprehension is here viewed as representation, while the appearance which is given to me,<italic>notwithstanding that it is nothing but the sum of these representations,</italic>is viewed as their object. And my concept, which I derive from the representations of apprehension, has to agree with it. Since truth consists in the agreement of knowledge with the object, it will at once be seen that we can here inquire only regarding the formal conditions of empirical truth, and that appearance, in contradistinction to the representations of apprehension, can be represented as an object distinct from them only if it stands under a rule which distinguishes it from every other apprehension and necessitates some one particular mode of connection of the manifold. The object is<italic>that</italic>in the appearance which contains the condition of this necessary rule of apprehension. Kant,<italic>Critique of Pure Reason,</italic>220, B 236. The first italicized passage is mine, the second is Kemp Smith's.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 78, B 52–53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 185, B 184.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See "Questions concerning Certain Faculties Claimed for Man," in<italic>Essential Peirce,</italic>vol. 1, 15.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On Peirce's waning enthusiasm for the nineteenth-century idea of intellectual progress, toward the "infinite long run," see Rulon Wells, "Charles S. Peirce as an American," in<italic>Perspectives on Peirce: Critical Essays on Charles Sanders Peirce,</italic>ed. Richard J. Bernstein (New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1965). On this general interpretation of Peirce, see my<italic>The Highroad around Modernism</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 1992), chap. 1.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On purpose in the pragmatic theory of interpretation and experience, see John E. Smith's<italic>Purpose and Thought: The Meaning of Pragmatism</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1978).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>My version of this philosophical cosmology is in<italic>Recovery of the Measure</italic>(Albany: State University of New York Press, 1989).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
