<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24708873</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>PLURALISM OF NORMS AND VALUES : ON THE CLAIM AND RECEPTION OF THE UNIVERSAL</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Jacob</given-names>
                  <surname>Klapwijk</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1994</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>59</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24708868</issue-id>
         <fpage>158</fpage>
         <lpage>192</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24708873"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1153e101a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e108" publication-type="other">
With thanks to Sander Griffioen for his contribution to the plan of this article and to
Herbert Donald Morton for the translation from the Dutch.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e118a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e125" publication-type="other">
For the distinction made here between pluralism in philosophy, in social theory and in
ethics, see especially the contributions by W. Kerber and L. Samson on "Pluralismus." The
distinction between philosophical, societal and normative pluralism is descriptive in
character and far from exhaustive. There is also a pluralism of world views (see Wilhelm
Dilthey's 'Streit der Weltanschauungen') and of scientific théories (see Thomas Kuhn's
'paradigm switch')·</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e148a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e155" publication-type="other">
See Oswald von Nell-Breuning, s.v., in Wörterbuch der Politik, Band V/2, 449ff.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e162a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e169" publication-type="other">
Bernard Zylstra, From Pluralism to Collectivism, 206ff.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e177a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e184" publication-type="other">
Friedrich Nietzsche, Jenseits von Gut und Böse, 260.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e191a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e198" publication-type="other">
The word 'ethical' often has a spécifie meaning. In that case it is placed on a level with other
terms having a normative significance such as 'aesthetic', juridical', 'religious' and means
about the same thing as 'moral'. An ethical problem thus regarded is a typical problem of
morality. The word can also have a comprehensive meaning, however, as in the ancient
Greeks. 'Ethical' is in that case more or less identifiable with 'normative'. That is so with the
term 'ethical pluralism'. What is usually meant by it is a pluralist view of moral and other
norms. In this essay I shall also use the term in this way. Yet I prefer to speak of a 'pluralism
of norms and values' (a) because I like to reserve the term 'ethical' for moral normativity and
(b) because in this study I also want to deal with logical and technological normativity, and
in common language these fall in any case outside the concept of 'ethical', even if it is
understood comprehensively.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e236a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e243" publication-type="other">
Since Hermann Lotze and the rise of the neokantian philosophy of values, 'values' and
'norms' have often been used interchangeably. Yet the expression 'norms and values'
indicates that the two terms are complementary. 'Norm' possesses a moment of foreignness
and exteriority, and 'value' a moment of récognition and intimacy. Values from my
perspective are those norms that people have integrated into their lives and thus have come
to value as such. See the second part of this essay.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e266a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e273" publication-type="other">
Arnold Gehlen, Moral und Hypermoral: Eine pluralistische Ethik, 1969.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e280a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e287" publication-type="other">
Troeltsch deals with pluralism in: "Die Zufalligkeit der Geschichtswahrheiten," p. 61. In
the last version of Oer Historismus und seine Problem and in Der Historismus und seine
Überwindung he speaks, more radically, of monadological or metaphysical individualism.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e300a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e307" publication-type="other">
Pluralistic' labels not only a particular view of the world, of society, or of morality. People
are also in the habit of attaching the name to the object under considération. One then speaks
of a pluralistic reality, a pluralistic church, a pluralistic ethos, and so forth. The word 'plural'
or 'pluriform' would in such cases seem more appropriate. Yet what is one to do when James
already spoke of a 'pluralistic universe'? In this essay I use 'pluralism' and 'pluralistic' in the
primary sense of the terms, i.e., as characteristic of a particular view or theory.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e331a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e338" publication-type="other">
See for example Ernst Troeltsch, Aufsàtze zur Geistesgeschichte und Religionssoziologie,
156-90.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e348a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e355" publication-type="other">
See the fundamental observations of pope John Paul II in Veritatis splendor §§43-53 and
§§71-75. Here lies the basis of the distinctive view of 'natural' birth control, and so forth.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e365a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e372" publication-type="other">
The transcendental critique of theoretical thought as it was developed by Herman
Dooyeweerd can be seen as a particularization of a général reflective critique of experience.
This perspective implies that theoretical thought and everyday experience do not stand
opposite each other as 'Gegenstand-relation' versus 'subject-object relation', as in
Dooyeweerd. I hope to show elsewhere the structural affinity of these two.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e391a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e398" publication-type="other">
From my plan of a 'général reflective critique of experience' if will be clear after ail that I
do not share Apel's one-sided attachment to the spécifie mode of experience formed by
logical-argumentative discourse as 'transzendentales Sprachspiel'. Cf. Karl-Otto Apel,
Transformation der Philosophie, Band 2, 256. His hésitation concerning whether to call the ideal
communication community a norm or a goal also arouses concern. See R. van Woudenberg,
"Einige Bemerkungen zur transzendentalpragmatischen Interprétation von Normativiteit,"
442-46.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e424a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e431" publication-type="other">
The Confessions of St. Augustine, XI, xiv, 17 (p. 224).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e438a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e445" publication-type="other">
Ernst Hirsch Ballin, "Recht in beweging."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e453a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e460" publication-type="other">
Generalization of the concept of positivizing is also to be observed in Dooyeweerd and
Vollenhoven. Although there are some différences between Vollenhoven's thinking and my
own at this point, he too proceeds from "the positive laws that form a bridge" between the
highest commandaient and the concrete situation. See A. Tol and Κ. A. Bril, Vollenhoven als
wijsgeer, 138 and 105; cf. 30.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e479a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e486" publication-type="other">
The process of positivization taken as an explication and application of normative
principles needs to be sharply distinguished from a supposed général process of disclosure of
norms, a sort of évolution and progression of the human spirit such as one finds in German
romanticism and to some extent still also in Kuyper and Dooyeweerd. See ]. Klapwijk,
"Verschuiving van normen en historistische filosofie," 36-40. Explication and application go
hand in hand. In the idea of progressive disclosure, however, the notion of contextualization
— the application of norms to spécifie situations — grows vague. Because the conditions of
human life undergo unremitting change, the process of positivization requires resumption
time and time again. Cf. S. Griffioen and J. Verhoogt in Norm and Context, 13; see also the
conclusion of the present essay.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e521a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e528" publication-type="other">
Cf. Gadamer's subtle analysis of Aristotle's concept of 'phronèsis' in Truth and Method,
280-88.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e538a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e545" publication-type="other">
P. van Tongeren, "Morality, Transcendence, Conception of Life," 50.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e552a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e559" publication-type="other">
Thus Laotse in the first chapter of his Book of Tao. See the introduction in Thomas
Merton, The Way of Chuang Tzu.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e569a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e576" publication-type="other">
Thus T. P. van der Kooy, Op het grensgebied van economie en religie, passim.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e584a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e591" publication-type="other">
Seren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Dread, 79.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e598a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e605" publication-type="other">
See the introduction in Bonhoeffer's Ethik.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e612a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e619" publication-type="other">
See also my observations about 'habit formation' and 'causal explanation' in: J. Klapwijk,
"Science and Social Responsibility in Neo-Marxist and Christian Perspective," 87-89.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e629a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e636" publication-type="other">
I let rest here the question of whether from Berger's standpoint human society is based
entirely on societal construction or whether he too discerns a transcendental moment, but see
the illuminating comments of Sander Griffioen in "Geloven is afzien," 113-14.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e649a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e656" publication-type="other">
In addition, ethics, and especially the ethics of idealism, knows an objective translation of
norms, in the doctrine of cultural goods, which entails the embodiment of norms in social
institutions (state, economy, religion); see the continuation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e669a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e676" publication-type="other">
See A. Troost, "Wijsheid, intuïtie en geweten," 142-50.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e684a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e691" publication-type="other">
The Greek term 'ethos' originally had the twofold sense of 'habitation' and 'habit'.
Etymologically those two English terms are affinitive, as too are the German equivalents
Wohnung and Gewohnheit and, for instance, also the German terms Sitz (seat) and Sitte
(custom, morals). Thus habits seek a habitation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e707a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e714" publication-type="other">
See Acts 9:2; 19:9, 23; 24:14, 22.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e721a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e728" publication-type="other">
Max Weber, "Die protestantische Ethik und der Geist des Kapitalismus," particularly pp.
84-206.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e738a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e745" publication-type="other">
See Hans Achterhuis, éd., Deugt de ethiek?</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e752a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e759" publication-type="other">
G. W. F. Hegel, Einleitung in die Geschichte der Philosophie, 13.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e766a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e773" publication-type="other">
See Alasdair Maclntyre, After Virtue, 205-9.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e781a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e788" publication-type="other">
It is a struggle that produces riot only accommodation or isolation but also the trans-
formation of prevailing norms. Cf. J. Klapwijk, "Epilogue: The Idea of Transformational
Philosophy."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1153e801a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1153e808" publication-type="other">
Ernst Troeltsch distinguished between naive, apologetic and evolutionistic absoluteness.
From the original spontaneity of 'naive absoluteness' and its artificial (partly super-
naturalistic, partly rationalistic) defence as 'apologetic absoluteness' (in the Middle Ages and
in the Enlightenment, respectively) there came forth in Hegel the idea of 'evolutionistic
absoluteness' — an ingenious but untenable attempt to reconcile the solid apologetic
conception of absoluteness of that day with the dynamics of history by presenting it as the
outcome and terminus of historical progression. See Troeltsch, Die Absolutheit des Christen-
tums, 87ff. Cf. J. Klapwijk, Tussen historisme en relativisme, 222-29. At present the belief in
progress and thus also the mix of it with the idea of absoluteness is no longer a subject of
discussion.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="d1153e852a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e856" publication-type="other">
Achterhuis, Hans, ed. Deugt de ethiek? Opstellen van vijftien auteurs. Baarn: Gooi &amp; Sticht, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e863a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e867" publication-type="other">
Apel, Karl-Otto. Transformation der Philosophie. Band 2: Das Apriori der Kommunikations-
gemeinschaft. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, 1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e877a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e881" publication-type="other">
Augustine, Aurelius. The Confessions of St. Augustine. Translated by Edward Β. Pusey. New
York: Washington Square Press, 1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e891a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e895" publication-type="other">
Berger, Peter L. and Thomas Luckmann. The Social Construction of Reality: A Treatise in the
Sociology of Knowledge (1966). Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e906a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e910" publication-type="other">
Bergson, Henri. Les deux sources de la morale et de la religion (1932). 3d printing. Paris: Presses
universitaires de France, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e920a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e924" publication-type="other">
Bonhoeffer, Dietrich. Werke. Vol. 6, Ethik (1949). Munich: Kaiser Verlag, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e931a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e935" publication-type="other">
Gadamer, Hans-Georg. Truth and Method. Translated and edited by Garrett Barden and John
Cumming. New York: Seabury Press, 1975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e945a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e949" publication-type="other">
Gehlen, Arnold. Moral und Hypermoral: Eine pluralistische Ethik (1969). 3d printing. Frankfurt
am Main: 1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e959a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e963" publication-type="other">
Griffioen, Sander and Jan Verhoogt, eds. Norm and Context in the Social Sciences. Lanham, New
York and London: University Press of America, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e973a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e977" publication-type="other">
Griffioen, Sander. "Geloven is afzien." In Om de toekomst van een traditie: Opstellen over
geloofsoverdracht, ed. A. van Harskamp, 111-27. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e988a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e992" publication-type="other">
Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich. Einleitung in die Geschichte der Philosophie. Edited by
Johannes Hoffmeister. 3d printing. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1966.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1002a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1006" publication-type="other">
Hirsch Ballin, Ernst (Ministry of Justice). "Recht in beweging: Een beleidsplan voor Justitie in
de komende jaren." Tweede Kamer, 1990-1991, 21829, nrs. 1-2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1016a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1020" publication-type="other">
James, William. A Pluralistic Universel Hibbert Lectures at Manchester College on the Present
Situation in Philosophy. New York: Longmans, Green and Company, 1909.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1030a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1034" publication-type="other">
John Paul II. Lettera encyclica Veritatis splendor. Vatican, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1041a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1045" publication-type="other">
Kerber, Walter. "Pluralismus I." In Historisches Wörterbuch der Philosophie, Band 7, col. 987-93.
Basel: Schwabe, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1055a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1059" publication-type="other">
Kierkegaard, Soren. The Concept ofDread. Translated by Walter Lowrie. Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1957. Translation of Begrebet Angest (1844).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1070a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1074" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. "Epilogue: The Idea of Transformational Philosophy." In Bringing into
Captivity Every Thought: Capita Selecta in the History of Christian Evaluations of
Non-Christian Philosophy, ed. J. Klapwijk, et al., 241-66. Lanham, New York and London:
University Press of America, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1090a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1094" publication-type="other">
— Tussen historisme en relativisme: Een studie over de dynamiek van het historisme en de wijsgerige
ontwikkelingsgang van Ernst Troeltsch. Assen: Van Gorcum, 1970. Doctoral dissertation,
Free University Amsterdam.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1107a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1111" publication-type="other">
— "Science and Social Responsibility in Neo-Marxist and Christian Perspective." In
Wetenschap wijsheid filosoferen: Opstellen aangeboden aan Hendrik van Riessen, ed. P.
Blokhuis, et al., 75-98. Assen: Van Gorcum, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1124a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1128" publication-type="other">
— "Verschuiving van normen en historistische filosofie." Philosophia Reformata 37 (1972):
26-41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1138a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1142" publication-type="other">
Kooy, Tjalling Pieter van der. Op het grensgebied van economie en religie. Wageningen: Zomer
en Keuning, 1953.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1152a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1156" publication-type="other">
Laski, Harold Joseph. Studies in the Problem of Sovereignty. New Haven: Yale University Press,
1917.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1167a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1171" publication-type="other">
Maclntyre, Alasdair. After Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory. London: Duckworth, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1178a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1182" publication-type="other">
Merton, Thomas. The Way ofChuang Tzu. Boston: Shambhala Publications, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1189a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1193" publication-type="other">
Nell-Breuning, Oswald von and Hermann Sacher. "Pluralismus". In Wörterbuch der Politik,
Band V/2, pp. 449ff. Freiburg: Herder, 1951.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1203a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1207" publication-type="other">
Nietzsche, Friedrich. Jenseits von Gut und Böse. Werke in drei Banden II, pp. 563-759.
Darmstadt: Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, n.d.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1217a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1221" publication-type="other">
Samson, Lothar. "Pluralismus II." In Historisches Wörterbuch der Philosophie, Band 7, col.
993-95. Basel: Schwabe, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1231a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1235" publication-type="other">
Tol, Anthony and Kornelis Arent Bril. Vollenhoven als wijsgeer: Inleidingen en teksten.
Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1250" publication-type="other">
Tongeren, Paul van. "Morality, Transcendence, Conception of Life." In Morality, Worldview
and Law, ed. A. W. Musschenga, et al., 39-51. Assen and Maastricht, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1260a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1264" publication-type="other">
Troeltsch, Ernst. Die Absolutheit des Christentums und die Religionsgeschichte (1902). 3d printing.
Tübingen: J. C. B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1929.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1274a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1278" publication-type="other">
— Aufsatze zur Geistesgeschichte und Religionssoziologie. Gesammelte Schriften, vol. 4. Tübingen:
J. C. B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1925.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1288a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1292" publication-type="other">
— Der Historismus und seine Problème, Erstes Buch: Das logische Problem der Geschichts-
philosophie. Gesammelte Schriften, vol. 3. Tübingen: J. C. B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1922.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1302a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1306" publication-type="other">
— Der Historismus und seine Überwindung: EünfVortrage. Berlin: Pan Verlag Rolf Heisse, 1924.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1313a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1317" publication-type="other">
— "Die Zufàlligkeit der Geschichtswahrheiten." Der Leuchter: Weltanschauung und
Lebensgestaltung 4 (1923): 31-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1328a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1332" publication-type="other">
Troost, Andree. "Wijsheid, intuïtie en geweten." In Wetenschap wijsheid filosoferen: Opstellen
aangeboden aan Hendrik van Riessen, ed. P. Blokhuis, et al., 142-50. Assen: Van Gorcum,
1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1345a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1349" publication-type="other">
Weber, Max. "Die protestantische Ethik und der Geist der Kapitalismus" (1920). In
Gesammelte Aufsatze zur Religionssoziologie, vol. 1, pp. 17-206. Tübingen: J. C. B. Mohr
(Paul Siebeck), 1963.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1362a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1366" publication-type="other">
Woudenberg, René van. "Einige Bemerkungen zur transzendentalpragmatischen Interpré-
tation von Normativitàt." In Transzendentalpragmatik: Ein Symposion für Karl-Otto Apel,
ed. A. Dorsel, et al., 442-67. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, 1993.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1153e1379a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1153e1383" publication-type="other">
Zylstra, Bernard. Erom Pluralism to Collectivism: The Development of Harold Laski's Political
Thought. Assen: Van Gorcum, 1968. Doctoral dissertation, Free University Amsterdam.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
