<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">canajpoliscierev</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100117</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Canadian Journal of Political Science / Revue canadienne de science politique</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00084239</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">17449324</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">25165887</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>In Search of a Postcolonial Theory of Normative Integration: Reflections on A.C. Cairns' Theory of "Citizens Plus"</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Heidi</given-names>
                  <surname>Libesman</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>38</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i25165879</issue-id>
         <fpage>955</fpage>
         <lpage>976</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2005 Canadian Political Science Association (l'Association canadienne de science politique) and/et la Société québécoise de science politique</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/25165887"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The focus of this article is the theory of integration advanced by Alan Cairns in his book, "Citizens Plus: Aboriginal peoples and the Canadian State". Cairns' theory has had a mixed reception since its publication. Like much scholarship and public policy in the Aboriginal rights field, "Citizens Plus" has attracted strong proponents and opponents. At present "Citizens Plus" remains one of the primary competitors vying for influence in guiding the postcolonial reconfiguration of the relationship between Aboriginal peoples, the Canadian state and civil society on terms of justice that may be perceived as legitimate by both Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal peoples. The prime alternative, as conceived by both Cairns and his critics, is the nation-to-nation constitutional vision of the Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples. The author provides a political theoretical reading of "Citizens Plus". She seeks to disclose the normative and conceptual structure of Cairns' argument and to situate Cairns' theory in the context of debates concerning the future of Aboriginal peoples and the constitution of Canada. This reading foregrounds an alternative interpretation of the relationship between "Citizens Plus" and the constitutional vision of the Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples, which makes it possible to see them as complementary rather than opposed constitutional visions. The author also raises broader questions concerning the reasons for continuing the search, at the heart of Cairns' work, for a post-colonial theory and praxis of normative integration in diverse societies, and the conditions of the possibility of such a theory and praxis. Ultimately the author argues that whether one agrees or disagrees with Cairns' prescription, at a minimum "Citizens Plus" should be understood as raising a fundamental question to which multinational constitutional theory must respond. /// Le présent article a pour objet d'examiner la théorie avancée par Alan Cairns dans son ouvrage, "Citizens Plus: Aboriginal Peoples and the Canadian State". Cette théorie est loin de faire l'unanimité; comme beaucoup d'autres ouvrages ou initiatives dans le domaine des droits autochtones, "Citizens Plus" a ses partisans et ses détracteurs. À l'heure actuelle, "Citizens Plus" demeure l'une des principales approches possibles de la redéfinition postcoloniale des relations entre les peuples autochtones et l'État et la société civile canadiens sur le fondement de conditions justes dont la légitimité est susceptible d'être reconnue autant par les peuples autochtones que par les non-autochtones. La vision de relations de nation à nation, telle qu'exprimée par la Commission royale sur les peuples autochtones, est, selon Cairns ainsi que ses détracteurs, la principale alternative à "Citizens Plus". Dans le présent article, l'auteure interprète "Citizens Plus" dans une optique de théorie politique. Elle cherche à faire ressortir la structure normative et conceptuelle de l'argument de Cairns et à situer la théorie de Cairns dans le contexte des débats concernant l'avenir des peuples autochtones et de la constitution canadienne. L'auteure veut ainsi attirer l'attention sur une autre interprétation possible de la relation entre "Citizens Plus" et la vision de la Commission royale sur les peuples autochtones. Selon cette interprétation, il s'agit de visions complémentaires plutôt que contradictoires. L'auteure soulève également des questions plus générales, concernant les raisons de poursuivre la recherche d'une théorie et d'une praxie d'intégration normative au sein de sociétés empreintes de diversité, ainsi que les conditions de la possibilité d'une telle théorie et d'une telle praxie. Cette recherche est, par ailleurs, au cœur de l'œuvre de Cairns. En dernière analyse, l'auteure soutient que, peu importe que l'on souscrive ou non à ce que Cairns propose, "Citizens Plus" soulève, à tout le moins, une question fondamentale à laquelle la théorie constitutionnelle multinationale doit répondre.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="d13313e126a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e135" publication-type="other">
Gordon Christie's review of Citizens Plus (2002)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e141" publication-type="other">
Gerald R. Alfred (2000)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e148a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e155" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, 1992</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e162a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e169" publication-type="other">
Cairns
at 5-9, 71, 91-95, 115, 158, 166, 203, 204, 206.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e179a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e186" publication-type="other">
He writes, for example: "How
we define ourselves is not a trivial matter. A label is not a theory, but it constrains
how we think about the subject matter the label encompasses.... At minimum, [labels]
define a situation and sometimes they are vehicles for a social or political theory"
(7).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e204" publication-type="other">
Cairns' perception that we are liv-
ing through a period of paradigmatic transition: "We are in the midst of a major
effort to overturn a historic pattern of inequality between Aboriginal peoples and
other Canadians.... The transformations ... under way are more than political with a
focus on self-government. They encompass virtually all of the ways in which we relate
to each other. They extend across the humanities and social sciences—the disciplines
of anthropology, archeology and history; literature, museum exhibits, and theatre—
and the theory and practice of law" (40-46).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e232" publication-type="other">
Cairns' comment referring to
"([o]ur) present location between a world we have incompletely left behind and a
future we have not fully worked out..." (45).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e246a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e253" publication-type="other">
Gordon Christie (2002)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e259" publication-type="other">
Dale Turner (see note 1)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e265" publication-type="other">
Gerald Alfred (2000)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e272a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e279" publication-type="other">
his comment describing the Hawthorn/Citizens Plus approach as making "Indi-
ans ... a bit more equal than other Canadians" (52).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e289a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e296" publication-type="other">
Cairns writes: "[O]ur constitutional thinking about Aboriginal futures, Cairns urges,
cannot restrict itself to the justification and elaboration of a third order of Aboriginal
government.... The questions of how individual Aboriginal Canadians, both those
within and those without self-governing communities, will relate as citizens to fed-
eral and provincial communities and their governments and how governments will
mesh with the other two orders deserve a degree of attention they have not had" (75).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e319a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e326" publication-type="other">
Urban Aboriginal Governance in Canada:
Re-Fashioning the Dialogue, a joint research project of the National Association of
Friendship Centres (NAFC) and the Law Commission of Canada..</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e338" publication-type="other">
1999: 17</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e345a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e352" publication-type="other">
Arendt
refers to, in her Lectures on Kant's Political Philosophy (1982)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d13313e371a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e375" publication-type="other">
Alfred, Gerald. 2000. "Editorial: Of White Heroes and Old Men Talking." Eastern Door,
June 4. http://easterndoor.com/archives/9-19/9-19-Editorial.htm (November 1, 2005).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e385a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e389" publication-type="other">
Arendt, Hannah. 1990 [1963]. On Revolution. London: Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e396a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e400" publication-type="other">
Arendt, Hannah. 1982. Lectures on Kant's Political Philosophy, ed. Ronald Beiner. Chi-
cago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e410a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e414" publication-type="other">
Borrows, John. 2002. Recovering Canada. Toronto: University of Toronto Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e422a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e426" publication-type="other">
Cairns, Alan C. 1995. "Aboriginal Canadians, Citizenship and the Constitution." In Recon-
figurations: Canadian Citizenship and Constitutional Change: Selected Essays by Alan
C. Cairns, ed. Douglas E. Williams. Toronto: McClelland and Stewart.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e439a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e443" publication-type="other">
Cairns, Alan C. 2000. Citizens Plus: Aboriginal Peoples and the Canadian State. Van-
couver: UBC Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e453a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e457" publication-type="other">
Cairns, Alan C. 2003. "Afterword: International Dimensions of the Citizen Issue for Indig-
enous Peoples/Nations." Citizenship Studies 7(4): 497-512.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e467a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e473" publication-type="other">
Canada. Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development. 1969. Statement of the
Government of Canada on Indian Policy: Presented to the First Session of the Twenty-
Eighth Parliament by the Hon. Jean Chrétien, Minister of Indian Affairs and North-
ern Development. Ottawa: Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e489a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e493" publication-type="other">
Canada. 1996. Report of the Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples. Ottawa: Canada
Communication Group Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e503a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e507" publication-type="other">
Christie, Gordon. 2002. "Review of Alan C. Cairns, Citizens Plus." Osgoode Hall Law
Journal 40: 189-200</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e518a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e522" publication-type="other">
Devlin, Richard and Alexandra Dobrowolsky. 2002. "Citizens Supplicant? Alan Cairns'
Citizens Plus and the Politics of Aboriginal Constitutional Scholarship." Review of
Constitutional Studies 7: 79-119.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e535a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e539" publication-type="other">
Erasmus, George. 2002. Third Annual LaFontaine-Baldwin Lecture, http ://www. operation-
dialogue.com/lafontaine-baldwin/e/2002_speech_1.html (November 1, 2005).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e549a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e553" publication-type="other">
Hawthorn, H.B., ed. 1966 and 1967. A Survey of the Contemporary Indians of Canada.
Ottawa: Queen's Printer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e563a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e567" publication-type="other">
Libesman, Heidi. 2002. "Review of Patrick Macklem, Indigenous Difference and the Con-
stitution of Canada.'" Osgoode Hall Law Journal 40: 200-14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e577a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e581" publication-type="other">
Macklem, Patrick. 1993. "Distributing Sovereignty: Indian Nations and Equality of Peo-
ples." Stanford Law Review 45: 1311.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e591a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e595" publication-type="other">
Macklem, Patrick. 2002. Indigenous Difference and the Constitution of Canada. Toronto:
University of Toronto Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e606a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e610" publication-type="other">
McNeil, Kent. 2001. Emerging Justice? Essays on Indigenous Rights in Canada and Aus-
tralia. Saskatoon: University of Saskatchewan Native Law Centre.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e620a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e624" publication-type="other">
National Association of Friendship Centres and the Law Commission of Canada. 1999.
Urban Aboriginal Governance in Canada: Re-Fashioning the Dialogue. Ottawa.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e634a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e638" publication-type="other">
Rawls, John. 2001. Justice as Fairness. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e645a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e649" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1992. Oneself as Another, trans. Kathleen Blarney. Chicago: University of
Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e659a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e663" publication-type="other">
Slattery, Brian. 1994. "The paradoxes of national self-determination." Osgoode Hall Law
Journal 32: 4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e673a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e677" publication-type="other">
Slattery, Brian. 2003. "Our Mongrel Selves: Pluralism, Identity and the Nation." In Commu-
nity of Right/Rights of the Community, ed. Ysolde Gendreau. Montreal: Editions Themis.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e688a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e692" publication-type="other">
Tully, James. 1993. An Approach to Political Philosophy: Locke in Contexts. Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e702a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e706" publication-type="other">
Tully, James. 1995. Strange Multiplicity: Constitutionalism in an Age of Diversity. Cam-
bridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e716a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e720" publication-type="other">
Tully, James. 2001. "Introduction." In Multinational Democracies, ed. James Tully and
Alain-G. Gagnon. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d13313e730a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d13313e734" publication-type="other">
Wood, Gordon S. 1969. The Creation of the American Republic 1776-1787. Chapel Hill:
University of North Carolina Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
