<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">renastudies</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50011039</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Renaissance Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">02691213</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14774658</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24411934</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Social identity in Renaissance Venice: the second Serrata</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Stanley</given-names>
                  <surname>Chojnacki</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>1994</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>8</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24411931</issue-id>
         <fpage>341</fpage>
         <lpage>358</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 1994 The Society for Renaissance Studies and Oxford University Press</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24411934"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d21606e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e114" publication-type="other">
P. J. Jones, 'Communes and despots: the city-state in late-medieval Italy', T Roy Hist, 5th ser.,
15 (1965), 71-96. An early version of this paper was read as the Eric Cochrane Lecture in
Renaissance History at the University of Chicago in April 1992; I would like to thank Lydia G.
Cochrane and Julius Kirshner for the honour of this invitation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e130a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e137" publication-type="other">
The most authoritative modern studies of the Serrata, with discussion of the historiographie
tradition, are Frederic C. Lane, 'The enlargement of the Great Council of Venice', in Florilegium
Historiale: Essays Presented to Wallace K. Ferguson, ed. J. G. Rowe and W. H. Stockdale (Toronto,
1971), 236-74; and Gerhard Rösch, Der venezianische Adel bis zur Schliessung des Grossen Rats. Zur
Genese einer Führungsschicht (Sigmaringen, 1989), ch. 6, 'Die sogenannte Serrata des Maggior Con-
siglio vom Jahre 1297'. See also Margarete Merores, 'Der grosse Rat von Venedig und die sogenannte
Serrata vom Jahre 1297', Vierteljahrschrift für Sozial- und Wirtschaftsgeschichte, 21 (1928), 33-113;
and Giorgio Cracco, Società e stato nel medioevo veneziano (Florence, 1967), 211-350.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e166a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e173" publication-type="other">
For recent statements of this view, see Guido Ruggiero, 'Modernization and the mythic state in
early Renaissance Venice: the Serrata revisited', Viator, 10 (1979), 245-56; and Reinhold C.
Mueller, 'Espressioni di status sociale a Venezia dopo la "Serrata" del Maggior Consiglio', in Studi
veneti offerti a Gaetano Cozzi (Venice, 1992), 53-61.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e189a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e196" publication-type="other">
James S. Grubb, 'When myths lose power: four decades of Venetian historiography', J Mod
Hist, 58 (1986), 43-94.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e207a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e214" publication-type="other">
The exceptions are John Easton Law, 'Age qualification and the Venetian constitution: the case
of the Capello family', Pap Brit Sch Rome, 39 (1971), 125-37; and Élizabeth Crouzet Pavan, 'Sopra
le acque salse: espaces, pouvoir et société à Venise à la fin du moyen âge Collection de l'Ecole
Française de Rome, 156 (2 vols, Rome, 1992), i, 383-6.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e230a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e237" publication-type="other">
An earlier analysis, stopping short of the Quattrocento, can be found in Stanley Chojnacki, 'In
search of the Venetian patriciate: families and factions in the fourteenth century', in Renaissance
Venice, ed. J. R. Hale (London, 1973), 47-90. A critical review of that article is in Ruggiero,
'Modernization and the mythic state'. Ruggiero's discussion does not assess the composition of the
ruling class either before or after the Serrata, nor does it consider the reconstruction of the class in
Merores, 'Der grosse Rat'. The corrective refinement of Merores's reconstruction in Rösch, Der
venezianische Adel, was published after Ruggiero's article.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e263a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e270" publication-type="other">
On identity as discussed here, see Anthony Giddens, Central Problems in Social Theory:
Action, Structure and Contradiction in Social Analysis (Berkeley and Los Angeles, 1979); Anne Nor-
ton, Reflections on Political Identity (Baltimore, Md, 1988); Paul Ricoeur, Oneself as Another,
trans. Kathleen Blarney (Chicago, 1992); and Charles Taylor, Sources of the Self: The Making of the
Modern Identity (Cambridge, Mass., 1989).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e289a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e296" publication-type="other">
For formulations of this principle, see Norton, Reflections on Political Identity, 46; and Joan
W. Scott, '"Experience"', in Feminists Theorize the Political, ed. Judith Butler and Joan W. Scott
(New York, 1992), 22-40, at p. 34.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e309a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e316" publication-type="other">
Claudio Donati, L'idea dinobiltà in Italia. Secoli XIV-XVIII {Bari and Rome, 1988). See also
Paola Lanaro Sartori, Un'oligarchia urbana nel Cinquecento veneto: istituzioni, economia, società
(Turin, 1992), 1-7, 21-4; Marino Berengo, 'Patriziato e nobiltà: il caso Veronese', in Potere e società
negli stati regionali italiani fra '500 e '600, ed. Elena Fasano Guarini (Bologna, 1978), 191-213. A
recent anthology of humanist writings on nobility is Albert Rabil, Jr (ed. and trans.), Knowledge,
Goodnness, and Power: The Debate over Nobility among Quattrocento Italian Humanists,
(Binghamton, N.Y., 1991).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e342a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e349" publication-type="other">
Donati, L'idea dinobiltà, 10—12ff; esp. p. 20 n. 12.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e357a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e364" publication-type="other">
Salutati's De nobilitate legum et medicine embodies an idea of hereditary nobility based on a
family's history of 'fama, gloria, potentia, dignitatibus, divitiis et clientelis' ('reputation, glory,
power, offices, wealth and clientele'), quoted in Donati, L'idea dinobiltà, 10.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e377a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e384" publication-type="other">
Donati's illustration of this hierarchy is based on a discussion of the De imperatore militum
diligendo (after 1453) by the Veronese jurist Bartolomeo Cipolla. Cipolla explicitly argued that the
dignity conveyed by appointment as a condottiere by the Venetian Senate exceeded that deriving
from (feudal) noble descent. See L'idea dinobiltà, 14-15.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e400a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e407" publication-type="other">
The act is in Archivio di Stato di Venezia ( = ASV), Maggior Consiglio, Reg. 21, 'Leona', fols.
241v-242r (18 March 1414). On the Barbarella, see Stanley Chojnacki, 'Kinship ties and young patri-
cians in fifteenth-century Venice', Renaiss Q, 38 (1985), 240-70; idem, 'Political adulthood in
fifteenth-century Venice', Am Hist R, 19 (1986), 791-810.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e423a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e430" publication-type="other">
An act of the Greater Council on 28 December 1376 forbidding membership to illegitimate sons
of nobles had asserted that the presence of such men in the government might 'denigrare honorem et
famam nostri dominii' ('besmirch the honour and reputation of our state'); ASV, Maggior Consiglio,
Reg. 19, 'Novella', fol. 17lv.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e446a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e453" publication-type="other">
For the view that notions of impurity in different cultures are rooted in a sense of the danger of
things out of place, especially in moments of transition, see Mary Douglas, Purity and Danger: An
Analysis of the Concepts of Pollution and Taboo (London and Boston, Mass., 1966), esp. pp.
114-28.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e469a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e476" publication-type="other">
The ledger's collocation is ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Balla d'Oro', Reg. 162. In their studies of
the Serrata, Lane and Rösch state that lists of applicants for admission to the Greater Council man-
dated in a law of 1315 constituted rosters of the nobility, and as such were forerunners of the Libri
d'Oro begun in 1506. Crouzet Pavan, following the older interpretation of Maranini, makes a similar
statement. However, the requirement of the 1315 law, which is reproduced verbatim by Rösch, ap-
plied not to men actually admitted to the Greater Council but only to applicants; its purpose was to
provide the electors, who in 1315 still chose Council members, with a record of each year's self-
nominees to which they could refer during their secret deliberations. The lists, which have not sur-
vived, therefore did not constitute a record of the nobility's membership but only of men who aspired
to it. See Rösch, Der venezianische Adel, 178-9; Lane, 'The enlargement of the Great Council', 258;
Crouzet Pavan, Espaces, pouvoir et société, I, 385, with reference to Giuseppe Maranini, La costitu-
zione de Venezia (2 vols., 1927-31; repr. Florence, 1974), II, 35.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e519a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e526" publication-type="other">
These 164 families registered sons for the Barbarella either in Avogaria di Comun, 'Balla
d'Oro', Reg. 162, which covers the years 1408-35, or in the subsequent registers 163, 164 or 165,
which cover the rest of the century; or they appear as noble in other official records of government
activity; ASV, Segretario alle Voci, 'Universi', serie antica, Regs. 4 and 6; and ASV, Avogaria di
Comun, 'Prove di Eta', Regs. 177, 178. The total of 164 includes 163 houses allocated space in
Register 162 plus the Lombardo, who are not included in Reg. 162 but are elsewhere documented as
noble in the Quattrocento and had served in government office during the Trecento; see Chojnacki,
'In search of the Venetian patriciate', 47-90, at pp. 72 and 84 n. 60. One source indicates that in
1491 the Lombardo merged with the Lambardo, who were included in Avogaria di Comun, 'Balla
d'Oro', Reg. 162; Biblioteca Marciana, Venice, It. vu 186 (7654), fol. 34v</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e561a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e568" publication-type="other">
The well-known proposal of 1403 to ennoble a new cittadino family for each noble family that
died out indicates an awareness of extinctions. Its failure, however, indicates also the prevailing con-
viction that replenishment was unnecessary or, more likely, undesirable. In any case, there is no
evidence that the officials of the Collegio, where the proposal was debated and defeated, possessed a
tally of the patriciate's membership. The debate is in ASV, Collegio, 'Notatorio', Reg. 3, fol. 11 lv
(24 October 1403).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e591a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e598" publication-type="other">
The main sources for extinction dates of noble families are lists compiled in the late Quattro-
cento by Marino Sanudo in his Le vite dei dogi, ed. Giovanni Monticolo, in Rerum Italicarum Scrip-
tores, new edn, vol. 22, pt 4 (Città di Castello, 1900); and the chronicle literature on the nobility
in the Biblioteca Marciana. Examples of houses long extinct that appear in the avogadoris register
are the Aicardo, reportedly extinct in 1353 or 1365; the Briosso, reportedly even before the Serrata,
either in 1280 or 1293; the Dondolo in 1307; the Grausoni (or Grasoni) in 1303; the Pantaleo already
in the 1270s; the Pollini in 1348; the Rampani in the 1310s; and Savoner, allegedly in 1321. Sanudo,
Le vite, 27, 31, 32, 39, 40, 42; Biblioteca Marciana, It. vn 185 (9008), fols. 4V, llv, 24v, 38r, 40v, 42r;
Biblioteca Marciana, It. vii 186 (7654), fols. 48v, 52r.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e630a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e637" publication-type="other">
The houses active in the government before the Serrata are identified in the lists of members of
the Greater Council between 1266 and 1297 in Roberto Cessi (ed.), Deliberazioni del Maggior Con-
siglio di Veneria, vol. 1 (Bologna, 1950), 269-392. These identifications have been supplemented by
the exhaustive researches on the pre-Serrata ruling group in Rösch, Der venezianische Adel.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e653a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e660" publication-type="other">
' Sixteen of the fifty-one were represented among the thirty popolani admitted to the nobility in
1381, as a reward for their contributions to the defence effort during the Genoese siege in the War
of Chioggia; the other inductees of 1381 had surnames already identified with the nobility. See
Chojnacki, In search of the Venetian patriciate', 57. The noble inductees of 1381 are listed in
Raphaynus Caresini, Chronica, ed. Ester Pastorello, Rerum Italicarum Scriptores, new edn, vol. 12,
pt 2 (Bologna, 1923), 57.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e683a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e690" publication-type="other">
The Libro d'Oro legislation is in ASV, Died, 'Misti', Reg. 31, fols. 109v—110r, 31 August 1506.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e698a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e705" publication-type="other">
ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Nascite-Libro d'Oro', Reg. 51/1. Only 128 of the 146 inscribed
houses registered male births between 1506 and 1525, the years covered in this register. However,
another fourteen were recorded by Marino Sanudo as extant in 1527; I Diarii di Marin Sanudo
(1496-1533), ed. Rinaldo Fulin et al. (Venice, 1879-1903), XLIV, 569-72.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e721a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e728" publication-type="other">
For discussions of these laws, see Lane, 'The enlargement of the Great Council', 252-8; and
Rösch, Der venezianische Adel, 172-80.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e738a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e745" publication-type="other">
ASV, Maggior Consiglio, Reg. 21, 'Leona', fols. 127rv (19 February 1401/2), 14lr (20 January
1403/4).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e755a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e762" publication-type="other">
Ibid. Reg. 22, 'Ursa', fol. 88r (5 March 1430).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e769a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e776" publication-type="other">
The attraction of the Barbarella lay in its chance of early entry (at age twenty) to voting
membership in the Council. This offered families larger representation in the nobility and gave
youths a head start in their political careers. On the significance of the different routes to adult noble
status, see Chojnacki, 'Political adulthood'; Law, 'Age qualification'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e792a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e799" publication-type="other">
An applicant was now obliged to prove to the avogadori that he belonged in the Greater Coun-
cil, was born legitimately and had reached age twenty-five; ASV, Maggior Consiglio, Reg. 22, 'Ursa',
fol. 88r. The fine levied on applicants who were found to lack the hereditary qualification was raised
in 1408 from 300 to 500 lire: another indication of increased watchfulness over the boundaries of the
nobility. Ibid. Reg. 21, 'Leona', fol. 181v (27 December 1408).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e819a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e826" publication-type="other">
ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Prove di Età', Reg. 177. The first entry in this register is dated 2
March 1430, a prompt retroactive response to the enabling legislation of 5 March. Proofs of requisite
age for office-holders were also recorded in these registers.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e839a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e846" publication-type="other">
'Debeant videre et sibi legi facere omnes illos qui se scribi fecerent ad XL pro possendo esse de
Maiori Consilio, et si eis vel maioriparti eorum videbitur dubium de aliquo ibiscripto, teneantur per
sacramentum diligenter inquirere et examinare... veritatem, si ille de quo dubitaverint poterit esse
di Maiori Consilio vel non' ('[The avogadori] are to note all who register with the Quarantia for ad-
mission to the Greater Council; and if at least two of them have doubts about any registrant, they are
to investigate carefully to discover whether he is qualified or not'); emphasis added. This law was
passed by the Greater Council on 25 November 1319 and added to the capitulary of the avogadori di
comun; see ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Capitolare', Reg. 2, cap. 220, fol. 68™. The law of 16
September 1323 which made explicit the requirement that candidates for membership in the Greater
Council demonstrate their descent from former members before the doge and his executive council
(Collegio) also endowed the avogadori with investigatory discretion: 'si vider et ur eis aliqua
obscuritas, quod ipsi possint et teneantur facere suum officium secundum formam sui capitularis et
consilii antedicti' ('if they perceive any uncertainty, they are to discharge their duty as indicated in
their capitulary and in the aforesaid act [i.e. that of 1319]'); emphasis added; ibid. cap. 221, fol. 68v.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e894a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e901" publication-type="other">
Crouzet Pavan has found evidence of an attentuation of lineage ties in the Quattrocento.
Although individual noble lineages remained localized within individual parishes (contracte), pro-
perty divisions among brothers and the restitution of the dowries of in-marrying widows frag-
mentized the holdings in real property that formerly had given residential concreteness to lineage
solidarity. Symbolic bonds persisted, however, not only within lineages but even within the noble
casa, dispersed (in contrast with the elites of other Italian cities) throughout the city; Crouzet
Pavan, Espaces, pouvoir et société, I, 435-62.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e927a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e934" publication-type="other">
See Donati, L'idea di nobiltà, 15, 22 n. 24.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e941a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e948" publication-type="other">
'Quod pro servando in hoc facto illam honestatem et ilium modum, quod habeat servire inten-
tionem terre quam equalius fieri potest, et pro non ponendo divisionem inter nobiles venetiarum:
Vadit pars...' ASV, Maggior Consiglio, Reg. 21, 'Leona', fol. 169r (5 July 1407). This measure
added the avogadori di comun to the body consisting of the doge, his ducal council and the three
capi of the judicial council of the Quarantia. It was rescinded eleven months later; ibid. fol. 176r
(10 June 1408).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e971a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e978" publication-type="other">
On the linguistic dimensions of changes in identity, see Scott, '"Experience"', 34.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e986a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e993" publication-type="other">
For these terms, see Jürgen Habermas, The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere:
An Inquiry into a Category of Bourgeois Society, trans. Thomas Burger and Frederick Lawrence
(Cambridge, Mass., 1991), esp. pp. 27-31. The chronological specificity of Habermas's application
of them is broadened in Roger Chartier, 'Figures of modernity: introduction', in A History of Private
Life, vol. in, Passions of the Renaissance, ed. Roger Chartier, trans. Arthur Goldhammer (Cam-
bridge, Mass., 1989), 15-19. See also Dena Goodman, 'Public sphere and private life: toward a syn-
thesis of current historiographie al approaches to the Old Regime', Hist Theory, 31 (1992), 1-20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1019a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1026" publication-type="other">
ASV, Senato, 'Misti', Reg. 53, fol. 70rv. The preamble is printed in Giulio Bistort, Il magistrato
alle Pompe nella Repubblica di Venezia (Venice, 1912; repr. Bologna, 1969), 107. For fuller discus-
sion of this act, see Stanley Chojnacki, 'Marriage legislation and patrician society in fifteenth-century
Venice', in Law, Custom, and the Social Fabric in Medieval Europe: Essays in Honor of Bryce Lyon,
ed. Bernard S. Bachrach and David Nicholas (Kalamazoo, Mich., 1990), 163-84.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1045a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1052" publication-type="other">
'Inter cives nostros pessima consuetudo orta sit' ('The wicked custom has arisen among our
citizenry ); but 'non est possibile quod multi nobiles nostri possint eorum filias maritare' ('it is im-
possible for many of our nobles to arrange marriages for their daughters'); Senato, 'Misti', Reg. 53,
fol. 70r (emphasis added). On the order of cittadini, see Stephen R. Ell, 'Citizenship and immigra-
tion in Venice, 1305 to 1500', PhD diss. (University of Chicago, 1976); and Andrea Zannini,
Burocrazia e burocrati a Venezia in eta moderna: i cittadini originari (sec. XVI-XVIII) (Venice,
1993), esp. pp. 11-60.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1078a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1085" publication-type="other">
'Divitum substantia attenuatur in maximum damnum et preiuditium suorum heredum... ali-
qui eorum filias coguntur in monasteriis carcerare, cum dignis lacrimis et plantibus ipsarum, aliqui
tenent ipsas innuptas, cum rubore et periculo...' ('Their wealth is reduced, gravely harming their
heirs... some fathers are forced to imprison their daughters in convents, amid justifiable tears and
wailing, others keep them as spinsters, risking dishonour'). Senato, 'Misti', Reg. 53, fol. 70r.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1104a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1111" publication-type="other">
Ibid. The amendment reaffirmed that the daughters of 'omnium civium' - referring to both
nobles and cittadini - must observe the 1,600 ducat limit.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1121a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1128" publication-type="other">
The proponent of the repeal measure, Leonardo Emo, asserted that the dowry limitation law
had produced 'diminutione honoris et libertatis huius civitatis' ('a reduction of the honour and
liberty of this city') because all Venetians were now 'de sua libertate privatos' ('deprived of their
freedom'). He urged repeal in order that 'omnes cives et fideles nostri' ('all citizens and loyal
subjects') might be restored to 'sua solita libertate in facta nuptiarum et dotium' ('their customary
freedom in matters regarding marriage and dowries'). ASV, Senato, 'Misti', Reg. 53, fol. 94v (30
December 1420). The repeal attempt was defeated by 73 nay votes against 45 yeas, with 8 absten-
sions. The act threatening a fine of 1000 ducats for proponents or supportors of further repeal efforts
was passed immediately after the defeat of the repeal proposal.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1161a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1168" publication-type="other">
ASV, Maggior Consiglio, Reg. 22, 'Ursa', fols. 47v-48r (26 May 1422). On this act see
Chojnacki, 'Marriage legislation'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1178a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1185" publication-type="other">
The surnames of mothers of Barbarella candidates were likewise not recorded in registration
records until 1431; ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Balla d'Oro', Reg. 162, passim. It thus appears that
the determination to record maternal identity did not become effective until after passage of the
1430 measure applying strict credentials tests to men who bypassed the Barbarella.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1201a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1208" publication-type="other">
In the useful formulation of Paul Ricoeur, the second Serrata framed a new collective noble
identity consisting of an idem component, whereby older and newer noble houses were assimilated by
means of the procedural measures that they now all were obliged to undergo; and an ipse compo-
nent, in which their separateness from the popolo was underscored; Ricoeur, Oneself as Another, 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1224a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1231" publication-type="other">
In addition to the law of 1420 which permitted daughters of popolani but not those of cittadini
to exceed the 1,600 ducat dowry limit when marrying nobles, another statute, of 1407, granted
citizenship privileges within Venice to any foreigner who settled in in the city and 'took as wife a resi-
dent of Venice'. Ell, 'Citizenship and immigration in Venice', 125-7; the act of 1407 is reproduced in
full on p. 233. On the 'hierarchization' of society in the late Trecento and Quattrocento, cf. Dennis
Romano, Patricians and Popolani: The Social Foundations of the Venetian Renaissance State
(Baltimore, Md, 1987), 152-8; Zannini, Burocrazia e burocrati, 34-40.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1257a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1264" publication-type="other">
Already in the 1420s nobilis juvenis was routinely applied to youths registering for the Bar-
barella; see ASV, Avogaria di Comun, 'Balla d'Oro', Reg. 162, passim. Nobilis mulier became stan-
dard later. In 1429 and 1430, noble widows filing for recovery of their dowries were normally given
the title honesta mulier by court scribes; by the 1460s the title normally attributed had become
nobilis domina or nobilis mulier. Compare ASV, Giudici del Proprio, 'Vadimoni', Reg. 1 (1429-33),
fols. 3r, 6V, etc., with ibid. Reg. 4 (1457-65), fols. 41v, 58v, 64v, etc.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1287a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1294" publication-type="other">
On liminality as providing a focus for collective identity, see Norton, Reflections on Political
Identity, 53. On the liminal stage among noble youths in Venice, see Chojnacki, 'Political
adulthood', 800ff.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1308a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1315" publication-type="other">
For example, a sumptuary law of 146S addressing excessive expenditure on dress by women im-
posed a fine on the 'husbands, fathers, or others with authority over the offending women [maritis,
sive patribus, vel illis sub quorum potestate contrafacientes mulieres essent]'; ASV, Senato, 'Terra',
Reg. 5, fol. 46r. Another law, of 1443, authorized fines and the loss of office-holding privileges for
fathers whose sons misbehaved during meetings of the Greater Council; ASV, Maeeior Consielio,
Reg. 22,'Ursa', fol. 148v</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1338a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1345" publication-type="other">
Francesco Barbara, De re uxoria, ed. Attilio Gnesotto (Padua, 1915). There is a translation of
the preface and book 2, with introduction, in B. G. Kohl and R. G. Witt (eds.), The Earthly
Republic (Philadelphia, Pa, 1978), 179-208. On the significance of Barbara's work for patrician
culture, see Margaret L. King, 'Caldiera and the Barbaras on marriage and the family', Journal of
Mediev R, 6 (1976), 19-50, at pp. 31-5; idem, Venetian Humanism in an Age of Patrician
Dominance (Princeton, N.J., 1985), 92-8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1368a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1375" publication-type="other">
The phrase 'reinforcement of patriarchy' was first used as a chapter heading in Lawrence
Stone, The Family, Sex, and Marriage in England 1550-1800 (London, 1977). The location in the
Renaissance of a strengthening of male prerogatives and a consequent deterioration in the position of
women received a formulation that has become canonical in the germinal essay of Joan Kelly, 'Did
women have a Renaissance?', in Becoming Visible: Women in European History, ed. Renate Briden-
thal and Claudia Koonz (Boston, Mass., 1977), 137-64.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1398a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1405" publication-type="other">
Giddens, Central Problems in Social Theory, 5, 72-73.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1412a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1419" publication-type="other">
On the lineage implications of dowry restitution, see Crouzet Pavan, Espace, pouvoir et société,
448-58; and Stanley Chojnacki, 'The power of love: wives and husbands in late medieval Venice', in
Women and Power in the Middle Ages, ed. Mary Erler and Maryanne Kowaleski (Athens, Ga, 1988),
126-48. For the relationship between dowry, corredo and marriage strategies outside Venice, see
Anna Caso, 'Per la storia délia società milanese: i corredi nuziali nell'ultima età viscontea e nel
periodo della repubblica ambrosiana (1433-1450), dagli atti del notaio Protaso Sansoni', Nuov Riv
St, 65 (1981), 521-51; Christiane Klapisch-Zuber, 'Les corbeilles de la mariée', in La maison et le
nom: stratégies et rituels dans l'Italie de la Renaissance (Paris, 1990), 215-27; Julius Kirshner,
'Materials for a gilded cage: non-dotal assets in Florence, 1300-1500', in The Family in Italy from
Antiquity to the Present, ed. David I. Kertzer and Richard P. Sailer (New Haven, Conn, and
London, 1991), 184-207.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1457a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1464" publication-type="other">
ASV, Giudici del Proprio, 'Vadimoni', Reg. 4, fol. 32r (marriage contract of 1430); ibid. Reg.
5, fol. llr (contract of 1428); Giudici del Esaminador, 'Vendizioni', Reg. 7, fol. 15v (contract of
1435).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1478a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1485" publication-type="other">
'Appresso promette el dicto ser Vetor Trun de far carta de dota hover impromessa a la dicta
dona de ducati mille sexanta sie e do terzi chomo vuol la leze. E lo resto fina a la summa de ducati
mille e siecento che son ducati zinquecento e trentatre e uno terzo sia liberamente dadi et donadi al
dicto ser Vetor Trun per doni e choriedi delà dicta dona.' ASV, Giudici del Proprio, 'Vadimoni',
Reg. 4, fol. 2V.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1504a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1511" publication-type="other">
ASV, Giudici del Proprio, 'De giudicatu', Regs. 1 and 2. The acts involved the dowries of wives
or daughters of nobles, including some who married popolani. The two registers record the cases of
135 such women, but in only 122 can the dowry amounts be ascertained.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1524a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1531" publication-type="other">
In a will of 1335, Piero Morosini bequeathed to each of his daughters 1,000 lire ad grossos
(roughly 385 ducats) for her dowry and corredo, 'secundum usum nobilium dominarum de Veneciis'
('as is customary for noble women in Venice'); ASV, Notarile, 'Testamenti', Busta 1154, Bruto, no.
32. In a civil action of 1382, the Giudici del Procurator ordered that the estate of Federico Corner
should add to his dowry allocation to his daughters 'quid deffecerit congruentie' ('what it lacks to
make it suitable') in order to carry out Federico's testamentary provision that the daughters receive
'quelo che besogna per maridarle' ('what is necessary for their marriages'); ASV, Giudici del Pro-
curator, 'Sentenze a Legge', Reg. 2, fol. 114". In 1385 Nicolô Morosini ordered in his will that if his
descendants should lack the means of providing dowries for their daughters, then his bequest to them
in immovables might be sold to 'maridarle segondo la condicion soa' ('arrange marriages appropriate
to their status'); Notarile, 'Testamenti', Busta 679, Bellancini, prot., fol. 26v. In his will of 1416
Giovanni Morosini instructed his brothers to add enough from his estate to their father's bequest of
1,400 ducats for the marriage of their sister 'ut ipsa cum honore et prout congruit conditionem
domus mee honorificentius maritetur' ('in order that she may marry as honorably as possible and in a
manner befitting the status of my house'); ibid. Busta 1234, Sorio, no. 509.
Fathers also specified that they wanted their daughters to marry noble husbands; Andrea Ari-
mondo in 1427 declared that each of his daughters was to be married 'in uno zentilomo de Veniesia'
('to a Venetian gentleman') (ASV, Cancelleria Inferiore, 'Miscellanea Testamenti', Notai Diversi,
Busta 27, no. 2697); that same year Michele Navagero instructed his executors that his daughter 'se
debia maridar in zentil homo' ('should marry a gentleman') (ASV, Notarile, 'Testamenti', Busta
1157, Croci, prot. Il, fol. 14r). In the Quattrocento, zentilomo was the usual vernacular term for
patrician (nobilis vir in Latin).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1604a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1611" publication-type="other">
In a will of 1476 Marino Pisani bequeathed his daughter, Pisana, 3,500 ducats 'pro eius docte et
coredis' ('for her dowry and corredo'); ASV, Notarile, Testamenti, Busta 727, Moisis, no. 1. In 1485
Alvise Zane allocated at least 3,500 ducats for the marriage portion of his daughter, Michela; ibid.
Busta 68, Bonicardi, no. 316.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1627a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1634" publication-type="other">
In a will of 1437 Giovanni Morosini noted 'con amaretudine non so che lasar' ('it fills me with
bitterness that I don't know what to bequeath') to his daughter, Marietta, because his estate 'no sera
sufficiente a maridarla dagandola tutto' ('will be insufficient to marry her off even if she gets all of
it'); ASV, Notarile, 'Testamenti', Busta 1232, Stefani, no. 314. Eleven years later, Francesco
Morosini allocated for his daughter's portion a range from 500 to 1,800 ducats, depending on
whether Venice was at war when she came to marriageable age, 'perche i tempi de guera le sera
molto piu in frété de danari per pagar faction' ('because in wartime taxes will weigh heavily'); ASV,
Procuratori di San Marco, 'Commissarie Miste', Busta 158a, 'Francesco Morosini', parchment dated
5 April 1448.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1666a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1673" publication-type="other">
See Natalie Zemon Davis, 'Boundaries and the sense of self in sixteenth-century France', in
Reconstructing Individualism: Autonomy, Individuality, and the Self in Western Thought, ed.
Thomas C. Heller et al. (Stanford, Calif., 1986), 53-63.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1687a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1694" publication-type="other">
Only one of 122 sample noble dowries was brought by a noble wife to a non-noble husband, the
400 ducats that Polisena, daughter of 'viri nobilis' Giorgio Capello, recovered from the estate of her
husband, Jacopo Caroldo; Giudici del Proprio, 'De Giudicatum', Reg. 1, fol. 2V. It is not known
whether this Caroldo was related to Gian Giacomo Caroldo, secretary of the Council of Ten in the
early Cinquecento, who wrote a Historia di Venetia, and who was certainly a cittadino; see Antonio
Carile, La cronachistica veneziana (secoli XIII-XVI) di fronte alla spartizione della Romania nel
1204 (Florence: Olschki, 1969), 158-9.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1720a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1727" publication-type="other">
On varied access to political office, see Donald Queller, The Venetian Patriciate: Reality versus
Myth (Urbana, 111., 1986). On matrimonial difficulties for men, see Stanley Chojnacki, 'Subaltern
patriarchs: patrician bachelors in Renaissance Venice', in Medieval Masculinities: Regarding Men in
the Middle Ages, ed. Clare A. Lees (Minneapolis, Minn., 1994), 73-90.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1743a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1750" publication-type="other">
A prominent factor in opening the possibilities of individual choice was the influence of
mothers, fortified with married women's autonomy in disposing of their wealth. Often endorsed by
their husbands but often independently of them, women offered their children the possibility of
framing their own social identity without direction from the structures of patriarchal authority,
paternal or governmental. On the varieties of adult experience, see Stanley Chojnacki, 'Measuring
adulthood: adolescence and gender in Renaissance Venice',/Fam Hist, 17 (1992), 371-95. On the
role of mothers in providing opportunities for elective adult vocation for both sons and daughters, see
idem, "'The most serious duty": motherhood, gender, and patrician culture in Renaissance Venice',
in Refiguring Woman: Gender Studies and the Italian Renaissance, ed. Marilyn Migiel and Juliana
Schiesari (Ithaca, N.Y., 1990), 133-54.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d21606e1785a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d21606e1792" publication-type="other">
Cf. Scott, "'Experience'", 34: '[Subjects] are not unified, autonomous individuals exercising
free will, but rather subjects whose agency is created through situations and statuses conferred on
them.'</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
