<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijasonline</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50014836</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>IJAS Online</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Irish Association for American Studies</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">20092377</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26234254</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>ARTICLES</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>DAVID FOSTER WALLACE</article-title>
            <subtitle>THE DEATH OF THE AUTHOR AND THE BIRTH OF A DISCIPLINE</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>KELLY</surname>
                  <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26234247</issue-id>
         <fpage>47</fpage>
         <lpage>59</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26234254"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Annesley, James. “David Foster Wallace.” Journal of American Studies 43.1 (2009): 131-34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Attridge, Derek. J.M. Coetzee and the Ethics of Reading: Literature in the Event. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aubry, Timothy. “Selfless Cravings: Addiction and Recovery in David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” American Fiction of the 1990s: Reflections of History and Culture. Ed. Jay Prosser. London: Routledge, 2008. 206-19.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baskin, Jon. “Death is Not the End: David Foster Wallace: His Legacy and his Critics.” The Point 1 (2009): 33-45. Online access (n.pg). 1 March 2010. http://www.thepointmag.com/ archive/death-is-not-the-end</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Beirne, Brendan. “Can We Say What We Mean?” Modernism/Modernity 16.1 (2009): 18-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Booth, Wayne. The Company We Keep: An Ethics of Fiction. Berkeley: U of California P, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boswell, Marshall. “David Foster Wallace.” Twenty-First-Century American Novelists, Second Series. Ed. Wanda H. Giles and James R. Giles. Dictionary of Literary Biography 350. London: Gale, 2009. 352-65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boswell, Marshall. “A Gesture Toward Understanding David Foster Wallace.” Modernism/Modernity 16.1 (2009): 7-9.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boswell, Marshall. Understanding David Foster Wallace. Columbia, SC: U of South Carolina P, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bresnan, Mark. “The Work of Play in David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Critique 50.1 (2008): 51-68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bucher, Matt. “Fantods: David Foster Wallace, wallace-l, and Literary Fandom Online.” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009. Online access. 1 March 2010. http://www.mattbucher.com/2009/11/24/ fantods/</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burn, Stephen J. David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest: A Reader’s Guide. London: Continuum, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burn, Stephen J.“Infinite Jest and the Twentieth Century: David Foster Wallace’s Legacy.” Modernism/Modernity 16.1 (2009): 12-18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burn, Stephen J. Jonathan Franzen at the End of Postmodernism. London: Continuum, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carlisle, Greg. “Consider David Foster Wallace.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009. Online access. 1 March 2010. http:// www.sideshowmediagroup.com/?p=97#respond</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carlisle, Greg.Elegant Complexity: A Study of David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest. Austin, TX: SSMG Press, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cioffi, Frank Louis. “‘An Anguish Become Thing’: Narrative as Performance in David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Narrative 8.2 (2000): 161-81.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Culler, Jonathan. Literary Theory: A Very Short Introduction. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Currie, Mark. Postmodern Narrative Theory. Basingstoke: Palgrave, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eckert, Maureen. “Where the Conversation Lapses…Understanding DFW’s Philosophy Thesis.” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eskin, Michael. “Introduction: The Double ‘Turn’ to Ethics and Literature?” Poetics Today 25.4 (2004): 557-72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freudenthal, Elizabeth. “Anti-Interiority: Compulsiveness, Objectifiction and Identity in Infinite Jest.” New Literary History. Forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freudenthal, Elizabeth.“David Foster Wallace, Embodiment, and Identity from the Outside In.” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gibson, Andrew. Postmodernity, Ethics and the Novel: From Leavis to Levinas. London and New York: Routledge, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Giles, Paul. “Sentimental Posthumanism: David Foster Wallace.” After Postmodernism: Form and History in Contemporary American Fiction. Ed. Andrew Hoberek. Spec. issue of Twentieth Century Literature 53.3 (2007): 327-44.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Goerlandt, Iannis. “‘Put the Book Down and Slowly Walk Away’: Irony and David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Critique 47.3 (2006): 309-28.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hale, Dorothy J. “Aesthetics and the New Ethics: Theorizing the Novel in the Twenty-First Century.” PMLA124.3 (2009): 896-905.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hayles, N. Katherine. “The Illusion of Autonomy and the Fact of Recursivity: Virtual Ecologies, Entertainment, and Infinite Jest.” New Literary History 30.3 (1999): 675-97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Holland, Mary K. “‘The Art’s Heart’s Purpose’: Braving the Narcissistic Loop of David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Critique 47.3 (2006): 218-42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jacobs, Timothy. “American Touchstone: The Idea of Order in Gerard Manley Hopkins and David Foster Wallace.” Comparative Literature Studies 38.3 (2001): 215–31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jacobs, Timothy.“The Brothers Incandenza: Translating Ideology in Fyodor Dostoevsky’s The Brothers Karamazov and David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Texas Studies in Literature and Language 49.3 (2007): 265-292.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jenner, Paul. “Don’t Compare, Identify: David Foster Wallace on John McCain.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Karnicky, Jeffrey. “Kinds of Stasis in David Foster Wallace.” Contemporary Fiction and the Ethics of Modern Culture. New York: Palgrave, 2007. 91-124.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kelly, Adam. “David Foster Wallace and the New Sincerity in American Fiction.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kelly, Adam.“Democracy in America: David Foster Wallace’s Political Essays.” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kiberd, Declan. Ulysses and Us: The Art of Everyday Living. London: Faber, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">LeClair, Tom. “The Prodigious Fiction of Richard Powers, William Vollmann, and David Foster Wallace.” Critique 38.1 (1996): 12-37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lipsky, David. Although Of Course You End Up Becoming Yourself: A Road Trip with David Foster Wallace. New York: Broadway Books, 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGurl, Mark. The Program Era: Postwar Fiction and the Rise of Creative Writing. London: Harvard UP, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McLaughlin, Robert. “Post-Postmodern Discontent: Contemporary Fiction and the Social World.” Symploke 12.1-2 (2004): 53-68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Moore, Steven. “In Memoriam David Foster Wallace.” Modernism/Modernity 16.1 (2009): 1-3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nichols, Catherine. “Dialogizing Postmodern Carnival: David Foster Wallace’s Infinite Jest.” Critique 43.1 (2001): 3-16.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nussbaum, Martha. Love’s Knowledge: Essays on Philosophy and Literature. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Olsen, Lance. “Termite Art, or Wallace’s Wittgenstein.” Review of Contemporary Fiction 13.2 (1993): 199-215.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parker, Scott. “Notes from Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies.” Rain Taxi Online (Winter 2009/2010). Online access. 1 March 2010. http://www.raintaxi.com/ online/2009winter/footnotesDFW.shtml</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Punday, Daniel. Narrative After Deconstruction. Albany: State U of New York P, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ribbat, Christoph. “New Journalism, New New Journalism, DFW Journalism: Wallace and Reporting.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roiland, Joshua. “Getting Away From It All: The Literary Journalism of David Foster Wallace and Nietzsche’s Concept of Oblivion.” Literary Journalism Studies 1.2 (2009): 89-105.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rother, James. “Reading and Riding the Post-Scientific Wave: The Shorter Fiction of David Foster Wallace.” Review of Contemporary Fiction 13.2 (1993): 216-34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Saunders, George. Untitled Tribute. Five Dials: Celebrating the Life of David Foster Wallace, 1962-2008. London: Hamish Hamilton, 2009. 15.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Scott, A. O. “The Panic of Influence.” The New York Review of Books 47.2 (10 Feb. 2000). Online access. 1 March 2010. http://www.nybooks.com/articles/232</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, Russell, ed. Beckett and Ethics. London: Continuum, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, Zadie. “Brief Interviews with Hideous Men: The Difficult Gifts of David Foster Wallace.” Changing My Mind: Occasional Essays. London: Hamish Hamilton, 2009. 257-300.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sperling, Joshua. “Reading Infinite Jest through Heidegger’s ‘The Question Concerning Technology.’” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Striphas, Ted. The Late Age of Print: Everyday Book Culture from Consumerism to Control. New York: Columbia UP, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thomas, Chris. “Infinite Jests: David Foster Wallace and Laurence Sterne.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Toal, Catherine. “Corrections: Contemporary American Melancholy.” Journal of European Studies 33.3-4 (2003): 305-22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Turnbull, Daniel. “This is Water and the Ethics of Attention: Wallace, Murdoch and Nussbaum.” Consider David Foster Wallace. University of Liverpool. 29 July 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tysdal, Dan. “Inarticulation and the Figure of Enjoyment: Raymond Carver’s Minimalism Meets David Foster Wallace’s ‘A Radically Condensed History of Postindustrial Life.’” Wascana Review 38.1 (2005): 66-83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Udelson, John. “Inconclusive Endings: DFW’s Search for the Right Word(s): ‘Planet Trillaphon,’ Broom, and ‘Good Old Neon.’” Footnotes: New Directions in David Foster Wallace Studies. CUNY Graduate Centre. 20 Nov. 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster. “Authority and American Usage.” Consider the Lobster and Other Essays. London: Abacus, 2005. 66-127.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.“Brief Interview with a Five Draft Man” (interview with Stacey Schmeidel). Amherst (Spring 1999). Online access. 1 March 2010. https://www.amherst.edu/aboutamherst/magazine/ extra/node/66410</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.Brief Interviews with Hideous Men. Boston: Little, Brown, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.“E Unibus Pluram: Television and U.S. Fiction.” Review of Contemporary Fiction 13.2 (1993): 151-94.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.“The Empty Plenum: David Markson’s Wittgenstein’s Mistress.” Review of Contemporary Fiction 10.2 (1990): 217-39.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.“Fictional Futures and the Conspicuously Young.” Review of Contemporary Fiction 8.3 (1988). Available as pdf, pages numbered 1-27. Online access. 1 March 2010. www.theknowe.net/ dfwfiles/pdfs/ffacy.pdf</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.Infinite Jest. Boston: Little, Brown, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.“An Interview with David Foster Wallace” (with Larry McCaffery). Review of Contemporary Fiction 13.2 (1993): 127-50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wallace, David Foster.Oblivion: Stories. Boston: Little, Brown, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
