<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">imagomundi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100002</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Imago Mundi</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">03085694</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14797801</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">40233993</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="pub-doi">10.1080/03085690500094966</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Maps, Painting and Lies Portraying Napoleon's Battlefields in Northern Italy</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                  <surname>Godlewska</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Marcus R.</given-names>
                  <surname>Létourneau</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                  <surname>Schauerte</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">57</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40008710</issue-id>
         <fpage>149</fpage>
         <lpage>163</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2005 Imago Mundi Ltd.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40233993"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>A comparison of Giuseppe Bagetti's landscape sketches, watercolours, oil paintings and engravings with contemporary maps and the existing landscape reveals that in the creation of Bagetti's landscapes, narrative played a role that differed in cartographic and artistic representations. The comparison also demonstrates that his images were powerful constructions that were more successful in reflecting a narrative of glorious conquest than was possible through cartography. This paper offers a critical examination of Bagetti's representations of Napoleon's northern Italian campaign, which he sketched and painted between 1802 and 1809. Bagetti's paintings were neither pacifist nor an expression of Piedmontese patriotism but instead were inspired by, and constructed according to, a narrative about the conquest that reflected the views of the French authorities. The narrative found expression in formal written instructions from the central cartographical office in the Dépôt de la guerre, Paris, in verbal and written instructions from Bagetti's immediate superior, Jean François Martinel, and in letters personally addressed to Bagetti from the officer commanding the Dépôt. It is clear from a careful reading of the correspondence and from a comparison of Bagetti's paintings with both the present landscape and maps made at the time that Bagetti's disputes with his supervisors revolved around protecting his artistic integrity and reputation rather than resisting the authority of a foreign regime. /// Une comparaison entre les dessins, aquarelles, peintures et gravures de paysages de Giuseppe Bagetti avec des cartes de son temps et les paysages actuels révèle que dans la création des paysages de Bagetti le récit ne joue pas le même rôle que dans les représentations cartographiques et artistiques. La comparaison démontre également que ses images étaient des constructions puissantes qui reflétaient l'histoire d'une conquête victorieuse plus efficacement que la cartographie ne le permettait. Cet article propose un examen critique des représentations des campagnes napoléoniennes en Italie du Nord, dessinées ou peintes par Bagetti entre 1802 et 1809. Les peintures de Bagetti n'étaient ni pacifistes, ni représentatives d'un patriotisme piémontais, mais au contraire inspirées par un récit de la conquête qui reflétait les vues des autorités françaises et construites selon celui-ci. Ce récit se trouvait exprimé dans les instructions écrites de l'office central de cartographie du Dépôt de la Guerre à Paris, dans les instructions verbales et écrites du supérieur direct de Bagetti, Jean-François Martinel, et dans les lettres adressées à Bagetti en personne par l'officier qui dirigeait le Dépôt. Il est clair, si on lit attentivement la correspondance et si l'on compare les peintures de Bagetti avec le paysage actuel et les cartes faites à l'époque, que les discussions entre Bagetti et ses chefs tournaient autour de la préservation de son intégrité et de sa réputation artistique plutôt que de sa résistance à l'autorité d'un régime étranger. /// Ein Vergleich von Giuseppe Bagettis Landschaftsskizzen, Aquarellen, Ölbildern und Druckgraphiken mit zeitgenössischen Karten und der erhaltenen realen Landschaft zeigt, dass bei der Entstehung von Bagettis Landschaftsdarstellungen eine Variante der Ereignisgeschichte eine Rolle spielte, die in seinem Werk zu anderen Ergebnissen führte als bei kartographischen und anderen künstlerischen Darstellungen. Die Vergleiche zeigen auch, dass dabei aussagestarke Bilder entstanden, die die Geschichte der erfolgreichen Eroberungen besser transportierten als es mit den Mitteln der Kartographie möglich war. In diesem Beitrag werden Bagettis Darstellungen der Oberitalienischen Feldzüge Napoleons, die er zwischen 1802 und 1809 anfertigte, kritisch gewürdigt. Seine Darstellungen waren weder pazifistisch noch Ausdruck eines Piemontesischen Patriotismus, sondern Bagetti folgte bei der Konzeption seiner Landschaftsdarstellungen der von offizieller französischer Seite bevorzugten Sichtweise der Geschichte der Eroberungen. Seine Grundlagen bildeten formelle schriftliche Instruktionen der zentralen kartographischen Einrichtung, des Dépôt de la guerre in Paris, sowie mündliche und schriftliche Anweisungen durch Bagettis unmittelbaren Vorgesetzten, Jean François Martinel. Darüber hinaus erhielt er Briefe, die vom Kommandanten des Dépôt de la guerre an ihn persönlich gerichtet waren. Bei sorgfältiger Auswertung dieser Korrespondenz und dem Vergleich seiner Gemälde mit der erhaltenen realen Landschaft und den zeitgenössischen Karten wird deutlich, dass es bei Bagettis Auseinandersetzungen mit seinen Vorgesetzten mehr um Fragen seiner künstlerischen Integrität und Reputation ging als um den Widerstand gegen die Autorität eines fremden Regimes. /// Una comparación de los bocetos de paisajes, aguadas, óleos y grabados de Giuseppe Bagetti con mapas contemporáneos y con el paisaje existente, revela que en la creación paisajística de Bagetti la narrativa jugó un papel diferente de las representaciones cartográficas y artísticas. La comparación también demuestra que sus imágenes eran poderosas construcciones que reflejaban una narrativa de famosas conquistas de manera más acertada de lo que era posible a través de la cartografía. Este artículo ofrece un examen crítico de las representaciones de las campañas napoleónicas en el norte de Italia, que Bagetti dibujó y pintó entre 1802 y 1809. Las pinturas de Bagetti no fueron ni pacifistas ni una expresión del patriotismo piamontés, sino que fueron inspiradas y construidas de acuerdo a una narrativa sobre la conquista que reflejaba el punto de vista de las autoridades francesas. La narrativa encontró su expresión en instrucciones formales escritas desde el centro cartográfico del Dépôt de la Guerre en Paris, en instrucciones verbales y escritas del inmediato superior de Bagetti, Jean François Martinel y en cartas personales dirigidas a Bagetti por el oficial que mandaba el Dépôt. Queda claro, a través de una cuidadosa lectura de la correspondencia y de la comparación de las pinturas de Bagetti con el paisaje actual y con los mapas de su tiempo, que las disputas de Bagetti con su supervisor se centraban en proteger su integridad artística y su reputación más que en resistirse a la autoridad de un régimen extranjero.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>Topographical painting</kwd>
            <kwd>landscape painting</kwd>
            <kwd>field mapping</kwd>
            <kwd>narrative analysis</kwd>
            <kwd>battlefields</kwd>
            <kwd>Napoleonic Wars</kwd>
            <kwd>Napoleon Bonaparte</kwd>
            <kwd>L. A. G. Bacler d'Albe</kwd>
            <kwd>Giuseppe Bagetti</kwd>
            <kwd>Jean François Martinel</kwd>
            <kwd>Nicolas-Antoine Sanson</kwd>
            <kwd>Austria</kwd>
            <kwd>France</kwd>
            <kwd>Italy</kwd>
            <kwd>Liguria</kwd>
            <kwd>Piedmont</kwd>
            <kwd>Ceva</kwd>
            <kwd>Cuneo</kwd>
            <kwd>Dego</kwd>
            <kwd>Fombio</kwd>
            <kwd>Lodi</kwd>
            <kwd>Loano</kwd>
            <kwd>Madonna della Corona</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Notes and References</title>
         <ref id="d14182e319a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e326" publication-type="other">
Annie Becq, Genèse de l'esthétique Française moderne. De
la raison classique à l'imagination creatrice 1680-1814 (Paris,
Albin Michel, 1984), 801-7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e339a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e348" publication-type="other">
Michael
Marrinan, 'Literal/literary /"lexie": history, text and
authority in Napoleonic painting', Word and Image 7:3
(July-September 1991): 177-200;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e363" publication-type="other">
Susan Siegfried,
'Naked history: the rhetoric of military painting in post-
revolutionary France', Art Bulletin 75:2 (June 1993): 235-
58;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e379" publication-type="other">
Frédérick Masson, he Sacre et le couronnement de
Napoleon (Paris, Société d'éditions littéraires et artistiques,
Libr. P. Ollendorff, 1908);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e391" publication-type="other">
Henri Gaubert, Le Sacre de
Napoléon ler (Paris, Flammarion, 1964);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e400" publication-type="other">
Christopher
Prendergast, Napoleon and History Painting: Antoine-Jean
Gros's La Bataille d'Eylau (Oxford, Clarendon Press,
1997).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e416a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e423" publication-type="other">
Jacques Dominique Cassini, Mémoires pour server a
Vhistoire des sciences (Paris, Bleuet, 1810), 135.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e432" publication-type="other">
Colonel Henri Berthaut, La Carte de France (Paris,
Imprimerie du service géographique de l'armée, 1898),
1: 65;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e444" publication-type="other">
Anne Godlewska, Geography Unbound: French
Geographic Science from Cassini to Humboldt (Chicago,
University of Chicago Press, 1999), 76-79.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e457a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e464" publication-type="other">
Anne Godlewska, 'Resisting the cartographic impera-
tive: Giuseppe Bagetti's landscapes of war', Journal of
Historical Geography 29 (2003): 22-50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e478a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e485" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricoeur, Time and
Narrative (Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1984-
1988), vols 1-3;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e497" publication-type="other">
Jeff Malpas, Place and Experience: A
Philosophical Topography (New York, Cambridge University
Press, 1999);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e509" publication-type="other">
Hayden White, The Content of the Form:
Narrative Discourse and Historical Representation (Baltimore
and London, The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1987).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e522a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e529" publication-type="other">
Godlewska, 'Resisting the cartographic imperative'
(see note 4), 24-26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e539a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e546" publication-type="other">
Carte topographique d'une partie du Piémont, entre
Mondovi et Savone, levée de 1804 à 1807, en 29 parties et 7
feuilles de profils, et canevas des ... champs de bataille de 1 796-
1800 (Vincennes, Archives de la guerre (hereafter AG),
L.III.433).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e564" publication-type="other">
Jean François Martinel's
'Mémoire sur la levée des plans de bataille ....',</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e573" publication-type="other">
Marco
Carassi, 'Bagetti e la rappresentazione dei campi di
battaglia napoleonici in Piemonte secondo il rapporto di
un ufficiale al generale Menou', Studi Piemontesi 7:2
(November 1978): 400-4.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e592" publication-type="other">
&lt;http://www.geog.queensu.ca/
napoleonatlas/Piedmont 1796/Mondovi_grid.htm&gt; .</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e602a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e609" publication-type="other">
Louis- Albert- Ghislain, baron Bacler d'Albe,
which was certainly inspired by Horace Benedict de
Saussure's Vue drculaire des montagnes qu'on decouvre du
sommet du glacier du Buet, plate 8 of his Voyages dans les
Alpes. Bacler d'Albe in his own map, Vue drculaire des
Montagnes et du Bassin en avant du village de Tende, près de la
Roya et de la Grande Route de Nice à Coni, où etoit situé le pare
d'Artillerie de campagne de l'armée d'ltalie à la fin de l'an 2 de
la République francaise (AG, L.2.789)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e641a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e648" publication-type="other">
Carte topogra-
phique de la portion des etats ex-vénitiens, comprise entre la
Piave et l'Adige (Vénétie) (7 ff., 17 ff. et tabl. d'ass, 4 parties
complètes), AG, MS M.B.04.108 (1);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e663" publication-type="other">
Carte de la partie
de la Vénétie comprise entre la Piave et l'Adige, avec la partie de
la Republique Cisalpine située sur la rive gauche du Pô, et, en
cartouche, reconnaissance entre la Piave et la Livenza (2 ff.),
AG, MS M.B.04.102 (1).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e681" publication-type="other">
&lt;http://www.geog.queensu.ca/
napoleonatlas/Series/Series_basemaps.htm&gt;.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e691a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e700" publication-type="other">
David
Livingstone, Putting Science in Its Place: Geographies of
Scientific Knowledge (Chicago and London, University of
Chicago Press, 2003).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e717a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e724" publication-type="other">
'Observations particulières de M. Bagetti sur la troisième
vue de la bataille de Rivoli (Traduction)', in Louis
Dussieux, 'Aquarelles militaires de Bagetti relatives à la
bataille de Rivoli', Archives de I' Art Français 1 (1861): 339-
56</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e742" publication-type="other">
Schede Vesme, L'Arte in Piemonte dal
XVI al XVIII secolo, vol. 1 (A-C) (Turin, Società Piemontese
di Archeologia e belle arti, 1963), 72);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e754" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Muriel,
22 February 1807 (AG, Box 3M 245).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e764" publication-type="other">
Le Colonel Henri Berthaut, Les ingénieurs-
géographes militaries 1624-1831: Etude historique (Paris,
Imprimerie du Service Géographique, 1902), 1: 291;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e776" publication-type="other">
Muriel to Bagetti, 6 October 1807 (AG, Box 3M 245);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e782" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Muriel, 18 November 1807 (AG, Box 3M 245);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e788" publication-type="other">
General of the Division of Génie (Sanson?) to Bagetti, 2
February 1808 (AG, Box 3M 245).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e797" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Martinel, 8 September 1803</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e803" publication-type="other">
Martinel to Sanson, 12 September 1803 (AG, Box 3M
246).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e813" publication-type="other">
Martinel to his superiors, 22 December
1803, 21 March 1804, 20 May 1805;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e822" publication-type="other">
Muriel to Bagetti, 5
March 1806, 6 January 1807;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e831" publication-type="other">
Sanson (?) to Bagetti, 2
April 1808 (all in AG, Box 3M 246).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e840" publication-type="other">
Martinel to Sanson,
15 November 1803 (AG, Box 3M 246)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e849" publication-type="other">
Gautier to Sanson sometime in
1802-1803;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e858" publication-type="other">
Sanson to Martinel, 14 November 1803,
Martinel to Sanson, 1 January 1804, 11 January 1804;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e868" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Muriel via Brossier, 5 July 1806 (all in AG, Box
3M 246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e878a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e885" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Martinel, 27 February 1804;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e891" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to
Muriel, 10 January 1806;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e900" publication-type="other">
Bagetti to Louis- Alexandre
Berthier, Minister of War, no date but the date of the
response is indicated as 4 frimaire an 14 (5 December
1805) (AG, Box 3M246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e916a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e923" publication-type="other">
Martinel to General Sanson, 20 fructidor an 12 (7
September 1804) (AG, Box 3M 246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e933a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e940" publication-type="other">
Martinel to Sanson, 4 May 1804 (AG,
Box 3 M 246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e950a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e957" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, Vue de Fombio (AG, MS C454);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e963" publication-type="other">
Parent, Vue du village de Fombio, 1796 (AG, MS B49).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e969" publication-type="other">
Berthaut, Les ingénieurs
geographes militaires (see note 12), 1: 290, and 2: 12 and
33</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e982a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e989" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, 'Combat au passage du Pô à
Plaisance le 19 floréal an 4 (1796)', in Vues des Cam-
pagnes de Français Italie 1800</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1003a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1010" publication-type="other">
Martinel to Bagetti,
26 thermidor an 12 (14 August 1804) (AG, Box
3 M 246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1023a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1030" publication-type="other">
J. Brian Harley, 'Silences and secrecy: the hidden
agenda of cartography in early modern Europe', Imago
Mundi 40 (1988): 57-76;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1042" publication-type="other">
J. Brian Harley, 'Deconstructing
the map', in T. J. Barnes and J. S. Duncan, Writing Worlds:
Discourse, Text and Metaphor in the Representation of
Landscape (New York, Routledge, 1992), 231^7;</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1057" publication-type="other">
Robert
A. Rundstrom, Introducing Cultural and Social Cartography
(Toronto, University of Toronto Press, 1993);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1070" publication-type="other">
John
Pickles, Ground Truth: The Social Implications of Geographic
Information Systems (New York, Guilford Press, 1995);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1082" publication-type="other">
Anne Godlewska, 'The idea of the map', in Ten Geographic
Ideas That Changed the World (New Brunswick, NJ, Rutgers
University Press, 1997);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1094" publication-type="other">
Denis Wood with John Fels,
The Power of Maps (New York, Guilford Press, 1992).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1104a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1111" publication-type="other">
Jeff Malpas, Place and Experience: A Philosophical
Topography (Cambridge and New York, Cambridge
University Press, 1999), 53-56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1124a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1131" publication-type="other">
Marshall G. S.
Hodgson. 'Islam and image', in History of Religions 3
(1964): 220-360)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1143" publication-type="other">
(Samuel Edgerton, 'From mental matrix to
Christian empire: the heritage of Ptolemaic cartography in
the Renaissance', in Art and Cartography: Six Historical
Essays, ed. David Woodward (Chicago and London,
University of Chicago Press, 1987): 10-50).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1161" publication-type="other">
John M. Headley, 'Geography and empire in the late
Renaissance: Botero's assignment, western universalism,
and the civilizing process', Renaissance Quarterly 53 (2000):
1119-55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1177a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1184" publication-type="other">
Sergio Sismondo and Nicholas
Chrisman, 'Deflationary metaphysics and the natures of
maps', Philosophy of Science 68:3 (Sept. 2001), Supplement:
Proceedings of the 2000 Biennial Meeting of the
Philosophy of Science Association, Part I: Contributed
Papers, S38-S49.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1207a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1214" publication-type="other">
Nigel Holmes, Pictorial Maps (New
York, Watson-Gupthill, 1991; London, The Herbert
Press, 1992), 37</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1228a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1237" publication-type="other">
Svetlana Alpers,
The Art of Describing: Dutch Art in the Seventeenth Century
(Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1983).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1249" publication-type="other">
Paolo Galluzzi, Renaissance
Engineers from Brunelleschi to Leonardo da Vinci (Florence,
Istituto e Museo di Storia della Scienza, 1996);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1262" publication-type="other">
Kim H.
Veltman in collaboration with Kenneth D. Keele, Linear
Perspective and the Visual Dimensions of Science and Art
(Munich, Deutscher Kunstverlag, 1986);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1277" publication-type="other">
Richard B. K.
McLanathan, Images of the Universe; Leonardo Da Vinci: The
Artist as Scientist (Garden City, N.Y., Doubleday, 1966);</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1289" publication-type="other">
Ronald Rees, 'Historical
links between cartography and art', Geographical Review 70
(1980): 60-78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1302a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1309" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricoeur's Time and Narrative
(Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1984-1988)</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1318" publication-type="other">
Malpas, Place and Experience (see
note 22), 42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1328a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1335" publication-type="other">
Berthaut, Les ingénieurs géographies militaires
(note 12), 2: 364-65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1345a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1352" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, Loano (Bataille de) (AG, B2)
(finished watercolour). A good map to consult for the
locations is Istituto Geographico Centrale, Carta dei sentieri
e dei rifugi, Sheet 15, Albenga, Alassio, Savona (1:50 000),
1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1371a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1378" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, Bataille de Loano, 23 novembre 1795,
feuille n° 1 (AG, MS C428)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1388a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1395" publication-type="other">
The differences in vegetation are most striking in the
4ème vue de Dego, 14 avril 1 796 (AG, MS B 14 (watercolour),
and AG, MS C440 (pen and ink sketch)), and in Vue du
Défilé de la Madona di Corona (AG, MS B42).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1412a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1419" publication-type="other">
Louis-Albert-Ghislain Bacler d'Albe, Bataille de Lodi
(AG, MS B160).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1429a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1436" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, Battaglia al ponte di Lodi (Galleria
d'Arte Moderna e Contemporanea di Torino, Box 520,
Sheet 13564).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1449a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1456" publication-type="other">
Giuseppe Bagetti, Fort de la Ceva le 16 avril 1796 (AG,
MS B16).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1466a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1473" publication-type="other">
Istituto Geographico Centrale, Carta dei sentieri e dei
rifugi, Sheet 18, Langhe Meridionali (1:50000), 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1483a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1490" publication-type="other">
Martinel (at Ceva) to his Superiors, 23 November
1803 (AGBox 3M246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1500a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1507" publication-type="other">
General Sanson to Martinel, 30 thermi-
dor an 12 (18 August 1804) (AG, Box 3M 246).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1518a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1525" publication-type="other">
Carte topographique d'une partie du Piémont, entre
Mondovi et Savone (see note 7), 2C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1535a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1542" publication-type="other">
David's Bonaparte franchissant le Grand Saint-Bernard</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1548" publication-type="other">
Gros's Bataille d'Eylau</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d14182e1555a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1562" publication-type="other">
Martinel and General Sanson, 20 prairial an 13 (9 June
1805) (AG, Box 3M 246).</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d14182e1571" publication-type="other">
&lt;www.geog.queensu.ca/napoleonatlas/bagetti/S942_
middle. htm&gt;.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
