<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="por">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">reviportfilo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000595</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08705283</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">2183461X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26196973</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Pessoa e Sociedade</article-title>
            <subtitle>o Chamado ao Existir Pessoal Compreendido como Apelo à Esperança a partir da Filosofia de Henrique Cláudio de Lima Vaz</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>DE OLIVEIRA</surname>
                  <given-names>CLÁUDIA MARIA ROCHA</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">
               <label>*</label>Faculdade Jesuíta de Filosofia e Teologia (Belo Horizonte), Brasil.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2017</year>
            <string-date>2017</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">73</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26196962</issue-id>
         <fpage>209</fpage>
         <lpage>238</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2017 Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia Copyright © 2017 Aletheia – Associação Científica e Cultural</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26196973"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>Abstract</label>
            <p>Starting by the distinction made by Henrique Cláudio de Lima Vaz between the democratic ideal and real democracy, and to assume that we will only be able to build a true democratic community if we act within that same community as authentic persons, we defend in this article that being a person is constituted as a call to hope. We will divide the article into three parts. In the first part, we will explain in what sense the personalism is constituted as an option for hope. Then we indicate what it means to be a person for Lima Vaz. Finally, we show how we can become a person and what are the difficulties to this accomplishment. Only when we exist as authentical people we will be able to establish the right relationship between the democratic ideal and real democracy.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <label>Keywords:</label>
            <kwd>democracy</kwd>
            <kwd>ethic</kwd>
            <kwd>hope</kwd>
            <kwd>justice</kwd>
            <kwd>person</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>por</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Referências</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aristóteles. Ética a Nicômaco. Traduzido por Edson Bini. Bauru: Edipro, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berti, Enrico. Novos Estudos Aristotélicos III: filosofia prática. Traduzido por Élcio de Gusmão Verçosa Filho. São Paulo: Loyola, 2014.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">De Finance, Joseph. Essai sur l’agir humain. Roma: Presses de l’Université Gregorienne, 1962.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gilbert, Paul. A simplicidade do princípio. Traduzido por Paulo Meneses. São Paulo: Loyola, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kant, Immanuel. Fundamentação da Metafísica dos Costumes. Traduzido por Guido Antônio de Almeida. São Paulo: Discurso Editorial-Barcarolla, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leonard, Andre. Metaphysique de l’être. Paris: Cerf, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Escritos de Filosofia I: Problemas de Fronteira. São Paulo: Loyola, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Escritos de Filosofia II: Ética e Cultura. São Paulo: Loyola, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Antropologia Filosófica I. São Paulo: Loyola, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Antropologia Filosófica II. São Paulo: Loyola, 1992.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Escritos de Filosofia V: Introdução à Ética Filosófica 2. São Paulo: Loyola, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lima Vaz, Henrique Cláudio de. Escritos de Filosofia VI: Ontologia e História. São Paulo: Loyola, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maritain, Jacques. Humanismo Integral. Traduzido por Afranio Coutinho. São Paulo: Companhia Editora Nacional, 1965.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mounier, Emmanuel. Manifesto ao serviço do personalismo. Traduzido por Antônio Ramos Rosa. Lisboa: Livraria Editora, 1967.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mounier, Emmanuel. O personalismo. Traduzido por João Bernard da Costa. Lisboa: Moraes Editores, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nedoncelle, Maurice. Para uma filosofia do amor e da pessoa. Traduzido por Manuel Breda Simoes. Lisboa: Livraria Morais Editora, 1961.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oliveira, Cláudia Maria Rocha de. Metafísica e ética: a filosofia da pessoa em Lima Vaz como resposta ao niilismo contemporâneo. São Paulo: Loyola, 2013.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Possenti, Vittorio. O novo princípio pessoa. Traduzido por Fernando Soares Moreira. São Paulo: Loyola, 2016.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Possenti, Vittorio. Il nuovo principio persona. Roma: Armando, 2013.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sousa, Maria Celeste. Comunidade ética: sobre os princípios ontológicos da vida social em Henrique Cláudio de Lima Vaz. São Paulo: Loyola, 2014.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tomás de Aquino, Suma teológica I. Traduzido por Aldo Vannucchi et al. São Paulo: Loyola, 2014.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
