<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24707953</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>FRAMEWORK FOR A TAXONOMY OF SCIENTIFIC METAPHOR</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>M. Elaine</given-names>
                  <surname>Botha</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1988</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>53</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24707951</issue-id>
         <fpage>143</fpage>
         <lpage>170</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24707953"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d387e101a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e108" publication-type="other">
Cf. Mellor's (1968) discussion of Duhem and Campbell's views concerning analogies, where
a similar point is made.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e118a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e125" publication-type="other">
is prepsupposed. Quine (1975: 322) succinctly formulâtes the underdetermination thesis as
follows: théories that are underdetermined by data are "... theory formulations that are empiri-
cally equivalent, logically incompatible, and irreconcilable by reconstrual of predicates'. The
unterdetermination thesis is the claim that for any theory for a given subject matter, there is an
incompatible rival theory which is evidentially equivalent, is presupposed.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e144a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e151" publication-type="other">
the image of the prism for the notion of time for example (My thanks to referees for pointing
out this and various other issues).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e161a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e168" publication-type="other">
In Reformational philosophy the term 'structure' can be used in two different senses: It could
refer to the factual or subject-side of reality and is then used in the sense of the structure of
reality. It could also refer to the law-side of reality, i.e. the structural laws governing and
conditioning the regularities perceived in phenomena. Then it is understood in the sense of the
structure for reality. When the term 'structure mapping' is used in this article it refers primarily
to the latter sense of the term, although it is conceded that analysis of the structures for reality
are inextricably bound to the analysis of the structures of reality.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e195a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e202" publication-type="other">
It is interesting that Hesse uses the metaphor 'network' to explain this process, whereas Kittay
and Lehrer (1981) the metaphor 'field' in a similar fashion.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e212a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e219" publication-type="other">
The distinction also forms the basis and criterion for distinguishing different théories of
metaphor (Edie, 1975: 3). Epiphors that express existing similarities would provide a basis for
the comparison or simile theory of metaphor (the so called réduction théories) whereas diaphors
provide the basis for the interaction theory.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e235a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e242" publication-type="other">
The Iatter question has been dealt with in Botha, 1986.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e249a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e256" publication-type="other">
The significance of such an ontology for the solution of problems concerning the relationship
between metaphorical models and scientific realism has been dealt with elsewhere, cf. Proceed-
ings of the Tenth Biennial meeting of the Philosophy of Science Association, USA, vol. 1, 1986.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d387e269a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d387e276" publication-type="other">
It would be more accurate to refer to 'ontic' or 'ontical' in this respect.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Bibliography</title>
         <ref id="d387e292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e296" publication-type="other">
Achinstein, P. 1964. Models, analogies and théories. Philosophy of Science, 31:336.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e303a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e307" publication-type="other">
Beardsley, M. C. 1967. 'Metaphor'. In: Edwards, P. Encyclopaedia of Philosophy, vol.v: 284-
289. New York: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e317a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e321" publication-type="other">
Black, Max. 1962. Models and metaphors: Studies in language and philosophy. Ithaca: Cornell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e328a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e332" publication-type="other">
Black, Max. 1980. In: Ortony, Andrew (éd.). Metaphor and thought. Cambridge: Cambridge
university press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e343a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e347" publication-type="other">
Bradie, M. 1984. The metaphorical character of science. Philosophia Naturalis. June 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e354a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e358" publication-type="other">
Burrell, David. 1973. Analogy andphilosophical language. New Haven: Yale University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e365a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e369" publication-type="other">
Butcher, S.H. (ed.) 1911. Thepoetics of Aristotle. 4th ed. London: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e376a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e380" publication-type="other">
Canguilhem, Georges. 1963. The role of analogies and models in biological discovery. Scientific
change, vol. 16, 507-520.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e390a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e394" publication-type="other">
Collins, Lyndhurst, 1976. The use of models in the social sciences. London: Tavistock.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e401a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e405" publication-type="other">
Colodny, R. G. (ed.) 1970. The nature and function of scientific théories. Essays in contemporary
science and philosophy. Pittsburgh: University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e416a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e420" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H, 1954. De analogische grondbegrippen der vakwetenschappen en hun betrek-
king tot de structuur van den menselijken ervaringshorizon. Nederlandse Akademie van Weten-
schappen. Afdeling Letterkunde. Mededelingen vol 17(6), 171-192.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e433a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e437" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. 1955. A New critique of theoretical thought, vol. II. Amsterdam: Paris.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e444a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e448" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. 1969. A New critique of theoretical thought, vol. III. Amsterdam: Paris.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e455a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e459" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. 1976. The epistemo-logical Gegenstands-relation and the logica! subject object-
relation. Philosophia Reformata, 41:1-8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e469a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e473" publication-type="other">
Edie, James M. 1975. Identity and metaphor: A phenomenological theory of polysemy. Journal
of the British Society for Phenomenology. vol. 6, no. 1, January 1975, p. 32-41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e483a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e487" publication-type="other">
Edwards, P. (ed.) 1967. Encyclopaedia of Philosophy. New York: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e495a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e499" publication-type="other">
Gentner, Dedre. 1982. Are scientific analogies metaphors? In: Miall, David S. (ed.) 1982.
Metaphor: Problems and perspectives. Sussex: The Harvester press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e509a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e513" publication-type="other">
Haynes, Felicity. 1975. Metaphor as interactive. Educational Theory, 23:272-277.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e520a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e524" publication-type="other">
Harre, Rom. 1976. The constructive role of models. In: Collins, Lyndhurst (éd.). The use of
models in the social sciences. London: Tavistock, 16-43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e534a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e538" publication-type="other">
Harre, R. and Martin, J. 1982. Metaphor and science. In: Miall, David S. (ed.) 1982. Metaphor:
Problems and perspectives. Sussex: The Harvester press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e548a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e552" publication-type="other">
Hart, H. 1984. Understanding our world. An intégral ontology. Lanham: University press of
America.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e562a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e566" publication-type="other">
Hart, H. 1986. Dooyeweerd's Gegenstand Theory of Theory. In: Mclntire, C. T. (ed.). The
legacy of Herman Dooyeweerd. Reflections on critica! philosophy in the Christian tradition.
Lanham: University press of America, 143-166.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e580a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e584" publication-type="other">
Hesse, Μ.Β. 1966. Models and analogies in science. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame
press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e594a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e598" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1970. Is there an independent observation language? In: Colodny, R. G. (ed.)
The nature and function of scientific théories. Essays in contemporary science and philosophy.
Pittsburgh: University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e611a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e615" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1972. The explanatory function of metaphor. In: Bar-Hillel, Y. (ed.) 1972.
Logic, methodology and philosophy of science. Proceedings of the 1964-lnternational Congress.
Amsterdam.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e628a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e632" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1974. The structure of inference. London: Macmilian.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e639a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e643" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1976. Models versus paradigms in the natural sciences, 1-15. In: Collins, Lyndhurst.
1976. The use of models in the social sciences. London: Tavistock.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e653a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e657" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1980. Révolutions and reconstructions in the philosophy of science. Brighton:
Harvester press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e668a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e672" publication-type="other">
Hesse, M. B. 1984. The cognitive claims of metaphor. In: Van Noppen, J. P. (ed.) Metaphor
and religion. Theolinguistics, 2. Brussel: Vrije Universiteit, Brussel, (27-46).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e682a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e686" publication-type="other">
Honeck, Richard P. and Hoffman, Robert R. 1980. Cognition and figurative language. New
Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e696a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e700" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Mark. 1980. A philosophical perspective on the problems of metaphor, 47-67. In:
Honeck, Richard, P. and Hoffman, Robert R. 1980. Cognition and figurative language. New
Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e713a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e717" publication-type="other">
Johnson, Mark (ed.) 1981. Philosophical perspectives on metaphor. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e727a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e731" publication-type="other">
Kittay, Eva. 1984. A reply to Donald Davidson's 'What metaphors mean' or Metaphor as
rearranging the furniture of the mind. (Unpublished article). Address of author: SUNY at
Stoney Brook. N.Y.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e744a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e748" publication-type="other">
Kittay, Eva and Lehrer, A. 1981. Semantic fields and the structure of metaphor. Studies in
Language, 5:31-63.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e759a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e763" publication-type="other">
Kuhn, T. S. 1973. The Structure of Scientific Révolutions. (2nd enlarged ed.) Chicago: University
press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e773a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e777" publication-type="other">
Lakoff, George and Johnson, Mark, 1980. Metaphors we live by. Chicago: The university of
Chicago press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e787a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e791" publication-type="other">
Lakoff, George and Johnson, Mark. 1981. Conceptual metaphor in everyday language. In:
Johnson, Mark. 1981. Philosophical perspectives on metaphor. Minneapolis: University of
Minnesota press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e804a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e808" publication-type="other">
Lakoff, George and Johnson, Mark, 1982. The metaphorical structure of the human conceptual
System. In: Norman, D. A. 1982. Perspectives on cognitive science. New Jersey: Ablex Publishing
co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e821a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e825" publication-type="other">
Leplin, Jarrett (ed.). 1984. Scientific realism. Berkely: University of Californie press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e832a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e836" publication-type="other">
Lewin, Kurt. 1959. Field theory in Social Science. London: Tavistock.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e844a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e848" publication-type="other">
Mclntire, C. T. (ed.). The legacy of Herman Dooyeweerd. Reflections on critical philosophy in
the Christian tradition. Lanham: University press of America.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e858a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e862" publication-type="other">
McMullin, Ernan. 1968. What do physical models tell us? In: Van Rootselaar, B. and Staal, J.
F. (ed.) Logic, methodology and Philosophy of Science. Amsterdam: North Holland.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e872a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e876" publication-type="other">
McMullin, Ernan. 1978. Structural explanation. American Philosophical Quarterley, 15:139-
147.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e886a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e890" publication-type="other">
McMullin, Ernan, 1984. The case for scientific realism. In: Leplin, Jarret (éd.). 1984. Scientific
realism. Berkely: University of California press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e900a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e904" publication-type="other">
Mellor, D. H. 1968. Models and analogies in science. Duhem versus Campbell? Isis, 59:282-
290.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e914a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e918" publication-type="other">
Miall, David S. (ed.) Metaphor: Problems and perspectives. Sussex: Harvester press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e926a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e930" publication-type="other">
Norman, D. A. 1982. Perspectives on cognitive science. New Jersey: Ablex Publishing co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e937a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e941" publication-type="other">
Ortony, Andrew, (éd.). 1980. Metaphor and thought. Cambridge: Cambridge university press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e948a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e952" publication-type="other">
Ortony, Andrew. 1975. Why metaphors are necessary and not just nice. Educational Theory,
Winter, 45-53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e962a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e966" publication-type="other">
Pepper, S. 1970. (6th e.d) World hypotheses. Berkely: University of California press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e973a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e977" publication-type="other">
Richards, I.A. 1936. The Philosophy of Rhetoric. Oxford: Oxford university press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e984a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e988" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1976. History and hermeneutics. Journal of Philosophy 73: 683-695.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e996a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1000" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1978. The metaphorical process as cognition, imagination and feeling. Critical
lnquiry, 5:143-159.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1010a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1014" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 1984. The rule of metaphor. Toronto: University of Toronto press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1021a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1025" publication-type="other">
Rothbart, Daniel, 1984. The semantics of metaphor and the structure of science. Philosophy of
Science, 51:595-615.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1035a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1039" publication-type="other">
Schön, D. 1963. Displacement of concepts. London: Tavistock publications.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1046a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1050" publication-type="other">
Schön, D. 1980. Generative metaphor; A perspective on problem setting in social policy. In:
Ortony, Andrew (ed.) Metaphor and thought. Cambridge: Cambridge university press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1060a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1064" publication-type="other">
Snell, Bruno, 1953. The discovery of the mind. The Greek origins of European thought. Oxford:
Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1075a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1079" publication-type="other">
Soskice, J. M. 1985. Metaphor and religious language. New York: Oxford University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1086a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1090" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M. D. 1980. Time and again. Toronto: Wedge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1097a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1101" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, M. D. 1982. Théories as logically qualified artefacts (II). Philosophia Reformata, 47:1,
20-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1111a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1115" publication-type="other">
Stanford, William Bedeli, 1936. Greek metaphor. Oxford.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1122a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1126" publication-type="other">
Strauss, D. F. M., N.d. Inleiding tot 'n studie in die Wysbegeerte. (Unpublished booklet).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1133a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1137" publication-type="other">
Strauss, D. F. M., 1973. Begrip en idee. Assen: Van Gorcum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1145a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1149" publication-type="other">
Strauss, D. F. M., 1984. An analysis of the structure of analysis. Philosophia Reformata, 49(1),
35-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1159a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1163" publication-type="other">
Sullivan, Harry Stack. 1964. The fusion of psychiatry and social science. New York: Norton.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1170a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1174" publication-type="other">
Suppe, Fred. (éd.). 1974. The Structure of scientific théories. Urbana: University of Illinois
press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1184a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1188" publication-type="other">
Swanson, J. W. 1966. On models. British Journal of Philosophy of Science, 17:297-311.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1195a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1199" publication-type="other">
Tiger, L. and Fox, R. 1971. The impérial animal. London: Secker and Warburg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1206a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1210" publication-type="other">
Van Noppen, J. P. (ed.) 1984. Metaphor and religion. Theolinguistics, 2. Study series of the
Vrije Universiteit, Brussel. New Series no. 12. Brussel: Vrije Universiteit Brussel.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1225" publication-type="other">
Wheelwright, Phillip. 1973. Metaphor and reality. Midland books, MB-122. Bloomington;
Indiana University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d387e1235a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d387e1239" publication-type="other">
Wittgenstein, Ludwig. 1958. The Blue and Brown Books. Preliminary studies for the 'Philoso-
phical investigations'. New York: Harper and Row.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
